<COMMEMORATION>

<NAME>The Eve (Paramony) of the Nativity</NAME>
<SERVICE>
	<ROYALHOURS><!-- The verses for the Idiomels are the same in all the hours -->
	<IDIOMEL Type="11" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8&lt;BR&gt;The Work of Sophronios, the Patriarch of Jerusalem" Author="Sophronios, the Patriarch of Jerusalem">
Prepare, O Bethlehem, and let the manger make ready and the cave receive; for truth hath come,
and shadow hath passed. And God hath appeared to mankind from the Virgin, taking our likeness
and deifying our nature. Wherefore, Adam and Eve are made new, crying, Goodwill hath appeared
on earth to save our race.
	</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<VERSE Type="1" >
 God will come from Theman, and the Holy One from a mountain overshadowed by forest. 
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="12" Tone="3" Header="Tropar, Tone 3">
Now, hath come the time for the aforesaid prophecy mystically uttered to be fulfilled; namely, And
thou Bethlehem in the land of Judah art not the least among princes, having gone before and
prepared the cave; for out of thee shall come a Governor of nations, from the Virgin Maiden
incarnate, by Whom I mean Christ God Who shall govern His people, the new Israel. Let us
therefore, ascribe unto Him magnification.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="2">
Lord, I heard your report and was afraid. Lord, I understood Your deeds and was scared.
</VERSE><!-- The English version that I had access to missed the second part of the verse, which I translated from the Church Slavonic (only an approximate version) Y.S. -->
<IDIOMEL Type="13" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Thus saith Joseph to the Virgin, What is this thing, O Mary, which I behold in thee? Verily, I am
surprised and perplexed, and my mind is dazzled. Wherefore, henceforth from this moment be thou
secluded in secret. What is this matter, O Mary, that I behold in thee? For thou hast given me
instead of honor, disgrace; and instead of gladness, sorrow; and instead of being extolled, thou hast
brought me blame. Therefore, I cannot bear the reproach of men, from the Temple of the Lord I
took thee; from the priests I received thee as innocent of all blame. What then is this thing I
behold?
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="1P" Tone="4" Header="Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The Lord said to me, "You are my Son, today I have begotten you."
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="1P" >
Ask of me, and I shall give you the Nations as your inheritance.
</VERSE>

<IDIOMEL Type="31" Tone="6" Header="Тropar, Tone 6" Author="">
This is our God, beside Whom none other may be considered. He it was Who was born of the
Virgin and went about among men, the only Son, beheld as a man placed in a mean manger, the
Lord of the house wrapped in swaddling clothes. And the star pointeth for the Magi to worship
Him; and we sing shouting, O Trinity, save our souls.
</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<IDIOMEL Type="32" Tone="8" Header="Troparion, Tone 8">
When the heavenly hosts beheld the mystery before Thy Birth, O Lord, they were struck with
surprise; for Thou Who didst adorn the heavens with stars was pleased to become like a babe, and
lie in a manger for beasts, O Thou Almighty One in Whose grasp are all the regions of the earth;
for by Thy dispensation, Thy compassion was made known, O Christ, and Thy Great Mercy.
Wherefore, glory to Thee.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="33" Tone="3" Header="Tropar, Tone 3" Author="">
Tell us, O Joseph, how it is that thou dost bring the Virgin whom thou didst receive from the holy
places to Bethlehem great with child? And he replieth, saying, I have searched the Prophets, and it
was revealed to me by the angel. Therefore, I am convinced that Mary shall give birth in an
inexplicable manner to God, whom Magi from the east shall come to worship and to serve with
precious gifts. Wherefore, O Thou who wast incarnate for our sakes, glory to Thee.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="3P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
For a Child has been born for us, and a Son has been given to us.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="3P" >
And the government is upon His shoulders.
</VERSE>
	
<IDIOMEL Type="61" Tone="1" Header="Tropar, Tone 1" Author="">
Come, ye believers, let us ascend in a divine manner and behold a divine condescension, revealed
to us from on high, openly in Bethlehem. And having purified our minds by good conduct, let us
offer virtues instead of frankincense. Let us go before and prepare with faith entrances for the
Nativity among the spiritual treasures, crying, Glory in the highest to God, the One in Trinity,
through Whom good-will appeared among men to deliver Adam from the ancient curse; for He is
the Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="62" Tone="4" Header="Tropar, Tone 4">
Listen, O heaven, and give ear, O earth. Let the foundations shake, and let trembling fall on all
below the earth; for God hath dwelt in a creation of flesh; and He Who made creation with a
precious hand is seen in the womb of a created one. O the depth of the riches and wisdom and
knowledge of God! How unsearchable are His judgments, and His ways past finding out.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="63" Tone="5" Header="Tropar, Tone 5" Author="">
Come, ye nations that have put on Christ, let us behold a wonder that overtaketh all minds with
astonishment; and as we kneel down in true worship, let us give praise in faith; for the Maiden,
having conceived, cometh today to Bethlehem, to give birth to the Lord. The ranks of angels
hasten, and Joseph, seeing these things, shouted, crying, What is this strange mystery that hath
befallen thee, O Virgin? And how shalt thou give birth, O ewe that hath not known wedlock?
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="6P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
From the womb before the Morning Star I have begotten you.
</PROKIMENON><!-- The Church Slavonic is slightly different here И҆з чре́ва пре́жде денни́цы роди́хъ тѧ̀, клѧ́тсѧ гдⷭь и҆ не раска́етсѧ. -->
<VERSE Type="6P" >
The Lord said to my Lord: Sit at my right hand, until I make your enemies a footstool for your feet.
</VERSE><!-- The Church Slavonic and the Greek are the laconic: Речѐ гдⷭь гдⷭви моемꙋ̀, сѣдѝ ѡ҆деснꙋ́ю менѐ. The fuller version makes more sense.-->

<IDIOMEL Type="91" Tone="7" Header="Tropar, Tone 7" Author="">
Verily, Herod was overtaken by astonishment when he saw the piety of the Magi. And having been
overridden with wrath, he began to inquire of them about the time. He robbed the mothers of their
children and ruthlessly reaped the tender bodies of the babes. And the breasts dried up, and the
springs of milk failed. Great then was the calamity. Wherefore, being gathered, O believers, in true
worship, let us adore the Nativity of Christ.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="92" Tone="2" Header="Tropar, Tone 2">
As Joseph was going his way to Bethlehem pierced with sadness, thou didst cry unto him, O
Virgin, saying, Why frownest thou and art troubled when thou seest me great with child,
completely ignorant of the terrible mystery that is in me? Drive away from thee all dismay,
comprehending the strange matter; for God, for His mercy’s sake, hath descended to earth and hath
now taken flesh in my womb, and thou shalt see Him born, as it pleased Him; for He is thy
Creator, Whom the angels praise ceaselessly and glorify, with the Father and the Holy Spirit.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.1" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
Today is born of the Virgin Him Who holdest all creation in the hollow of His hand.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.2" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
He Whose essence is untouchable is wrapped in swaddling clothes as a babe.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.3" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
The God Who from of old established the heavens lieth in a manger.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.4" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
He Who showered the people with manna in the wilderness feedeth on milk from the breasts.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.5" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
And the bridegroom of the Church calleth the Magi.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.6" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
And the Son of the Virgin accepteth gifts from them.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.7" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
We worship Thy Nativity, O Christ.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.8" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
Show us also Thy divine Theophany!
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="9P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
Sion is our mother, a man will say; and a man has been born in her.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="9P">
Her foundations are in the holy mountains.
</VERSE>

	</ROYALHOURS>
</SERVICE>

</COMMEMORATION>