<DAY>
<LANGUAGE>
<SCRIPTURE Type="vespers" Reading="Composite_6" Cmd="nday != -48" />
<SCRIPTURE Type="vespers" Reading="Isa_6:1-12" Cmd="nday != -48" />
<SCRIPTURE Type="vespers" Reading="Isa_19:1-5, 12, 16, 19-21" Cmd="nday != -48" />
<SCRIPTURE Type="matins" Reading="Lk_2:25-32" Cmd="nday != -48" />
<SCRIPTURE Type="apostol" Reading="Heb_7:7-17" Cmd="nday != -48" />
<SCRIPTURE Type="gospel" Reading="Lk_2:22-40" Cmd="nday != -48" />
<INSTRUCTIONS Cmd="nday == -48">
Note:  The combination of the Meeting of the Lord and Clean Monday is extremely rare.  The Typicon currently in use in the Russian Church calls for transferring the service for the feast to Forgiveness Sunday, February 1.  Divine Liturgy on Clean Monday is not served.  This was the way the feast was last observed in 1915.  Typica of earlier provenance suggest an alternative practice of the Russian Church, in which the service to the Meeting of the Lord is not transferred, but is combined with the service for Clean Monday.  The rubrics are similar to a service to the Annunciation observed during Great Lent and call for a Vesperal Liturgy of St John Chrysostom.  The instructions are taken from the book Oko Tserkovnoye published under Patriarch Joasaph I and Tsar Michael in 1640 (p. 949). This was probably the practice followed in 1573 and 1668.
 
Serve the All-night Vigil.
At Small Vespers:
	At Lord, I have cried, stichera for the feast, tone 1, on 4.  GN:  of the feast, tone 4.
	At the Aposticha, sticherion ideomelon of the Triodion, tone 4, twice, Thy grace hast shown forth, O Lord; sticherion for the martyrs from the Triodion; GN: of the feast, tone 2, Receive, O Simeon.
	Troparion of the feast.

 At Great Vespers:
	The usual beginning Psalm.  Blessed is the man (the first antiphon only).
	At Lord, I have cried, stichera on 10:  the idiomelon of the Triodion, tone 4 (twice), Thy grace hast shown forth, O Lord (written in the Triodion as the first sticherion Aposticha); the prosomia of the Triodion, tone 2, on 3 (written in the Triodion at Lord, I have cried, starting with Let us make haste to humble the flesh); and the ideomela of the feast, tone 1, on 5 (the first two stichera – twice), Say, O Simeon.  GN:  of the feast, tone 6, Let the door of the heaven open.
	Entrance with the censor.  O Joyful Light.
	Great Prokeimenon of the Triodion, tone 8:  “Turn not away Thy face from Thy servant, for I am afflicted; hear me speedily, draw nigh to my soul and redeem it.”  Verse:  “The salvation of Thy countenance has helped me.”  Verse:  “Let the poor see and rejoice.”  Verse:  “Seek the Lord diligently, and ye shall live.”
	The three Old Testament readings of the feast (Exodus, Isaiah, and Isaiah).
	At the Litya, stichera of the feast, tone 1, The Ancient of days.  G: of the feast, tone 5, Search the scriptures.  N: of the feast, same tone, The Ancient of days.
	At the Aposticha, stichera of the feast, tone 7, Embellish thy palace, O Zion, with their verses.  GN:  of the feast, tone 8, He that is carried by the Cherubim.
	At the blessing of the breads, troparion of the feast thrice.

At Matins:
	At God is the Lord, the troparion of the feast thrice.
	The kathismata:  4th, 5th, and 6th (each divided into three parts).  After each kathisma, the Small Litany.
	After the first kathisma reading, both sessional hymns of the Triodion:  tone 2, Let us seek humility, G: the same, N: Thou art the font of mercies; and same tone, Let us radiantly begin, G: the same, N: We have Thy unceasing prayers.
	After the second kathisma reading, the sessional hymn of the feast, tone 1, Let the angelic choir.
	After the third kathisma reading, the sessional hymn of the feast, tone 1, He that is with the Father.
	Polyeleos.  Magnificant to the feast:  “We magnify Thee, Christ the Giver of Life, and we honour Thy Most-Pure Mother, by Whom Thou hast now been brought into the temple of the Lord according to the law.”  Selected Psalm for the Theotokos, “My heart has uttered a good matter: I declare my works to the King” (see the Heirmologion).
	Small Litany and sessional hymn of the feast, tone 4, For my sake dost Thou, O Ancient of days.
	The Songs of Ascent, tone 4, first antiphon, From my youth.
	Prokeimenon of the feast, tone 4, “I will commemorate Thy name in every generation and generation.”  Verse:  “My heart has uttered a good matter.”
	Gospel reading:  Lk #8.
	After Psalm 50, the sticherion of the feast, tone 6, Let the door of the heaven open today.
	The Canons:
	At Odes 3, 4, 5, 6 and 7:  the canon of the feast on 14 (heirmos twice).  Katavasia:  heirmos of the feast, The sun rose once upon a dry land.  The Biblical Odes in their festal redaction, Let us sing to the Lord.  (Where the singing of the Biblical Odes is not practical, the refrain “Glory to Thee, our God, glory to Thee” may be chanted instead.)
	At Odes 1 and 8:  the canon of the feast on 6 (heirmos twice) and the three-oded canon of the Triodion on 8.  Katavasia:  the heirmoi of the Triodion, Come O ye people.  For the three-oded canon, the refrain “Glory to Thee, our God, glory to Thee.”
	After Ode 3, the Sessional Hymn of the feast, tone 4, On Mount Sinai Moses was of old.
	After Ode 6, the kontakion and oikos of the feast.
	At Ode 9:  More honourable is not sung, rather Ode 9 is chanted in this way:
	Deacon (or, Priest), the first refrain:  “O Theotokos—Virgin, the hope of Christians! Do Thou shelter, preserve and save those who trust in Thee.”
	1st Choir:  Heirmos of the feast, In the law, in the shadow and the scriptures.
	2nd Choir:  second refrain O Theotokos—Virgin, the benign help and the same heirmos.
	Then read the troparia of the first canon (on 4):
	Refrain O God-bearing Simeon and troparion With the ancients.
	Refrain Simeon the ancient and the same troparion.
	Refrain It is not the ancient and troparion Thou, O Christ.
	Refrain O mysterious tongs and troparion The chaste and righteous Anna.
	Then Ode 9 of the three-oded canon of the Triodion on 8.
	Then, heirmos of the second canon of the Triodion, Let us, O faithful magnify without ceasing.  Refrain:  O Theotokos—Virgin, the hope of Christians and heirmos of the feast, In the law.

	It is truly meet is not sung. 
	Photogogicon of the feast, Having come into the Holy place, thrice.
	Let every breath is sung.  At the Praises:  stichera of the feast on 4.  GN:  of the feast, tone 6, Having been pleased.
	Reader:  “Glory to Thee, who hast shown us the light” (To Thee is due glory is not read) and the daily doxology.1  Litany:  Let us complete our morning prayer.
	At the Aposticha, stichera of the Triodion, tone 5, Lent, the mother of chastity, has come with refrains from the Horologion.  GN:  of the feast, tone 5, The Ancient of days.2
	Good it is.  Trisagion.  After Our Father, troparion of the feast once.  Litany:  Have mercy on us, O God.  “Wisdom!”  Choir:  “Father, bless!”  Priest:  “He who Is is blessed ...” Prayer O King of Heaven (or, Establish, O Lord). Prayer of St Ephraim the Syrian with three prostrations.  1st Hour.

At the First Hour:
	No kathisma.  Troparion and kontakion of the feast.  After the exclamation God be merciful unto us the Prayer of St Ephraim the Syrian with sixteen bows (three prostrations, then twelve bows with the words “O God, cleanse me a sinner”, then the entire prayer with one full prostration).  The Trisagion and Lord, have mercy are not read, but immediately the prayer O Christ, the True Light.  By custom, To Thee, the Champion Leader or the kontakion of the feast.  Great dismissal and polychronion.

The 3rd, 6th and 9th Hours are served together with Typica, Vespers and Liturgy (customarily, on Monday morning).
At the Third Hour:
	The 7th kathisma.  Troparion and kontakion of the feast (the Lenten verses are not read and there are no prostrations).  After the exclamation God be merciful unto us, the Prayer of St Ephraim the Syrian (just as at 1st Hour).  Then the prayer for the end of the hours, O Master God and 6th Hour.

At the Sixth Hour:
	The 8th kathisma.  Troparion and kontakion of the feast (the Lenten verses are not read).  After the theotokion, troparion of the prophecy from the Triodion, tone 5, Lord, O Lord.  Prokeimenon, tone 4:  “For the Lord knows the way of the righteous; but the way of the ungodly shall perish.”  Verse:  “Blessed is the man who has not walked in the counsel of the ungodly.”  Reading of the Triodion (Prophecy of Isaiah).  Second prokeimenon, tone 7, “Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice in Him with trembling.”  Verse:  “Wherefore did the heathen rage, and the nations imagine vain things?”  Prayer of St Ephraim, just as at 3rd Hour.

At the Ninth Hour:
	The 9th kathisma.  Troparion and kontakion of the feast (the Lenten verses are not read).  At the end of the hour, the exclamation God, be merciful unto us and the the Prayer of St Ephraim the Syrian with three prostrations.  Prayer:  O Master, Lord Jesus Christ, our God and Typica.

At Typica:
	The curtain is drawn (but the Royal Doors remain shut).  The Beatitudes are read (not chanted).   Remember us, O Lord is read without prostrations.  After Our Father, kontakion of the feast.  “Lord, have mercy” (x40).  GN.  More honourable.  Reader:  “In the name of the Lord, Father, bless!”  Priest:  God be merciful unto us.  The Prayer of St Ephraim the Syrian with sixteen bows.  Prayer:  O All-Holy Trinity.  Priest:  “Wisdom!”  Choir:  “It is truly meet to bless Thee, the Theotokos, ever-blessed and most-blameless and Mother of our God.”  Priest:  “O Most-Holy Theotokos, save us!”  Choir:  More honourable (the rest of the hymn).  Priest:  Glory to Thee, Christ, our God.  Choir:  GN, “Lord, have mercy” (thrice), “Father, bless!”  Priest:  the dismissal Christ, our True God.  Choir:  “Lord, have mercy” (thrice).  Polychronion is not chanted.

Vespers with the Divine Liturgy of St John Chrysostom (without kathismata and without bows):
	No kathisma.
	At Lord, I have cried, stichera on 11:  idiomelon of the Triodion, tone 3, Let us fast with a pleasant fast, twice (printed as the first sticherion Aposticha for Monday evening Vespers); the prosomia of the Triodion, tone 2 and tone 5, on 3, I have wrought every sin (printed at Lord, I have cried for Monday evening Vespers); of the feast, tone 1, on 3, The Creator of all things; and of St Simeon, tone 4, on 3, Thou art righteous and perfect (see the Menaion under February 3).  For the 11th sticherion, the refrain:  “Thou art a priest for ever, after the order of Melchisedec.”  GN:  of the feast, tone 5, The Ancient of days.
	During the singing of Lord, I have cried, the priest finishes the Proskomedia (if using this rubric, then the Lambs for the Pre-sanctified Liturgies on Wednesday and Friday would be prepared and sanctified at this Liturgy, not on Sunday).
	Entrance with the Gospel Book.  O Joyful Light.
	Prokeimenon of the Triodion, tone 6, “Deliverance is the Lord’s, and Thy blessing is upon Thy people.”  Verse:  “O Lord, why are they that afflict me multiplied?”
	Reading of the Triodion, from Genesis.
	Second prokeimenon of the Triodion, tone 5, “The Lord will hear me when I cry to Him.”  Verse:  “When I called upon Him, the God of my righteousness heard me.”
	[Then, Priest:  “Peace be unto thee.”  Deacon:  “Wisdom!”  And the singing of the Great Prokeimenon, Let my prayer arise (as at the Pre-sanctified Liturgy). – this was the practice at all festive services during the lent.  By analogy with current Annunciation practices, it would not be sung, but immediately the Small litany.]  Small litany.  Exclamation:  For Holy art Thou, O our God.  Trisagion.
	Prokeimenon of the feast, tone 3, “My soul magnifieth the Lord and My spirit rejoiceth in God, My Saviour”. Verse:  “For He hath looked down upon the humility of His Handmaiden, for behold, from henceforth every generation shall call Me blessed.”
	Epistle:  Hebrews #316.
	Alleluia of the feast, tone 8, “Now lettest Thou Thy servant depart in peace, O Master, according to Thy word.”  Verse:  “A light for the enlightening of the gentiles and the glory of Thy people, Israel.”  
	Gospel:  Lk #7.
	Instead of It is truly meet, the verse:  O Theotokos—Virgin, the hope of Christians and heirmos of the feast, In the law.
	Koinonikon of the feast, I will take the cup of salvation.

At the trapeza, xerophagy with wine, but no fish.

Small Compline with the reading of the Great Canon, without prostrations:
	The order of Small Compline is as usual; the Great Canon of St Andrew of Crete is inserted in the customary place.  After Our Father, the kontakion to St Simeon, tone 4.
	Instead of the exclamation Through the prayers, the exclamation O God be merciful unto us.  Then the Prayer of St Ephraim the Syrian with 16 bows (3 prostrations, 12 lesser bows with the words, “O God, cleanse me a sinner”, then one more full prostration).  Then:  Trisagion.  Our Father.  Exclamation:  For Thine.  “Lord, have mercy” (x12).  Prayer O undefiled, untainted and the rest of Small Compline.
</INSTRUCTIONS>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<SAINT Name="The Meeting of our Lord, God, and Saviour Jesus Christ in the Temple" Id="373" Type="7" Cmd="nday != -48" />
<SAINT Name="(The feast of the Meeting of the Lord is observed on Sunday)" Id="" Type="0" Cmd="nday == -48"/>
<SAINT Name="Martyr Tryphon of Campsada near Apamea in Syria (+250)" Id="369" Type="1" Cmd="nday == -48"/>
<SAINT Name="New Martyr Jordan of Trapesunt" Id="" Type="0" />
<SAINT Name="Venerable Martyr Gabriel" Id="" Type="0" />
<SAINT Name="Icon of the Mother of God 'Softening of evil hearts'" Id="" Type="0" />
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 1">
<SAINT Name="Sainte Rencontre (Hypapante) de notre Seigneur" Id="373" Type="7" />
<SAINT Name="St Agathodore" Id="" Type="0" />
<SAINT Name="St Néomartyr Jourdain de Trébizonde" Id="" Type="0" />
<SAINT Name="St Néomartyr Gabriel à Constantinople" Id="" Type="0" />
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<SAINT Name="Сретение Господне" Id="373" Type="7" />
</LANGUAGE>
</DAY>
