<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой праведный Иов"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святой праведный Иов жил за 2000—1500 лет до Рождества Христова, в Северной Аравии, в стране Авситидийской, в земле Уц. Жизнь и страдания его описаны в Библии (Книга Иова). Есть мнение, что Иов приходился племянником Аврааму; был сыном брата Авраама — Нахора. Иов был человеком богобоязненным и благочестивым. Всей душой он был предан Господу Богу и во всем поступал согласно Его воле, удаляясь от всего злого не только в де- лах, но и в мыслях. Господь благословил его земное существова- ние и наделил праведного Иова большим богатством: у него было множество скота и всякого имения. Семь сыновей праведного Иова и три дочери были дружны между собой и собирались на общую трапезу все вместе поочередно у каждого из них. Через каждые семь дней праведный Иов приносил за своих детей жерт- вы Богу, говоря: «Может быть, кто из них согрешил или похулил Бога в сердце своем». За свою справедливость и честность святой Иов был в великом почете у сограждан и имел большое влияние на общественные дела.     Однажды, когда перед Престолом Божиим предстали Святые Ангелы, явился между ними и сатана. Господь Бог спросил сатану, не видел ли он раба Его Иова, мужа праведного и чуждого вся- кого порока. Сатана дерзко отвечал, что недаром богобоязнен Иов — Бог бережет его и умножает его богатства, но если наслать на него несчастья, то он перестанет благословлять Бога. Тогда Господь, желая показать терпение Иова и веру, сказал сатане: «Все, что есть у Иова, Я предаю в твои руки, только самого его не касайся». После этого Иов внезапно лишился всех своих богатств, а потом и всех своих детей. Праведный Иов обратился к Богу и сказал: «Нагим вышел я из чрева матери моей, нагим и возвращусь к матери своей земле. Господь дал, Господь и взял. Да будет Имя Господне благословенно!» И не согрешил Иов перед Господом Богом, и не произнес ни одного неразумного слова.     Когда Ангелы Божий вновь предстали перед Господом и среди них сатана, то диавол сказал, что Иов праведен, пока сам невре- дим. Тогда Господь возвестил: «Я попускаю тебе сделать с ним, что хочешь, только душу его сбереги». После этого сатана поразил праведного Иова лютой болезнью — проказой, которая покрыла его с ног до головы. Страдалец принужден был выселиться из общества людей, сел вне города на куче пепла и глиняным череп- ком скоблил свои гнойные раны. Все друзья и знакомые остави- ли его. Жена&apos; его принуждена была добывать себе пропитание, трудясь и скитаясь из дома в дом. Она не только не поддержи- вала своего мужа в терпении, но думала, что Бог наказывает Иова за какие-либо тайные грехи, плакала, роптала на Бога, уко- ряла и мужа и наконец посоветовала праведному Иову похулить Бога и умереть. Праведный Иов тяжко скорбел, но и в этих стра- даниях остался верен Богу. Он отвечал жене: «Ты говоришь, как одна из безумных. Неужели доброе мы будем принимать от Бога, а злого не будем принимать?» И не согрешил праведный ни в чем перед Богом.    Услышав о несчастиях Иова, три его друга пришли издалека к нему разделить его скорбь. Они считали, что Иов наказан Богом за грехи, и убеждали неповинного ни в чем праведника покаяться. Праведник отвечал, что он страдает не за грехи, но что эти испы- тания посланы ему от Господа по непостижимой для человека Божественной воле. Друзья, однако, не верили и продолжали счи- тать, что Господь поступает с Иовом по закону человеческого воз- мездия, наказывая его за совершенные грехи. В тяжкой душевной скорби праведный Иов обратился с молитвой к Богу, прося Его Самого засвидетельствовать перед ними его невиновность. Тогда Бог явил Себя в бурном вихре и укорил Иова за то, что он пытал- ся проникнуть своим разумом в тайны мироздания и судеб Божи- их. Праведник всем сердцем раскаялся в этих мыслях и сказал: «я ничтожен, отрекаюсь и раскаиваюсь в прахе и пепле». Тогда Господь повелел друзьям Иова обратиться к нему и просить его принести за них жертву, «ибо,—сказал Господь,—только лицо Иова я приму, чтобы не отвергнуть вас за то, что вы говорили обо Мне не так верно, как раб Мой Иов». Иов принес жертву Богу и помо- лился за друзей, и Господь принял его ходатайство, а также воз- вратил праведному Иову здоровье и дал ему вдвое больше того, что он имел прежде. Вместо умерших детей у Иова родилось семь сыновей и три дочери, прекраснее которых не было па земле. Пос- ле перенесенных страданий Иов прожил еще 140 лет (всего же он прожил 248 лет) и видел потомство свое до четвертого рода.    Святой Иов прообразует Господа Иисуса Христа, сошедшего на землю, пострадавшего ради спасения людей, а потом просла- вившегося славным Своим Воскресением.    «Я знаю, — говорил праведный Иов, пораженный проказой,— знаю, что Искупитель мой жив и Он восставит из праха в послед- ний день распадающуюся кожу мою, и я во плоти моей узрю Бога. Я узрю Его сам, мои глаза, не глаза другого увидят Его. Чаяни- ем сего истаивает сердце мое в груди моей!» (Иов 19, 25—27).    «Знайте, что есть суд, на котором оправдается только име- ющий истинную премудрость — страх Господень и истинный ра- зум— удаление от зла».    Святой Иоанн Златоуст говорит: «Нет несчастья человеческого, которого не перенес бы этот муж, твердейший всякого адаманта, испытавший вдруг и голод, и бедность, и болезни, и потерю детей, и лишение богатства, и затем, испытав коварство от жены, оскорб- ления от друзей, нападения от рабов, во всем оказался тверже всякого камня, и притом до Закона и Благодати». 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Бога́тство ви́дѣвъ добродѣ́телей ї҆́ѡвлихъ, ѹ҆кра́сти ко́знствоваше пра́ведныхъ вра́гъ, и҆ растерза́въ сто́лпъ тѣлесѐ, сокро́вище не ѹ҆кра́де дх҃а: ѡ҆брѣ́те бо воѡрꙋже́ннꙋ непоро́чнагѡ дꙋ́шꙋ, мене́ же и҆ ѡ҆бнажи́въ плѣнѝ: предвари́въ ѹ҆́бѡ мѧ̀ пре́жде конца̀, и҆зба́ви мѧ̀ льсти́вагѡ, сп҃се и҆ сп҃си́ мѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="3">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ и҆́стиненъ и҆ првⷣнъ, бг҃очести́въ и҆ непоро́ченъ, ѡ҆сщ҃е́нъ же ꙗ҆́вльсѧ всесла́вне, бж҃їй ѹ҆го́дниче и҆́стинный, просвѣти́лъ є҆сѝ мї́ръ въ терпѣ́нїи твое́мъ, терпѣли́вѣйшїй и҆ до́блѣйшїй: тѣ́мже всѝ бг҃омꙋ́дре па́мѧть твою̀ воспѣва́емъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Saint Job the Righteous"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Saint Job the Righteous lived about 2000-1500 years before the Birth of Christ, in Northern Arabia, in the country of Austidia in the land of Uz. His life and sufferings are recorded in the Bible (Book of Job). There exists an opinion, that Job was by descent a nephew of Abraham, and that he was the son of a brother of Abraham -- Nakhor. Job was a man God-fearing and pious. With all his soul he was devoted to the Lord God and in everything conducted himself in accord with God&apos;s will, refraining from everything evil not only in deeds, but also in thoughts. The Lord blessed his earthly existence and rewarded Righteous Job with great wealth: he had many cattle and all kinds of possessions. Righteous Job&apos;s seven sons and three daughters were amiable amongst themselves and gathered for common repast all together in turns at each of their homes. Every seven days Righteous Job made for his children offerings to God, saying: &quot;If perchance any of them hath sinned or offended God in their heart&quot;. For his justness and honesty Saint Job was held in high esteem by his fellow citizens and he had great influence in public matters. 	One time however, when the Holy Angels did stand before the Throne of God, Satan appeared amongst them. The Lord God asked Satan, whether he had seen His servant Job, a man righteous and without blemish. Satan answered audaciously, that it was not for nothing that Job was God-fearing -- since God was watching over him and multiplying his riches, but if misfortune were sent him, he would then cease to bless God. Then the Lord, wishing to prove Job&apos;s patience and faith, said to Satan: &quot;Everything, that Job hath, I give into thine hand, but only he himself touch not&quot;. After this Job suddenly lost all his wealth, and then also all his children. Righteous Job turned to God and said: &quot;Naked did I emerge from the womb of my mother, and naked shalt I be returned to my mother the earth. The Lord giveth, and the Lord taketh away. Blest be the Name of the Lord!&quot; And thus did Job not sin before the Lord God, nor utter even an unthinking word. 	When the Angels of God again did stand before the Lord and amongst them Satan also, then said the devil, that Job was righteous, since that he himself was without harm. Thereupon declared the Lord: &quot;I permit thee to do with him, what thou wishest, sparing only his soul&quot;. After this Satan inflicted upon Righteous Job an horrid illness, leprous boils, which covered him head to foot. The sufferer was compelled to remove himself from the company of people, he sat outside the city on an heap of ashes and had to scrape at his pussing wounds with an shard of clay. All his friends and acquaintances abandoned him. His wife had to see after her own welfare, toiling and roaming from house to house. She not only did not support her husband with patience, but rather she thought, that God was punishing Job for some kind of secret sins, and she wept, and wailed against God, she reproached also her husband and finally advised Righteous Job to curse God and die. Righteous Job sorrowed grievously, but even in these sufferings he remained faithful to God. He answered his wife: &quot;Thou speakest, like someone hysterical. Shalt we have from God only the good, and have nothing bad?&quot; And Righteous Job did sin in nothing before God. 	Hearing about the misfortunes of Job, three of his friends came afar off to comfort his sorrow. They reckoned, that Job was being punished by God for his sins, and they urged this righteous man though innocent to repent. The righteous one answered, that he was suffering not for sins, but that these tribulations were sent him from the Lord in accord with the Divine Will, which is inscrutable for man. His friends however did not believe him and they continued to think that the Lord was dealing with Job in accord withe the laws obtaining under human standards, thus punishing Job for the committing of sins. In begrieved sorrow of soul Righteous Job turned with a prayer to God, beseeching Him Himself to bear witness before them of his innocence. God thereupon manifested Himself in a tempestuous whirlwind and reproached Job, in that he had tried to penetrate by his reason into the mystery of the world-order and the judgemental-purposes of God. The Righteous Job with all his heart repented himself in these thoughts and said: &quot;I am as nothing, and I foreswear and repent myself in dust and ashes&quot;. The Lord thereupon commanded the friends of Job to have recourse to him in asking him to offer sacrifice for them. &quot;Since, -- said the Lord, -- only the person Job do I accept it of, lest I spurn ye for this, that ye did speak concerning Me not thus rightly, as hath instead My servant Job&quot;. Job offered sacrifice to God for his friends, and the Lord accepted his intercession, and the Lord likewise returned to Righteous Job his health and gave him twice over more than he had previously. In place of his deceased children was born to him seven sons and three daughters, more beautiful than any other in that land. After bearing his sufferings, Job lived yet another 140 years (altogether he lived 248 years) and he lived to see his descendants down to the fourth generation.  	Saint Job prefigures the Lord Jesus Christ, having come down to earth and suffering for the salvation of mankind, and then glorified in His glorious Resurrection.  	&quot;I know, -- said Righteous Job, afflicted with the leprous boils, -- I know, that my Redeemer liveth and He wilt raise up from the dust on the last day my decayed skin, and I in my flesh shalt see God. I shalt see Him myself with mine own eyes, and not through the eyes of some other see Him. In expectation of this, my heart doth jump within my bosom!&quot; (Job 19: 25-27). 	&quot;Know ye, the judgement, in which be justified only those having true wisdom -- the fear of the Lord, and true understanding -- the departing from evil&quot; (Job 28: 28). 	Saint John Chrysostom says: &quot;There was no human misfortune, which this man did not undergo. He was the firmest and most adamant, beset by sudden tribulation by hunger, and by woe, and sickness, and bereft of children, and loss of riches, and then suffering abuse from his wife, insult from his friends, reproach from his servants, and in everything he showed himself more solid than a stone, and a source before the Law also of Grace&quot;.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Seeing the richness of the virtues of Job,/ the enemy of the righteous plotted to steal them;/ yet though he broke down the tower of his body,/ he could not steal the treasure of his spirit;/ for he who, having stripped me naked, took me captive/ found the soul of the blameless one fully armed./ Wherefore, anticipating my need before the end, O Savior,// deliver me from the deceiver and save me.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="3">
Shown to be truthful and righteous, pious, blameless and sanctified, O most glorious one,/ thou true favorite of God, thou hast enlightened the world with thy patience, O most patient and valiant one.// Wherefore, O thou who art divinely wise, we all hymn thy memory.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>