<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой апостол Карп"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
    Святой апостол Карп (из числа 70-ти) — ученик и спутник свя- того апостола Павла. Во 2-м послании к Тимофею апостол упо- минает имя Карпа, в доме которого в Троаде он оставил фелонь и книги (2 Тим. 4, 13). Зная Карпа как человека добродетельного и обладавшего возвышенной чистотой ума, апостол Павел поста- вил его епископом Берии Фракийской. Апостол Карп ходил с про- поведью Евангелия на остров Крит. Здесь его посетил святой Дио- нисий Ареопагит (память 3 октября). В своих воспоминаниях Дио- нисий рассказывает о чудесном видении апостолу Карпу.     Святой апостол Карп скончался мирно в Берии (по другим источникам он принял мученическую, кончину в гонение императо- ра Нерона).     Святой апостол Алфей (из числа 70-ти) происходил из гали- лейского города Капернаума и был отцом апостолов Иакова Ал- феева и Матфея. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
А҆пⷭле ст҃ы́й ка́рпе, молѝ млⷭтиваго бг҃а, да прегрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе пода́стъ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ ѕвѣздꙋ̀ пресвѣ́тлꙋю цр҃ковь всегда̀ стѧжа́ тѧ а҆пⷭле ка́рпе, чꙋде́съ твои́хъ многоподава́нїемъ просвѣща́ема: сп҃сѝ вѣ́рою чтꙋ́щихъ па́мѧть твою̀. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Disciple Carpus"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
	The Holy Disciple Carpus (from the 70) -- was a disciple and companion of the holy Apostle Paul. In the 2nd Epistle to Timothy, the apostle mentions the name Carpus, at the house of whom in Troias he left a phelon and books (2 Tim. 4: 13). Knowing Carpus as a man of virtue and possessing a mind of lofty purity, the Apostle Paul made him bishop of Thracian Bereia. The disciple Carpus went preaching the Gospel to the island of Crete. Here he encountered Saint Dionysios the Areopagite (Comm. 3 October). In his reminiscences Dionysios recounts about a miraculous vision to the disciple Carpus.  	The holy disciple Carpus died peacefully at Bereia (according to other histories he received a martyr&apos;s end during the persecution under the emperor Nero).  	The Holy Disciple Alphaeus (of the 70) came from the Galilean city of Capernaum and was the father of the Apostles James Alphaeus and Matthew. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
O holy apostle Carpus/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Illumined by the great outpouring of thy miracles,/ the Church hath ever acquired thee as an all-radiant star, O Apostle Carpus.// Save those who honor thy memory with faith.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>