<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Кирилл, архиепископ Александрийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святитель Кирилл, архиепископ Александрийский, выдающий- ся борец за Православие и великий учитель Церкви, происходил из знатной и благочестивой христианской семьи. Он изучил свет- ские науки, в том числе и философию, но больше всего стремился приобрести знание Священного Писания и истин христианской ве- ры. В юности святой Кирилл поступил в скит святого Макария в Нитрийских горах, где пробыл шесть лет. Патриарх Александрий- ский Феофил (385—412) посвятил его в сан диакона, причислил к клиру и, видя его одаренность, поручил произносить проповеди.    По смерти Патриарха Феофила святой Кирилл единодушно был избран на патриарший престол Александрийской Церкви и возглавил борьбу с распространившейся в Александрии ересью Новациана, который учил, что христиане, отпавшие во время гоне- ний от Церкви, не могут быть вновь приняты ею.    Святитель Кирилл, видя безрезультатность увещания еретиков, добился их изгнания из Александрии. Более опасными для Церкви являлись иудеи, неоднократно производившие возмущения, сопро- вождавшиеся зверскими убийствами христиан. Святителю приш- лось долго бороться с этим. Чтобы покончить и с остатками язы- чества, святитель изгнал бесов из древнего языческого капища и устроил на том месте храм. В него были перенесены мощи святых бессеребреников Кира и Иоанна. Еще более трудная борьба пред- стояла святителю с возникшей несторианской ересью.    Несторий, пресвитер Антиохийской Церкви, в 428 году был из- бран на Константинопольскую кафедру и получил возможность ши- роко распространять свое еретическое учение, направленное против догмата о неслитном соединении двух естеств в Лице Господа Иису- са Христа. Несторий называл Матерь Божию не Богородицей, а Христородицей, подразумевая, что она родила не Бога, а человека Христа. Святой Патриарх Кирилл неоднократно писал Несторию и разъяснял его заблуждения, но тот продолжал упорствовать. Тогда святитель направил клиру Константинопольской Церкви по- слания против несторианства, а святому благоверному царю Фео- досию Младшему (408—450) —-два трактата с обличением ереси. Писал святитель Кирилл и другим Церквам — Папе Целестину и другим Патриархам, а также инокам некоторых монастырей, пре- дупреждая о возникновении опасной ереси.     Несторий начал открытое гонение на православных. В его при- сутствии один из его приверженцев, епископ Дорофей, с церков- ной кафедры провозгласил анафему тем,, кто именует Пресвятую Деву Марию Богородицей.     Несторий ненавидел святителя Кирилла и в своих доносах воз- водил на него всякие клеветы и измышления, называя еретиком. Святитель всеми силами продолжал защищать Православие. По- ложение обострилось настолько, что возникла необходимость в созыве Вселенского Собора, который открылся в 431 году в городе Ефесе. На Собор прибыло 200 епископов от всех Христианских Церквей. Несторий, ожидая прибытия епископа Антиохийского Иоанна и других сирийских епископов, не соглашался на открытие Собора. Но отцы Собора начали заседание. Председательствовал Александрийский Патриарх, святитель Кирилл. Рассмотрев уче- ние Нестория, Собор осудил его как ересь. Несторий не подчинил- ся Собору, а прибывший епископ Иоанн открыл беззаконный со- бор, который провозгласил святителя Кирилла еретиком. Смута увеличивалась. По повелению императора архиепископы Кирилл Александрийский и Мемнон Ефесский были заключены в тюрьму. Этой же мере подвергся и Несторий.     Вскоре святители Кирилл и Мемнон были освобождены, и заседания Собора продолжались. Несторий, не подчинившийся определению Собора, был лишен сана и по повелению императора сослан в отдаленное место Сасим, в Ливийской пустыне, где он скончался в тяжелых мучениях: его язык, хуливший Матерь Бо- жию, постигла кара—-в нем завелись черви. Определение Ефес- ского Собора подписали также епископ Иоанн Антиохийский и остальные сирийские епископы.     Святитель Кирилл управлял Александрийской Церковью 32 го- да: к концу его плодотворной деятельности паства была очищена от еретиков. Мягко и осторожно святитель Кирилл подходил к тем, кто по своей простоте и неведению впадал в ложное мудрование. К одному старцу, подвижнику высокой жизни, неправильно мыс- лившему о ветхозаветном праведнике архиерее Мелхиседеке как о Сыне Божием, святитель обратился с просьбой помолиться Гос- поду, чтобы Он открыл,, как правильно мыслить об этом правед- нике. Через три дня старец пришел к святителю Кириллу и сказал, что Господь открыл ему, что Мелхиседек был архиереем и обык- новенным человеком.     Святитель Кирилл сумел преодолеть предубеждение к памяти великого святителя Иоанна Златоуста ( { 407; память 13 ноября).                                      •• Патриарх Александрийский Феофил, родной дядя святителя, был противником святителя Иоанна и председательствовал на осудив-  шем его Соборе. Святитель Кирилл с молодых лет находился в  окружении противников Иоанна Златоуста и невольно приобрел  против него предубеждение. Преподобный Исидор Пелусиот (+ ок. 436—-440; память 4 февраля) неоднократно писал святителю Ки-  риллу и побуждал его внести имя великого отца Церкви в диптих святых, но святитель Кирилл не соглашался. Но однажды он уви- дел во сне дивный храм, в котором находилась Божия Матерь, окруженная сонмом Ангелов и святых, в числе которых стоял и святитель Иоанн Златоуст. Когда святитель Кирилл хотел при- близиться к Пресвятой Владычице и воздать Ей поклонение, свя- титель Иоанн Златоуст не допустил его. Матерь Божия просила святителя Иоанна простить святого Кирилла, согрешившего про- тив него по неведению. Увидев, что святой Иоанн медлит, Матерь Божия сказала: «Прости его для Меня, ибо он много потрудился для Моей чести, прославил Меня среди людей и наименовал Бо- городицей». Святитель Иоанн отвечал: «По Твоему, Владычице, ходатайству прощаю его», — и затем с любовью обнял и облобы- зал святителя Кирилла.     Святитель Кирилл раскаялся в том, что держал гнев против великого угодника Божия. Созвав всех египетских епископов, он совершил торжественное празднование в честь святителя Иоанна Златоуста.     Скончался святитель Кирилл в 444 году, оставив много творе- ний. Особенно следует отметить Толкования на Евангелия от Луки, от Иоанна, Послания апостола Павла к Коринфянам и Евреям, а также апологию в защиту христианства против импе- ратора Юлиана Отступника (361—363). Огромное значение име- ют пять книг против Нестория, труд о Пресвятой Троице, под названием «Сокровище», написанный против Ария и Евномия, и два догматических сочинения о Пресвятой Троице, отличающие- ся точностью изложения Православного учения о Исхождении Святого Духа. Сочинение против антропоморфизма написано свя- тителем Кириллом для некоторых египтян, которые по неведению представляли Бога в человеческом образе. В числе творений свя- тителя Кирилла имеются и «Беседы», среди которых особенно трогательно и назидательно «Слово об исходе души», помещенное в славянской «Следованной Псалтири». 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Правосла́вїѧ наста́вниче, бл҃гоче́стїѧ ѹ҆чи́телю и҆ чистоты̀, вселе́нныѧ свѣти́льниче, а҆рхїере́євъ бг҃одꙋхнове́нное ѹ҆добре́нїе. кѷрї́лле премꙋ́дре, ѹ҆че́ньми твои́ми всѧ҄ просвѣти́лъ є҆сѝ, цѣвни́це дх҃о́внаѧ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
Бе́зднꙋ на́мъ ѹ҆че́нїй бг҃осло́вїѧ и҆сточи́лъ є҆сѝ ꙗ҆́вѣ, ѿ и҆стѡ́чникъ сп҃совыхъ, є҆́рєси погрꙋжа́ющꙋю бл҃же́нне кѷрї́лле, и҆ ста́до невреди́мо ѿ треволне́нїй сп҃са́ющꙋю: страна́мъ бо всѣ҄мъ наста́вникъ прпⷣбне, ꙗ҆́кѡ бж҃е́ствєннаѧ ꙗ҆влѧ́ѧ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Cyril, ArchBishop of Alexandria"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Cyril, ArchBishop of Alexandria, a distinguished champion of Orthodoxy and a great teacher of the Church, came from an illustrious and pious Christian family. He studied the secular sciences, among which number also was philosophy, but most of all he strove to acquire knowledge of the Holy Scriptures and the truths of the Christian faith. In his youth Saint Cyril entered the skete-monastery of Saint Makarios in the Nitreia hills, where he stayed for six years. The Patriarch of Alexandria Theophilos (385-412) ordained him to the dignity of deacon, numbered him among the clergy and, seeing his giftedness, entrusted him to preach. 	Upon the death of Patriarch Theophilos, Saint Cyril was unanimously chosen to the patriarchal throne of the Alexandrian Church. He headed the struggle against the spread in Alexandria of the Novatian heresy, which taught that a Christian, having fallen away from the Church during time of persecution, is not able to be received back by it again. 	Saint Cyril, seeing the futility of admonishing the heretics, sought their expulsion from Alexandria. The Jews appeared a greater danger for the Church, repeatedly making riots, accompanied by the brutal killing of Christians. The saint long contended with them. And to end with the remaining paganism, the saint cast out devils from an ancient pagan temple and built on the place a church. Into it were transferred the relics of the holy Unmercenaries Cyrus and John. Still more difficult a struggle awaited the saint with the emergence of the Nestorian heresy. 	Nestorius, a presbyter of the Antioch Church, was chosen in 428 to the Constantinople cathedra and therein got the chance to widely spread about his heretical teaching, directed against the dogma about the uncommingled union of two natures in the Person of the Lord Jesus Christ. Nestorius called the Mother of God not the Bogoroditsa (Theotokos or &quot;Birth-giver of God&quot;), but rather Khristoroditsa (Christotokos or &quot;Birthgiver of Christ&quot;), implying that she gave birth not to God, but only to the man Christ. The holy Patriarch Cyril repeatedly wrote to Nestorius and pointed out his error,  but Nestorius continued to persevere in it. Then the saint sent out epistles against Nestorianism to the clergy of the Constantinople Church and to the holy nobleborn emperor Theodosius the Younger (408-450) -- two treatises with a denunciation of the heresy. Saint Cyril wrote also to other Churches -- to Pope Celestine and to the other Patriarchs, and even to monks of several monasteries, warning about the emergence of a dangerous heresy. 	Nestorius started an open persecution against the Orthodox. In his presence one of his partisans, bishop Dorotheos,  pronounced from the church cathedra an anathema for anyone who would call the MostHoly Virgin Mary the Bogoroditsa (Theotokos). 	Nestorius hated Saint Cyril and brought out against him every kind of slander and fabrication, calling him an heretic. The saint with all his powers continued to defend Orthodoxy. The situation became so aggravated, that it became necessary to convene an OEcumenical Council, which opened in the year 431 in the city of Ephesus. At the Council arrived 200 bishops from all the Christian Churches. Nestorius, awaiting the arrival of the bishop of Antioch John and other Syrian bishops, did not agree to the opening of the Council. But the fathers of the Council began the sessions. The Alexandrian Patriarch Saint Cyril presided. Having examined the teaching of Nestorius, the Council condemned him as an heretic. Nestorius did not submit to the Council, and the arriving bishop John opened a &quot;robber council&quot;, which decreed Saint Cyril an heretic. The unrest increased. By order of the emperor, Patriarch Cyril of Alexandria and Archbishop Memnon of Ephesus were locked in prison. And in this measure, Nestorius also was deposed. 	Soon Saints Cyril and Memnon were freed, and the sessions of the Council continued. Nestorius, not submitting himself to the determinations of the Council, was deprived of priestly rank and by order of the emperor sent to the faraway place Sasim in the Libean wilderness, where he died in grievous torments: his tongue, having blasphemed the Mother of God, was overtaken by punishment -- in it there developed worms. Even Bishop John of Antioch and the remaining Syrian bishops signed the decretals of the Ephesus Council. 	Saint Cyril guided the Alexandrian Church for 32 years: towards the end of his abundant activity the flock was cleansed of heretics. Gently and cautiously Saint Cyril approached towards anyone, who by their own simpleness and lack of knowledge fell into false wisdom. To a certain elder, an ascetic of profound life, -- who incorrectly considered the Old Testament Righteous HighPriest Melchisedek to be the Son of God, -- Saint Cyril turned with a request to pray to the Lord so that He should reveal, correctly how to consider that righteous one. After three days the elder came to Saint Cyril and said, that the Lord revealed to him, that Melchisedek was high-priest and a mere man. 	Saint Cyril learned to overcome his prejudice against the memory of the great Sainted-hierarch John Chrysostomos (Zlatoust&apos;) (+ 407, Comm. 13 November). The Patriarch of Alexandria Theophilos, by birth an uncle of the saint, was an antagonist of Sainted John, and presided in a council in judgement of him. Saint Cyril from his youthful years found himself thus in a circle antagonistic to John Chrysostom and involuntarily acquired prejudice against him. The Monk Isidoros Pelusiotes (+ c. 436-440, Comm. 4February) repeatedly wrote to Saint Cyril and urged him to include the name of the great father of the Church into the diptych-list of the saints, but Saint Cyril would not agree. But once in a dream he saw a wondrous temple, in which was present the Mother of God surrounded by an host of Angels and saints, in which number stood also Saint John Chrysostom. When Saint Cyril wanted to approach the MostHoly Lady and offer to Her veneration, Saint John Chrysostom would not let him. The Mother of God asked Saint John to forgive Saint Cyril, for having sinned against him through ignorance. Seeing that Saint John hesitated, the Mother of God said: &quot;Forgive him for Me, since he hath laboured much for My honour, and hath glorified Me among the people calling Me the Mother of God, the Theotokos Bogoroditsa&quot;. Saint John answered: &quot;By Thy intercession, Lady, I do forgive him&quot;, -- and then with love he hugged and embraced Saint Cyril. 	Saint Cyril repented himself that he had maintained anger against the great saint of God. Having convened all the Egyptian bishops, he made a solemn festal celebration in honour of Sainted John Chrysostom.  	Saint Cyril died in the year 444, leaving behind many works. In particular ought to be mentioned: Commentaries -- On the Gospel of Luke, On the Gospel of John, On the Epistles of the Apostle Paul to the Corinthians and to the Hebrews; also an Apologia in Defence of Christianity against the Emperor Julian the Apostate (361-363). Of vast significance are: Five Books against Nestorius; a work About the MostHoly Trinity; -- under the title &quot;Thesaurus&quot;, written against Arius and Eunomios; also two dogmatic compositions About the MostHoly Trinity, -- distinguished by a precise exposition of the Orthodox teaching about the Procession of the Holy Spirit. Saint Cyril wrote a composition -- Against Anthropomorphism, for several Egyptians, who through ignorance depicted God in human form. Amidst a number of works by Saint Cyril are also the &quot;Discussions&quot;, among which is the moving and edifying &quot;Discourse on the Exodus of the Soul&quot;, inserted in the Slavonic &quot;Following Psalter&quot;. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
O instructor of Orthodoxy, teacher of piety and purity,/ beacon for the whole world, divinely inspired adornment of hierarchs./ O most wise Cyril by thy doctrines thou hast illumined all.// O harp of the Spirit, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
Thou hast manifestly poured forth upon us an abyss of doctrines of theology/ from the well-springs of the Savior,/ drowning heresies and saving thy flock unharmed by threefold waves, O blessed Cyril;// for thou art shown to be a guide for all lands, O venerable one, revealing things divine.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>