<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Дорофей"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Священномученик Дорофей в период гонений на христиан при императоре Диоклитиане (284—305]^ был епископом города Тира Финикийского. По слову Евангелия (Мф. 10, 23), святитель уда- лился из Тира и скрылся от мучителей. В царствование святого Константина Великого (306—337, память 21 мая) он вернулся в Тир, вновь занял епископский престол и управлял паствой более 50 лет, обратив в христианство множество язычников. Когда Юли- ан Отступник (361—363) начал открыто преследовать христиан, святителю Дорофею было уже более 100 лет. Он удалился из Тира в Мизийский город Уд (ныне Варна). Там его схватили придвор- ные императора. За отказ принести жертву идолам святого старца стали жестоко истязать, и под пыткой он предал душу свою Гос- поду (I около 362 года в возрасте 107 лет).    Священномученику Дорофею некоторые приписывают составле- ние «Синопсиса» — собрания сказаний, а также житий святых про- роков и апостолов. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="5">
Добродѣ́тельми сїѧ́ѧ, и҆ бж҃е́ственными ѹ҆че́нїи па́че со́лнца, и҆ страда́нїи бл҃же́нне ѡ҆блиста́лъ є҆сѝ: просвѣти́лъ є҆сѝ зе́млю дѡроѳе́е, ѿгна́въ мглꙋ̀ многобо́жїѧ, и҆ лю҄тыѧ є҆́рєси. сегѡ̀ ра́ди па́мѧть твою̀ свѣ́тлѡ пра́зднꙋемъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="PriestMartyr Dorotheos"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
	The PriestMartyr Dorotheos was bishop of the Phoenician city of Tyre, during the time of the persecution against Christians under the emperor Diocletian (284-305). Heeding the words of the Gospel (Mt. 10: 23), the saint withdrew from Tyre and hid away from the persecutors. He returned to Tyre during the reign of Saint Constantine the Great (306-337, Comm. 21 May), again occupying the bishop&apos;s throne he guided his flock for more than 50 years, and converted many of the pagans to Christianity. When the emperor Julian the Apostate (361-363) began openly to persecute Christians, Saint Dorotheos was already over 100 years old. He withdrew from Tyre to the Myzean city of Udum (present day Bulgarian Varna). Delegates of the emperor arrested him there. For his refusal to offer sacrifice to idols they began cruelly to torture the holy elder, and under torture he gave up his soul to the Lord (+ c. year 362, at age 107). 	To Saint Dorotheos is ascribed by some the compiling of a work, &quot;The Synopsis&quot;, a collection of sayings, and including lives of the holy prophets and apostles.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
As thou didst share in the ways of the apostles/ and didst occupy their throne,/ thou didst find thine activity to be a passage to divine vision,/ O divinely inspired one./ Wherefore, ordering the word of truth,/ thou didst suffer for the Faith even to the shedding of thy blood.// O hieromartyr Dorotheas, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="5">
Resplendent with virtues brighter than the sun/ and with thy sufferings, O blessed Dorotheus,/ thou didst shine forth and illumine the land,/ dispelling the darkness of polytheism and vile heresy./ Wherefore, we celebrate thy memory with splendor.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>