<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Виссарион, чудотворец Египетский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Преподобный Виссарион, чудотворец Египетский, по происхож- дению египтянин, еще в молодости крестился и вел строгую жизнь, стараясь сохранить данную ему при Крещении благодать. Желая узнать ближе монашескую жизнь, он предпринял путешествие по святым местам, был в Иерусалиме, посетил преподобного Гера- сима (память 4 марта) в Иорданской пустыне, видел и других пустынников, поучаясь у всех правилам иноческой жизни. По воз- вращении он принял постриг и стал учеником преподобного Иси- дора Пелусиота (память 4 февраля). Святой Виссарион принял на себя обет безмолвия, вкушал пищу один раз в неделю, а ино- гда оставался без пищи и питья по 40 дней. Был случай, когда преподобный, погрузившись в молитву, стоял неподвижно 40 дней и 40 ночей без пищи и сна.    От Бога преподобный Виссарион получил дар чудотворений: когда его ученику в пути сильно захотелось пить, он усладил горь- кую воду; по его молитве Господь посылал на землю дождь, он мог, как по суше, переходить реки; одним словом изгонял бесов, но делал это прикровенно, чтобы избежать славы. Смирение его было так велико, что, когда однажды священник велел одному из насель- ников скита, впавшему в грех, выйти из храма, вместе с ним вышел и преподобный со словами: «и я грешен». Спал преподобный Висса- рион только стоя или сидя. Большую часть жизни святой провел под открытым небом в молитвенном уединении. Мирно отошел ко Господу, достигнув глубокой старости. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е ѻ҆тє́цъ на́шихъ, творѧ́й при́снѡ съ на́ми по твое́й кро́тости, не ѡ҆ста́ви млⷭть твою̀ ѿ на́съ, но мл҃твами и҆́хъ въ ми́рѣ ѹ҆пра́ви живо́тъ на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Вы́шнихъ си́лъ подража́въ прпⷣбне, ѡ҆́бразомъ пти́цъ житїѐ пожи́лъ є҆сѝ: вре́мєннаѧ въ забы́тїи положи́въ, непреста́ннымъ жела́нїемъ влеко́мь къ нбⷭнымъ добро́тамъ хрⷭта̀ цр҃ѧ̀, до́ндеже тогѡ̀ дости́глъ є҆сѝ висарїѡ́не. молѝ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Bessarion, Wonderworker of Egypt"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Bessarion, Wonderworker of Egypt, by descent an Egyptian, was baptised while still in his youth and he led a strict life, striving to preserve the grace given him during Baptism. Seeking to become more closely acquainted with the monastic life, he undertook a journey to the holy places, -- he was in Jerusalem, he visited the Monk Gerasimos (Comm. 4 March) in the Jordanian wilderness, he viewed other monastic wilderness-monasteries, and assimilated all the rules of monastic life. Upon his return, he accepted monastic tonsure and became a disciple of the Monk Isidor Pelusiotes (Comm. 4February). Saint Bessarion took upon himself a vow of silence, he partook of food only once a week, and sometimes he remained without food or drink for 40 days. There was an instance when the monk, immersed in prayer, stood motionless for 40 days and 40 nights without food or sleep. 	The Monk Bessarion received from God the gift of wonderworking: when on a journey his disciple was strongly beset by thirst, he sweetened bitter water; by his prayer the Lord sent rain upon the earth, and he could as though on dry land cross a river; with but a single word he cast out devils, but he did this privately to avoid glory. His humility was so great, that when one time a priest ordered someone from the skete settlement to leave church for having fallen into sin, together with him went also the monk with the words: &quot;I too am a sinner&quot;. The Monk Bessarion slept only standing or sitting. A large portion of the life of the saint was spent under the open sky in prayerful solitude. He peacefully expired to the Lord, having reached old age.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O God of our fathers,/ deal with us ever according to Thy meekness./ Deprive us not of Thy mercy,/ but through their supplications// direct our life in peace.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Emulating the powers on high,/ by example thou didst live the life of the birds, O venerable one;/ and putting transitory things from thy mind,/ led to the heavenly beauties of Christ the King by thy constant desire,/ thou didst come even unto Him.// O Bessarion, entreat Him unceasingly in behalf of us all!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>