<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Лев I Великий, папа Римский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святитель Лев I Великий, папа Римский (440—461), получил прекрасное и разностороннее образование, которое открывало пе- ред ним блестящую светскую карьеру. Однако, стремясь к духов- ной жизни, он избрал иной путь и стал архидиаконом при святом папе Сиксте III (432—440), а после его смерти был избран, в сен- тябре 440 года, папой Римской Церкви. Это было трудное для Церкви время, когда еретики осаждали твердыню Православия своими соблазнительными лжеучениями. Святитель Лев умел сов- мещать пастырскую мягкость и доброту с несокрушимой твердо- стью в вопросах вероисповедания. Именно он явился основным за- щитником Православия против ереси Евтихия и Диоскора, учив- ших об одном естестве в Господе Иисусе Христе, и ереси Нестория. Он употребил всё свое влияние для того, чтобы умирить смущае- мую еретиками Церковь и своими посланиями к святым Константи- нопольским царям Феодосию II (408—450) и Маркиану (450—457) деятельно способствовал созыву IV Вселенского Халкидонского Собора (451) для осуждения ереси монофизитов. На Соборе, где присутствовало 630 епископов, было оглашено послание святителя Льва к уже почившему тогда святителю Флавиану, Патриарху Кон- стантинопольскому (447—449), пострадавшему за Православную веру от разбойничьего Ефесского собора в 449 году. В послании святителя Льва было изложено Православное учение о двух есте- ствах в Господе Иисусе Христе. С учением этим согласились все присутствовавшие на Соборе епископы. Еретики Евтихий и Диос- кор были отлучены от Церкви. Святитель Лев явился также защит- ником своего отечества от натиска варваров. В 452 году он силою своего слова удержал от разорения Италии грозного предводителя гуннов Аттилу, а в 455 году, когда предводитель вандалов Гензе- рих вторгся в Рим, он сумел убедить его не предавать город раз- рушению, не жечь зданий и не проливать крови. Святитель Лев до- жил до глубокой старости. Он заранее знал о своей смерти и при- готовил себя теплой молитвой и добрыми делами к переходу из этого мира в вечность.     Он умер в 461 году и был погребен в Риме, в Ватиканском со- боре. Его литературное и Богословское наследие состоит из 96 про- поведей и 143 посланий, из которых самое знаменитое — к святи- телю Флавиану. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Правосла́вїѧ наста́вниче, бл҃гоче́стїѧ ѹ҆чи́телю и҆ чистоты̀, вселе́нныѧ свѣти́льниче, а҆рхїере́євъ бг҃одꙋхнове́нное ѹ҆добре́нїе. львѐ премꙋ́дре, ѹ҆че́ньми твои́ми всѧ҄ просвѣти́лъ є҆сѝ, цѣвни́це дх҃о́внаѧ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
На прⷭто́лѣ сла́вне сщ҃е́нства сѣ́дъ, и҆ львѡ́въ ѹ҆ста̀ слове́сныхъ загради́въ, догма́ты бг҃одꙋхнове́нными чⷭтны́ѧ трⷪцы ѡ҆зари́лъ є҆сѝ свѣ́тъ бг҃оразꙋ́мїѧ твоемꙋ̀ ста́дꙋ. сегѡ̀ ра́ди просла́вилсѧ є҆сѝ ꙗ҆́кѡ бж҃е́ственный таи́нникъ бж҃їѧ бл҃года́ти. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Leo I the Great, Pope of Rome"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Leo I the Great, Pope of Rome (440-461), received an exceedingly fine and diverse education, which opened for him the possibility of an excellent worldly career. But his yearning was in the spiritual life, and so he chose the different path of becoming an archdeacon under holy Pope Sixtus III (432-440) -- after whose death Saint Leo in turn was chosen as Pope of the Roman Church, in September 440. These were difficult times for the Church, when heretics besieged the bulwarks of Orthodoxy with their tempting false-teachings. Saint Leo combined within himself a pastoral solicitude and goodness, together with an unshakable firmness in questions of the confession of the faith. He was in particular one of the basic defenders of Orthodoxy against the heresies of Eutykhios and Dioskoros -- who taught that there was only one nature in the Lord Jesus Christ, and he was a defender also against the heresy of Nestorius. He exerted all his influence to put an end to the unrest by the heretics in the Church, and by his missives to the holy Constantinople emperors Theodosius II (408-450) and Marcian (450-457) he actively promoted the convening of the Fourth OEcumenical Council, at Chalcedon in 451, for condemning the heresy of the Monophysites. At this OEcumenical Council at Chalcedon, at which 630 bishops were present, there was proclaimed a missive of Saint Leo to the then already deceased Sainted Flavian, Patriarch of Constantinople (447-449). Saint Flavian had suffered for Orthodoxy under the Ephesus &quot;Robber Council&quot; in the year 449. In the letter of Saint Leo was posited the Orthodox teaching about the two natures [the Divine and the human] in the Lord Jesus Christ. And with this teaching all the bishops present at the Council were in agreement. The heretics Eutykhios and Dioskoros were excommunicated from the Church. 	Saint Leo was likewise a defender of his fatherland against the incursions of barbarians. In the year 452, by the persuasive power of his word, he stopped a pillaging of Italy by the dreadsome leader of the Huns, Attila. And again in the year 455, when the leader of the Vandals [a Germanic tribe], Henzerich, turned towards Rome, he boldly persuaded him not to pillage the city, burn buildings, nor spill blood. He knew about his death beforehand and he prepared himself by ardent prayer and good deeds, for the passing over from this world into eternity. 	He died in the year 461 and was buried at Rome, in the Vatican cathedral. His literary and theological legacy is comprised of 96 sermons and 143 letters -- of which the best known is his missive to Saint Flavian.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
O instructor of Orthodoxy, teacher of piety and purity,/ beacon for the whole world, divinely inspired adornment of hierarchs./ O most wise Leo by thy doctrines thou hast illumined all.// O harp of the Spirit, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Seated upon the throne of the priesthood,/ O glorious one, and having shut the mouths of the noetic lions,/ with the divinely inspired dogmas of the worshipful Trinity/ thou didst shed upon thy flock the light of the knowledge of God.// Wherefore, thou hast been glorified as a divine initiate of the mysteries of the grace of God.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>