<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой апостол Иуда"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святой апостол Иуда, из числа 12-ти учеников Христовых, про- исходил из рода царя Давида и Соломона, был сыном праведного Иосифа Обручника от его первой жены. Святой апостол Иоанн Богослов в своем Евангелии пишет: «Ни братья бо Его вероваху в Него» (Ин. 7, 5). Святитель Феофилакт, архиепископ Болгарский, объясняет эти слова так: в начале зем- ного служения Господа Иисуса Христа сыновья Иосифа, в том числе и Иуда,, не верили в Его Божественную сущность. Предание указывает, что, когда праведный Иосиф Обручник, возвратившись из Египта, стал делить между сыновьями принадлежавшую ему землю, он пожелал выделить часть и Христу Спасителю, рожден- ному преестественно и нетленно от Пречистой Девы Марии. Братья воспротивились этому, и только старший из них, Иаков, принял Христа Иисуса в совместное владение своей долей и за это был назван братом Господним. Позднее Иуда поверил во Хри- ста Спасителя как ожидаемого Мессию, всем сердцем обратился к Нему и был избран Им в число ближайших 12-ти учеников. Но, помня свой грех, апостол Иуда считал себя недостойным назы- ваться братом Божиим и в своем соборном послании именует себя лишь братом Иакова. Святой апостол Иуда имел и другие имена: евангелист Матфей называет его «Леввеем, прозванным Фаддеем» (Мф. 10, 3), святой евангелист Марк тоже называет его Фаддеем (Мк. 3, 18), а в Дея- ниях святых апостолов он упоминается под именем Варсавы (Де- ян. 15, 22). В то время это было в обычае. По Вознесении Господа Иисуса Христа апостол Иуда отпра- вился с проповедью Евангелия. Он распространял веру во Христа сначала в Иудее, Галилее, Самарии и Идумее, а затем — в стра- нах Аравии, Сирии и Месопотамии и, наконец, пришел в город Эдессу. Здесь он завершил то, что не было закончено его предше- ственником, апостолом из числа 70-ти, Фаддеем. Сохранилось изве- стие, что святой апостол Иуда ходил с проповедью в Персию и оттуда написал на греческом языке свое соборное послание, в кратких словах которого заключено много глубоких истин. Оно содержит догматическое учение о Святой Троице, о воплощении Господа Иисуса Христа, о различии Ангелов добрых и злых, о бу- дущем Страшном Суде. В нравственном отношении апостол убеж- дает верующих беречь себя от плотской нечистоты, быть исправ- ными в своих должностях, молитве, вере и любви, заблудших обра- щать на путь спасения, охранять себя от учений еретиков. Апо- стол Иуда учит, что недостаточно только веры во Христа, необхо- димы еще и добрые дела,, свойственные христианскому учению. Святой апостол Иуда мученически скончался около 80-го года в Армении, в городе Арате, где он был распят на кресте и пронзен стрелами.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Хрⷭто́ва тѧ̀ сро́дника, ѽ ї҆ꙋ́до, вѣ́дꙋще, и҆ мч҃нка тве́рда, сщ҃е́ннѡ восхвалѧ́емъ, пре́лесть попра́вша, и҆ вѣ́рꙋ соблю́дша: тѣ́мже дне́сь всест҃ꙋ́ю твою̀ па́мѧть пра́зднꙋюще, грѣхѡ́въ разрѣше́нїе мл҃твами твои́ми прїе́млемъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Па́ѵлꙋ ꙗ҆́вльсѧ собесѣ́дникъ а҆пⷭле, съ си́мъ на́мъ про́повѣдь возвѣсти́лъ є҆сѝ бж҃е́ственныѧ бл҃года́ти, тайноглаго́льниче ї҆ꙋ́до бл҃же́нне. сегѡ̀ ра́ди вопїе́мъ тѝ: не преста́й молѧ́сѧ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Тве́рдымъ ѹ҆мо́мъ и҆збра́нъ ѹ҆ч҃нкъ ты̀ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ, и҆ сто́лпъ неѡбори́мь це́ркве хрⷭто́вы, ꙗ҆зы́кѡмъ проповѣ́далъ є҆сѝ сло́во хрⷭто́во, вѣ́ровати, глаго́лѧ, во є҆ди́но бж҃ество̀: ѿ негѡ́же просла́вивсѧ, прїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ да́ръ и҆сцѣле́нїй, цѣли́ти недꙋ́ги притека́ющымъ къ тебѣ̀, а҆пⷭле ї҆ꙋ́до всехва́льне. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Apostle Jude"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Apostle Jude, among the rank of the 12 disciples of Christ, is descended from the lineage of King David and Solomon, and was the son of Righteous Joseph the Affianced from his first wife. 	The Holy Apostle John the Theologian writes in his Gospel: &quot;For none of his brethren believe on Him&quot; (Jn. 7, 5). Sainted Theophilact, ArchBishop of Bulgaria, explains these words thus: at the beginning of the worldly ministry of the Lord Jesus Christ -- the sons of Joseph, among whose number was Jude, did not believe in His Divine essence. The tradition relates that when Righteous Joseph the Affianced, having returned from Egypt, began to divide among his sons the worldly things belonging to him, he wanted to alot part also to Christ the Saviour, born miraculously and incorruptibly from the All-Pure Virgin Mary. The brothers were opposed to this and only the eldest of them, James, accepted Christ Jesus in a joint ownership of his allotment, and for this he was termed Brother of the Lord. Later on Jude believed in Christ the Saviour as the awaited Messiah, and with all his heart he turned to Him and was chosen by Him into the number of the closest 12 disciples. But mindful of his sin, the Apostle Jude considered himself unworthy to be termed a brother with God and in his own soborno-catholic Epistle he calls himself merely the brother of James. 	The Holy Apostle Jude also had other names: the Evangelist Matthew terms him &quot;Levi, nicknamed Thaddeus&quot; (Mt. 10, 3). The Holy Evangelist Mark also calls him Thaddeus (Mk. 3, 18), and in the Acts of the Holy Apostles he is mentioned under the name Barsaba (Acts 15, 22). This was customary at that time.  	After the Ascension of the Lord Jesus Christ, the Apostle Jude set off preaching the Gospel. He propagated the faith in Christ at first in Judea, Galilee, Samaria and Idumeia, and later -- in the lands of Arabia, Syria and Mesopotamia, and finally he went to the city of Edessa. Here he finished that which was not completed by his predecessor, the disciple from the 70 -- Thaddeus. There is preserved an account, that the Holy Apostle Jude went preaching to Persia and from there wrote in the Greek language his soborno-catholic Epistle, in the brief wording of which consisted much profound truth. It contained dogmatic teaching about the Holy Trinity, about the Incarnation of the Lord Jesus Christ, about the separation of Angels good and bad, and about the Dread Last-Judgement. In its moral content the Apostle urges believers to guard themselves against fleshly impurity, to be diligent in their obligations in prayer, faith and love, to convert the lost to the way of salvation, and to guard themselves from the teachings of heretics. The Apostle Jude taught that faith alone in Christ is not sufficient, good works also are necessary, the evidence to Christian teaching. 	The Holy Apostle Jude died a martyr about the year 80 in Armenia in the city of Arata, where he was crucified on a cross and pierced by arrows.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Knowing thee to be the kinsman of the Christ/ and a steadfast martyr, O Jude,/ with sanctity we praise thee/ who trampled falsehood underfoot and preserved the Faith./ Wherefore, celebrating thy most holy memory today,// through thy supplications we receive remission of sins.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
As one who conversed with Paul,/ with him thou didst announce the proclamation of divine grace,/ O blessed apostle Jude,/ who hast uttered divine mysteries.// Wherefore, we cry out to thee: Cease thou never to pray for us all.
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Thou wast shown, for thine adamantine mind, to be the chosen disciple/ and a steadfast pillar of the Church of Christ,/ and thou didst preach the word of Christ to the nations,/ telling them to believe in the one Godhead;/ and, glorified by Him, thou hast received the gift of healings,// to cure the infirmities of those who have recourse unto thee, O most lauded apostle Jude.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>