<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Евсевий, епископ Самосатский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Священномученик Евсевий, епископ Самосатский, твердо стоял за православное исповедание, утвержденное на I Вселенском Со- боре в Никее в 325 году, за что терпел преследования от ариан, неоднократно лишавших его кафедры и изгонявших в заточение. Император Констанций (337—361), покровитель ариан, узнав о том, что у святителя Евсевия хранится соборный акт об избрании на Антиохийскую кафедру православного архиепископа Мелетия, послал к нему приказ отдать этот акт. Святитель решительно от- казался исполнить-приказание. Разгневанный император послал сказать, что если он не отдаст акт, то ему отсекут правую руку. Святой Евсевий протянул посланному обе руки со словами: «От- секите, но акта собора, в котором обличается злоба и беззаконие ариан, я не отдам». Император Констанций удивился смелости епископа, но не причинил ему вреда. После Констанция воцарился Юлиан Отступник (361—363). Наступило еще более трудное время —• началось открытое гонение на христиан. Святитель Евсевий, скрывая свой сан, в одежде воина прошел через всю Сирию, Финикию и Палестину,, утверждая хри- стиан в православной вере. Он поставлял в пустующие церкви священников и диаконов, рукополагал епископов, отвергавших арианскую ересь. После гибели Юлиана Отступника воцарился благочестивый царь Иовиан (363—364), в правление которого го- нение прекратилось. Возвратившийся из ссылки архиепископ Ме- летий по совету святого Евсевия в 379 году созвал в Антиохии Поместный Собор. В нем участвовало 27 епископов и было под- тверждено православное вероучение, принятое на I Вселенском Соборе. Ариане, боясь твердых исповедников Православия — свя- тителей Мелетия, Евсевия и Пелагия, пользовавшихся большим уважением императора, поставили свои подписи под соборным определением. После смерти императора Иовиана началось прав- ление арианина Валента (364—378). Православные вновь стали подвергаться преследованиям. Святой Мелетий был изгнан в Ар- мению, святой Пелагий — в Аравию, а святитель Евсевий осужден на заточение во Фракию. Получив царский указ, святой Евсевий ночью уехал из Самосаты, чтобы предотвратить возмущение почи- тавшего его народа. Узнав об отъезде епископа, верующие настиг- ли его и с плачем умоляли возвратиться. Святитель отказался исполнить просьбу пасомых, сказав, что следует повиноваться существующей власти. Святитель убеждал пасомых твердо дер- жаться Православия, благословил их и отправился на место ссылки. На Самосатскую кафедру был послан арианин Евномий, однако народ не принял еретика. Православные не ходили в храм и избегали встречи с ним. Еретик-арианин понял, что не сможет привлечь к себе самостоятельную паству. Вступивший на престол император Грациан (375—383) воз- вратил из изгнания всех пострадавших при арианах православных архиереев. Святитель Евсевий также возвратился в Самосаты и продолжил труды по церковному благоустроению. Вместе со свя- тым Мелетием они поставляли на место ариан православных ар- хиереев и священнослужителей. Около 380 года он прибыл в ари- анский город Долихины, чтобы поставить в нем православного епископа Марина. Женщина-арианка сбросила с крыши черепицу, которая пробила голову святителю. Умирая, он по примеру Спа- сителя простил ей вину и просил окружавших не делать ей зла. Тело святителя Евсевия было перенесено в Самосаты и с плачем погребено его пасомыми. На место святителя был возведен его племянник, блаженный Антиох, и Самосатская Церковь продол- жала твердо исповедовать православную веру, прочно насажден- ную трудами святого священномученика Евсевия. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆ нра́вѡмъ прича́стникъ, и҆ прⷭто́лѡмъ намѣ́стникъ а҆пⷭлѡмъ бы́въ, дѣѧ́нїе ѡ҆брѣ́лъ є҆сѝ бг҃одохнове́нне, въ видѣ́нїѧ восхо́дъ: сегѡ̀ ра́ди сло́во и҆́стины и҆справлѧ́ѧ, и҆ вѣ́ры ра́ди пострада́лъ є҆сѝ да́же до кро́ве, сщ҃енномч҃нче є҆ѵсе́вїе, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Бл҃гоче́стнѡ во ст҃и́тельствѣ пожи́въ, и҆ мꙋче́нїѧ пꙋ́ть проше́дъ, ї҆́дѡльскїѧ ѹ҆гаси́лъ є҆сѝ жє́ртвы ст҃и́телю є҆ѵсе́вїе: но ꙗ҆́кѡ и҆мѣ́ѧй дерзнове́нїе ко хрⷭтꙋ̀ бг҃ꙋ, молѝ сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Priestmartyr Eusebios, Bishop of Samosata"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Priestmartyr Eusebios, Bishop of Samosata, stood firmly for the Orthodox confession of faith confirmed at the Ist OEcumenical Council at Nicea in the year 325. For this he underwent persecution by the Arians, being repeatedly deprived of his cathedra and banished into exile. The emperor Constantius (337-361), patron of the Arians, having learned that Saint Eusebios kept a conciliar decree about the election to the Antioch cathedra of the Orthodox Archbishop Meletios, sent him a command to give up the decree. The saint boldly refused to do as ordered. The enraged emperor sent a message, that if he did not give up the decree, then his right hand would be cut off. Saint Eusebios stretched out both hands to the emissary with the words: &quot;Cut them off, but the Decree of the Council, which doth denounce the wickedness and iniquity of the Arians, I will not give up&quot;. The emperor Constantius marveled at the audacity of the bishop, but did him no harm. 	After Constantius, there reigned Justin the Apostate (361-363). Even more difficult times ensued -- there began an open persecution against Christians. Sainted Eusebios, having concealed his dignity, went about in the garb of a soldier across the whole of Syria, Phoenicia and Palestine, urging Christians to the Orthodox faith. He established priests and deacons in desolated churches, he put hands upon bishops renouncing the Arian heresy. After Julian the Apostate perished, there ruled the pious emperor Jovian (363-364), during which time the persecutions stopped. Having returned from exile, Archbishop Meletios upon the advice of Saint Eusebios convened a Local Council at Antioch in the year 379. In it participated 27 bishops, and it re-affirmed the Orthodox teaching of faith accepted at the Ist OEcumenical Council. The Arians, fearing the steadfast defenders of Orthodoxy -- Sainted-hierarchs Meletios, Eusebios and Pelagios, who had great influence with the emperor, put their signatures under the conciliar definition. After the death of the emperor Jovian began the rule of the Arian Vanlentus (364-378). The Orthodox were again subjected to persecution. Saint Meletios was banished to Armenia, Saint Pelagios -- to Arabia, and Saint Eusebios was condemned to exile in Thrace. Having received the imperial decree, Saint Eusebios left Samosata by night so as to prevent tumult among the people that esteemed him. Having learned about the departure of the bishop, believers followed after him and with tears entreated him to return. The saint refused to fulfill the entreaty of those who had come, saying that it was necessary to obey the existing authorities. The saint urged his flock to hold firm to Orthodoxy, blessed them and set off to the place of exile. The Arian Eunomios was put upon the Samosata cathedra, but the people did not accept the heretic. The Orthodox would not go to the church and avoided meeting with him. The heretic Arian perceived, that it was impossible to entice the independent flock to him. 	The emperor Gracian (375-383) came upon the throne, and there were brought back from exile all the Orthodox hierarchs banished under the Arians. Saint Eusebios also returned to Samosata and continued with the task of building up the church. Together with Saint Meletios he supplied Orthodox hierarchs and clergy to Arian places. In about the year 380, he arrived in the Arian city of Dolikhina to establish there the Orthodox bishop Marinos. An Arian woman flung a roof tile which struck the head of the sainted-bishop. In dying, he on the example of the Saviour asked her for wine and requested those around not to do her any harm. The body of Sainted Eusebios was taken to Samosata and with lamantation he was buried by his flock. In place of the saint was raised up his nephew, Blessed Antiokhos, and the Samosata Church continued to steadfastly confess the Orthodox faith, firmly spread through the efforts of the holy Priestmartyr Eusebios.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Having lived piously in the rank of hierarch/ and traversed the path of martyrdom,/ thou didst extinguish the burnt offerings of the idolaters,/ O holy hierarch Eusebius./ / But as thou hast boldness before Christ God, entreat Him, that our souls be saved.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>