<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Феоген"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Священномученик Феоген был епископом малоазийского города Пария в начале IV века. В царствование императора Ликиния (307—324), соправителя Константина Великого, трибун Заликин- тий принуждал его оставить священный сан, отречься от Христа и поступить на военную службу. После решительного отказа свя- титель Феоген был беспощадно избит палками и брошен в тем- ницу, где отказался принимать пищу. Тогда его приговорили к утоплению в море. Перед казнью святой просил дать ему время на молитву, во время которой его осиял необычайный свет. Кора- бельщики и некоторые из воинов, которым было поручено утопить святого, пораженные светом, обратились ко Христу, но другие вои- ны поспешили бросить святого в море. Святитель Феоген воспринял мученическую кончину около 320 года. Впоследствии тело его было взято христианами из воды и погребено у городской стены. На месте этом стали совершаться многочисленные исцеления. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The PriestMartyr Theogenes"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The PriestMartyr Theogenes was bishop of the Asia Minor city of Pareia at the beginning of the IV Century. During the reign of the emperor Licinius (307-324), -- a coruler of Constantine the Great, the tribune Zalicentius demanded him to forsake the priestly dignity, to renounce Christ and to enlist in military service. After his resolute refusal, Saint Theogenes was mercilessly beaten with canes and thrown into prison, where it was forbidden to allow him food. They then sentenced him to be drowned in the sea. Before execution the saint requested time for prayer, during which time an extraordinary light shone on him. The sailors and certain of the soldiers entrusted to drown the saint were struck by the light and were converted to Christ, but other soldiers hastened to cast the saint into the sea. Saint Theogenes accepted a martyr&apos;s death in about the year 320. His body was afterwards taken from the waters by Christians and buried at the city walls. And at this spot numerous healings occurred.  
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>