<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой пророк Малахия"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святой пророк Малахия жил за 400 лет до Рождества Хрис- това, во времена возвращения иудеев из плена Вавилонского. Ма- лахия был последним из ветхоз-аветн-ых пророков, поэтому святые отцы называют его «печатью пророков». Являясь образцом душев- ной доброты и благочестия, он приводил в удивление народ и был назван Малахией, то есть ангелом, или вестником. В канон Свя- щенных книг входит его пророческая книга, в которой он обличал иудеев, предсказывая пришествие Иисуса Христа и Его Предтечи и последний Суд (3, 1—5; 4, 1—6). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Прⷪро́чества дарова́нїемъ богатѣ́ѧ, прⷪро́че, хрⷭто́во предвозвѣсти́лъ є҆сѝ прише́ствїе ꙗ҆́вѣ, и҆ мї́рови сп҃се́нїе, є҆гѡ́же сїѧ́нїемъ мї́ръ просвѣти́сѧ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Prophet Malachi"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Prophet Malachi lived 400 years before the Birth of Christ, during the time of the return of the Jews from the Babylonian Captivity. Malachi was the last of the Old Testament prophets, wherefore the holy fathers call him &quot;the sealing-shut of the prophets&quot;. Manifesting himself an image of spiritual goodness and piety, he astounded the nation and was called Malachiei, i.e. an angel or messenger. In the Canon of Scriptural Books is included also his prophetic book, in which he upbraids the Jews, foretelling the coming of Jesus Christ and His Forerunner, and also the Last Judgement (Mal. 3: 1-5; 4:1-6).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Enriched by the gift of prophecy, O prophet,/ thou didst manifestly proclaim salvation to the world and the advent of Christ,// by Whose radiance the world hath been illumined.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>