<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой апостол и евангелист Марк"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
    Святой апостол и евангелист Марк, называемый также Иоанн- Марк (Деян. 12, 12), апостол от 70-ти, племянник апостола Вар- навы (память 11 июня), родился в Иерусалиме. Дом его матери Марии примыкал к Гефсиманскому саду. Как говорит церковное предание, в ночь Крестных страданий Христа он следовал за Ним, завернувшись в плащ, и убежал от схвативших его воинов (Мк. 14, 51—52). После Вознесения Господня дом матери святого Мар- ка стал местом молитвенных собраний христиан и пристанищем для некоторых из апостолов (Деян. 12, 12).     .Святой Марк был ближайшим сподвижником апостолов Пет- ра, Павла (общая память 29 июня) и Варнавы. Вместе с апосто- лами Павлом и Варнавой святой Марк был в Селевкии, оттуда отправился на остров Кипр и прошел его весь с востока на запад. В городе Пафе святой Марк был свидетелем того, как апостол Павел поразил слепотой волхва Елима (Деян. 13, 6—12).      После трудов с апостолом Павлом святой Марк вернулся в Иерусалим, а затем вместе с апостолом Петром побывал в Риме, откуда по его повелению отправился в Египет, где основал Церковь.      Во время второго благовестнического путешествия апостола Павла святой Марк встретился с ним в Антиохии. Оттуда он отправился на проповедь с апостолом Варнавой на Кипр, а затем опять ушел в Египет, где вместе с апостолом Петром основал мно- го Церквей, в том числе в Вавилоне. Из этого города апостол Петр направил послание малоазийским христианам, в котором с любовью отзывался о святом Марке, своем духовном сыне  (1 Пет. 5, 13).      Когда апостол Павел находился в узах в Риме, апостол Марк был в Ефесе, где кафедру занимал святитель Тимофей (память 4 января). Вместе с ним апостол Марк прибыл в Рим. Там он и написал святое Евангелие (ок. 62—63).      Из Рима святой Марк снова удалился в Египет и в Александ- рии положил начало христианскому училищу, из которого впо- следствии вышли такие знаменитые отцы и учители Церкви, как Климент Александрийский,, святитель Дионисий (5 октября), свя- титель Григорий Чудотворец (память 5 ноября) и другие. Ревнуя ° устроении церковного Богослужения, святой апостол Марк сос- тавил чин Литургии для Александрийских христиан.    Затем святой Марк с проповедью Евангелия посетил внутрен- ние области Африки, был в Ливии, Нектополе.    Во время этих путешествий святой Марк получил повеление от Духа Святого вновь идти в Александрию для проповеди и противодействия язычникам. Там он поселился в доме сапожни- ка Анании, которому исцелил больную руку. Сапожник с ра- достью принял святого апостола, с верой внимал его повество- ваниям о Христе и принял Крещение. Вслед за Ананией крести- лись многие жители той части города, где он- жил. Это возбудило ненависть язычников, и они собирались убить святого Марка. Узнав об этом, святой апостол поставил Ананию епископом, а трех христиан: Малка, Савина и Кердина — пресвитерами.    Язычники напали на святого Марка, когда апостол совершал Богослужение. Его избили, волокли по улицам города и бросили в темницу. Там святой Марк удостоился видения Господа Иису- са Христа, Который укрепил его перед страданиями. На следую- щий день разъяренная толпа снова повлекла святого апостола по улицам города на судилище, но по дороге святой Марк скончал- ся со словами: «В руки Твои, Господи, предаю дух мой».     Язычники хотели сжечь тело святого апостола. Но когда раз- вели костер, все померкло, раздался гром и произошло земле- трясение. Язычники в страхе разбежались, а христиане взяли тело святого апостола и погребли его в каменной гробнице. Это было 4 апреля 63 года. Память его Церковь празднует 25 апреля.    В 310 году над мощами святого апостола Марка была построе- на церковь. В 820 году, когда в Египте установилась власть ара- бов-магометан и Христианскую Церковь теснили иноверные, мощи святого перенесли в Венецию и поставили в храме его имени.    В древней иконографической традиции, усвоившей святым Евангелистам символы, заимствованные из видения святого Иоан- на Богослова (Откр. 4, 7), святой Евангелист Марк изображается со львом — в ознаменование могущества и царственного достоин- ства Христа (Откр. 5, 5). Святой Марк писал свое Евангелие для христиан из язычников, поэтому он останавливается преиму- щественно на речах и делах Спасителя, в которых особенно про- является Его Божественное всемогущество. Многие особенности его повествования можно объяснить близостью его к апостолу Петру. Все древние писатели свидетельствуют, что Евангелие от Марка является краткой записью проповеди и рассказов перво- верховного апостола. Одной из центральных Богословских тем в Евангелии святого Марка является тема силы Божией, совершаю- щейся в немощи человеческой, ибо Господь делает возможным то, что у людей невозможно. При действии Христа (Мк. 16, 20) и Духа Святого (13, 11) ученики его идут по всему миру и пропо- ведуют Евангелие всей твари (13, 10; 16, 15). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
А҆пⷭле ст҃ы́й и҆ є҆ѵⷢлї́сте ма́рко, молѝ ми́лостиваго бг҃а, да прегрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе пода́стъ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
Ѹ҆ верхо́внагѡ петра̀ наꙋчи́всѧ, а҆пⷭлъ хрⷭто́въ бы́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ ꙗ҆́кѡ со́лнце страна́мъ возсїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ, а҆леѯсандрї́ѡмъ ѹ҆добре́нїе бы́въ бл҃же́нне. тобо́ю є҆гѵ́петъ ѿ пре́лести свободи́сѧ, є҆ѵⷢльскимъ твои́мъ ѹ҆че́нїемъ просвѣ́щъ всѧ҄, ꙗ҆́кѡ свѣ́тъ сто́лпъ цр҃ко́вный. сегѡ̀ ра́ди твою̀ па́мѧть чтꙋ́ще, свѣ́тлѡ пра́зднꙋемъ ма́рко бг҃огла́се: молѝ тобо́ю бл҃говѣсти́маго бг҃а, да согрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе пода́стъ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Съ высоты̀ прїи́мъ бл҃года́ть дх҃а, ри́тѡрскаѧ плетє́нїѧ разрꙋши́лъ є҆сѝ а҆пⷭле, и҆ ꙗ҆зы́ки всѧ҄ ѹ҆лови́въ, ма́рко всесла́вне, твоемꙋ̀ влⷣцѣ приве́лъ є҆сѝ бж҃е́ственное проповѣ́давъ є҆ѵⷢлїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Disciple and Evangelist Mark"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Disciple and Evangelist Mark, named also John-Mark (Acts 12: 12), was a Disciple from among the Seventy, and was also a nephew of the Disciple Barnabas (Comm. 11 June). He was born at Jerusalem. The house of his mother Mary adjoined the Garden of Gethsemane. As Church Tradition relates, on the night of the Sufferings of Christ on the Cross he followed after Him, wrapped in a linen winding-cloth, and he fled from the soldiers catching hold of him (Mk. 14: 51-52). After the Ascension of the Lord, the house of his mother Saint Mary became a place of prayerful gatherings of Christians and a lodging for certain of the Apostles (Acts 12: 12). 	Saint Mark was a very close companion of the Apostles Peter and Paul (Comm. 29June) and of the Disciple Barnabas. Saint Mark was at Seleucia together with Paul and Barnabas, and from there he set off to the island of Cyprus, and he crossed over the whole of it from East to West. In the city of Paphos Saint Mark was an eye-witness, of how the Apostle Paul had struck blind the sorcerer Elymas (Acts 13: 6-12). 	After working with the Apostle Paul, Saint Mark returned to Jerusalem, and then with the Apostle Peter he arrived in Rome, from whence at the latter&apos;s bidding he set out for Egypt, where he became founder of the Church. 	During the time of the second evangelic journey of the Apostle Paul, Saint Mark met up with him at Antioch. From there he set out preaching with the Disciple Barnabas to Cyprus, and then he went off again to Egypt, where together with the Apostle Peter he founded many churches, and then also at Babylon. From this city the Apostle Peter directed an Epistle to the Christians of Asia Minor, in which he points to Saint Mark as his spiritual son (1 Pet. 5: 13). 	When the Apostle Paul came in chains to Rome, the Disciple Mark was at Ephesus, where the cathedra-seat was occupied by Saint Timothy (Comm. 4 January). The Disciple Mark arrived together with him in Rome. There also he wrote his holy Gospel (c.62-63). 	From Rome Saint Mark again set off to Egypt. At Alexandria he made the beginnings of a Christian school, from which later on emerged such famous fathers and teachers of the Church, as Clement of Alexandria, Sainted Dionysios (5 October), Sainted Gregory Thaumatourgos (&quot;Wonderworker&quot;, Comm. 5 November), and others. Zealous with the arranging of Church Divine-services, the holy Disciple Mark compiled the order of Liturgy for the Alexandrian Christians. 	Later on in preaching the Gospel, Saint Mark also visited the inner regions of Africa, and he was in Libya at Nektopolis. 	During the time of these journeys, Saint Mark received inspiration of the Holy Spirit to go again to Alexandria and confront the pagans. There he visited at the home of the dignitary Ananias, for whom he healed a crippled hand. The dignitary happily took him in, hearkened with faith to his narratives, and received Baptism. And following the example of Ananias, many of the inhabitants of that part of the city where he lived were baptised after him. This roused the enmity of the pagans, and they gathered to kill Saint Mark. Having learned of this, the holy Disciple Mark made Ananias bishop, and the three Christians: Malchos, Sabinos and Kerdinos -- presbyters. 	The pagans pounced upon Saint Mark when he was making Divine-services. They beat him, dragged him through the streets and threw him in prison. There Saint Mark was granted a vision of the Lord Jesus Christ, Who strengthened him before his sufferings. On the following day the angry crowd again dragged the holy disciple through the streets towards the court-room, but along the way Saint Mark died with the words: &quot;Into Thy hands, O Lord, I commend my spirit&quot;. 	The pagans wanted to burn the body of the holy disciple. But when they lit up the bon-fire, everything grew dim, thunder crashed and an earthquake occurred. The pagans fled in terror, and Christians took up the body of the holy disciple and buried it in a stone crypt. This was on 4 April in the year 63. The Church celebrates his memory on 25 April. 	In the year 310, a church was built over the relics of the holy Disciple Mark. In the year 820, when the Mahometan Arabs had established their rule in Egypt and those of this different faith oppressed the Christian Church, the relics of Saint Mark were transferred to Venice and placed in the church of his name.  	In the ancient iconographic tradition, which adopted symbols for the holy Evangelists borrowed from the vision of Saint John the Theologian (Rev. 4: 7), the holy Evangelist Mark is depicted by a lion -- symbolising the might and royal dignity of Christ (Rev. 5: 5). Saint Mark wrote his Gospel for Christians from among the gentile-pagans, since he emphasises predominantly the words and deeds of the Saviour, in which particularly is manifest His Divine Almightiness. The many particularities of his account can be explained by his proximity to the holy Apostle Peter. All the ancient writers testify, that the Gospel of Mark represents a concise writing-down of the preaching and narratives of the first-ranked Apostle Peter. One of the central theological themes in the Gospel of Saint Mark is the theme of the power of God, doing the humanly impossible, wherein the Lord makes possible that which of man is impossible. By the efficacy of Christ (Mk.16:20) and the Holy Spirit (Mk. 13: 11), His disciples are to go forth into the world and preach the Gospel to all creatures (Mk. 13: 10, 16: 15).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
O holy apostle and evangelist Mark/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
	Thou wast an apostle of Christ who learned from the pre-eminent Peter,/ and didst shine like the sun upon the lands of the Alexandrians, being their adornment./ Through thee was Egypt freed from deception, O blessed one,/ who as the Church's pillar of fire dost illumine all with thy teaching of the Gospel./ Wherefore, honoring thy memory, we keep splendid festival, O divinely eloquent Mark./ Entreat God Who was announced by thee,// that He grant our souls remission of offenses.
	</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Receiving from on high the grace of the Spirit,/ thou didst destroy the snares of the orators, O apostle,/ and, hunting all the nations,/ thou didst lead them to thy Master,/ O most glorious Mark,// preaching the divine Gospel.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>