<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Никифор"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святитель Никифор был сановником при дворе императрицы Ирины (797—802). Приняв монашество, он прославился благоче- стием и в 806 году был возведен на патриарший престол. Святи- тель был ревностным защитником иконопочитания и с воцарением императора-иконоборца Льва Армянина (813—820) в 815 году был сослан на остров Проконнис, где скончался в 828 году.    В 846 году святые мощи Патриарха Никифора были обретены нетленными и благоухающими. Их перенесли из Проконниса в Константинополь и положили на один день в храме святой Софии, а затем перенесли в храм святых Апостолов. Рука святителя хра- нится в Хилендарском монастыре на Афоне.    Святитель оставил после себя три сочинения, направленные против иконоборцев.    Память святителя празднуется 2 июня.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1" Podoben="2">
Ли́къ патрїа́ршескїй ст҃ꙋ́ю твою̀ па́мѧть хвала́ми и҆ пѣ́сньми нїки́форе че́ствꙋетъ: въ преложе́нїи бо прїѧ́тъ дꙋ́шꙋ твою̀, сла́вне. тѣ́мъ дне́сь честна́ѧ цр҃ковь, велича́ющи хрⷭта̀ цр҃ѧ̀, сла́витъ є҆ди́наго чл҃вѣколю́бца. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Nicephoros"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Nicephoros was a dignitary at the court of the empress Irene (797-802), and then accepting monasticism, he became known for his piety. In the year 806 he was elevated to the patriarchal throne. The saint was a zealous defender of Icon-Veneration. When the Iconoclast emperor Leo the Armenian (813-820) came to rule, the saint in 815 was exiled to the Island of Prokonnis, where he died in the year 828.  	In the year 846 the holy relics of Patriarch Nicephoros were opened, undecayed and fragrant. They transferred them from Prokonnis to Constantinople and placed them for one day in the church of Saint Sophia, and then they transferred them to the church of the Holy Apostles. The hands of the saint are preserved in the Khilendaria monastery on Mount Athos.  	The saint left behind three writings, directed against Iconoclasm. The memory of Saint Nicephoros is celebrated also on 2 June.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1" Podoben="2">
The choir of patriarchs doth honor thy holy memory/ with praises and hymns, O Nicephorus;/ for it received thy soul at thy translation, O glorious one./ Wherefore, today the holy Church, magnifying Christ the King,// doth glorify Him Who alone loveth mankind.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>