<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="  Святое Богоявление. Крещение Господа Бога и Спаса нашего Иисуса Христа."/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Богоявлением называется праздник потому, что при Крещении Господа явилась миру Пресвятая Троица (Мф. 3, 13—17; Мк. 1, 9—11; Лк. 3, 21—22). Бог Отец глаголал с небес о Сыне, Сын крестился от святого Предтечи Господня Иоанна, и Дух Святой сошел на Сына в виде голубя. С древних времен этот праздник на- зывался днем Просвещения и праздником Светов, потому что Бог есть Свет и явился просветить «седящих во тме и сени смертней» (Мф. 4, 16) и спасти по благодати падший человеческий род.    В древней Церкви был обычай крестить оглашенных в навече- рие Богоявления, так как Крещение и является духовным просве- щением людей.     Начало праздника Богоявления восходит к апостольским вре- менам. О нем упоминается в Апостольских постановлениях. От II века сохранилось свидетельство святителя Климента Алексан- дрийского о праздновании Крещения Господня и совершаемом пред этим праздником ночном бдении.     В III веке на праздник Богоявления известны беседы при Бого- служении святого мученика Ипполита и святого Григория Чудо- творца. В последующие столетия—с IV по IX век—все великие от- цы Церкви — Григорий Богослов, Иоанн Златоуст, Амвросий Ме- диоланский, Иоанн Дамаскин проводили особые беседы о праздни- ке Богоявления. Преподобные Иосиф Студит, Феофан и Византии написали много песнопений на этот праздник, которые поются и сейчас за Богослужением. Преподобный Иоанн Дамаскин говорил, что Господь крестился не потому, что Сам имел нужду в очищении,  но чтобы, «водами погребсти человеческий грех», исполнить закон, открыть таинство Святой Троицы и, наконец, освятить «водное естество» и подать нам образ и пример Крещения.    Святая Церковь в празднике Крещения Господня утверждает нашу веру в высочайшую, непостижимую разумом тайну Трех Лиц Единого Бога и научает нас равночестно исповедовать и про- славлять Святую Троицу Единосущную и Нераздельную; обли- чает и разрушает заблуждения древних лжеучителей, пытавшихся мыслью и словом человеческим объять Творца мира. Церковь по- казывает необходимость Крещения для верующих во Христа, вну- шает нам чувство глубокой благодарности к Просветителю и Очи- стителю нашего греховного естества. Она учит, что наше спасение и очищение от грехов возможно только силою благодати Святого Духа и потому необходимо достойно хранить эти благодатные да- ры святого Крещения для сохранения в чистоте той драгоценной одежды, о которой говорит нам праздник Крещения: «Елицы во Христа крестистеся, во Христа облекостеся» (Гал. 3, 27). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Во ї҆ѻрда́нѣ креща́ющꙋсѧ тебѣ̀ гдⷭи, трⷪческое ꙗ҆ви́сѧ поклоне́нїе: роди́телевъ бо гла́съ свидѣ́тельствоваше тебѣ̀, возлю́бленнаго тѧ̀ сн҃а и҆менꙋ́ѧ, и҆ дх҃ъ въ ви́дѣ голꙋби́нѣ и҆звѣ́ствоваше словесѐ ѹ҆твержде́нїе. ꙗ҆вле́йсѧ хрⷭтѐ бж҃е, и҆ мї́ръ просвѣще́й, сла́ва тебѣ̀. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ дне́сь вселе́ннѣй, и҆ свѣ́тъ тво́й гдⷭи зна́менасѧ на на́съ, въ ра́зꙋмѣ пою́щихъ тѧ̀: прише́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ, свѣ́тъ непристꙋ́пный. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Theophany: the Baptism of Our Lord and God and Saviour Jesus Christ."/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Theophany / Bogoyavlenie denotes the feast whereby through the Baptism of the Lord the MostHoly Trinity has been revealed to the world (Mt. 3: 13-17; Mk. 1: 9-11;  Lk. 3: 21-22). God the Father spoke from Heaven about the Son, the Son was baptised by the holy ForeRunner of the Lord John, and the Holy Spirit descended upon the Son in the form of a Dove. From ancient times this feast was called the Day of Illumination and the Feast of Lights, since that God is Light and has appeared to illumine &quot;those sitting in darkness and the shadow of death&quot; (Mt. 4: 16) and to save through grace the fallen race of mankind. 	In the ancient Church it was the custom to baptise catechumens at the vespers of Theophany, such that Baptism also is revealed as a spiritual illumination of mankind. 	The origin of the feast of Theophany came about in Apostolic times. Mention is made concerning it in the Apostolic Decretals. From the II Century there is preserved the testimony of Sainted Clement of Alexandria concerning the celebration of the Baptism of the Lord and performing the night vigil before this feast. 	In the III Century on the feast of Theophany there is known the dialogue concerning Divine-services between the holy martyr Hyppolitus and Saint Gregory the WonderWorker. In the following centuries -- from the IV to IX Century -- all the great fathers of the Church -- Gregory the Theologian, John Chrysostomos, Ambrose of Milan, John Damascene, had their own comments about the feast of Theophany. The monks Joseph the Studite, Theophanes and Byzantios composed much liturgical music for this feastday, which even now  is sung for Divine-services. The Monk John Damascene said, that the Lord was baptised not because He Himself had need for cleansing, but so that &quot;by water to bury human sin&quot;, to fulfill the law, to reveal the mystery of the Holy Trinity, and finally, to sanctify &quot;watery nature&quot; and to proffer it to us in the form and example of Baptism. 	On the feastday of the Baptism of Christ, Holy Church asserts our faith in the mystery -- most sublime and incomprehensible to human intellect -- of the Three Persons of the One God. It teaches us to confess and glorify as equally-honoured the Holy Trinity One-Essence and Undivided. It exposes and collapses the fallacies of the ancient pseudo-teachings, which attempted with reason and by human terms to explain the Creator of the world. The Church shews the necessity of Baptism for believers in Christ, and it inspires for us a sense of deep gratitude for the Illumination and Purification of our sinful nature. The Church teaches that our salvation and cleansing from sin is possible only by the power of the grace of the Holy Spirit, wherefore it is necessary to preserve worthily these gifts of the grace of holy Baptism -- keeping clean this priceless garb, about which the feast of the Baptism tells us: &quot;As many as have been baptised into Christ, have put on Christ&quot; (Gal. 3:27). [Translator Note: literally rendered from Greek &quot;Theophany&quot; means &quot;Manifestation of God&quot;, whereas &quot;Epiphany&quot; connotes &quot;Manifest upon&quot;; &quot;Theophany&quot; is the more accurate rendering of Slavonic &quot;Bogoyavlenie&quot;.]
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
When Thou, O Lord, wast baptized in the Jordan,/ the worship of the Trinity was made manifest;/ for, the voice of the Father bare witness unto Thee,/ calling Thee His beloved Son;/ and the Spirit in the form of a dove/ confirmed the certainty of His word./ O Christ our God, Who hast appeared and enlightened the worlds,// glory be to Thee!
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Thou hast appeared today to the whole world,/ and Thy light, O Lord, hath been signed upon us/ who hymn Thee with understanding./ Thou hast come, Thou hast appeared,/ the Light unapproachable.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>