<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Мученики Пров, Тарах и Андроник"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov">
Святые мученики Пров, Тарах и Андроник пострадали за Христа в 304 году в городе Тарсе Киликийском. На предложение язычников принести жертву идолам святой Тарах, старый воин, ответил, что он приносит жертву Единому, Истинному Богу в чистом сердце. Видя твердость святых в исповедании истинной веры, проконсул предал их пыткам. "Когда мое тело страдает, - говорил идолопоклонникам святой Пров, - тогда душа моя исцеляется и оживляется". Истязатели изощрялись в мучениях, какие только могла измыслить их злоба, а потом разрубили тела святых на части. Христиане тайно взяли останки мучеников и похоронили.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="5">
Ст҃ы́хъ мч҃нкъ и҆справле́нїємъ нбⷭныѧ си҄лы преꙋдиви́шасѧ, ꙗ҆́кѡ въ тѣ́лѣ сме́ртнѣмъ, безтѣле́снаго врага̀ си́лою крⷭта̀, подвиза́вшесѧ до́брѣ, побѣди́ша неви́димѡ: и҆ мо́лѧтсѧ гдⷭꙋ поми́ловатисѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2">
Трⷪцы на́мъ сла́вꙋ ꙗ҆ви́ша, до́блїи хрⷭтѡ́вы ѻ҆рꙋ́жницы и҆ мч҃нцы, съ тара́хомъ про́въ же и҆ а҆ндронї́къ: ѡ҆бличи́ша бо всѐ мꙋчи́телей безбо́жїе, вѣ́рою до́блественнѣ страда́льчествовавше. 
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyrs Probus, Tarachus, and Andronicus"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Fr. Eugene Tarris">
       St. Tarachus, a Roman citizen and warrior, was born in Claudiopolis,
Isauria. St. Probus, a Thracian, from Perga, Pamphylia, and St. Andronicus was the
son of a famous citizen of Ephesus. For confessing Christ all severely suffered first
in the city of Tarsus (in Cilicia), then in Mopsuestia and finally in the city of
Anazarbus. They were all beheaded after undergoing terrible tortures in the year
304.

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="5" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
The heavenly powers were amazed at the struggles of the Holy Martyrs,
for even in their mortal bodies,
they fell upon the bodiless enemy by the power of the Cross,
invisibly defeating them.
Therefore they are praying to the Lord that He may have mercy on our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
Soldiers and Martyrs of Christ, Probus, Tarachus, and Andronicus,
Revealed to us the glory of the Trinity: For you cleansed all from the errors of atheism,
Fighting valiantly for the faith,
O honorable sufferers.

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>
