<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Косма, епископ Маиумский, творец канонов"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov">
Преподобный Косма, епископ Маиумский, творец канонов, родом из Иерусалима, воспитывался родителями преподобного Иоанна Дамаскина вместе с их сыном и получил прекрасное образование. Когда святой Косма достиг совершеннолетия, то поступил в одну из палестинских обителей, где прославился монашескими подвигами. Во время гонения на святые иконы преподобный Косма вместе с преподобным Иоанном выступил в защиту Православия. Они написали много сочинений против иконоборцев. В 743 году Косма был поставлен епископом Маиумским. Преставился он в глубокой старости (+ ок. 787), оставив после себя много канонов на праздничные дни и трипеснцы на четыре дня Страстной седмицы.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Правосла́вїѧ наста́вниче, бл҃гоче́стїѧ ѹ҆чи́телю и҆ чистоты̀, вселе́нныѧ свѣти́льниче, а҆рхїере́євъ бг҃одꙋхнове́нное ѹ҆добре́нїе. космо̀ премꙋ́дре, ѹ҆че́ньми твои́ми всѧ҄ просвѣти́лъ є҆сѝ, цѣвни́це дх҃о́внаѧ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Ѹ҆кра́шенъ добродѣ́тельми, космо̀ бг҃одꙋхнове́нне, цр҃кве хрⷭто́вы ѹ҆краше́нїе бы́лъ є҆сѝ: пѣ́сньми бо ѹ҆краси́лъ є҆сѝ сїю̀, бл҃же́нне. но моли́сѧ ко гдⷭꙋ, и҆зба́витисѧ на́мъ ѿ всѧ́кихъ ко́зней ра́тника, тебѣ̀ зовꙋ́щымъ: ра́дꙋйсѧ, ѻ҆́тче требога́те. 
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Our Venerable Father Cosmas of the Holy City, Bishop of Maium, and Author of Canons"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Fr. Eugene Tarris">
       He was the closest friend and co-worker of the Venerable John of
Damascus. For his piety he was installed as the Bishop of Maium, and worked very
hard in this position for his flock and died in peace at the end of the Eighth Century (after 776). Glorifying the hierarch as "nourisher of wisdom, "nurse of purity",
"enlightener of the faithful" and "renowned theologian", the Holy Church
witnesses that Bishop Cosmas was "meek and humble of mind, calm and blameless
in speech, kind and guileless, chaste and righteous, most simple and wholesome".
Brought up "in piety and faith" and "with the mind and soul adorned in wisdom",
Bishop Cosmas adorned the Church "with systematic and didactic hymns",
satisfying "reason", and "which clearly open to all" "the truly strange and most
wonderful mysteries of Christ".

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
Instructor of Orthodoxy, teacher of piety and purity, light of the universe and God-inspired adornment of the hierarchs, O wise Cosmas, with thy teachings thou hast enlightened all. O spiritual flute, pray unto Christ God that our souls may be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
O God-inspired Cosmas, thou hast adorned thyself with virtues,
adorning the church of Christ with hymns, O Blessed One.
But pray to the Lord that He may deliver us from the snares of our enemies, as we cry out to thee: rejoice, O most richly adorned Father.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>
