<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Прокопий Декаполит"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобный Прокопий Декаполит жил в VIII веке в области Декаполиса или Десятиградия (Мк. 7, 31), к востоку от озера Галилейского. Там он и спасался, предаваясь иноческим подвигам.    Святой Прокопий вместе со своим сподвижником святым Васи- лием (память 28 февраля) и другими ревнителями Православия мужественно противостал возникшей в то время иконоборческой ереси. По приказу императора Льва Исаврянина (716—741) пре- подобный Прокопий был схвачен, предан жестокому бичеванию и брошен в темницу, где вместе со святым Василием томился до самой смерти царя-мучителя, после чего преподобные исповедники были выпущены на свободу. Остальное время жизни преподобный Прокопий провел мирно, в иноческих подвигах, наставляя многих на путь добродетели и спасения. Скончался он в глубокой старо- сти, около 750 года. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Сле́зъ твои́хъ тече́ньми пꙋсты́ни безпло́дное воздѣ́лалъ є҆сѝ, и҆ и҆̀же и҆з꙽ глꙋбины̀ воздыха́ньми, во сто̀ трꙋдѡ́въ ѹ҆плодоноси́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ бы́лъ є҆сѝ свѣти́льникъ вселе́ннѣй, сїѧ́ѧ чꙋдесы̀, проко́пїе ѻ҆́тче на́шъ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Денни́цꙋ дне́сь цр҃ковь и҆мꙋ́щи, всѧ́кꙋю ѕлосла́вїѧ мглꙋ̀ разгонѧ́етъ, почита́ющи тѧ̀ нбⷭнотаи́нниче проко́пїе пресла́вне. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Prokopios Dekapolites"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Prokopios Dekapolites lived during the VIII Century in the region of Dekapolis (Mk. 7: 31), to the east of Lake Galilee. And there also he devoted himself to salvation, occupied with monastic deeds.  	Saint Prokopios, together with his co-ascetic Saint Basil (Comm. 28 February) and others zealous for holy Orthodoxy, rose up against the Iconoclast heresy that had arisen in those times. By order of the emperor Leo the Isaurian (716-741), the Monk Prokopios was arrested, subjected to a fierce scourging and thrown into prison. Here he languished together with the Monk Basil until the very death of the oppressive emperor, after which the holy confessors were set free. The Monk Prokopios spent the rest of his life peacefully at monastic deeds, guiding many on the way of virtue and salvation. He died in old age, in about the year 750.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
With the streams of thy tears thou didst irrigate the barren desert,/ and with sighs from the depths of thy soul thou didst render thy labors fruitful an hundredfold./ Thou wast a beacon for the whole world, radiating miracles.// O our father Procopius, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
The Church, possessing thee today as a morning star, dispelleth all the darkness of heresy,/ honoring thee, O all-glorious Procopius,// initiate of the heavenly mysteries.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>