<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="   Святой апостол и священномученик Симеон, сродник Господень"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святой апостол и священномученик Симеон, сродник Госпо- день, был сыном Клеопы, младшего брата святого Иосифа Обруч- лика. В зрелом возрасте он увидел чудеса Господа Иисуса Хри- ста, уверовал в Него и стал одним из 70-ти апостолов. Святой Си- меон проповедовал учение Христово, наставлял в истинах святой веры и обличал идолослужение. После убиения святого апостола Иакова (1&quot; 63; память 23 октября), первого епископа Иерусалим- ского, на его место христиане избрали святого апостола Симеона. В правление императора Траяна (98—117) римскому правителю Аттику донесли, что святой Симеон происходит из рода царя Да- вида (римляне уничтожали всех потомков царя Давида) и испо- ведует христианскую веру. Язычники схватили святого Симеона, который в то время был уже столетним старцем и после долгих мучений распяли на кресте. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Хрⷭто́ва тѧ̀ сро́дника, сѷмеѡ́не сщ҃еннонача́льниче, и҆ мч҃нка тве́рда сщ҃е́ннѡ восхвалѧ́емъ, пре́лесть потреби́вшаго, и҆ вѣ́рꙋ соблю́дшаго. тѣ́мже дне́сь всест҃ꙋ́ю твою̀ па́мѧть пра́зднꙋюще, грѣхѡ́въ разрѣше́нїе мл҃твами твои́ми прїе́млемъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ ѕвѣздꙋ̀ преве́лїю, це́рковь и҆мꙋ́щи дне́сь бг҃оглаго́ливаго сѷмеѡ́на, свѣтово́дитсѧ зовꙋ́щи: ра́дꙋйсѧ мч҃нкѡвъ честны́й вѣ́нче. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Disciple and PriestMartyr Simeon, Kinsman of the Lord"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Disciple and PriestMartyr Simeon, Kinsman of the Lord, was the son of Cleopas, younger brother of Saint Joseph the Betrothed. In his adolescent years he beheld the miracles of the Lord Jesus Christ, believed in Him and became one of the 70 Disciples. Saint Simeon preached the teachings of Christ, exhorted the truths of holy faith and denounced idol-worship. After the killing of the holy Apostle James, the first bishop of Jerusalem (+ 63, Comm. 23 October) -- in his place the Christians chose the holy Disciple Simeon. During the reign of emperor Trajan (98-117) it was reported to the Roman governor Atticus that Saint Simeon was descended from the lineage of King David (the Romans exterminated all the descendants of King David) and was confessing the Christian faith. The pagans seized hold of Saint Simeon, who at that time was already an hundred year old man, and after lengthy torture they crucified him on a cross.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
In sacred manner do we praise thee, O sacred hierarch Symeon,/ as the kinsman of Christ and a steadfast martyr/ who destroyed deception and kept the Faith./ Wherefore, celebrating today thy most holy memory,// we receive remission of sins through thy supplications.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Today, the Church, possessing the divinely eloquent Symeon/ as a exceeding great star, shineth, crying aloud:// Rejoice, O honored crown of martyrs!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>