<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобные отцы, в Синае и Раифе избиенные"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Преподобные отцы, в Синае и Раифе избиенные, подвизались в обителях и пещерах горы Синайской, где были даны Богом через Моисея десять заповедей, и близкой к ней пустыни Раифы  (на берегу Красного моря) и пострадали от сарацин и влеммиан, кочевых арабских племен. Первое избиение произошло около 312 года. Оно было описано Аммонием, египетским иноком, оче- видцем гибели 40 святых отцов Синайских. В это же время арабы избили 39 отцов в Раифе. Вторичное избиение совершено через сто лет и описано также очевидцем, чудом избежавшим гибели, преподобным Нилом Постником (память 12 ноября).     Синайские и раифские подвижники проводили особо строгую жизнь — всю неделю они пребывали в келлиях в молчании, в суб- боту собирались на всенощное бдение и в воскресенье причаща- лись Святых Тайн. Питались только финиками и водой. Многие из пустынников прославились даром чудотворения — старцы Мои- сей, Иосиф и другие. По именам в службе преподобным отцам упоминаются Исайя, Савва, Моисей, ученик его Моисей, Иеремия, Павел, Адам, Сергий, Домн, Прокл, Ипатий, Исаак, Макарий, Марк, Вениамин, Евсевий и Илия. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е ѻ҆тє́цъ на́шихъ, творѧ́й при́снѡ съ на́ми по твое́й кро́тости, не ѡ҆ста́ви млⷭть твою̀ ѿ на́съ, но мл҃твами и҆́хъ въ ми́рѣ ѹ҆пра́ви живо́тъ на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Ѿ мїрскї́ѧ молвы̀ и҆збѣго́сте, и҆ къ ти́хомꙋ приста́нищꙋ преста́вистесѧ, мч҃нчества кровьмѝ, и҆ по́стничества трꙋда́ми вѣнча́еми. тѣ́мже и҆ показа́стесѧ мч҃нкѡвъ и҆ прпⷣбныхъ є҆диновсе́льницы. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monastic Fathers, Murdered at Sinai and Raipha"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monastic Fathers, Murdered at Sinai and Raipha, asceticised at the monasteries and caves of Mount Sinai, where previously the Ten Commandments had been given through Moses; near to it also was the Raipha monastic wilderness (on the shores of the Red Sea). They suffered under the Saracens and under nomadic brigands from among the Arab tribes. The first massacre occurred in about the year 312. It was recorded by Ammon, an Egyptian monk, who witnessed the murder of the 40 holy fathers in Sinai. During this time the Arabs also killed 39 fathers at Raipha. The second period of the massacres occurred nearly an hundred years later, and was likewise recorded by an eye-witness who himself in the process miraculously escaped -- the Monk Nilos the Faster (Comm. 12 November). 	The Sinai and Raipha ascetics lived a particularly strict lifestyle: they spent the whole week in their cells at prayer, on Saturday they gathered for the all-night vigil, and on Sunday they communed the Holy Mysteries. Their only food was dates and water. Many of the wilderness ascetics were glorified by wonderworking -- the elders Moses, Joseph and others. By name, remembered in the service to these monastic fathers are commemorated: Isaiah, Sava, Moses and his student Moses, Jeremiah, Paul, Adam, Sergios, Domnos, Proklos, Ipatios, Isaac, Makarios, Mark, Benjamin, Eusebios and Elias.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O God of our fathers,/ deal with us ever according to Thy meekness./ Deprive us not of Thy mercy,/ but through their supplications// direct our life in peace.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Ye fled from the tumult of the world/ and have found rest in the calm haven,/ crowned with the blood of martyrdom/ and the labors of asceticism.// Wherefore, ye have been shown to dwell together with the martyrs and the venerable.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>