<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Феодосии Великий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Преподобный Феодосии Великий жил в V—VI вв. и был осново- положником общежительных монастырей. Он родился в Каппадо- кии от благочестивых родителей. Обладая прекрасным голосом, он усердно трудился в церковном чтении и пении. Преподобный Феодосии горячо молился, чтобы Господь наставил его на путь спасения. В юные годы он посетил Святую Землю и виделся с преподобным Симеоном Столпником (+ 459; память 1 сентября), который благословил его и предсказал ему будущее пастырское служение. Стремясь к отшельнической жизни, святой Феодосии поселился в Палестине в пустынной пещере, в которой, по преда- нию, ночевали три волхва, пришедшие поклониться Родившемуся Спасителю мира. В ней он прожил 30 лет в великом воздержа- нии и непрестанной молитве. К подвижнику постепенно начали стекаться желавшие жить под его руководством. Когда пещера уже не вмещала собравшихся иноков, преподобный Феодосии стал молиться, чтобы Господь Сам указал место для обители. Взяв с собой кадило с холодными углями, преподобный пошел по пус- тыне. На одном месте внезапно угли разгорелись и воскурился фимиам. Тут преподобный и основал первый общежительный монастырь, или Лавру, по уставу святителя Василия Великого  (+ 379; память 1 января). Скоро Лавра преподобного Феодосия сделалась знаменитой, и в ней собралось до 700 иноков. По завету преподобного Феодосия, Лавра выполняла служение ближним, оказывая помощь всем бедным и давая приют стран- никам.     Преподобный Феодосии был необыкновенно милостив. Однаж- ды, когда в Палестине случился голод и к монастырю собралось множество людей, преподобный приказал всех пустить в ограду. Ученики смутились, зная, что монастырь не имеет возможности насытить всех пришедших. Но когда вошли в хлебопекарню, то увидели, что она, по молитвам аввы, наполнена хлебами. И такое чудо повторялось всякий раз, когда преподобный Феодосии хотел помочь бедствующим.     В монастыре преподобный устроил странноприимные дома, от- дельные больницы для иноков и мирян, а также убежища для  престарелых. Ввиду того, что в Лавре собрались люди из разных  стран, преподобный устроил Богослужение на разных языках —  греческом, грузинском и армянском. Для приобщения Святых Тайн все собирались в большую церковь, где Богослужение совер-  шалось на греческом языке.     Во время правления Константинопольского императора Анаста- сия (491—518) возникла ересь Евтихия и Севера, не признавав- ших ни таинств, ни священства. Император примкнул к лжеуче- нию, и православные начали терпеть гонения. Преподобный Фео- досии твердо встал на защиту Православия и написал от лица пустынников послание императору, где обличал его и опровергал все бывшие и осужденные Вселенскими Соборами ереси. Он под- твердил, что пустынножители и иноки будут твердо держаться Православного исповедания. Император смирился на недолгое время, а потом возобновил гонение на православных. Святой ста- рец тогда проявил великую ревность за истину. Он, оставив оби- тель, пришел в Иерусалим и в Великой церкви, став на возвы- шении, возгласил во всеуслышание: «Кто не почитает четыре Все- ленских Собора, да будет анафема». За этот смелый поступок преподобный был сослан в заточение, но скоро возвратился после смерти императора.     Преподобный Феодосии при жизни совершал много исцелений и других чудес, приходя на помощь бедствующим. Однажды он молитвой погубил саранчу, опустошавшую поля в Палестине; по его предстательству воины сохранялись от гибели, спасались поги- бающие в кораблекрушениях и заблудившиеся в пустынях.     Однажды преподобный велел ударить в било, чтобы братия собрались на молитву, и сказал: «Гнев Божий надвигается на восточную страну». Через несколько дней стало известно, что сильное землетрясение разрушило город Антиохию в тот час, когда преподобный призвал иноков на молитву. Перед своей кончиной преподобный Феодосии призвал к себе трех любимых епископов и открыл им, что скоро отойдет ко Господу. Через три дня он скончался в возрасте 105-ти лет, в 529 году. Тело святого было с честью погребено в пещере, в которой он жил в начале своего подвига. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Сле́зъ твои́хъ тече́ньми пꙋсты́ни безпло́дное воздѣ́лалъ є҆сѝ, и҆ и҆̀же и҆з꙽ глꙋбины̀ воздыха́ньми, во сто̀ трꙋдѡ́въ ѹ҆плодоноси́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ бы́лъ є҆сѝ свѣти́льникъ вселе́ннѣй, сїѧ́ѧ чꙋдесы̀, ѳеодо́сїе ѻ҆́тче на́шъ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Насажде́нъ во дво́рѣхъ гдⷭа твоегѡ̀, прпⷣбными твои́ми добродѣ́тельми краснѡ̀ процвѣ́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ ѹ҆мно́жилъ є҆сѝ ча҄да твоѧ҄ въ пꙋсты́ни, сле́зъ твои́хъ тꙋ́чами напаѧ́ємаѧ, стадонача́льниче бж҃їй бж҃е́ственныхъ дворѡ́въ. тѣ́мже зове́мъ: ра́дꙋйсѧ ѻ҆́тче ѳеодо́сїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Theodosios the Great"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Theodosios the Great lived during the V-VI Centuries, and was the initiator of common-life (coenobitic) monasteries. He was born in Cappadocia of pious parents. Endowed with a splendid voice, he zealously toiled at church reading and singing. And the Monk Theodosios prayed fervently, that the Lord would guide him on the way to salvation. In his early years he visited the Holy Land and met with the Monk Simeon the Stylite (&quot;Pillar-Dweller&quot;,  + 459, Comm. 1 September), who blessed him and predicted future pastoral service for him. Yearning for the solitary life, Saint Theodosios settled in Palestine into a desolate cave, -- in which by tradition, the three Magi had spent the night, having come to worship at the Nativity of the Saviour of the world. In it he dwelt for 30 years in great abstinence and unceasing prayer. Steadily there began to throng to the ascetic those wanting to live under his guidance. When the cave could no more hold all the gathered monks, the Monk Theodosios began to pray, that the Lord Himself would point out the place for the monks. Taking with him a censer with cold unlit coals, the monk went into the wilderness. At a certain spot the coals fired up and set the incense smoke to rising. Here also the monk founded the first common-life monastery, or Lavra [Greek &quot;Laura&quot; meaning &quot;broad&quot; or populous&quot;; in Russia were four such: Trinity-Sergeev, Kievo-Pechersk, Alexander-Nevsk and Pochaev], under the ustav-rule of Saint Basil the Great (+379, Comm. 1 January). Soon the Lavra of the Monk Theodosios became reknown, and up to 700 monks gathered at it. According to the final testament of the Monk Theodosios, the Lavra rendered service to neighbour, giving aid to all the poor and providing shelter for wanderers. 	The Monk Theodosios was extremely compassionate. One time when there was a famine in Palestine and a multitude of people gathered at the monastery, the monk gave orders to allow everyone into the monastery enclosure. His disciples were annoyed, knowing, that the monastery did not have the means to feed all those who had come. But when they went into the bakery, they saw that then through the prayers of the abba, that it was filled with bread. And suchlike a miracle was repeated every time, when the Monk Theodosios wanted to give help to the destitute. 	At the monastery the Monk Theodosios built an home for taking in strangers, separate infirmaries for monks and laymen, and also a shelter for the dying. Seeing that at the Lavra were gathered people from various lands, the monk arranged for Divine-services in the various languages -- Greek, Gruzian (Georgian) and Armenian. For communing the Holy Mysteries all gathered in the large church, where Divine-services were done in Greek. 	During the reign of the Constantinople emperor Anastasias (491-518) there arose the heresy of Eutykhios and Severus, which recognised neither the sacraments nor the clergy. The emperor joined in with the false-teaching, and the Orthodox began to suffer persecution. The Monk Theodosios stood firmly in defense of Orthodoxy and on behalf of the wilderness monks wrote a missive to the emperor, in which they denounced him and refuted the condemned heresy with the teachings of the OEcumenical Councils. He affirmed moreover, that the wilderness-dwellers and monks would firmly support the Orthodox confession. The emperor showed restraint for a short while, but then he renewed persecution of the Orthodox. The holy elder then manifest great zeal for the truth. Leaving the monastery, he came to Jerusalem and in the &quot;Great&quot; church, stood at the high place and cried out for all to hear: &quot;Whoever honoureth not the four OEcumenical Councils, let them be anathema!&quot;. For this bold deed the monk was sent to prison, but soon returned after the death of the emperor.  	The Monk Theodosios during his life accomplished many healings and other miracles, coming to the aid of the needy. One time by prayer he destroyed locusts that were devastating the fields in Palestine; also by his intercession, soldiers were kept from perishing, and he saved both those perishing in shipwreck and those lost in the desert.  	One time the monk gave orders to strike the signal, so that the brethren would gather at prayer, and said: &quot;The wrath of God draweth near the Eastern land&quot;. After several days it became known, that a strong earthquake had destroyed the city of Antioch at that very hour, when the monk had summoned the brethren to prayer. Before his death, the Monk Theodosios summoned to him three beloved bishops and revealed to them, that he would soon expire to the Lord. After three days he died at the age of 105, in the year 529. The body of the saint was buried with reverence in the cave, in which he lived at the beginning of his ascetic deeds. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
With the streams of thy tears thou didst irrigate the barren desert,/ and with sighs from the depths of thy soul thou didst render thy labors fruitful an hundredfold./ Thou wast a beacon for the whole world, radiating miracles.// O our father Theodosius, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Planted in the courts of thy Lord, thou didst flourish most beauteously in thy venerable virtues,/ and didst increase in number thy children in the desert,/ watering them with the torrents of thy tears, O godly chief shepherd of the flocks divine.// Wherefore, we cry out: Rejoice, O father Theodosius!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>