<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Фома Малеин"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Преподобный Фома Малеин (X) до принятия иночества был военачальником. Могучий и храбрый, он участвовал во многих сражениях, приносил победы своим соотечественникам, за что поль- зовался славой и уважением. Но, стремясь всем сердцем к Богу, Фома оставил мир с его почестями и принял иноческий постриг. С великим смирением он посещал старцев-монахов, прося у них руководства в духовной жизни. Через несколько лет Фома полу- чил благословение на уединенную пустынническую жизнь и, укреп- ленный особым откровением, полученным через святого пророка Божия Илию, удалился на гору Малея (восточная часть Афона). Пребывая в полном одиночестве, святой Фома, боролся с невиди- мыми врагами с таким же мужеством, как раньше на войне с ви- димыми врагами отечества. Жизнь и подвиги святого Фомы не могли скрыться от окру- жающих, к нему стали стекаться люди, искавшие духовного руко- водства, а также страдавшие от болезней, ибо он получил от Бога благодать исцеления недугов. Многие верующие получали помощь по молитвам преподобного и по отшествии его к Богу (X). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е ѻ҆тє́цъ на́шихъ, творѧ́й при́снѡ съ на́ми по твое́й кро́тости, не ѡ҆ста́ви млⷭть твою̀ ѿ на́съ, но мл҃твами и҆́хъ въ ми́рѣ ѹ҆пра́ви живо́тъ на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Ве́лїю побѣ́дꙋ мꙋ́жески показа́лъ є҆сѝ, ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже бж҃е́ственною любо́вїю разгорѣ́всѧ, царѧ̀ тлѣ́ннаго и҆ всѧ҄ кра҄снаѧ преѡби́дѣлъ є҆сѝ: на горѣ̀ мале́йстѣй вселе́нїе соверши́въ, ѿ неѧ́же въ нбⷭнаѧ возше́лъ є҆сѝ къ цр҃ю̀ царе́й ѳѡмо̀, молѝ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Thomas the Maleian"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Thomas the Maleian was a military commander before accepting monasticism. Powerful and brave, he had participated in many a battle, and he brought victory to his countrymen, for which he gained glory and esteem. But, striving with all his heart towards God, Thomas left the world with its honours and he took monastic vows. 	With great humility he visited monastic-elders, asking of them guidance in the spiritual life. After several years Thomas received the blessing for solitary wilderness life and, strengthened in particular by a revelation through the holy prophet of God Elias, he settled on Mount Maleia (eastern part of Athos). Dwelling in complete seclusion, Saint Thomas fought with invisible enemies with suchlike a courage, as before he had against the visible enemies of his country. 	The life and deeds of Saint Thomas were not able to be concealed from the surrounding area. People began to flock to him seeking spiritual guidance, and even those suffering from sickness, since he received from God the blessing to heal infirmities.  	Many believers received help through the prayers of the monk and upon his departure to God (X). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O God of our fathers,/ deal with us ever according to Thy meekness./ Deprive us not of Thy mercy,/ but through their supplications// direct our life in peace.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Truly thou didst show forth a great victory!/ Wherefore, aflame with divine life, thou didst vanquish the corrupt king and all beautiful things,/ making thine abode on Mount Maleum,/ from whence thou didst ascend to the King of kings in the heavens.// O Thomas, pray thou unceasingly for us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>