<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Лазарь Галисийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov">
Преподобный Лазарь Галисийский родился в Лидии, в городе Магнезии. Образованный и Боголюбивый юноша, Лазарь стал иноком в обители святого Саввы, основанной великим подвижником благочестия в Палестине. Десять лет провел преподобный в стенах этой обители, стяжав любовь и благоговение братии перед высотой его монашеского подвига.

Рукоположенный Иерусалимским патриархом во пресвитера, преподобный Лазарь возвратился на родину и поселился недалеко от Ефеса на пустынной горе Галисийской. Здесь он был удостоен чудного видения: огненный столп, восходящий на небо, окружали Ангелы, поющие: "Да воскреснет Бог и расточатся врази Его". На месте, где святому было явлено это чудо, он построил храм во имя Воскресения Христова и принял на себя подвиг столпничества. Вскоре к великому подвижнику стали стекаться иноки, жаждущие мудрого духовного окормления Боговдохновенным словом и благим примером святого. Так возник монастырь.

Получив откровение о своей скорой кончине, преподобный оповестил об этом братию, но по слезной молитве всех Господь продлил земную жизнь святого Лазаря еще на 15 лет.

Преподобный Лазарь скончался 72-х лет, в 1053 году. Братия похоронила тело святого в столпе, на котором он подвизался. Преподобный прославлен многими посмертными чудесами.


</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Бдѣ́нными мл҃твами, тече́ньми сле́зными сто́лпъ ѡ҆мочи́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ и҆з꙽ глꙋбины̀ воздыха́ньми во сто̀ трꙋдѡ́въ ѹ҆плодоноси́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ бы́лъ є҆сѝ па́стырь, всѣ҄мъ подаѧ̀ проще́нїе, прпⷣбне ѻ҆́тче на́шъ ла́заре, моли́сѧ хрⷭтꙋ̀ бг҃ꙋ сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ свѣти́льника превели́каго, цр҃ковь хрⷭто́ва сла́витъ тѧ̀ съ весе́лїемъ ѱсало́мски: тѣ́мже не преста́й молѧ́сѧ хрⷭтꙋ̀ да́ти всѣ҄мъ прегрѣше́нїй проще́нїе.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Our Venerable Father and Wonderworker Lazarus, an Ascetic of Mount Galesius"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
       The Ven. Lazarus was born in the village of Magnesia in Asia Minor. From
childhood he distinguished himself by gentleness, meekness, compassion and love
of the poor, and during his whole life he signed himself with great asceticism.
Having traveled to worship in the Jerusalem holy places, he practiced asceticism
for ten years as a monk in the Laura of St. Sabbas in Palestine. Being worthy of
holiness by his good works, the Ven. Lazarus, upon revelation from above, left for
Mount Galesius (near Ephesus) and built on it the Monastery of the Resurrection of
Christ, where he practiced asceticism on a pillar. “Having subdued the flesh to the
spirit”, having tamed “its great turmoil” “through spiritual armor”, “in the
mountains and arid deserts ever learning to ascend to the divine being”, he
achieved the gift of prophecy and insight. Pious people began to gather around
him, wishing to learn from him the highest asceticism of perfection. He died at age
72, in the middle of the 11th Century, and was buried on a pillar. See July 17.

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
With prayerful vigils and outpourings of tears didst thou water thy pillar,/ and with sighs from the depths of thy soul thou didst render thy labors fruitful an hun­dredfold./ Thou wast a shepherd granting the petitions of all.// O our father Lazarus, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
With gladness the Church of Christ doth glorify thee in psalms as a luminary most great./ Wherefore, cease thou never to beseech Christ,// that He grant forgiveness of transgressions unto all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>
