<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святая мученица Феодосия Тирская"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святая мученица Феодосия Тирская пострадала в 307 или 308 году, сведения о ее жизни помещены 3 апреля. 29 мая празднуется память перенесения ее мощей в Константинополь и Венецию. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Добродѣ́тель бл҃гопрїѧ́тнѡ мч҃нце пости́гла є҆сѝ, хрⷭто́во прїѧ́телище бы́вши чи́стое, и҆ ст҃а́гѡ дх҃а до́мъ возлю́бленъ: ѿню́дꙋже посрами́ла є҆сѝ врага̀ борю́щаго ро́дъ человѣ́ческїй, до́брѣ страда́вшаѧ, и҆ посѣ́кла є҆сѝ копрѡнѵ́ма ѳеодо́сїе, мече́мъ вѣ́ры: и҆ къ черто́гꙋ нбⷭномꙋ преста́виласѧ є҆сѝ ра́дꙋющисѧ. тебѐ вѣ́рою чтꙋ́щымъ при́снѡ просѝ ве́лїѧ млⷭти. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Трꙋда́ми живо́тъ нетрꙋ́дный дости́гла є҆сѝ, кро́вїю же копрѡнѵ́ма ѹ҆дави́ла є҆сѝ мч҃нце, скве́рнаго врага̀ хрⷭто́вы це́ркве, всебл҃же́ннаѧ ѳеодо́сїе: и҆ съ вы́шними ра́дꙋешисѧ во́инствы, чтꙋ́щыѧ па́мѧть твою̀ покрыва́ющи. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyress Theodosia of Tyre"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyress Theodosia of Tyre suffered for Christ in the year 307 or 308, and the account of her life is under 3 April. On 29 May is celebrated the memory of the transfer of her relics to Constantinople and Venice.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Thou didst right-pleasingly attain unto virtue, O martyr,/ and becamest a pure habitation of Christ, the beloved abode of the Holy Spirit./ Wherefore, suffering well,/ thou didst put to shame the enemy who wageth war upon the human race./ and didst cut down Copronymus with the sword of the Faith, O Theodosia;/ and, rejoicing, thou hast passed over to the heavenly bridal-chamber.// Ask thou great mercy for those who ever honor thee with faith.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Through labors thou didst attain unto the life abounding in ease, O martyr,/ and with thy blood thou didst choke Copronymus,/ the enemy of the Church of Christ,/ O most blessed Theodosia;/ and thou dost rejoice with the armies on high,// protecting those who honor thy memory.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>