<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Явление иконы Пресвятой Богородицы во граде Казани (1579)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
1 октября 1552 года, в праздник Покрова Пресвятой Богоро- дицы, ночью, Иоанн IV, предводитель русских воинов, готовивших- ся к решительному штурму татарской Казани, вдруг услышал бла- говест московских колоколов. Царь понял, что это — знамение милости Божией: по молитвам Взбранной Воеводы Господь вос- хотел обратить к Себе народ казанский. Покорением Казани под покровом Пресвятой Богородицы было завершено дело, начатое в 1164 году святым князем Андреем Бо- голюбским (11 1174; память 4 июля). Волга — главный водный путь страны — стала русской рекой. Из татарского плена было освобождено 60 000 русских людей. Началось просвещение татар светом Евангельской истины. Явились первые мученики — святые Петр и Стефан (память 24 марта). Новоучрежденная Ка- занская епархия вошла в состав Русской Церкви и вскоре просия- ла своими архиепископами: святителем Гурием (+ 1563; память 5 декабря) и святителем Германом ( } 1567; память 6 ноября). • • Но особенно способствовало возвышению Православия среди волжских магометан явление в городе Казани 8 июля 1579 года чудотворной иконы Божией Матери. Трудно шло дело проповеди Евангелия в покоренном царстве среди закоренелых мусульман и язычников. Пресвятая Богороди- ца, покровительница проповедников Слова Божия, еще в земной Своей жизни разделявшая со святыми Апостолами благовест- нические труды, видя старания русских миссионеров, не замед- лила послать им Небесную помощь, явив Свою чудотворную икону. 28 июня-1579 года страшный пожар, начавшийся около церкви святителя Николая Тульского, истребил часть города и обратил в пепел половину Казанского Кремля. Злорадствовали поклонники Магомета, думая, что Бог прогневался на христиан. «Вера Хри- стова,— говорит летописец, — сделалась притчею и поруганием». Но пожар в Казани явился предзнаменованием окончательного падения ислама и утверждения Православия на всей златоордын- ской земле, будущем Востоке Русского государства. Город вскоре начал вставать из руин. Вместе с другими пого- рельцами, недалеко от места начала пожара строил дом стрелец Даниил Онучин. Его девятилетней дочери Матроне явилась в сон- ном видении Божия Матерь и повелела достать Ее икону, зарытую в земле еще при господстве мусульман тайными исповедниками Православия. На слова девочки не обратили внимания. Трижды являлась Богородица и указывала место, где укрыта чудотворная икона. Наконец, Матрона со своей матерью стали рыть в указан- ном месте и обрели святую икону. На место чудесного обретения прибыл во главе духовенства архиепископ Иеремия и перенес свя- той образ в близрасположенный храм во имя святителя Николая, откуда, после молебна,, перенесли его с Крестным ходом в Благо- вещенский собор — первый православный храм города Казани, воздвигнутый Иоанном Грозным. Во время шествия получили ис- целение два слепца — Иосиф и Никита. Список с иконы, явленной в Казани, изложение обстоятельств ее обретения и описание чудес были посланы в 1579 году в Моск- ву. Царь Иоанн Грозный повелел устроить на месте явления храм в честь Казанской иконы Божией Матери, где и поместили святую икону, и основать женский монастырь. Матрона и ее мать, послу- жившие обретению святыни, приняли постриг в этой обители. В Никольском храме, где был совершен первый молебен пред Казанской иконой, был в то время священником будущий Патри- арх Ермоген, святитель Московский {\ 1612; память 17 февраля). Через пятнадцать лет, в 1594 году, уже будучи митрополитом Ка- занским, он составил сказание о священных событиях, очевидцем и участником которых был: «Повесть и чудеса Пречистая Богоро- дицы честнаго, славнаго Ея явления образа, иже в Казани». С большой фактической точностью описаны в повести многие слу- чаи исцеления, совершившиеся от чудотворной иконы по молитвам верующих. Рукопись «Повести» — автограф Святейшего Патриарха Ермогена — целиком воспроизведена в факсимильном издании: Сказание о чудотворной Казанской иконе Пресвятыя Богородицы. С предисловием А. И. Соболевского, М., 1912. Небольшая икона, обретенная девочкой Матроной на недавно присоединенной инородческой окраине Российского царства, стала вскоре всенародной святыней, знамением Небесного покрова Бо- жией Матери, явленного всей Русской Церкви, ибо душа право- славного народа чувствовала особое участие Пречистой Владычи- цы в исторических судьбах Родины. Не случайно Казанский образ является списком с древней Влахернской иконы (празднование 7 июля), написанной святым Евангелистом Лукой, и относится по иконографическому типу к иконам, именуемым Одигитрия-Путе- водительница. Много раз «Матушка Казанская» указывала путь к победе русским православным воинам в исполнении их священ- ного долга перед Богом и Родиной. В год явления ее в Казани (по другим источникам двумя года- ми позже) начался знаменитый поход «за Казань» (за Уральские горы) блаженного Германа, казачьего атамана Ермака Тимофееви- ча Повольского ( | 1584), увенчавшийся присоединением Сибири. Благодатной энергии, излученной чудотворным образом, было до- статочно, чтобы за несколько десятков лет русские землепроходцы- миссионеры прошли на восток, «встречь солнца» многие тысячи километров и в праздник Покрова в 1639 году вышли в первое плавание по Тихому океану, благовествуя спасение окрестным народам. Православные воины и миссионеры шли на восток, отступники бежали на запад. Волной самозванцев и «воровских людей» ста- рались затопить Русь в начале XVII столетия иезуиты. Промыслом Божиим в период польского нашествия (1605—1612), который на- род назвал «Смутным временем», Русскую Церковь возглавлял великий исповедник Православия — священномученик Ермоген, Патриарх Московский и всея Руси, почитатель Казанской иконы Пресвятой Богородицы, автор «Сказания» о ней и Службы ей. В трудные дни. когда Москва была занята поляками, а по стране ширились усобицы и нестроения, непреклонный страдалец за Святую веру и Отечество, находясь под стражей, сумел тайно отправить в Нижний Новгород воззвание: «Пишите в Казань к митрополиту Ефрему, пусть пошлет в полки к боярам и к казац- кому войску учительную грамоту, чтобы они крепко стояли за веру, унимали грабеж, сохраняли братство, и как обещались положить души свои за дом Пречистой и за чудотворцев и за веру, так бы и совершили. Да и во все города пишите... везде говорите моим именем». Нижегородцы откликнулись на призыв первосвятителя. Собранное ополчение возглавил князь Димитрий Михайлович По- жарский. Присоединившиеся к ополчению казанские дружины принесли с собой список с Казанской чудотворной иконы, которую в Яро- славле передали князю Димитрию. Пресвятая Владычица взяла ополчение под Свое покровительство, и Ее заступлением была спасена Россия. Огромные трудности испытывали русские войска: внутреннюю вражду, недостаток оружия и продовольствия. В осеннюю непого- ду двинулось русское воинство на штурм Москвы, находившейся в руках поляков. Трехдневный пост и усердная молитва пред Казанской иконой Божией Матери приклонили Господа на милость. В осажденном Кремле находился в то время в плену прибывший из Греции, тя- жело больной от потрясений и переживаний, архиепископ Элас- сонский Арсений (впоследствии архиепископ Суздальский; + 1626; 13 апреля). Ночью келлия святителя Арсения вдруг озарилась Божественным светом, он увидел Преподобного Сергия Радонеж- ского (память 5 июля и 25 сентября), который сказал: «Арсений, наши молитвы услышаны; предстательством Богородицы суд Бо- жий об Отечестве преложен на милость; заутра Москва будет в руках осаждающих и Россия спасена». Как бы в подтверждение истинности пророчества архиепископ получил исцеление от болезни. Святитель послал известие об этом радостном событии русским воинам. На следующий день, 22 ок- тября 1612 года, русские войска,, воодушевленные видением, одер- жали крупную победу и взяли Китай-город, а через 2 дня — Кремль. В воскресенье, 25 октября, русские дружины торжественно, с Крестным ходом, пошли в Кремль, неся Казанскую икону. На Лобном месте Крестный ход был встречен вышедшим из Кремля архиепископом Арсением, который нес Владимирскую икону Бого- родицы, сохраненную им в плену. Потрясенный свершившейся встречей двух чудотворных икон Богородицы, народ со слезами молился Небесной Заступнице. По изгнании поляков из Москвы князь Димитрий Пожарский, по данным Никоновской летописи, поставил святую Казанскую икону в своей приходской церкви Введения во храм Пресвятой Богородицы, на Лубянке, в Москве. Позже иждивением князя- патриота на Красной площади был воздвигнут Казанский собор. Святая икона, бывшая в войсках Пожарского при освобождении Москвы, в 1636 году перенесена была в новоустроенный храм. Ныне этот святой образ находится в Богоявленском Патриаршем соборе Москвы. В память освобождения Москвы от поляков установлено было совершать 22 октября особое празднование в честь Казанской иконы Божией Матери. Сначала это празднование совершалось лишь в Москве, а с 1649 года было сделано всероссийским. В 1709 году перед Полтавской битвой Петр Великий со своим воинством молился перед иконой Казанской Божией Матери (из села Каплуновки). В 1721 году Петр перенес один из списков с Казанской иконы Богородицы из Москвы в Петербург, где икона вначале была поставлена в часовне, потом в Александро-Невской Лавре, а с 1737 года в храме в честь Рождества Богородицы на Невском проспекте. В 1811 году перед Отечественной войной свя- тая икона Небесной Заступницы перенесена в новосозданный Ка- занский собор. В 1812 году Казанский образ Божией Матери осенял русских солдат, отразивших французское нашествие. В праздник Казанской иконы 22 октября 1812 года русские отряды под предводительством Милорадовича и Платова разбили арьергард Даву. Это было пер- вое крупное поражение французов после ухода из Москвы, враг потерял 7 тысяч человек. В тот день выпал снег, начались силь- ные морозы, а армия покорителя Европы начала таять. ...Казанский собор в Петербурге строился с 1801 по 1811 год — как бы специально для того, чтобы стать храмом-памятником русской славы в Отечественной войне 1812 года. Иконостас глав- ного алтаря тонкой чеканной работы, исполнен из ста пудов се- ребра: из них сорок пожертвованы храму донскими казаками, отбившими в 1812 году это серебро у французов. Стены собора украшены трофеями, взятыми у французов в 1812 году. Враже- ские знамена склонились у священной гробницы погребенного в соборе князя Михаила Кутузова-Смоленского, спасителя Оте- чества. Бронзовые изваяния Кутузова и Барклая де Толли стоят перед храмом у концов колоннады, полукругом обнявшей собор- ную площадь... В многочисленных чудотворных списках с Казанской иконы прославляется на Руси Пречистая Богородица, Покровительница православного русского народа. Из множества икон Богородицы, почитаемых в Русской Православной Церкви, ни одна не распро- странена в таком числе, как Казанская. Всей Православной Русью она свято чтится, к ней чаще всего обращают взоры в бе- дах и болезнях, взывая: «Заступнице усердная, Мати Господа Вышняго, за всех молиши Сына Твоего Христа Бога нашего... всем полезная даруй и вся спаси, Богородице Дево, Ты бо еси Божественный покров рабом Твоим». Благодатным осенением расположились иконы Пречистой Бо- городицы по лицу нашей Отчизны, воистину образуя Небесный покров, Ее неустанным ходатайством ниспосланный Божествен- ным Сыном, принесшим Себя в жертву для спасения человечества. Древний Владимирский святой образ Богородицы хранит и бла- гословляет наши северные пределы, Смоленская и Почаевская иконы ограждают запад, а на восток, до края земли сияет лучами неизбывной благодати чудотворный Казанский образ Пречистой нашей Матери. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Застꙋ́пнице ѹ҆се́рднаѧ, мт҃и гдⷭа вы́шнѧгѡ, за всѣ́хъ мо́лиши сн҃а твоего̀ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а на́шего, и҆ всѣ҄мъ твори́ши сп҃сти́сѧ, въ держа́вный тво́й покро́въ прибѣга́ющымъ. всѣ́хъ на́съ застꙋпѝ, ѽ гпⷭжѐ цр҃и́це и҆ влⷣчце, и҆̀же въ напа́стехъ и҆ ско́рбехъ, и҆ въ болѣ́знехъ ѡ҆бремене́нныхъ грѣхѝ мно́гими, предстоѧ́щихъ и҆ молѧ́щихсѧ тебѣ̀ ѹ҆миле́нною дꙋше́ю, и҆ сокрꙋше́ннымъ се́рдцемъ, пред꙽ пречⷭтымъ твои́мъ ѡ҆́бразомъ со слеза́ми, и҆ невозвра́тнѡ наде́ждꙋ и҆мꙋ́щихъ на тѧ̀, и҆збавле́нїѧ всѣ́хъ ѕѡ́лъ, всѣ҄мъ полє́знаѧ да́рꙋй, и҆ всѧ҄ сп҃сѝ бцⷣе дв҃о: ты́ бо є҆сѝ бж҃е́ственный покро́въ рабѡ́мъ твои҄мъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Притеце́мъ лю́дїе къ ти́хомꙋ семꙋ̀ и҆ до́бромꙋ приста́нищꙋ, ско́рой помо́щницѣ, гото́вомꙋ и҆ те́пломꙋ сп҃се́нїю, покро́вꙋ дв҃ы, ѹ҆скори́мъ на мл҃твꙋ, и҆ потщи́мсѧ на покаѧ́нїе: и҆сточа́етъ бо на́мъ неѡскꙋ҄дныѧ млⷭти, пречⷭтаѧ бцⷣа, предварѧ́етъ на по́мощь, и҆ и҆збавлѧ́етъ ѿ вели́кихъ бѣ́дъ и҆ ѕѡ́лъ, бл҃гонра҄вныѧ и҆ бг҃обоѧ́щыѧсѧ рабы҄ своѧ҄. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Appearance of the Icon of the MostHoly Mother of God in the City of Kazan (1579)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
On 1 October 1552, on the feastday of the Pokrov-Protection of the MostHoly Mother of God, at night, tsar Ivan IV in heading the Russian forces made ready for a decisive assault against the Tatar city of Kazan, and suddenly he heard the peeling of the Moscow bells. The tsar realised that this was a sign of the mercy of God: that through the prayers of the mighty commander-in-chief, the Lord deigned that the Kazan people should be converted to Him. 	The surrender of Kazan on the feast of the Pokrov-Protection of the MostHoly Mother of God completed a course of events, initiated way back centuries earlier in the year 1164 by holy Prince Andrei Bogoliubsky (+ 1174, Comm. 4 July), against the Moslem Volga Bulgars. With the taking of Kazan, the Volga -- the chief waterway route of the land, became finally a Russian river. And from Tatar servitude were liberated 60,000 Russian people. The enlightenment of the Tatars with the light of the Gospel truth was started. There were the first martyrs -- Saints Peter and Stephen (Comm. 24 March). The newly established Kazan diocese entered into the complexion of the Russian Church and was soon illustrious in its own archbishops: Sainted Gurii (+ 1563, Comm. 5December) and Sainted German (+ 1567, Comm. 6 November). 	But the advance of Orthodoxy was especially enabled amongst the Volga Mahometans by the appearance, on 8 July 1579, of the wonderworking Icon of the Mother of God in the city of Kazan. Preaching the Gospel had been a difficult matter in this conquered kingdom amongst the incorrigible Moslems and pagans. The MostHoly Mother of God, Mediatrix of preachers of the Word of God, Who even during Her earthly life shared in the evangelic work of the holy Apostles, -- in looking down upon the efforts of the Russian missionaries, She did not hesitate to send them Heavenly help, manifest through Her wonderworking Icon. 	On 28 June 1579 there occurred a terrible conflagration which had started around the church of Sainted Nikolai of Tula. This fire destroyed part of the city and turned to ashes half of the Kazan Kremlin. The adherents of Mahomet gloated, supposing, that God had become angered against the Christians. &quot;The faith of Christ, -- says the chronicler, -- is rendered a fable and an outrage&quot;. But the conflagration at Kazan was the foreboding of the ultimate fall of Islam and affirmation of Orthodoxy throughout all the land of the Golden Horde, the future East portion of the Russian realm. 	The city began quickly to rise up from its ruins. Together with others who had been burned out, and not far from where the conflagration had started, -- was built the house of the musketeer Daniil Onuchin. The Mother of God appeared in a dream to his nine year old daughter Matrona and commanded her to find Her icon, hidden in the ground by secret confessors of Orthodoxy way back still in the time of Moslem rule. But to the words of a mere girl they paid no attention. Thrice the Mother of God appeared and pointed out the spot, where the wonderworking icon had been concealed. Finally, Matrona with her mother began to dig in the indicated place and they found the sacred icon. To this place of the miraculous discovery there came archbishop Jeremii at the head of his clergy and transported the holy image into a church of Saint Nicholas situated nearby. From there, after a molieben, amidst a church procession they transferred it to the Annunciation cathedral -- the first Orthodox temple in the city of Kazan, erected by tsar Ivan the Terrible. During the time of the procession there occurred the healing of two blind men -- Iosif and Nikita. 	A copy of the Icon, which had appeared at Kazan, together with an account of the circumstances of its discovery and descriptions of the miracles was dispatched in 1579 to Moscow. Tsar Ivan the Terrible gave orders to build at the place of its appearance a temple in honour of the Kazan Icon of the Mother of God, to install therein the holy icon, and to found there also a women&apos;s monastery. Matrona and her mother, instrumental in finding the sacred icon, accepted monastic tonsure at this monastery. 	At the Nikol&apos;sk (Nicholas) church, where the first molieben had been made before the Kazan Icon, was serving at this time as priest the future Sainted Ermogen, Patriarch of Moscow (+ 1612, Comm. 17 February). Fifteen years later, in 1594, now as Metropolitan of Kazan, he compiled a report of the holy events to which he had been an eyewitness and participant: &quot;Account and Miracles of the MostPure Mother of God from Her Venerable and Gloriously Manifest Image at Kazan&quot;. In this account are descriptions with great factual precision regarding many an instance of healing, from the wonderworking Icon through the prayers of believers. The &quot;Account&quot; manuscript -- written by His Holiness Patriarch Ermogen -- was in its entirety reproduced in facsimile edition: &quot;Report about the Wonderworking Kazan Icon of the MostHoly Mother of God&quot;, with an introduction by A. I. Sobolevsky, M(oscow) 1912. 	The not-large Icon, discovered by the girl Matrona in the then recently annexed foreign frontier of the Russian realm, soon became a national sacred item, a sign of the Heavenly protection of the Mother of God, manifest for all the Russian Church, since the soul of the Orthodox nation sensed the special participation of the All-Pure Lady Mother of God in the historical destiny of its &quot;Rodina&quot; native-land. Not by mere chance was the Kazan Image a copy of the ancient Blakhernae Icon (Comm. 7 July) written by the holy Evangelist Luke, and considered in its iconographic type  to be of icons named &quot;Hodegetria&quot; (&quot;Putevoditel&apos;nitsa&quot;, &quot;Way-Guide&quot;). Many a time the &quot;Kazan Mother&quot; showed the way to victory for Russian Orthodox soldiers in the fulfilling of their sacred duty for God and Country.  	In the year of its appearance at Kazan (in other sources two years afterwards) there began the remarkable onward march &quot;Beyond Kazan&quot; (beyond the Ural Mountains) envisioned by Blessed German (+ 1567, Comm. 6 November), and taken by the Cossack ataman Ermak Timofeevich Povol&apos;sky (+ 1584), an effort crowned finally with the annexation of Siberia. With a graced energy and coursing about in miraculous manner it proved sufficient, that for some several decades Russian explorer-missionaries should proceed to the East, &quot; to meet the sun&quot;, going many thousands of kilometers. On the feastday of the Pokrov (Protection, 1 October) in 1639 they sailed out on their first voyage along the Pacific Ocean, preaching salvation to the surrounding peoples. 	Orthodox soldiers and missionaries went east, while apostates fled to the West. Jesuits seemingly attempted to drown Rus&apos; at the beginning XVII Century with tumultuous waves of sovereign-imposters and &quot;rapacious people&quot;. It was indeed through Divine Providence, during the period of the Polish Occupation (1605-1612), which the nation termed the &quot;Time of Troubles&quot;, that the Russian Church was headed by a great confessor of Orthodoxy -- the PriestMartyr Ermogen, Patriarch of Moscow and All Rus&apos;, who had been among those first to venerate the Kazan Icon of the MostHoly Mother of God, becoming the author of the &quot;Account&quot; about it and the Service to it. 	During the difficult days when Moscow was occupied by the Polish, and discord and disorder having spread throughout all the land, this resolute sufferer for the Holy Faith and Fatherland was held under guard, and he managed secretly to send off to Nizhni Novgorod an appeal: &quot;Write to Kazan to metropolitan Emphrem, and let there be sent a document of direction to the regiments for the boyars and to the Cossack forces, that they should rise up in force for the faith, put an end to the plundering and preserve brotherhood, and should vow to pledge their souls for the house of the All-Pure and the wonderworkers and for the faith, let there be done. And in every city... write thus in my name&quot;. The Nizhni Novgorod people responded to the appeal of the archpastor. Prince Dimitrii Mikhailovich Pozharsky headed the gathered militia. 	The Kazan forces, joining in with the militia, brought with them a copy of the wonderworking Kazan Icon, which they gave to prince Dimitrii at Yaroslavl&apos;. The MostHoly Lady Mother of God took the militia under Her protection, and by Her intercession Russia was saved. 	The Russian forces experienced tremendous difficulties: inward hostilities, and insufficient armament and supplies. In the bad weather of Autumn the Russian army moved on to storm Moscow, situated in the hands of the Polish.  	A three day fast and fervent prayer before the Kazan Icon of the Mother of God inclined the Lord to mercy. Within the besieged Kremlin at this time was held captive the Hellas Archbishop Arsenios (Arsenii, afterwards Suzdal&apos; archbishop, + 1626, 13 April), who had arrived from Greece and was grievously ill from his journeying and being shaken about. By night the cell of Sainted Arsenii was suddenly lit up by a Divine light, and he beheld the Monk Sergei of Radonezh (Comm. 5 July and 25 September), who said: &quot;Arsenii, our prayers are heard; through the intercession of the Mother of God the Divine judgement of the Fatherland is changed to mercy; on the morrow Moscow wilt be in the hands of its besiegers and Russia saved&quot;. 	As though in proof of the veracity of this prophecy, the archbishop received healing from his sickness, and then this joyful occurrence became known to the Russian forces. On the following day, 22 October 1612, Russian forces, inspired by the vision, seized a sweeping victory and took the Chinese-quarter, and 2 days later -- the Kremlin itself.  	On Sunday, 25 October, Russian forces triumphantly in church procession made entry into the Kremlin, bearing the Kazan Icon. At the Skull-Place (&quot;Lobnoe mesto&quot;, i.e. the public execution spot), the church procession was met by Archbishop Arsenii emerging from the Kremlin, bearing the Vladimir Icon of the Mother of God, saved by him in his captivity. Moved by the effect of the meeting of the two wonderworkings icons of the Mother of God, the people with tears made prayer to the Heavenly Mediatrix. 	With the expulsion of the Polish from Moscow, -- according to the Nikonov chronicle, prince Dimitrii Pozharsky had the holy Kazan Icon placed in his own parish church of the Entry in the Temple of the MostHoly Mother of God, at Lubyanka in Moscow. Afterwards, at the expense of the prince-patriot, there was erected the Kazan cathedral on Red Square. The holy icon, which had been with the armies of Pozharsky during the liberation of Moscow, was transferred in 1636 into the newly constructed temple, the Kazan cathedral. At present, this holy image is situated in the Patriarch&apos;s Theophany cathedral in Moscow.  	In commemoration of the liberation of Moscow from the Polish, a special feastday in honour of the Kazan Icon of the Mother of God was established under 22 October. At first this celebration was made only at Moscow, but from 1649 it became an all-Russian celebration. 	In 1709, before the Poltava Battle, Peter the Great prayed with his soldiery in front an icon of the Kazan Mother of God (that from the village of Kaplunovka). In 1721 Peter transferred one of the copies of the Kazan Icon of the Mother of God from Moscow to Peterburg, where at first the icon was placed in a chapel, then at the Alexandro-Nevsky Lavra monastery, and from 1737 it was in the church of the Nativity of the Mother of God on Nevsky Prospekt. In 1811, before the Fatherland War, the holy icon of the Heavenly Mediatrix was transferred into the newly constructed Kazan cathedral.  	In 1812 the Kazan Icon of the Mother of God provided blessing for Russian soldiers in repulsing the French invasion. On the feast of the Kazan Icon, 22 October 1812, Russian detachments under the command of Miloradovich and Platov destroyed the Davu rearguard. This was the first outstanding blow against the French after their departure from Moscow, and in which the enemy lost seven thousand men. And on this day snow fell, bitter frosts began, and the army that had subdued Europe began to falter.  	...The Kazan cathedral at Peterburg was built in the years 1801-1811 -- as though especially for this, to be a commemorative temple of Russian glory in the 1812 Fatherland War. The iconostas of the main altar was an elaborately wrought work, made of an hundred pud-weight [pud = 36 lbs] of silver: of  this, forty puds were an offering to the temple by the Don Cossacks, having taken this silver in 1812 from the French. The walls of the cathedral were adorned with trophies, taken from the French in 1812. Buried at the cathedral and with enemy standards draped over his holy tomb was prince Mikhail Kutuzov-Smolensky, saviour of the Fatherland. Bronzen sculptures of Kutuzov and Barclay de Tolli stand before the temple at the end of the colonnades, in the hemisphere circling upon the cathedral square... 	Numerous wonderworking copies of the Kazan Icon in Rus&apos; glorify the All-Pure Mother of God, Protectress of the Orthodox Russian people. Of the plethora of icons of the Mother of God venerated in the Russian Orthodox Church, none is more widespread in number than the Kazan Icon. For all Orthodox Rus&apos; it is esteemed as holy, and to it oftenest of all do they turn their gaze in misfortunes and illnesses, crying out: &quot;O fervent Mediatrix, Mother of the Lord MostHigh, for all pray Thine Son Christ our God... with everything grant benefit and save all, O Virgin Birthgiver of God, and be Thou the Divine protection for Thine servant&quot;. 	With blessings of grace are dispersed icons of the All-Pure Mother of God throughout the extent of the Russian land, truly imaging the Heavenly protection, with Her constant intercession sent down by Her Divine Son, having offered Himself in sacrifice for the salvation of mankind. The ancient Vladimir holy Image of the Mother of God preserves and blesses the Northern bounds, the Smolensk and Pochaev Icons guard the West, and in the East, to the ends of the land shine the rays of the inexhaustible grace of the wonderworking Kazan Image of our All-Pure Mother.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O earnest helper, Mother of the Lord Most High,/ thou dpst entreat Christ, thy Son and our God, in behalf of all,/ and causest all to be saved who have recourse to thy mighty protection,/ O Lady, Queen and Mistress,/ help us all who, amid temptations, sorrows and sickness,/ are heavy laden with many sins,/ who stand before thee and with tears pray to thee with compunctionate soul/ and contrite heart before thine all-pure image,/ and who have unfailing hope in thee:/ grant deliverance from all evils,/ and things profitable unto all, O Virgin Theotokos,/ and gave us all, for thou art the divine protection// of thy servants.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
O ye people, let us flee to that calm and good haven, the speedy helper/ and ready and fervent salvation, the protection of the Virgin,/ and let us make haste to prayer and speed to repentance./ For the all-pure Theotokos poureth forth upon us inexhaustible mercies;/ she goeth before to help us and delivereth ,her good-hearted and God-fearing servants// from great misfortunes and evils.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>