<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святители Афанасий и Кирилл, архиепископы Александрийские"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святителям Афанасию и Кириллу, архиепископам Александрий- ским, установлено совместное празднование в знак глубокой бла- годарности Святой Церкви за многолетние неустанные труды в ут- верждении догматов Православной веры и ревностной защиты их от еретических учений.    Сведения о святителе Афанасии помещены 2 мая, о святителе Кирилле — 9 июня. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е ѻ҆тє́цъ на́шихъ, творѧ́й при́снѡ съ на́ми по твое́й кро́тости, не ѡ҆ста́ви млⷭть твою̀ ѿ на́съ, но мл҃твами и҆́хъ въ ми́рѣ ѹ҆пра́ви живо́тъ на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
Дѣ́лы возсїѧ́вше правосла́вїѧ, всѐ погаси́вше ѕлосла́вїе, побѣди́телїе побѣдоно́сцы бы́сте, благоче́стїемъ всѧ҄ ѡ҆богати́вше, це́рковь вельмѝ ѹ҆краси́вше: досто́йнѡ ѡ҆брѣто́стѣ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, да́рꙋюща на́мъ ве́лїю млⷭть. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Сщ҃еннонача́льницы велича́йшїи благоче́стїѧ, и҆ до́блїи побо́рницы це́ркве хрⷭто́вы, всѧ҄ соблюди́те пою́щыѧ: спасѝ ще́дре вѣ́рою чтꙋ́щыѧ тѧ̀. 
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="6">
Правосла́вїѧ насади́въ ѹ҆чє́нїѧ, ѕлосла́вїѧ те́рнїе и҆зсѣ́клъ є҆сѝ, ѹ҆мно́живъ сѣ́мѧ вѣ́ры ѡ҆дожде́нїемъ дх҃а прпⷣбне: тѣ́мже тѧ̀ пое́мъ а҆ѳана́сїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Athanasias and Cyril, Archbishops of Alexandria"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Athanasias and Cyril, Archbishops of Alexandria, have a conjoined feast established to them in acknowledgement of the profound gratitude of Holy Church for their incessant lengthy labour in affirmation of the dogmas of the Orthodox faith and their zealous defense of such against heretical teachings.  	The account about Saint Athanasias is located under 2 May, and about Saint Cyril -- under 9 June.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O God of our fathers,/ deal with us ever according to Thy meekness./ Deprive us not of Thy mercy,/ but through their supplications// direct our life in peace.
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
	Shining forth with works of Orthodoxy and reducing all heresy to ashes,/ ye were victors and conquerors, enriching all with piety;/ and, having greatly adorned the Church,/ ye have acquired Christ God, as is meet,// Who granteth us great mercy.
	</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
O sacred primates most great, champions of the Church of Christ,/ preserve all who chant:// Save those who honor Thee with faith, O Compassionate One!
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="6">
Planting Orthodox doctrine, thou didst cut down the tares of heresy,/ causing the seed of faith to increase/ through the rain of the Spirit, O venerable one.// Wherefore, we hymn thee, O Athanasius.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>