<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Рождество святого Предтечи и Крестителя Господня Иоанна"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Рождество святого Предтечи и Крестителя Господня Иоанна. Как повествует Евангелие (Лк. 1, 57—80), праведные родители святого Иоанна Крестителя — священник Захария и Елисавета, жившие в древнем городе Хевроне, достигли старости,, но не имели детей, так как Елисавета была неплодна. Однажды святой Заха- рия совершал богослужение в Иерусалимском храме и увидел Ар- хангела Гавриила, стоящего по правую сторону жертвенника ка- дильного. Он предсказал, что у Захарии родится сын, который бу- дет провозвестником ожидаемого Ветхозаветной Церковью Спа- сителя— Мессии. Захария смутился, на него напал страх. Он усомнился, что в старости возможно иметь сына, и просил зна- мения. Оно было дано ему, являясь одновременно и наказанием за неверие: Захария был поражен немотой до времени исполне- ния слов Архангела. Святая Елисавета зачала и, боясь насмешек над поздней бере- менностью, таилась пять месяцев, пока ее не посетила приходив- шаяся ей дальней родственницей Преблагословенная Дева Мария, чтобы разделить Свою и ее радость. Елисавета, исполнившись Святого Духа, первая приветствовала Деву Марию как Матерь Божию. Вместе с ней Пресвятую Деву Марию и воплотившегося в Ней Сына Божия приветствовал «играньми, яко песньми» и свя- той Иоанн, еще находившийся в утробе матери своей, праведной Елисаветы. Настало время, и святая Елисавета родила сына, все родствен- ники и друзья радовались вместе с ней. На восьмой день по за- кону Моисееву совершилось его обрезание. Мать назвала его Иоанном. Все были удивлены, так как никто в их роде не носил этого имени. Когда спросили об этом святого Захарию, он попро- сил дощечку и написал на ней: «Иоанн имя ему» — и тотчас свя- зывавшие по предсказанию Архангела его речь узы разрешились, и святой Захария,, исполнившись Духа Святого, прославил Бога и произнес пророческие слова о Явившемся в мир Мессии и о своем сыне Иоанне — Предтече Господа. После Рождества Господа нашего Иисуса Христа и поклонения пастырей и волхвов нечестивый царь Ирод повелел избить всех младенцев. Услышав об этом, святая Елисавета убежала со своим сыном в пустыню и скрывалась в пещере. Святой Захария как священник находился в Иерусалиме и исполнял свое священниче- ское служение в храме. Ирод послал к нему воинов с приказанием открыть местопребывание младенца Иоанна и его матери. Заха- рия ответил, что это ему неизвестно, и был убит прямо в храме. Праведная Елисавета с сыном продолжала жить в пустыне и там умерла. Отрок Иоанн, охраняемый Ангелом, находился в пустыне до того времени, как вышел на проповедь о покаянии и сам спо- добился крестить пришедшего в мир Господа. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Прⷪро́че и҆ прⷣте́че прише́ствїѧ хрⷭто́ва, досто́йнѡ восхвали́ти тѧ̀ недоꙋмѣ́емъ мы̀, любо́вїю чтꙋ́щїи тѧ̀: непло́дство бо ро́ждшїѧ, и҆ ѻ҆́тчее безгла́сїе разрѣши́сѧ сла́внымъ и҆ честны́мъ твои́мъ ржⷭтво́мъ, и҆ воплоще́нїе сн҃а бж҃їѧ мї́рови проповѣ́дꙋетсѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Пре́жде непло́ды, дне́сь хрⷭто́ва прⷣте́чꙋ ражда́етъ, и҆ то́й є҆́сть и҆сполне́нїе всѧ́кагѡ проро́чества: є҆го́же бо прⷪро́цы проповѣ́даша, на сего̀ во ї҆ѻрда́нѣ рꙋ́кꙋ положи́въ, ꙗ҆ви́сѧ бж҃їѧ сло́ва прⷪро́къ, проповѣ́дникъ, вкꙋ́пѣ и҆ прⷣте́ча. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Nativity of the Holy Forerunner and Baptist of the Lord, John"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Nativity of the Holy Forerunner and Baptist of the Lord, John: The Gospel (Lk. 1: 57-80) relates that the righteous parents of Saint John the Baptist -- the Priest Zachariah and Elizabeth, lived in the ancient city of Hebron, and reached old age being childless, since Elizabeth was barren. One time, Saint Zachariah was making Divine services at the Jerusalem Temple and saw the Archangel Gabriel, standing on the right side of the incense offertory. He predicted, that Saint Zachariah would father a son, who would announce the Saviour -- the Messiah, awaited by the Old Testament Church. Zachariah was troubled, and fear fell upon him. He had doubts that in old age it was possible to have a son, and he asked for a sign. And it was given to him -- it appeared at the same time as a chastisement for his unbelief: Zachariah was struck speechless until the time of the fulfillment of the archangel&apos;s words.  	Saint Elizabeth came to be with child, and fearing derision over the lateness of her pregnancy, she kept it secret for five months, until there came visiting her distant relative the All-Blessed Virgin Mary, to share with her Her own joy. Elizabeth, at the prompting of the Holy Spirit, was the first to greet the Virgin Mary as the Mother of God. And together with her Saint John also -- in the womb of his mother Righteous Elizabeth -- did greet &quot;with leaps as in song&quot; the MostHoly Virgin Mary and the Son of God incarnated within Her. 	It became time, and Saint Elizabeth gave birth to a son, and all the relatives and acquaintances rejoiced together with her. On the eighth day, in accord with the law of Moses, was made the circumcision. His mother named him John. Everyone was amazed, since no one in their family had been named such. When they asked Saint Zachariah about this, he motioned for a tablet and wrote on it: &quot;John is his name&quot; -- and immediately the binding of his tongue at the prediction of the archangel was unbound, and Saint Zachariah, at the prompting of the Holy Spirit, glorified God and pronounced the words of prophecy about the Advent-Coming into the world of the Messiah, and about his own son John -- the Forerunner of the Lord. 	After the Nativity of our Lord Jesus Christ and the worship of the shepherds and the Magi, wicked king Herod gave orders to kill all the infants. Hearing about this, Saint Elizabeth fled into the wilderness and hid in a cave. Saint Zachariah as a priest was at Jerusalem and was doing his priestly service in the Temple. Herod sent soldiers to him to find out the abode of the infant John and his mother. Zachariah answered, that their whereabouts were unknown to him, and he was killed right there in the Temple. Righteous Elizabeth continued to live in the wilderness with her son and she died there. The lad John, protected by an Angel, dwelt in the wilderness until such time, when he came preaching about repentance and was himself vouchsafed worthy to baptise the Lord Who was come into the world.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O prophet and forerunner of the coming of Christ,/ we who honor thee with love are at a loss how to praise thee worthily;/ for by thy glorious and honored nativity/ thou didst loose the barrenness of her who gave birth to thee/ and the muteness of thy father,/ and dost proclaim unto the world// the incarnation of the Son of God.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Today she who before was barren/ giveth birth unto the forerunner of Christ,/ and he is the fulfillment of all prophecy;/ for, laying his hand in the Jordan upon Him Whom the prophets foretold,// he hath been shown to be the prophet, herald and forerunner of the Word of God.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>