<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="  Святая мученица Филицата имела семь сыновей: Ианнуария, Феликса, Филиппа, Сильвана, Александра, Виталия и Марциала"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Святая мученица Филицата имела семь сыновей: Ианнуария, Феликса, Филиппа, Сильвана, Александра, Виталия и Марциала. Она была родом из богатой римской семьи. Жрецы обвинили ее в оскорблении богов через распространение христианской веры. Святая Филицата раздала всё свое имение и вместе с сыновьями открыто исповедала веру во Христа. Всех их предали мучениям. Святая Филицата, видя страдания своих сыновей, молила Бога, чтобы они устояли в подвиге и прежде нее вошли в Царство Не- бесное. Все сыновья мученически скончались на глазах матери. После них и сама святая Филицата претерпела мученическую кончину. Святая семья пострадала в Риме около 164 года. Мученице Филицате святитель Григорий Двоеслов посвятил похвальное слово в третьей беседе, произнесенной в храме ее имени. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Holy Martyress Felicita with her Seven Sons: Jannuarius, Felix, Philip, Sylvanus, Alexander, Vitalius and Marcial"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyress Felicita with her Seven Sons: Jannuarius, Felix, Philip, Sylvanus, Alexander, Vitalius and Marcial. Saint Felicita was born of a rich Roman family. Pagan priests made reports of denunciation against her for insulting the gods through spreading the Christian faith. Saint Felicita gave off all her possessions, and together with her sons openly confessed faith in Christ. They were all handed over to torture. Saint Felicita, seeing the suffering of her sons, besought God, that they would stand firm and enter the Heavenly Kingdom before her. All the sons died as martyrs before the eyes of their mother. After them, Saint Felicita herself underwent a martyr&apos;s death. The holy family suffered at Rome in about the year 164. Sainted Gregory Dialogus gave a laudatory sermon for the Martyress Felicita in a third talk, preached in a church named for her.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>