<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Елевферий, мать его мученица Анфия и мученик Корив епарх"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
Святой Елевферий, сын знатного римского гражданина, был воспитан в христианском благочестии своей матерью. Добродетели его были столь высоки, что 20-ти лет от роду он уже был поставлен епископом Иллирийским. При императоре Адриане (II в.) святой Елевферий за смелую проповедь о Христе после мучений был обезглавлен в Риме вместе со своей матерью святой Анфией. Епарх Корив, мучивший святого Елевферия, сам уверовал во Христа и также был казнен.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆ нра́вѡмъ прича́стникъ, и҆ прⷭто́лѡмъ намѣ́стникъ а҆пⷭлѡмъ бы́въ, дѣѧ́нїе ѡ҆брѣ́лъ є҆сѝ бг҃одохнове́нне, въ видѣ́нїѧ восхо́дъ: сегѡ̀ ра́ди сло́во и҆́стины и҆справлѧ́ѧ, и҆ вѣ́ры ра́ди пострада́лъ є҆сѝ да́же до кро́ве, сщ҃енномч҃нче є҆леѵѳе́рїе, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ ѹ҆добре́нїе сщ҃е́нникѡвъ преподо́бне и҆ предꙋвѣща́нїе стрⷭтоте́рпцєвъ всѝ восхвалѧ́емъ, и҆ про́симъ тѧ̀, сщ҃енномꙋ́чениче є҆леѵѳе́рїе: любо́вїю па́мѧть твою̀ пра́зднꙋющыѧ бѣ́дъ многоѡбра́зныхъ свободѝ, молѧ̀ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Hieromartyr Eleutherius and his mother, the Martyr Anthia"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
       His mother, Anthia, brought up St. Eleutherius, the son of a famous Roman citizen, in Christian piety. &quot;Having fixed his most pure mind to God from youth&quot;, he &quot;removed fleshly wisdom from his soul and bountifully enriched himself with the grace of wonders&quot;. His good works were so great, that at 20 years of age he was already installed as the Bishop of Illyricum (Albania). During the reign of Hadrian St. Eleutherius after being tortured was beheaded in Rome together with St. Anthia for zealously preaching Christ. The Eparch Choribus, who tortured Eleutherius, himself believed in Christ and also was beheaded. The relics of St. Eleutherius repose in Rome. The Holy Martyr Anthia is not mentioned in the church services by name. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
As thou didst share in the ways of the apostles/ and didst occupy their throne,/ thou didst find thine activity to be a passage to divine vision,/ O divinely inspired one./ Wherefore, ordering the word of truth,/ thou didst suffer for the Faith even to the shedding of thy blood.// O hieromartyr Eleutherius, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
We all praise thee as the adornment of priests/ and the proclamation of passion-bearers,/ O venerable hieromartyr Eleutherius,/ and we entreat thee:/ From multifarious misfortunes free those who celebrate thy memory with love,// praying unceasingly for us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>