<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Бессребреников мучеников Кира и Иоанна и с ними мучениц Афанасии и дочерей ее: Феодотии, Феоктисты и Евдоксии"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Святой бессребреник Кир был знаменитым врачом в городе Александрии, где родился и вырос. Он был христианином и лечил всех больных безвозмездно, не только подавая помощь в телесных болезнях, но исцеляя также и душевные недуги, которые бывают причинами телесных болезней. Проповедуя Евангельское учение, святой врач многих язычников обращал ко Христу. Во время гоне- ния Диоклитиана (284—305) святой Кир удалился в Аравийскую пустыню, где принял иночество, и продолжал и там лечить людей своей молитвой, получив от Бога дар исцелять все болезни.     В городе Едессе в то время жил воин Иоанн, благочестивый христианин. Когда началось гонение, он пришел в Иерусалим и там, услышав о святом Кире, стал его разыскивать, пошел для это- го в Александрию, затем в Аравию. Найдя святого Кира, Иоанн всей душой привязался к нему и стал его верным последователем. Узнав, что в Египте, в городе Канопе, схвачена христианка Афана- сия с тремя юными дочерьми: Феоктистой — 15 лет, Феодотией —  13 лет и Евдоксией—11 лет, святые Кир и Иоанн поспешили прийти к ним на помощь, опасаясь, как бы страх перед мучениями не заставил их отречься от Христа. Они посетили их в темнице и укрепили в мужестве перед предстоявшим подвигом. Узнав об этом, правитель города схватил святых Кира и Иоанна и, убе- дившись в их твердом и безбоязненном исповедании веры во Хри- ста, предал их страшным пыткам на глазах Афанасии и ее доче- рей. Исповедницы так же стойко перенесли все мучения и были обезглавлены. Вслед за ними на том же месте казнили святых бессребреников Кира и Иоанна (+ 311). Тела их христиане погреб-  ли в церкви святого апостола и евангелиста Марка. В V веке мощи  святых Кира и Иоанна были перенесены из Канопа в Мануфин.  Позднее их мощи были перенесены в Рим, а оттуда в Мюнхен  (сведения помещены 28 июня). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="5">
Чꙋдеса̀ ст҃ы́хъ твои́хъ мч҃нкъ, стѣ́нꙋ неѡбори́мꙋ на́мъ дарова́вый, хрⷭтѐ бж҃е: тѣ́хъ мл҃твами совѣ́ты ꙗ҆зы́кѡвъ разорѝ, ца́рства ски́птры ѹ҆крѣпѝ, ꙗ҆́кѡ є҆ди́нъ бл҃гъ и҆ чл҃вѣколю́бецъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Ѿ бж҃е́ственныѧ бл҃года́ти да́ръ чꙋде́съ прїе́мше ст҃ї́и, чꙋдодѣ́йствꙋете непреста́ннѡ, всѧ҄ на́шѧ стра҄сти рꙋкодѣ́йствомъ сѣкꙋ́ще неви́димымъ, кѵ́ре бг҃омꙋ́дре со ї҆ѡа́нномъ сла́внымъ: вы́ бо бж҃е́ственнїи вра́чеве є҆стѐ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="UnMercenary Martyrs Cyrus and John, and together with them the Martyress Athanasia and her Daughters: Theodotia, Theoktista and Eudoxia"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy UnMercenary Cyrus was a noted physician in the city of Alexandria, where he was born and grew up. He was a Christian and he doctored all the sick for free, not only offering help for bodily ills, but healing also infirmities of soul, such as were causes of bodily sickness. Preaching the Gospel teaching, the holy physician converted many pagans to Christ. During the time of the persecution by Diocletian (284-305), Saint Cyrus withdrew into the Arabian wilderness, where he took on the monastic life, and continued there also to doctor people by his prayer, having received from God the gift to heal every sickness. 	In the city of Edessa at this time lived the soldier John, a pious Christian. When the persecution started, he went to Jerusalem and there, hearing about Saint Cyrus, he began to search for him, and he went first to Alexandria and then to Arabia. Having finally found Saint Cyrus, John with all his heart became attached to him and became his faithful follower. They learned that in Egypt in the city of Canopis had been arrested the Christian Athanasia and her three young daughters: Theoktista -- age 15, Theodotia -- age 13, and Eudoxia -- age 11. Saints Cyrus and John hastened to go to them in help, worrying that fear in the face of torture might impel them to renounce Christ. They visited them in prison and gave them courage to stand what was before them. Learning of this, the governor of the city arrested Saints Cyrus and John, and convincing himself of their steadfast and fearless confession of faith in Christ, he gave them over to terrible tortures before the very eyes of Athanasia and her daughters, who in turn bravely endured all the tortures and were beheaded. After them at the same place they executed the holy UnMercenaries Cyrus and John (+ 311). Christians buried their bodies in a church of the holy Disciple and Evangelist Mark. In the V Century the relics of Saints Cyrus and John were transferred from Canopis to Manuphin. Later on their relics were transferred to Rome, and from there to Munchen (Munich) (an account further is located under 28June).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="5">
O Christ God, Thou hast given us an impregnable rampart in the miracles of Thy holy martyrs./ Through their supplications destroy Thou the councils of the heather/ and strengthen the scepters of kingdoms,// in that Thou alone art good and lovest mankind.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Receiving the gift of miracles from'grace divine,/ O saints, ye work wonders unceasingly/ cutting down all our passions with invisible skill,/ O divinely wise Cyrus and glorious John;// for ye are divine physicians.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>