<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Никита, епископ Новгородский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святитель Никита, епископ Новгородский, в молодые годы по- ступил в Киево-Печерский монастырь и вскоре пожелал уйти в затвор. Игумен предупреждал его о преждевременности такого подвига для молодого инока, но он, понадеявшись на свои силы, не послушался. В затворе святой Никита впал в искушение. Диа- вол явился ему в виде Ангела, и неопытный подвижник покло- нился ему. Бес дал ему совет, как уже достигшему совершенства: «Ты не молись, а только читай и учи других, а я буду молиться вместо тебя»,— и стал около затворника, делая вид, что молится за него. Прельщенный инок Никита превзошел всех в знании книг Ветхого Завета, а о Евангелии ни говорить, ни слушать не хотел. Киево-Печерские старцы пришли к прельщенному и, помолившись, отогнали от него беса. После этого преподобный Никита, оставив по благословению старцев затвор, жил в строгом посте и молит- ве, более всего упражняясь в послушании и смирении. Милосерд- ный Господь, по молитвам святых старцев, возвел его из глубины падения на высокую степень духовного совершенства. Впоследст- вии он был поставлен епископом в Новгород и за свою святую жизнь был награжден от Бога даром чудотворений. Однажды во время засухи он молитвой низвел дождь с неба, в другой раз по его молитве прекратился в городе пожар. 13 лет управлял святитель Никита новгородской паствой и мирно скончался в 1109 году. В 1558 году, при царе Иоанне Васильевиче,, состоялось прославление святителя. Мощи его покоятся ныне в церкви свя- того апостола Филиппа в Новгороде. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Наслади́всѧ бг҃омꙋ́дре воздержа́нїѧ, и҆ жела́нїе пло́ти твоеѧ̀ ѡ҆бꙋзда́въ, на престо́лѣ ст҃и́тельства сѣ́лъ є҆сѝ: и҆ ꙗ҆́кѡ ѕвѣзда̀ многосвѣ́тлаѧ просвѣща́ѧ вѣ́рныхъ сердца̀ зарѧ́ми чꙋде́съ твои́хъ, ѻ҆́тче на́шъ ст҃и́телю нїки́то: и҆ ны́нѣ молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, да сп҃се́тъ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
А҆рхїере́йства са́номъ почти́всѧ, и҆ чи́стѣ чистѣ́йшемꙋ. предстоѧ̀, прилѣ́жнѡ моле́нїе за лю́ди твоѧ҄ приноси́лъ є҆сѝ: ꙗ҆́кѡ и҆ до́ждь мл҃твою све́лъ є҆сѝ, ѻ҆вогда́ же и҆ гра́да запалє́нїѧ ѹ҆гаси́лъ є҆сѝ. и҆ ны́нѣ ст҃и́телю нїки́то, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃стѝ ї҆мпера́тора правосла́внаго, нїкола́ѧ а҆леѯса́ндровича, и҆ лю́ди твоѧ҄ молѧ́щыѧсѧ, да всѝ вопїе́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ ст҃и́телю ѻ҆́тче преди́вный. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Nikita, Bishop of Novgorod"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Nikita, Bishop of Novgorod, in his youth entered the Kievo-Pechersk monastery and soon wished to become an hermit. The hegumen cautioned him that such an exploit for a young monk was premature, but he trusting in his own strength would not take heed. In the hermitage Saint Nikita fell into temptation. The devil appeared to him in the guise of an angel, and the inexperienced ascetic bowed down to him. The devil gave him advice, as it were to one having attained to perfection: &quot;Bother not to pray, but only read and study other things, and I shall pray in place of thee&quot;, -- and he stood about the hermit, giving the appearance of seeming to pray for him. The seduced monk Nikita came to surpass everyone in knowledge of the Books of the Old Testament, but about the Gospel he would not speak, nor wanted to hear it. The Kievo-Pechersk elders went to the seduced monk, and having prayed, they drove out the devil from him. After this the Monk Nikita, remaining an hermit with the blessing of the elders, lived in strict fasting and prayer, more than anyone else practising obedience and humility. Through the prayer of the holy elders, the Merciful Lord brought him up from the depths of his fall to an high degree of spiritual perfection. Afterwards he was made bishop in Novgorod and for his holy life he was rewarded of God with a gift of wonderworking. Once during a time of drought by his prayer he brought down rain from the heavens, and another time by his prayer he stopped a conflagration in the city. Saint Nikita guided the Novgorod flock for 13 years and he died peacefully in 1109. In 1558 during the time of tsar Ioann Vasilievich, the glorification of the saint was made. His relics now rest in the church of the holy Apostle Philip in Novgorod.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>