<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Исидор Пелусиот"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Преподобный Исидор Пелусиот жил в IV—V веках. Родом из Александрии. Вырос в среде благочестивых христиан. Он состоял в родстве с Феофилом, архиепископом Александрийским, и его преемником святым Кириллом. Еще юношей он покинул мир и удалился в Египет на Пелусиотскую гору, которая стала местом его иноческих подвигов. Духовная мудрость и строгий аскетизм преподобного Исидора в соединении с широкой просвещенностью и природным знанием человеческой души позволили ему в корот- кое время снискать уважение и любовь иноков. Они избрали его своим настоятелем и возвели в сан пресвитера. Следуя примеру святителя Иоанна Златоуста, которого ему довелось видеть и слы- шать во время путешествия в Константинополь, преподобный Исидор посвятил себя преимущественно христианской проповеди, той «практической философии», которая, по его собственным сло- вам, является «основанием здания и самим зданием», в то время как логика «есть его украшение», а «созерцание — венец». Он был учителем и безотказным подателем советов для всех, кто обра- щался к нему за духовной поддержкой — будь то простой чело- век,, вельможа, епископ, патриарх Александрийский или сам импе- ратор. После него осталось около 10 000 писем, из которых до нас дошло 2090. Большая часть этих писем содержит глубокие по Богословской мысли и вместе нравственно назидательные толко- вания Священного Писания. Здесь преподобный Исидор выступает как лучший ученик святителя Иоанна Златоуста. Любовь и пре- данность преподобного Исидора к святому Иоанну Златоусту  проявились в решительных действиях в защиту святого Иоанна во  время гонения на него императрицы Евдоксии и архиепископа  Феофила. После смерти святителя, преподобный Исидор убедил  преемника Феофила, святого Кирилла Александрийского, вписать  имя святого Иоанна Златоуста в церковные диптихи как исповед-  ника. По инициативе преподобного Исидора был созван III Все-  ленский Собор в Ефесе (431), на котором было осуждено лжеуче-  ние Нестория о Лице Иисуса Христа.    Преподобный Исидор достиг глубокой старости и скончался около 436 года. Церковный историк Евагрий (VI век) о преподоб- ном Исидоре пишет, что «жизнь его казалась всем жизнью ангель- ской на земле». Другой историк, Никифор Каллист (XI в.), так восхваляет преподобного Исидора: «Он был живым и одушевлен- ным столпом иноческих уставов и Божественного видения и как бы самым высшим образцом теплейшего подражания и учения духовного».    На русском языке издано: Полное собрание сочинений (Непол- ный перевод). — «Христианское чтение», 1828, 1830, 1832, 1834. То же — «Творения святых отцев в русском переводе, издаваемые при Московской Духовной Академии». Тт. 34, 35, 36. М., 1859. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Въ тебѣ̀, ѻ҆́тче, и҆звѣ́стнѡ сп҃се́сѧ є҆́же по ѡ҆́бразꙋ: прїи́мъ бо крⷭтъ послѣ́довалъ є҆сѝ хрⷭтꙋ̀, и҆ дѣ́ѧ ѹ҆чи́лъ є҆сѝ презира́ти ѹ҆́бѡ пло́ть, прехо́дитъ бо: прилѣжа́ти же ѡ҆ дꙋшѝ, ве́щи безсме́ртнѣй: тѣ́мже и҆ со а҆́гг҃лы сра́дꙋетсѧ, прпⷣбне ї҆сї́дѡре дх҃ъ тво́й. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Денни́цꙋ дрꙋгꙋ́ю тѧ̀ цр҃ковь ѡ҆брѣ́тши пресла́вне, твои́хъ слове́съ мо́лнїѧми ѡ҆свѣща́ема, взыва́етъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ всебл҃же́нне бг҃омꙋ́дре ї҆сї́дѡре. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Isidor Pelusiotes"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Isidor Pelusiotes lived during the IV-V Centuries. He was a native of Alexandria, and was raised amidst pious Christians. He was a kinsman of Theophilos, Archbishop of Alexandria, and of his successor, Saint Cyril. While still a youth he quit the world and withdrew within Egypt to Mount Pelusiotes, which became the site of his monastic efforts. The spiritual wisdom and strict asceticism of the Monk Isidor, in combination with his broad erudition and innate knowledge of the human soul, allowed him in a short while to win the respect and love of his fellow monks. They chose him as their head and had him elevated to the dignity of presbyter. Following the example of Saint John Chrysostom, whom he had managed to see and hear during the time of a journey to Constantinople, the Monk Isidor devoted himself primarily to Christian preaching, -- that &quot;practical wisdom&quot; which, in his own words, is both &quot;the foundation of the edifice and the edifice itself&quot;, while at the same time logic is &quot;its embellishment&quot; and contemplation -- its crown&quot;. He was a teacher and a willing giver of counsel for anyone recoursing to him for spiritual encouragement: whether it be a simple man, a dignitary, a bishop, the Patriarch of Alexandria or even the emperor himself. He left after him about 10,000 writings, of which 2,090 have survived. A large portion of these writings are profound in theological thought and contain morally edifying interpretations of Holy Scripture. It is here that the Monk Isidor stands out as the finest disciple of Saint John Chrysostom. The love and devotion of the Monk Isidor for Saint John Chrysostom resulted in decisive acts in defense of Saint John during the time of his persecution by the empress Eudoxia and archbishop Theophilos. After the death of Saint John, the Monk Isidor persuaded Theophilos&apos; successor Saint Cyril to inscribe the name of Saint John Chrysostom into the Church diptyches as a confessor. And through the initiative of the Monk Isidor was convened the Third OEcumenical Council at Ephesus (431), at which was condemned the false-teachings of Nestorius concerning the Person of Jesus Christ. 	The Monk Isidor lived into old age and died in about the year 436. The Church historian Euagrios (Evagrius, VI Century) writes about the Monk Isidor, that &quot;his life seemed to everyone the life of an angel upon the earth&quot;. Another historian, Nicholas Kallistos (IX Century), praises the Monk Isidor thus: &quot;He was a vital and inspired pillar of monastic rules and Divine vision and as such he presented a very lofty image of most fervent example and spiritual teaching&quot;.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
In thee, O father, that which was created according to the image of God was manifestly saved./ For accepting thy cross thou didst follow after Christ,/ and praying thou didst learn to disdain the flesh,/ for thou didst transcend it to take care of thine immortal soul.// Wherefore, with the angels doth thy soul rejoice, O venerable Isidore.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
The Church, finding thee to be another morning-star, O all-glorious one,/ crieth out to thee, illumined by the lightning-flashes of thy words:// Rejoice, O most blessed and divinely wise Isidore!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>