<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Положение честной Ризы Господа нашего Иисуса Христа в Москве (1625)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Честную Ризу Спасителя не следует отождествлять с нешвенным Его Хитоном — они ясно различаются в Священном Писании: «Воины же, когда распяли Иисуса, взяли одежды Его и разделили на четыре части, каждому воину по части, и хитон; хитон же был не сшитый, а весь тканый сверху. И так сказали друг другу: не станем раздирать его, а бросим о нем жребий, чей будет, — да сбудется реченное в Писании: разделили ризы Мои между собою и об одежде Моей бросали жребий» (Ин. 19, 23—24; Пс. 21, 19). По преданию Грузинской Православной Церкви, Хитон Госпо- день был принесен еврейским раввином Элиозом из Иерусалима в Мцхету и поныне пребывает под спудом в основании Мцхетского Патриаршего собора Светицховели (празднование в честь Хитона Господня совершается 1 октября). Никто из мусульманских завое- вателей не осмелился посягнуть на это место, прославленное зна- мением милости Божией — Животворящим Столпом (см. Синак- сарий мцхетского собора No 48. «ЖМП», 1977, No 9, с. 53). Риза Господня, вернее, одна из ее четырех частей, а именно срачйца (известны также части Ризы Господней в Западной Европе — в г. Трире, Германия, и Аржантейле, близ Парижа, Франция), как и Хитон Господень, оказалась в Грузии. В отличие от Хитона, Риза хранилась не в земле, а в сокровищнице собора Светицхо- вели вплоть до XVII века, когда персидский шах Аббас I, опусто- шивший Грузию, вывез вместе с другими сокровищами и Ризу Господню. Чтобы расположить к себе царя Михаила Феодоровича, шах прислал в 1625 году Ризу Господню в дар Патриарху Фила- рету (1619—1633) и царю Михаилу. Подлинность этой ризы была засвидетельствована Нектарием, архиепископом Вологодским, патриархом Иерусалимским Феофаном, прибывшим из Византии, и Иоанникнем греком, в особенности же чудесными знамениями, явленными Господом над больными через принесенную святыню. Впоследствии две части Ризы Господней находились в Петербур- ге: одна в соборе Зимнего Дворца, другая в Петропавловском соборе. Часть Ризы хранилась также в Успенском соборе в Моск- ве и малые частицы — в Киево-Софийском соборе, в Ипатьевском монастыре близ Костромы и в некоторых других древних храмах. В Москве ежегодно 10 июля Риза Господня торжественно выноси- лась из придела во имя святых апостолов Петра и Павла Успен- ского собора, и она полагалась на аналое для поклонения во время Богослужения. После Литургии Ризу уносили на прежнее место. В этот день полагается также служба Животворящему Кресту Господню, ибо положение Ризы в Успенском соборе в 1625 году совершилось 27 марта, в день, который тогда приходился на Не- делю крестопоклонную. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Дне́сь притеце́мъ вѣ́рнїи, къ бж҃е́ственнѣй и҆ цѣльбоно́снѣй ри́зѣ сп҃си́телѧ на́шегѡ бг҃а, бл҃гоизво́лившагѡ сїю̀ пло́тїю носи́ти, и҆ на крⷭтѣ̀ ст҃ꙋ́ю свою̀ кро́вь и҆злїѧ́ти, є҆́юже и҆скꙋпѝ на́съ ѿ рабо́ты вра́жїѧ. тѣ́мъ бл҃годарѧ́ще вопїе́мъ є҆мꙋ̀: сп҃сѝ правосла́внаго ї҆мпера́тора  на́шего, нїкола́ѧ а҆леѯса́ндровича, и҆ ст҃и́телей, и҆ гра́дъ, и҆ всѧ҄ лю́ди честно́ю твое́ю ри́зою защитѝ, и҆ сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ ꙗ҆́кѡ чл҃вѣколю́бецъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Ѡ҆дѣѧ́нїе нетлѣ́нїѧ, сп҃си́тельнагѡ цѣле́нїѧ, всѣ҄мъ человѣ́кѡмъ влⷣко дарова́лъ є҆сѝ твоѐ бж҃е́ственное сокро́вище, честнꙋ́ю ри́зꙋ, ꙗ҆́же є҆́сть хїтѡ́нъ, є҆́юже живоно́снꙋю и҆ ст҃ꙋ́ю пло́ть вочл҃вѣ́ченїѧ твоегѡ̀ ѡ҆дѣ́ѧти бл҃говоли́лъ є҆сѝ. сїю̀ жела́нїемъ прїе́млюще свѣ́тлѡ пра́зднꙋемъ, стра́хомъ же и҆ любо́вїю, ꙗ҆́кѡ бл҃года́телю воспѣва́юще зове́мъ тѝ хрⷭтѐ: сохранѝ въ ми́рѣ бл҃говѣ́рнаго ї҆мпера́тора на́шего, нїкола́ѧ а҆леѯса́ндровича, и҆ ст҃и́телей и҆ всѧ҄ лю́ди, по вели́цѣй твое́й млⷭти. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Placing of the Venerable Robe of Our Lord Jesus Christ at Moscow (1625)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Saviour&apos;s venerable Robe [Slavic &quot;Riza&quot;, Greek &quot;himatia&quot;, Latin &quot;vestimenta&quot;, literally &quot;over-garments&quot;] is not identically the same thing with His seamless &quot;Chiton&quot; [Greek and Slavic &quot;khiton&quot;, Latin &quot;tunica&quot;, literally &quot;under-garb tunic&quot;] -- they are clearly distinct within Holy Scripture: &quot;The soldiers then, when they had crucified Jesus, took His garments (odezhdu, vestimenta, ta himatia) and divided them into four parts, to each soldier a part, and the chiton-shirt (et tunicam, kai ton khitona). The chiton indeed was without seam, woven whole from the top down, and so they did say one to another: let us not rend it asunder, but for it cast lots, whose it wilt become. Wherefore was fulfilled the saying in Scripture: they divided My raiment-garb (riza, vestimenta, ta imatia) amongst them, and upon My vesture-garb (imatisme, in vestem, epi ton himatismon) did they cast lots&quot; (Jn. 19: 23-24; Ps. 21 [22]: 18-19). 	According to the tradition of the Gruzinian (Georgian) Orthodox Church, the Chiton-tunic of the Lord was carried by the Hebrew rabbi Elioz from Jerusalem to Mtsketa and at present is beneathe a crypt in the foundations of the Mtsketian Patriarchal cathedral of Svetitskhoveli (the feast in honour of the Chiton-tunic of the Lord is celebrated on 1 October). None of the Mohamedan invaders ever ventured to enroach upon this spot, glorified with a sign by the mercy of God -- the Life-Creating Pillar. 	The Robe of the Lord, -- actually one of its four parts, the lower portion namely (other parts of the Robe of the Lord are likewise known of in Western Europe: in the city of Trier in Germany, and in Argenteuil near Paris in France), just like the Chiton-tunic of the Lord, came to be in Gruzia. In contrast to the Chiton-tunic, the Robe portion was not kept underground, but was in the treasury of the Svetitskhoveli cathedral right up to the XVII Century, when the Persian shah Abbas I, in devastating Gruzia, carried off with other treasures also the Robe of the Lord. In order to ingratiate himself with tsar Mikhail Feodorovich, the shah in 1625 dispatched the Robe of the Lord as a gift to Patriarch Philaret (1619-1633) and tsar Mikhail. The authenticity of the Robe was testified to by Nektarii, Archbishop of Vologda, also by the Jerusalem Patriarch Theophanes who had come from Byzantium, and by Ioannikes the Greek, but especially also by the miraculous signs, manifest by the Lord through the venerable relic. 	Afterwards two parts of the Robe came to be in Peterburg: one in the cathedral at the Winter Palace, and the other in the Petropavlovsk (Peter and Paul) cathedral. A portion of the Robe was preserved likewise at the Uspenie-Dormition cathedral in Moscow, and small portions -- at the Kiev Sophia cathedral, at the Ipat&apos;ev monastery near Kostroma and at certain other old temples. At Moscow annually on 10 July the Robe of the Lord is solemnly brought out of a chapel named for the holy Apostles Peter and Paul at the Uspensky cathedral, and it is placed on an analoi-stand for veneration during the time of Divine-services. After Liturgy they carry the Robe to its former place.  	On this day likewise is proper a service to the Life-Creating Cross of the Lord, since the Placing of the Robe in the Uspensky cathedral in 1625 was done on 29 March, on the day which then occurred to be the Lenten Sunday of the Veneration of the Cross. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Needs English translation
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Needs English translation
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>