<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Харалампий, епископ Магнезийский, мученики Порфирий и Ваптос и три жены мученицы"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Священномученик Харалампий, епископ Магнезийский, мучени- ки Порфирий и Ваптос и три жены мученицы пострадали в 202 году.     Святой Харалампий, епископ фессалийского города Магнезии (северо-восточная область Греции), успешно распространял веру во Христа Спасителя. Весть о его проповеди дошла до правителя области Лукиана и военачальника Лукия, по распоряжению кото- рого святой был схвачен и приведен на суд, где твердо исповедал веру во Христа и отказался принести жертву идолам. Несмотря на преклонный возраст епископа (ему было уже 113 лет), его подвергли чудовищным истязаниям: терзали тело железными крючьями, пока не содрали всю кожу с головы до ног. Святой при этом обращался к мучителям: «Благодарю вас, братия, вы обно- вили дух мой!»     Видя терпение старца и полное его незлобие, два воина — Порфирий и Ваптос открыто исповедали Христа, за что тотчас же были усечены мечом. Присутствовавшие при страданиях епископа Харалампия три женщины также стали прославлять Христа и не- медленно были замучены.     Разгневанный Лукий сам схватил орудия пыток и стал терзать священномученика, но внезапно у него, как отсеченные мечом, отнялись руки. Пришедший к месту казни правитель плюнул в лицо святого, и тотчас голова его оказалась повернутой назад. Тогда Лукий стал умолять святого о пощаде, и по его молитве оба мучителя тут же получили исцеление. При этом множество свиде- телей уверовали во Христа. Среди них был и Лукий, который при-  пал к ногам святого старца,, прося прощения.     Лукиан донес о случившемся императору Септимию Северу  (193—211), находившемуся в это время в Антиохии Писидийской  (западная часть Малой Азии), и тот распорядился привести свя- того Харалампия к себе, что было исполнено с невиданной жесто-  костью: священномученика влачили, привязав веревку к бороде. Император приказал мучить епископа еще сильнее, и его стали палить огнем. Но Сила Божия помогала святому, и он остался невредим. Кроме того, по его молитве стали совершаться чудеса: воскрес умерший юноша, исцелился бесноватый, мучимый бесом 35 лет, так что народ во множестве стал исповедовать Христа Спа- сителя. Во Христа уверовала даже дочь императора Галина, дважды сокрушившая идолов в языческом храме. По приказу императора святителя били камнями по устам, хотели поджечь бороду, из которой вышло пламя, опалившее мучителей. Полные злобы, Септимий Север и его вельможа Крисп воздвигли хулу на Господа, глумливо призывая Его сойти на землю, похваляясь своей силой и властью. Во гневе Господь поколебал землю, вели- кий страх напал на всех,, оба же нечестивца повисли в воздухе, связанные невидимыми узами, и лишь по молитве святителя были возвращены вниз. Устрашенный император поколебался было в своем нечестии, но вскоре опять впал в заблуждение и приказал мучить святого, наконец, осудил его на усечение мечом. Во время своей последней молитвы святой удостоился видеть Самого Спа- сителя и просил Его даровать тому месту, где будут почивать его мощи, мир, плодородие, а людям—• прощение грехов и спасение. Господь обещал исполнить прошение и восшел на небеса, унося с Собой душу священномученика Харалампия, который принял, по милости Божией, мирную кончину до казни. Дочь императора — блаженная Галина погребла тело мученика с великой честью. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нкъ тво́й гдⷭи, харала́мпїй, во страда́нїи свое́мъ вѣне́цъ прїѧ́тъ нетлѣ́нный ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мѣ́ѧй бо крѣ́пость твою̀, мꙋчи́телей низложѝ, сокрꙋшѝ и҆ де́монѡвъ немощны́ѧ де́рзѡсти: тогѡ̀ мл҃твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="3">
Подо́бствовавъ бл҃года́тїю сщ҃е́нства сла́вне, цр҃ковь свѣ́тлѡ ѹ҆краси́лъ є҆сѝ бж҃е́ственнымъ страда́нїемъ, є҆́же за хрⷭта̀ прїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ до́блественнѡ ра́дꙋѧсѧ, харала́мпїе честны́й, свѣти́льниче всемї́рный, ѡ҆сїѧва́ѧй концы̀, ꙗ҆́кѡ непобѣди́мый. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="PriestMartyr Charalampios, Bishop of Magnezia, the Martyrs Porphyry and Baptos and the Three Martyresses"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The PriestMartyr Charalampios, Bishop of Magnezia, the Martyrs Porphyry and Baptos and the Three Martyresses suffered in the year 202. 	Saint Charalampios, bishop of the Thessalonian city of Magnezia (northwest region of Greece), successfully spread faith in Christ the Saviour. News about his preaching reached the governor of the district Lucian and the military-commander Lucius. The saint was arrested and brought to trial, where he firmly confessed his faith in Christ and refused to offer sacrifice to idols. Despite the decrepit age of the bishop (he was already 113 years of age), they subjected him to monstrous tortures: they lacerated his body with iron hooks, while they scourged all his skin from head to foot. During this the saint turned to his tormentors: &quot;I bless you, brethren, ye have restored my spirit!&quot; 	Having seen the endurance of the elder and his complete lack of malice, two soldiers -- Porphyry and Baptos openly confessed Christ, for which they were immediately beheaded with a sword. Being present at the sufferings of bishop Charalampios were likewise three women who began to glorify Christ and were quickly martyred.  	The enraged Lucius himself seized hold of the instruments of torture and began to tear at the priest-martyr, but suddenly his hand was cut off as though by a sword. Also arriving at the place of execution the governor spat in the face of the saint, and immediately he bent backwards. Then Lucius began to beseech the saint for forgiveness, and through his prayer both torturers at once received healing. During this a multitude of witnesses came to believe in Christ. Among them also was Lucius, who fell at the feet of the holy elder, begging forgiveness. 	Lucian reported about the occurrence to the emperor Septimus Severus (193-211), situated at this time at Pisidian Antioch (western part of Asia Minor). The emperor gave orders to bring Saint Charlampios to him, and this was done with a stupid ferocity: they dragged the priest-martyr, having tied a rope to his beard. The emperor then gave orders to torture the bishop more intensely, and they began to burn at him with fire. But the Power of God aided to the saint, and he remained unharmed. Besides this, miracles were done through his prayer: he raised up a dead youth, and healed a demoniac tormented by devils for 35 years, so that the people in a multitude began to believe in Christ the Saviour. Even Galina the daughter of the emperor began to believe in Christ, and twice smashed idols in a pagan temple. By order of the emperor they beat the saint with stones about the mouth, and they wanted to set afire his beard, from which the flames went forth burning the torturer. Full of wickedness, Septimus Severus and his dignitary Crispus hurled blasphemy at the Lord, mockingly summoning Him to come down to the earth, and bragging of their own power and might. In wrath the Lord quaked the earth, great fear fell upon all, both the impious ones were suspended in mid-air held by invisible bounds, and only by the prayer of the saint were they put down. The dazed emperor was shaken in his former impiety, but again quickly fell into error and gave orders to torture the saint. And finally, he sentenced him to beheading with a sword. During the time of his final prayer, the saint was vouchsafed to behold the Saviour Himself and besought Him to grant that place where his remains would repose, in peace, would be fruitful for people, bringing forgiveness of sins and salvation. The Lord promised to fulfill the request and ascended to heaven, bearing with Him the soul of the priestmartyr Charalampios -- who through the mercy of God accepted a peaceful death before execution. The daughter of the emperor, blessed Galina, buried the body of the martyr with great honour.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In his suffering, O Lord,/ Thy martyr Charalampius received an imperishable crown from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ he set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By his supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="3">
Perfected by the grace of the priesthood, O glorious one,/ thou didst splendidly adorn the Church with thy divine suffering,/ which, rejoicing, thou didst manfully accept for Chris's sake,/ O Charalampius, thou honored beacon of the whole world,// illumining the ends of the earth, in that thou art invincible.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>