<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Афиноген и десять его учеников"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Священномученик Афиноген и десять его учеников пострадали за Христа во время гонений на христиан в городе Севастии. Пра- витель Филомарх устроил большой праздник в честь языческих богов и приказал севастийским гражданам принести жертву идо- лам. Но жители Севастии, в большинстве христиане, отказались участвовать в нечестивом празднестве и приносить жертвы идо- лам. Воинам приказано было избивать народ, и многие христиане приняли тогда мученические венцы. Правителю стало известно, что христианство широко распро- странилось благодаря проповеди епископа Афиногена. Было при- казано разыскать старца и привести на суд. Святой Афиноген и десять его учеников жили неподалеку от города в небольшом монастыре. Не застав епископа, воины схватили учеников. Прави- тель велел заковать их в цепи и бросить в тюрьму. Святитель Афиноген пришел в Севастию и стал укорять судью за то, что в темницу брошены невиновные. Он был схвачен. В тюрьме святой Афиноген укреплял своих духовных детей на подвиг. Приведенные на суд, все святые мученики исповедали себя христианами и отказались принести жертву идолам. Перенеся жестокие истязания, ученики святого епископа были обезглавле- ны. После казни учеников, палачам было приказано пытать стар- ца. Укрепляемый Господом, святитель Афиноген с достоинством перенес мучения. Единственной его просьбой было — казнить его в монастыре. Приведенный в свою обитель святой в молитве благодарил Бога, радуясь страданиям, перенесенным за Него. Святой Афино- ген молился Господу о прощении грехов тех людей, которые будут поминать его и учеников. Господь сподобил святого услышать перед смертью Его голос, возвестивший обетование, данное благоразумному разбойнику: «Днесь со Мною будешь в раю». Священномученик сам склонил свою голову под меч. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Влⷣчню рече́нїю послѣ́довавъ, ꙗ҆́кѡ па́стырь и҆зрѧ́дный дꙋ́шꙋ твою̀ положи́лъ є҆сѝ за хрⷭтѡ́вы ѻ҆́вцы, сщ҃енномч҃нче а҆ѳиноге́не. сегѡ̀ ра́ди восхвалѧ́емъ тѧ̀, и҆ съ тобо́ю десѧти́цꙋ ѹ҆чени҄къ твои́хъ, и҆̀же пострада́ша, стра́хомъ бж҃їимъ и҆ твои́мъ ѹ҆че́нїемъ наставлѧ́еми. тѣ́мъ ѹ҆годи́вшихъ влⷣка вѣнча̀ ва́съ живонача́льною десни́цею: є҆го́же ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ моли́те. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="PriestMartyr Athenogoras and his Ten Disciples"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The PriestMartyr Athenogoras and his Ten Disciples suffered for Christ during the time of persecution against Christians in the city of Sebasteia. The governor Philomarkhos made a large festival in honour of the pagan gods and summoned the Sebasteia citizenry to offer sacrifice to the idols. But the inhabitants of Sebasteia, Christian in the majority, refused to participate in the impious celebration with its offering of sacrifice to idols. Soldiers were ordered to kill people, and many Christians then accepted a martyr&apos;s crown. 	It came to the governor&apos;s attention, that Christianity was being widely spread about by the graced preaching of Bishop Athenogoras. Orders were issued to seek out the elder and arrest him. Saint Athenogoras and ten of his disciples lived not far from the city in a small monastery. But not finding the bishop there, the soldiers arrested his disciples. The governor gave orders to slap them into chains and throw them in prison. 	Saint Athenogoras came then to Sebasteia and began reproaching the judge that those thrown into prison were guiltless. He was arrested. In prison, Saint Athenogoras encouraged his spiritual children for their impending deed. Led forth to trial, all the holy martyrs confessed themselves Christians and refused to offer sacrifice to idols. After undergoing fierce tortures, the disciples of the holy bishop were beheaded. And after the execution of the disciples, the executioners were ordered to put the elder to the test of torture. Strengthened by the Lord, Saint Athenogoras underwent the tortures with dignity. His only request was -- that he be executed in the monastery. 	Taken to his own monastery, the saint in prayer gave thanks to God, and he rejoiced in the sufferings that he had undergone for Him. Saint Athenogoras besought of the Lord the forgiveness of sins of all those people, who should remember both him and his disciples. 	The Lord granted the saint to hear His Voice before death, announcing the promise given to the penitent thief: &quot;Today with Me thou shalt be in paradise&quot;. The priestmartyr himself bent his neck beneathe the sword. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Following the love of the Master,/ as an excellent pastor thou didst lay down thy life for the sheep of Christ,/ O hieromartyr Athenogenes;/ for this cause we praise thee, and with thee the ten disciples who suffered with thee,/ instructed by the fear of God and thy teaching./ Wherefore, with His life-creating right hand the Master hath crowned you who pleased Him.// Him do ye entreat in behalf of us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>