<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой пророк Иезекииль"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святой пророк Иезекииль жил в VI веке до Рождества Хри- стова. Родился в городе Сарире, происходил из колена Левиина, был священником и сыном священника Вузия. Во второе нашест- вие на Иерусалим вавилонского царя Навуходоносора, в 25-лет- нем возрасте Иезекииль был отведен в Вавилон вместе с царем Иехонией II и многими другими иудеями. В плену пророк Иезекииль жил при реке Ховар. Там, на 30-м году жизни, в видении ему было открыто будущее еврейского на- рода и всего человечества. Пророк увидел сияющее облако, в сере- дине которого был пламень, а в нем — таинственное подобие дви- жимой духом колесницы и четырех крылатых животных, имевших каждое четыре лица: человека, льва, тельца и орла. Перед их ли- цами находились колеса, усеянные очами. Над колесницей возвы- шался как бы кристальный свод, а над сводом — подобие престола как бы из сверкающего сапфира. На этом престоле сияющее «по- добие Человека», а вокруг Него радуга (Иез. 1, 4—28). По толкованию отцов Церкви, пресветлое «подобие Человека», сидящего на сапфировом престоле, было прообразом воплощения Сына Божия от Пресвятой Девы Марии, явившейся Престолом Божиим; четыре животных прообразовывали четырех евангелистов, колеса со множеством очей — части света со всеми народами зем- ли. При этом видении святой пророк от страха упал на землю, но глас Божий повелел ему встать и затем объявил, что Господь по- сылает его на проповедь к народу израильскому. С этого времени началось пророческое служение Иезекииля. Пророк Иезекииль воз- вестил народу израильскому, находившемуся в плену вавилонском, о предстоявших испытаниях в наказание за заблуждения в вере и отступничество от Истинного Бога. Пророк возвещал также и наступление лучших времен для своих пленных соотечественников, предсказывал возвращение их из вавилонского плена и восстанов- ление Иерусалимского храма. Особенно важны два знаменательных видения пророка — о хра- ме Господнем, исполненном славы, и о сухих костях на поле, кото- рым Дух Божий дал новую жизнь. Видение о храме было таинст- венным прообразом освобождения рода человеческого от работы вражией и устроения Церкви Христовой через искупительный под- виг Сына Божия, воплотившегося от Пресвятой Девы Марии, име- нуемой пророком «вратами затворенными», которыми прошел толь- ко Один Господь Бог (Иез. 44, 2). Видение о сухих костях на по- л е — прообраз&apos; всеобщего воскресения мертвых и новой вечной жизни искупленных Крестной смертью Господа Иисуса Христа (Иез. 37, 1—14). Святой пророк Иезекииль имел от Господа дар чудотворения. Он, как и пророк Моисей, молитвой к Богу разделил воды реки Ховара, и евреи перешли на другой берег, избежав преследования халдеев. Во время голода пророк испросил у Бога умножения пищи для голодавших. За обличение в идолопоклонстве одного еврейского князя, свя- того Иезекииля предали казни: привязанный к диким коням, он был разорван на части. Благочестивые евреи собрали растерзан- ное тело пророка и похоронили его на поле Маур, в усыпальнице Сима и Арфаксада, прародителей Авраама, недалеко от Багдада. Пророчества Иезекииля записаны в книге, названной его именем и включенной в Библию. Святитель Димитрий Ростовский обращал внимание верующих на следующие слова в книге пророка Иезекииля: если праведник, надеясь на свою праведность, дерзнет грешить и в грехе умрет — будет отвечать за грех и подлежит осуждению; а грешник, если покается, и умрет в покаянии — его прежние грехи не воспомянут- ся перед Богом (Иез. 3, 20; 18, 21—24). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
Celebratїng the memory/ oѳ Thy prophet Ezekїel O Lord,// through hїm do ѡe entreat Thee, ѕaѵe Thou our ѕoulѕ.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Thou haѕt been ѕhoѡn to be a prophet oѳ God,/ O ѡondrouѕ Ezekїel,/ and haѕt proclaїmed unto all the їncarnatїon oѳ the Lord,/ the Lamb and Creator,// the Ѕon oѳ God Ѡho hath reѵealed Hїmѕelѳ ѳoreѵer.
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Prophet Ezekiel"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Prophet Ezekiel lived in the VI Century before the Birth of Christ. He was born in the city of Sarir, and descended from the Levite tribe; he was a priest and the son of the priest Buzi. In the second invasion against Jerusalem by the Babylonian emperor Nebuchadnessar, at age 25 Ezekiel was led off to Babylon together with the king Jechoniah II and many other Jews. 	In captivity the Prophet Ezekiel lived by the River Chobar. There, in his 30th year of life, in a vision there was revealed to him the future of the Hebrew nation and of all mankind. The prophet beheld a shining cloud, in the midst of which was a flame, and in it - a mysterious likeness of a chariot moving by the spirit and four-winged beasts, each having four faces: of a man, a lion, an ox and an eagle. Under their faces was situated a wheel, bestrewn with eyes. Over the chariot towered as it were a crystalline firmament, and over the firmament -- the likeness of a throne as though of glittering sapphire. And upon this throne a radiant &quot;likeness of Man&quot;, and about Him a rainbow (Ez. 1: 4-28). 	According to the explanation of the fathers of the Church, the most-bright &quot;likeness of Man&quot; radiant upon the sapphire throne, was a prefigurament of the Incarnation of the Son of God from the MostHoly Virgin Mary, manifest as the Throne of God. The four creatures prefigured the four evangelists, the wheel with a multitude of eyes -- the sharing of light with all the nations of the earth. During this vision the holy prophet out of fear fell down upon the ground, but the voice of God commanded him to get up and then explained, that the Lord was sending him to preach to the nation of Israel. From this time began the prophetic service of Ezekiel. The Prophet Ezekiel announces to the nation of Israel, situated in Baylonian Captivity, about its coming tribulations for straying in the faith and forsaking the True God. The prophet proclaimed also a better time for his captive fellow-countrymen, and he predicted their return from Babylon and the restoration of the Jerusalem Temple. 	Particularly important are two significant elements in the vision of the prophet -- the one about the vision of the temple of the Lord, full of glory, -- the second about the bones upon the field, to which the Spirit of God gave new life. The vision about the temple was a mysterious prefigurament of the freeing of the race of man from the working of the enemy and the building up of the Church of Christ through the redemptive deed of the Son of God, incarnated of the MostHoly Virgin Mary, -- called by the prophet &quot;the shut gates&quot;, through which would be entered the One only Lord God (Ez. 44: 2). The vision about the dry bones upon the field -- prefigured the universal resurrection of the dead and the new eternal life of the redeemed by the death on the Cross of the Lord Jesus Christ (Ez. 37: 1-14). 	The holy Prophet Ezekiel had from the Lord a gift of wonderworking. He, like the Prophet Moses, by prayer to God divided the waters of the river Chobar, and the Hebrews crossed to the opposite shore, escaping the pursuing Chaldeans. During a time of famine the prophet besought of God an increase of food for the hungry. 	For his denunciation of the idol-worship of a certain Hebrew prince, Saint Ezekiel was given over to execution: bound to wild horses, he was torn to pieces. Pious Hebrews gathered up the torn body of the prophet and buried it upon Maur Field, in the tomb of Sim and Arthaxad, fore-fathers of Abraham, not far from Baghdad. The prophecy of Ezekiel was written down in a book, mentioning him by name, and is included in the Bible. 	Sainted Dimitrii of Rostov drew attention for believers to the following concept in the book of the Prophet Ezekiel: if a righteous man, hoping on his own righteousness, were to venture to sin and in sin would die -- he would answer for the sin and be subject to judgement; but a sinner, if he repenteth, and in repentance would die -- his former sin would not be remembered before God (Ez. 3: 20; 18: 21-24).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
\' w` i=i' ', \, ', j' ` ', ~` ' '. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
~i j=' _=` \' i=i' ', \ 'i j^ j' _=`, ` =' = ' ~ ~i j='  j'. 
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>