<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученики Ермолай, Ермипп и Ермократ, иереи Никомидийские"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Священномученики Ермолай, Ермипп и Ермократ, иереи Нико- мидийские, в числе немногих остались в живых после того, как по повелению императора Максимиана (284—305) в Никомидий- ской церкви были сожжены 20 000 христиан в 303 году (память 28 декабря). Они скрывались в отдаленных местах и не переста- вали учить язычников христианской вере. Мимо дома, в котором скрывался святой Ермолай, часто проходил юноша-язычник Пан- толеон (святой великомученик Пантелеймон; память 27 июля). Однажды святой Ермолай вышел навстречу юноше и попросил его зайти к нему в дом. В беседе святой Ермолай стал разъяснять своему гостю ложность, нечестие и суетность поклонения языче- ским божествам. С этого дня Пантолеон стал ежедневно заходить к святому Ермолаю и принял от него святое Крещение. Когда со- вершался суд над святым великомучеником Пантелеймоном, были схвачены и святые Ермолай, Ермипп и Ермократ. Накануне свя- тому Ермолаю явился Господь Иисус Христос и открыл ему, что на следующий день он пострадает за Него и примет мученический венец. После святого Ермолая были схвачены и приведены на судилище и святые Ермипп и Ермократ. Всем троим было предло- жено отречься от Христа и принести жертву идолам. Но они реши- тельно отказались, исповедали свою веру в Господа Иисуса Хри- ста и готовность с радостью умереть за Него. Язычники стали угрожать святым иереям муками и смертью. Внезапно началось сильное землетрясение, и идолы в капище упали и разбились. Об этом было доложено императору. Разгневанный Максимиан отдал святых мучеников на истязания и вынес им смертный приговор. Мужественно претерпев все мучения, святые иереи — мученики Ер- молай, Ермипп и Ермократ были обезглавлены около 305 года. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нцы твоѝ гдⷭи, во страда́нїихъ свои́хъ вѣнцы̀ прїѧ́ша нетлѣ҄нныѧ ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мꙋ́ще бо крѣ́пость твою̀ мꙋчи́телей низложи́ша, сокрꙋши́ша и҆ де́мѡнѡвъ немощны҄ѧ де́рзѡсти. тѣ́хъ моли́твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ ст҃и́тель бл҃гоче́стнѡ пожи́въ, и҆ сщ҃енномꙋче́нїѧ вѣне́цъ прїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ, ї҆́дѡльскїѧ жє́ртвы погаси́въ, до́брый па́стырь хрⷭто́ва ста́да бы́лъ є҆сѝ премꙋ́дре, и҆ пантелеи́монꙋ и҆́стинный ѹ҆чи́тель. сегѡ̀ ра́ди почита́емъ тѧ̀ пѣ́сньми вопїю́ще: ѿ бѣ́дъ и҆зба́ви на́съ при́снѡ мл҃твами твои́ми, є҆рмола́е ѻ҆́тче на́шъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="PriestMartyrs Hermolaus, Hermippos and Hermocrates, Clergy of Nicomedia"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The PriestMartyrs Hermolaus, Hermippos and Hermocrates, Clergy of Nicomedia, were among the small number of those remaining alive after the burning of 20,000 Christians of the Nicomedia Church in the year 303 (Comm. 28 December), -- done upon the orders of the emperor Maximian (284-305). They hid themselves in remote places and did not cease to teach pagans the Christian faith. Often there passed by the house, in which Saint Hermolaus had concealed himself, the young pagan named Pantoleon (Holy GreatMartyr Panteleimon, Comm. 27 July). One time Saint Hermolaus chanced upon the youth and asked him to stop by for him at the house. In their conversation Saint Hermolaus began to explain to his guest the falseness, impiety and vanity of worshipping the pagan gods. From that day on Pantoleon began daily to visit Saint Hermolaus and received of him holy Baptism. When the trial of the holy GreatMartyr Panteleimon was being held, Saints Hermolaus, Hermippos and Hermokrates, were also arrested. The Lord Jesus Christ appeared to Saint Hermolaus on an evening and revealed to him, that on the following day he would suffer for Him and receive a martyr&apos;s crown. Saints Hermippos and Hermokrates were arrested and brought to trial after Saint Hermolaus. All three were given the chance to abjure from Christ and offer sacrifice to idols. But they resolutely refused, confessed their faith in the Lord Jesus Christ and were prepared gladly to die for Him. The pagans began to threaten the holy priests with torture and death. Suddenly a strong earthquake occurred, and the idols and pagan temple collapsed and shattered. A report was made about this to the emperor. The enraged Maximian gave the holy martyrs over to torture and pronounced upon them a sentence of death. Bravely enduring all the torments, the holy PriestMartyrs Hermolaus, Hermippos and Hermokrates were beheaded in about the year 305.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In their sufferings, O Lord,/ Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By their supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Having lived piously as a hieraich,/ thou hast received the crown of a martyred bishop;/ and extinguishing the sacrifices of the idols,/ thou wast a good shepherd of the flock of Christ/ and a true teacher for Panteleimon, O all-wise one./ Wherefore, we honor thee with hymns, crying out:// Ever deliver us from misfortunes by thy supplications, O Hermolaus our father!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>