<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Мученики Аникита и Фотий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Мученики Аникита и Фотий (его племянник) были родом из Никомидии. Аникита, военный сановник, обличал императора Диоклитиана (284—305), установившего на городской площади орудия казни, чтобы устрашать христиан. Разгневанный Диокли- тиан приказал мучить святого Аникиту, а затем бросить его на съедение зверям. Но выпущенный лев сделался кроток и ласкался к нему. Внезапно началось сильное землетрясение, отчего упало капище Геркулеса, и под обвалившейся городской стеной погибло много язычников. Палач занес меч, чтобы отсечь голову святому, но сам упал без чувств. Святого Аникиту стали колесовать и па- лить огнем, но колесо остановилось, а огонь погас. Мученика бро- сили в котел с кипящим оловом, но олово остыло. Так Господь хранил Своего раба для утверждения многих. Племянник мучени- к а — святой Фотий, приветствовал страдальца и, обратившись к царю, заметил: «Идолопоклонник, твои боги — ничто!» Меч, зане- сенный над новым исповедником, поразил самого палача. Мучени- ков посадили в темницу. Через три дня Диоклитиан стал уговари- вать их: «Поклонитесь богам нашим, и я прославлю вас и обога- щу». Мученики отвечали: «Погибни ты со своею честью и богат- ством!». Тогда их привязали за ноги к диким коням, но святые, влачимые по земле, оставались невредимыми. Не пострадали они и в накаленной бане, которая развалилась. Наконец Диоклитиан велел разжечь огромную печь, и множество христиан, воодушев- ленных подвигами святых Фотия и Аникиты, сами ступили в нее со словами: «Мы христиане!» Все они скончались с молитвою на устах. Тела святых Аникиты и Фотия не пострадали от огня и даже волосы их остались целы. Видя это, многие из язычников уверова- ли во Христа. Это событие произошло в 305 году. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нцы твоѝ гдⷭи, во страда́нїихъ свои́хъ вѣнцы̀ прїѧ́ша нетлѣ҄нныѧ ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мꙋ́ще бо крѣ́пость твою̀ мꙋчи́телей низложи́ша, сокрꙋши́ша и҆ де́мѡнѡвъ немощны҄ѧ де́рзѡсти. тѣ́хъ моли́твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Martyrs Anicetas and Photios"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Martyrs Anicetas and Photios (his nephew) were natives of Nicomedia. Anicetas, a military official, denounced the emperor Diocletian (284-305) for having set up in the city square an implement of execution for frightening Christians. The enraged emperor ordered Saint Anicetas to be tortured, and later condemned him to be devoured by wild beasts. But the lions they set loose became gentle and fondled up to him. Suddenly there began a strong earthquake, resulting in the collapse of the pagan temple of Hercules, and many pagans perished beneathe the crumbled city walls. The executioner took up a sword to cut off the saint&apos;s head, but he himself fell down insensible. They tried to break Saint Anicetas on the wheel and burn him with fire, but the wheel stopped and the fire went out. They threw the martyr into a furnace with boiling tin, but the tin got cold. Thus the Lord preserved His servant for the edification of many. The martyr&apos;s nephew, Saint Photios, saluted the sufferer and turn to the emperor, remarking: &quot;O idol-worshipper, thine gods -- be nothing!&quot; The sword, held over the new confessor, instead struck the executioner himself. Then the martyrs were thrown into prison. After three days Diocletian began to urge them: &quot;Worship our gods, and I shalt give ye glory and riches&quot;. The martyrs answered: &quot;Perish thou with thine honour and riches!&quot; Then they tied them by the legs to wild horses, but the saints, dragged along the ground, remained unharmed. They did not suffer either in the heated up bath-house, which tumbled apart. Finally Diocletian ordered a great furnace to be fired up, and many Christians, inspired by the deeds of Saints Anicetas and Photios, went in themselves with the words: &quot;We are Christians!&quot; They all died with prayer on their lips. The bodies of Saints Anicetas and Photios were not harmed by the fire, and even their hair remained whole. seeing this, many of the pagans came to believe in Christ. This event happened in the year 305.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In their sufferings, O Lord,/ Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By their supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>