<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Тарасий, Патриарх Константинопольский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святитель Тарасий, Патриарх Константинопольский, происхо- дил из знатного рода, родился и был воспитан в Константинополе, где получил хорошее образование. Он быстро выдвинулся при дворе императора Константина VI Порфирородного (780—797) и его матери, святой царицы Ирины (797—802; память 7 августа), и достиг звания сенатора. В те времена Церковь волновали ико- ноборческие смуты. Святой Патриарх Павел (780—784; память 30 августа), не сочувствовавший в душе иконоборчеству, по сла- бости характера не мог решительно бороться с ересью и потому удалился в монастырь, где принял схиму. Когда к нему пришла святая царица Ирина со своим сыном-императором, святитель Павел объявил им,, что достойным преемником его может быть только святой Тарасий (в то время мирянин). Тарасий долго отка- зывался, не считая себя достойным столь высокого сана, но потом подчинился общему желанию, с условием, что будет созван Все- ленский Собор для осуждения иконоборческой ереси. Пройдя в короткое время все иерархические ступени, святой Тарасий был возведен на патриарший престол в 784 году. В 787 году под пред- седательством святителя — Патриарха Тарасия в г. Никее состо- ялся VII Вселенский Собор, на котором присутствовало 367 епи- скопов. На Соборе было утверждено почитание святых икон. Те из епископов, которые принесли покаяние в иконоборчестве, были вновь приняты Церковью.     Святитель Тарасий мудро управлял Церковью 22 года. Он вел суровую аскетическую жизнь. Всё свое имение он истратил на Богоугодные дела, питая и покоя стариков, нищих, сирот и вдов,  а в Святую Пасху устраивал для них трапезу, на которой сам прислуживал. Святой Патриарх бесстрашно обличил царя Кон- стантина Порфирородного, когда тот оклеветал свою супругу,  императрицу Марию,, внучку праведного Филарета Милостивого {\ 792; память 1 декабря), чтобы заточить Марию в монастырь и сочетаться браком со своей родственницей. Святитель Тарасий решительно отказался расторгнуть брак императора, за что под- вергся опале. Вскоре, однако, Константин был низложен своей матерью, царицей Ириной. Святитель Тарасий скончался в 806 го- ду. При кончине бесы, напоминая его жизнь с самой юности, ста- рались приписать святителю не совершенные им грехи. «Я непо- винен в том, о чем вы говорите, — отвечал святитель. — Вы ложно клевещете на меня, нет у вас надо мной никакой власти». Опла- киваемый Церковью, святитель был погребен в устроенном им монастыре на Босфоре. У гроба его совершались многие чудеса. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Пра́вило вѣ́ры и҆ ѡ҆́бразъ кро́тости, воздержа́нїѧ ѹ҆чи́телѧ ꙗ҆ви́ тѧ ста́дꙋ твоемꙋ̀, ꙗ҆́же веще́й и҆́стина: сегѡ̀ ра́ди стѧжа́лъ є҆сѝ смире́нїемъ высѡ́каѧ, нището́ю бога҄таѧ, ѻ҆́тче тара́сїе, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Правосла́вными догма́ты цр҃ковь ѹ҆ѧсни́въ, и҆ хрⷭто́вꙋ бл҃же́нне честнꙋ́ю ї҆кѡ́нꙋ почита́ти и҆ покланѧ́тисѧ всѣ́хъ наꙋчи́въ, ѡ҆бличи́лъ є҆сѝ ї҆кѡнобо́рцєвъ безбо́жное велѣ́нїе. сегѡ̀ ра́ди вопїе́мъ тѝ: ѽ ѻ҆́тче ра́дꙋйсѧ, мꙋ́дре тара́сїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Tarasias, Patriarch of Constantinople"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Tarasias, Patriarch of Constantinople, came of illustrious lineage. He was born and raised in Constantinople, where he received a fine education. He was rapidly promoted at the court of the emperor Constantine VI Porphyrigenitos (780-797) and Constantine&apos;s mother, the holy Empress Irene (797-802; Comm. 7 August), and the saint reached the rank of senator. During these times the Church was agitated by the turmoil of the Iconoclast disturbances. The holy Patriarch Paul (780-784, Comm. 30August) although not sympathetic in soul with Iconoclasm, through his weakness of character was not able to decisively contend with the heresy and he therefore withdrew to a monastery, where he took the schema. When the holy Empress Irene together with her son the emperor came to him, Saint Paul declared to them, that the most worthy successor to him would be Saint Tarasias (who at this time was still a layman). Tarasias for a long time refused, not considering himself worthy of so very high a dignity, but he then gave in to the common accord, on the condition, that an OEcumenical Council be convened for rendering judgement on the Iconoclast heresy. Proceeding in a short while through all the degrees of clergy dignity, Saint Tarasias was elevated to the Patriarchal throne in the year 784. In the year 787 in the city of Nicea, with holy Patriarch Tarasias presiding, -- the Seventh OEcumenical Council was convened, at which were present 367 bishops. The affirmation of holy icons was confirmed at the Council. Those of the bishops, who repented of Iconoclasm, were again received by the Church. 	Saint Tarasias wisely governed the Church for 22 years. He led a strict ascetic life. He used up all his money on God-pleasing ends, feeding and giving comfort to the old, to the impoverished, to widows and orphans, and on Holy Pascha he set out for them the meal at which he himself served. The holy Patriarch fearlessly denounced the emperor Constantine Porphyrigenitos when that one slandered his spouse, the empress Maria -- the grand-daughter of Righteous Philaretos the Merciful (+ 792, Comm. 1 December), so that he could be rid of Maria to a monastery thus freeing him to marry his own kins-woman. Saint Tarasias resolutely refused to dissolve the marriage of the emperor, for which the saint fell into disgrace. Soon, however, Constantine was deposed by his own mother, the Empress Irene. Saint Tarasias died in the year 806. Before his death, devils reminded him of his life from the time of his youth, and they tried to get the saint to admit to sins that he had not even committed. &quot;I am innocent in that of which ye speak, -- replied the saint, -- and ye do falsely slander me, yet mustneeds it be ye have no power over me&quot;. Mourned by the Church, the saint was buried in a monastery built by him on the Bosphorus. From his grave was worked many a miracle. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
The truth of things revealed thee to thy flock as a rule of faith,/ a model of meekness and a teacher of abstinence/ wherefore thou hast attained the heights through humility/ and riches through poverty.// O hierarch Tarasius our father, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Having illumined the Church with Orthodox dogmas/ and taught all to honor and bow down before the precious icon of Christ, O blessed one,/ thou didst denounce the godless decree of the iconoclasts./ Wherefore, we cry out to thee:// Rejoice, O wise rather Tarasius!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>