<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Блаженный Симон Юрьевецкий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov">
Родился в селе Братском, Костромской губернии. С юношеских лет, оставив родительский дом, ушел в дремучие леса около села Елнати и принял на себя подвиг юродства Христа ради.

Когда елнатские поселяне, найдя его в лесу, привели в село, святой начал ходить по домам жителей, помогая им в исполнении самых трудных работ, а плату не брал.

Зимой и летом святой ходил босой, в одной льняной рубахе, так что кожа его почернела и от поста иссохла. Неразумные люди нередко били его, но блаженный кротко переносил все оскорбления и насмешки. Прожив в Елнати 15 лет, святой переселился в г. Юрьевец Поволжский. Здесь любимым местом его пребывания стали церковные паперти, где он возносил горячие молитвы ко Господу.

За подвиг самоотречения блаженный Симон получил от Господа дары предвидения и чудотворения. Так, по его молитвам утих сильный пожар в городе, исцелился священник Олимпий, спасся от потопления в Волге некий горожанин Иосиф.

Перед своей кончиной блаженный пришел в дом воеводы Феодора Петелина, который, не зная подвигов святого, в порыве гнева приказал побить его. Здесь св. Симон тяжко заболел. Причастившись перед смертью Святых Христовых Тайн, блаженный мирно почил 4 ноября 1584 г.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Repose of the Blessed Simon of Yuriev"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
       The son of a villager, living in the village of Odelev, Nerekhta District,
Kostroma Province (not far from the unattached city of Ples), since his early years he
distinguished himself with unusual diligence (an artesian well dug by him serves as a
memorial of this, and by the way, is found near a chapel by the village of Odelev).
Wishing to carry out a virgin life, Simon secretly left the house of his parents and
practiced asceticism first near the village of Elnat (Yuriev District), and then in
Yurievets Volga region. Here, being homeless, he went to the streets, pretending a
deprived mind. His favorite places were church porches, and especially the church
porch of the Holy Theophany Monastery where at night he fervently prayed to God.
From this severe life and strong winter frosts his body turned black and his skin stuck
to his bones. For these God-pleasing efforts he received the gift of insight from God.
He died as a martyr, being beaten by the governor who threw him into a cellar in
1584. In 1619 a new church into which his coffin was finally brought inside was built
in the Yuriev Theophany Monastery where the Blessed Simon was buried. In 1635
Patriarch Joasaph blessed, "for the sake of the patient the life and miracles of the
Blessed Simon, which existed during his lifetime and after his repose", to write his
icon "with light around his head, together with his namesake the Apostle Simon the
Zealot and to honor him among the saints". This local celebration of the Blessed
Simon stopped since 1722 and has not been subsequently restored. At the present time
an easy approach to the tomb is open. The shrine of the Blessed Simon is remodeled,
and in it is placed a cypress icon in a covering, representing the blessed one with the
fingers of his hands intertwined. The memory of the Blessed Simon is considered holy
in Yuriev and its vicinity.

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>
