<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Ефрем Сирин"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Преподобный Ефрем Сирин, учитель покаяния, родился в на- чале IV века (год его рождения точно неизвестен) в городе Низи- бии (Месопотамии) в христианской семье бедных земледельцев-. Родители воспитали сына в благочестии. Но, отличаясь с детства вспыльчивым, раздражительным характером, он в юности часто ссорился, совершал необдуманные поступки, даже сомневался в Промысле Божием, пока не получил от Господа вразумление, на- правившее его на путь покаяния и спасения. Однажды его неспра- ведливо обвинили в краже овец и посадили в темницу. В ней он услышал во сне голос, призывавший его к покаянию и исправле- нию жизни. Он был оправдан и освобожден.     В Ефреме пробудилось глубокое покаяние. Юноша удалился в окрестные горы и стал отшельником. Такой род христианского подвижничества был введен в Низибии учеником преподобного Антония Великого египетским пустынником Евгением.     Среди отшельников особенно выделялся знаменитый аскет, проповедник христианства и обличитель ариан епископ Низибий- ской Церкви святой Иаков (память 13 января). Преподобный Ефрем стал одним из его учеников. Под благодатным руководст- вом святителя преподобный Ефрем стяжал христианскую кро- тость, смирение, покорность Промыслу Божию, дающую силу без- ропотно переносить различные искушения. Святитель Иаков знал высокие достоинства своего ученика и использовал их на благо Церкви — поручал ему читать проповеди, обучать детей в учили- ще, взял его с собой на I Вселенский Собор в Никее (325 г.). Преподобный Ефрем 14 лет был в послушании у святителя Иако- ва, до его кончины.     После взятия Низибии персами в 363 году преподобный Ефрем покинул пустыню и поселился в монастыре близ города Едессы. Здесь он увидел много великих подвижников, проводивших жизнь в молитвах и псалмопении. Пещеры были их единственным убе- жищем, питались они одними растениями. Особенно он сблизился с подвижником Иулианом (память 18 октября), который был с ним одного покаянного духа. Преподобный Ефрем сочетал с под- вижническими трудами непрестанное изучение Слова Божия, по- черпая в нем для своей души умиление и мудрость. Господь дал ему дар учительства, к нему начали приходить люди, ждавшие услышать его наставления, которые особенно действовали на души потому, что он начинал их с обличений себя. Преподобный и уст- но и письменно учил всех покаянию, вере и благочестию, обличал арианскую ересь, волновавшую тогда христианское общество. Язычники, слушая проповеди преподобного, обращались в христи- анство.      Немало потрудился он и в истолковании Священного Писа- н и я — объяснении Пятокнижия Моисея. Им написано много мо- литв и песнопений, обогативших церковное Богослужение. Извест- ны молитвы к Пресвятой Троице, Сыну Божию, Пресвятой Богоро- дице. Он написал для своей Церкви песнопения на дни двунаде- сятых Господних праздников (Рождество Христово, Крещение),  Воскресение, погребальные песнопения. Его покаянная молитва  «Господи и Владыко живота моего...» читается Великим постом  и призывает христиан к духовному обновлению. Церковь с древ-  них времен высоко ценила труды преподобного Ефрема: его тво-  рения читались в некоторых церквах на собраниях верных после  Священного Писания. И ныне по Уставу Церкви некоторые его  поучения положено читать в дни поста. Между пророками святой  Давид, по преимуществу, псалмопевец; между святыми отцами  Церкви преподобный Ефрем Сирин — по преимуществу молитвен-  ник. Духовная * опытность сделала его наставником иноков и  помощником едесских пастырей. Преподобный Ефрем писал по-  сирийски, но его творения очень рано были переведены на грече-  ский и армянский языки, а с греческого — на латинский и славян-  ский.      В многочисленных творениях преподобного встречаются цель-  ные картины жизни сирийских подвижников, главное место в ко-  торой занимала молитва и затем труд на общую братскую пользу,  послушания. Воззрения на смысл жизни у всех сирийских аскетов   были одинаковы. Конечной целью своих подвигов иноки считали  Богообщение и вселение Божественной благодати в душу подвиж-  ника, настоящая жизнь была для них временем плача, поста и  трудов.      «Если Сын Божий в тебе, то и царство Его в тебе. Вот царст-  во Божие — внутри тебя, грешник. Войди в самого себя, ищи   усерднее и без труда найдешь его. Вне тебя — смерть, и дверь к   ней — грех. Войди в себя, пребывай в сердце своем, ибо там — Бог». Непрестанное духовное трезвение, развитие блага в душе человека дает ему возможность воспринять труд как блаженство, и самопринуждение как святость. Воздаяние предначинается в земной жизни человека, подготавливается степенью ее духовного усовершения. Кто на земле взрастил себе крылья, говорит препо- добный Ефрем, тот там воспаряет в горняя; кто здесь очистит ум свой — тот там узрит славу Божию; в какой мере каждый возлю- бит Бога — в той мере насытится любовью Его. Человек, очистив- ший себя и стяжавший благодать Духа Святого еще здесь, на земле, предвкушает Царство Небесное. Стяжать жизнь вечную, по учению преподобного Ефрема, не значит перейти из одной об- ласти бытия в другую, а значит обрести «небесное» духовное со- стояние. Вечная жизнь не даруется человеку односторонним про- изволением Божиим, но, как зерно, постепенно произрастает в нем чрез подвиг, труды и борения.    Залог обожения в нас — Крещение Христово, главный двига- тель жизни христианской — покаяние. Преподобный Ефрем Сирин был великий учитель покаяния. Прощение грехов в таинстве По- каяния, по его учению, это не внешнее оправдание, не забвение грехов, а полное уничтожение их. Слезы покаяния смывают и сжи- гают грех. И еще — они животворят, преображают греховное естество, дают силу «ходить путем заповедей Господних», укреп- ляясь упованием на Бога. В огненной купели Покаяния, писал преподобный, «сам себя- переплавляешь ты, грешник, сам себя воскрешаешь из мертвых».    Преподобный Ефрем, по своему смирению считая себя ниже и хуже всех, в конце своей жизни отправился в Египет, чтобы увидеть подвиги великих пустынников. Он был принят там как желанный гость и сам получил большое утешение от общения с ними. На возвратном пути он посетил в Кесарии Каппадокийской святителя Василия Великого (память 1 января), который пожелал посвятить его во пресвитера, но преподобный счел себя недостой- ным иерейства и, по настоянию святителя, принял лишь сан диа- кона, в котором пребывал до смерти. Впоследствии святитель Ва- силий Великий приглашал преподобного Ефрема на кафедру епископа, но святой представился юродивым, чтобы отклонить от себя эту честь, по смирению считая себя недостойным ее.    По возвращении в свою Едесскую пустынь преподобный Ефрем хотел конец жизни провести в уединении. Но Промысл Божий еще раз вызвал его на служение ближним. Жители Едессы стра- дали от свирепствовавшего голода. Сильным словом преподоб- ный побудил богатых оказывать помощь неимущим. На приноше- ния верующих он построил богадельню для нищих и больных. Затем преподобный удалился- в пещеру под Едессой, где и остался до конца своей жизни. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Ѹ҆́стъ твои́хъ ꙗ҆́коже свѣ́тлость ѻ҆гнѧ̀ возсїѧ́вши бл҃года́ть, вселе́ннꙋю просвѣтѝ. не сребролю́бїѧ мї́рови сокрѡ́вища сниска̀, высотꙋ̀ на́мъ смиреномꙋ́дрїѧ показа̀: но твои́ми словесы̀ наказꙋ́ѧ, ѻ҆́тче ї҆ѡа́нне златоꙋ́сте, молѝ сло́ва хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Возвесели́сѧ та́инственнѡ чⷭтна́ѧ цр҃ковь, возвраще́нїемъ чⷭтны́хъ твои́хъ моще́й, и҆ сїѧ҄ сокры́вши ꙗ҆́кѡ зла́то многоцѣ́нное, пою́щымъ тѧ̀ неѡскꙋ́днѡ подава́етъ мл҃твами твои́ми и҆сцѣле́нїй бл҃года́ть, ї҆ѡа́нне златоꙋ́сте. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Ephrem the Syrian"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Ephrem the Syrian, a teacher of repentance, was born at the beginning of the IV Century (his precise year of birth is unknown) in the city of Ninevah (Mesopotamia) into the family of impoverished toilers of the soil. His parents raised their son in piety. But from the time of his childhood he was known for his quick temper and irascible character, and in his youth he often had fights, he acted thoughtlessly, and even doubted of God&apos;s Providence, until he finally recovered his senses from the Lord&apos;s doing, guiding him on the path of repentance and salvation. One time he was unjustly accused of the theft of a sheep and was thrown into prison. And there in a dream he heard a voice, calling him to repentance and rectifying his life. After this, he was acquitted of the charges and set free.  	Within Ephrem there took place a deep repentance. The youth withdrew outside the city and became an hermit. This form of Christian asceticism had been introduced at Ninevah by a disciple of the Monk Anthony the Great, -- the Egyptian Wilderness-Dweller Eugenios (Eugene). 	Among the hermits especially prominent was the noted ascetic, a preacher of Christianity and denouncer of the Arians, the bishop of the Ninevah Church, Saint James (Comm. 13 January). The Monk Ephrem became one of his disciples. Under the graced guidance of the holy hierarch, the Monk Ephrem attained to Christian meekness, humility, submission to the Will of God, and the strength without murmur to undergo various temptations. Saint James knew the high qualities of his student and he used them for the good of the Ninevah Church -- he entrusted him to read sermons, to instruct children in the school, and he took Ephrem along with him to the First OEcumenical Council at Nicea (in the year 325). The Monk Ephrem was in obedience to Saint James for 14 years, until the bishop&apos;s death. 	After the capture of Ninevah by the Persians in the year 363, the Monk Ephrem abandoned the wilderness and settled in a monastery near the city of Edessa. Here he saw many a great ascetic, passing their lives in prayer and psalmody. Their caves were solitary shelters, and they fed themselves off a certain plant. He became especially close with the ascetic Julian (Comm. 18 October), who was one with him in a spirit of repentance. The Monk Ephrem combined with his ascetic works an incessant study of the Word of God, gathering within it for his soul both solace and wisdom. The Lord gave him a gift of teaching, and people began to come to him, wanting to hear his guidances, which produced a particular effect upon the soul, since he began with self-accusation. The monk both verbally and in writing instructed everyone in repentance, faith and piety, and he denounced the Arian heresy, which during those times was disrupting Christian society. And pagans likewise, listening to the preaching of the monk, were converted to Christianity. 	He also toiled no little at the interpretation of Holy Scripture -- with an explication of the Pentateuch (i.e. &quot;Five Books&quot;) of Moses. He wrote many a prayer and church-song, thereby enriching the Church&apos;s Divine-services. Famed prayers of Saint Ephrem are to the MostHoly Trinity, to the Son of God, and to the MostHoly Mother of God. He wrote for his Church song for the Twelve Great Feastdays of the Lord  (the Nativity of Christ, the Baptism, the Resurrection), and funereal song. Saint Emphrem&apos;s Prayer of Repentance, &quot;O Lord and Master of my life...&quot;, is said during Great Lent, and it summons Christians to spiritual renewal. The Church since times ancient valued highly the works of the Monk Ephrem: his works were read in certain churches, at gatherings of the faithful, after the Holy Scripture. And now at present in accord with the Church Ustav (Rule), certain of his instructions are prescribed to be read on the days of Lent. Amidst the prophets, Saint David is pre-eminently the psalmodist; amidst the holy fathers of the Church the Monk Ephrem the Syrian -- is pre-eminently a man of prayer. His spiritual experience made him a guide to monks and an help to the pastors of Edessa. The Monk Ephrem wrote in Syrian, but his works were very early translated into the Greek and Armenian languages, and from the Greek -- into the Latin and Slavonic languages.  	In numerous of the works of the Monk Ephrem are encountered glimpses of the life of the Syrian ascetics, the centre of which involved prayer and with it thereupon the toiling for the common good of the brethren, in the obediences. The outlook of the meaning of life among all the Syrian ascetics was the same. The end purpose of their efforts was considered by the monks to be communality with God and the diffusion of Divine grace within the soul of the ascetic; the present life for them was a time of tears, fasting and toil. 	&quot;If the Son of God be within thee, then also His Kingdom is within thee. Here then  is the Kingdom of God -- within thee, a sinner. Go inwards into thine self, search diligently and without toil thou shalt find it. Outside of thee -- is death, and the door to it -- is sin. Go inwards into thine self, dwell within thine heart, for since there -- is God&quot;. Constant spiritual sobriety, the developing of good within the soul of man gives unto him the possibility to take upon himself a task like blessedness, and a self-constraint like sanctity. The requital is presupposed in the earthly life of man, it is an undertaking by degrees of its spiritual perfection. Whoso grows himself wings upon the earth, says the Monk Ephrem, is one who soars up into the heights; whoso down here purifies his mind -- there glimpses the Glory of God; in what measure each one loveth God -- is that measure wherein is satiated to fullness by the love of God. Man, cleansing himself and attaining the grace of the Holy Spirit while still here, down upon the earth, has a foretaste therein of the Kingdom of Heaven. To attain to life eternal, in the teachings of the Monk Ephrem, does not mean to pass over from one sphere of being into another, but means rather to discover &quot;the Heavenly&quot; spiritual condition of being. Eternal life is not bestown man as a one-sided working by God, but rather like a seed, it constantly grows within him through effort, toil and struggle. 	The pledge within us of &quot;theosis&quot; (&quot;obozhenie&quot; or &quot;deification&quot;) -- is the Baptism of Christ, and the primal propulsion for the Christian life -- is repentance. The Monk Ephrem was a great teacher of repentance. The forgiveness of sins in the sacramental-mystery of Repentance, according to his teaching, is not an external exoneration, not a forgetting of the sins, but rather their complete undoing, their annihilation. The tears of repentance wash away and burn away the sin. And moreover -- they (i.e. the tears) vivify, they transfigure sinful nature, they give the strength &quot;to walk in the way of the commandments of the Lord&quot;, encouraging the hope on God. In the fiery font of Repentance, wrote the Monk, &quot;thou dost sail thyself across, O sinner, thou dost resuscitate thyself from the dead&quot;. 	The Monk Ephrem, in his humility reckoning himself the least and worst of all, at the end of his life set out to Egypt, to see the efforts of the great ascetics. He was accepted there as a welcome guest and received for himself great solace in his associating with them. On the return journey he visited at Caesarea Cappadocia with Sainted Basil the Great (Comm. 1 January), who wanted to ordain him a priest, but the monk considered himself unworthy of priesthood, and at the insistence of Saint Basil, he accepted only the dignity of deacon, in which he remained until death. Even later on, Saint Basil the Great invited the Monk Ephrem to accept the cathedra-chair of a bishop, but the saint feigned folly to avoid for himself this honour, in humility reckoning himself unworthy of it. 	Upon his return to his own Edessa wilderness, the Monk Ephrem intended to spend the rest of his life in solitude. But Divine Providence again summoned him to service of neighbour. The inhabitants of Edessa were suffering from a devastating famine. By the influence of his word, the monk induced the wealthy to render aid to those that lacked. From the offerings of believers he built a poor-house for the destitute and sick. The Monk Ephrem then withdrew to a cave nigh to Edessa, where he remained to the end of his days.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
With the streams of thy tears thou didst irrigate the barren desert,/ and with sighs from the depths of thy soul thou didst render thy labors fruitful an hundredfold./ Thou wast a beacon for the whole world, radiating miracles.// O our father Ephraim, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Ever looking forth toward the hour of judgement,/ thou didst bitterly lament, O Ephraim;/ and though a lover of stillness/ thou wast also a teacher of activity, O venerable one,/ Wherefore, O universal father,// thou movest the slothful to repentance.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>