<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой мученик Терентий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святой мученик Терентий и его дружина пострадали при импе- раторе Декии (249—251). Император издал указ, в котором пове- левалось всем подданным приносить жертвы языческим идолам.    Когда этот указ получил правитель Африки Фортунатиан, он созвал народ на площади, показал страшные орудия пыток и объ- явил, что все без исключения должны принести жертвы идолам. Многие, испугавшись мучений, согласились, но сорок христиан во главе со святым Терентием мужественно заявили о своей верности Спасителю. Фортунатиан удивился их смелости и спросил, как они, разумные люди, могут исповедовать Богом Того, Кто был распят иудеями как злодей. В ответ на это святой Терентий смело отве- тил, что они веруют в Спасителя, добровольно претерпевшего Кре- стную смерть и в третий день Воскресшего. Фортунатиан понял, что Терентий своим примером воодушевляет других, и велел за- точить его в темницу вместе с тремя его ближайшими друзьями— Африканом, Максимом и Помпием. Остальных мучеников, в том числе Зинона, Александра и Феодора, Фортунатиан решил прину- дить к отречению от Христа. Однако ни уговоры, ни страшные мучения не поколебали святых мучеников: их жгли раскаленным железом, поливали раны уксусом, растирали солью, строгали же- лезными когтями. Несмотря на страдания, святые не ослабевали в исповедании Христа, и Господь укреплял их.     Фортунатиан велел привести страдальцев в храм и еще раз предложил им принести жертву идолам. Мужественные воины Хри- стовы воззвали к Богу: «Боже Всесильный, проливший некогда огонь на Содом за беззаконие его, разори и ныне этот нечестивый храм идольский, ради истины Твоей». Идолы упали с грохотом и рассыпались, а затем разрушился весь храм. Разъяренный пра- витель приказал казнить их. Мученики, славя Бога, преклонили свои головы под меч палача.     После казни 36 мучеников Фортунатиан призвал к себе Терен- тия, Максима, Африкана и Помпия, показал им казненных и снова предложил принести жертву идолам. Мученики отказались. Пра- витель наложил на них тяжелые оковы и приказал морить в тем- нице голодом. Ночью Ангел Господень снял с мучеников оковы и напитал их. Наутро стража нашла святых бодрыми и полными сил. Тогда Фортунатиан приказал волхвам и заклинателям на- вести в темницу змей и всяких гадов. Стражи через отверстие в крыше заглянули в темницу и увидели невредимых мучеников, которые молились, а змеи ползали у их ног. Когда заклинатели, исполняя приказание, открыли двери темницы, змеи, не слушая заклинаний, бросились на них и стали жалить. Разъяренный Фор- тунатиан повелел обезглавить святых мучеников. Христиане взяли их святые тела и погребли с честью за городом. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="4">
Мч҃нческаѧ честна́ѧ па́мѧть прїи́де дне́сь, веселѧ́щи всѧ́чєскаѧ, тере́нтїа премꙋ́драгѡ и҆ дрꙋжи́ны є҆гѡ̀. те́плѣ ѹ҆̀бо стеце́мсѧ, да прїи́мемъ и҆сцѣлє́нїѧ: сї́и бо бл҃года́ть ѡ҆ бг҃а прїѧ́ша дх҃а ст҃а́гѡ, и҆сцѣлѧ́ти недꙋ́ги дꙋ́шъ на́шихъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Holy Martyr Terence"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyr Terence and his companions suffered under the emperor Decius (249-251). The emperor issued an edict, which commanded all subjects to offer sacrifice to the pagan idols. 	When the governor of Africa Fortunatian received this edict, he gathered the people into the city-square, set out cruel instruments of torture and declared, that everyone without exception had to offer the sacrifice to the idols. Many, afraid of torture, complied, but forty Christians with Saint Terence at their head bravely stood forth for their faith in the Saviour. Fortunatian was amazed at their boldness and he asked, how they as rational people, could confess as God, One Who was crucified by the Jews as a malefactor. In answer to this, Saint Terence boldly answered, that their belief was in the Saviour, Who voluntarily endured death on the Cross and on the third day was resurrected. Fortunatian perceived, that Terence by his example inspired the others, and so he gave orders to isolate him in prison together with his three closest companions -- Africanus, Maximus and Pompius. The remainder of the martyrs -- which included Xenon, Alexander and Theodore, Fortunatian resolved to force into renouncing Christ. But neither threats nor terrible tortures could sway the holy martyrs: they burned at them with red-hot iron, they poured vinegar on the wounds, they sprinkled on salt, they tore at them with iron claws. In spite of their sufferings, the saints did not weaken in their confession of Christ, and the Lord gave them strength.  	Forunatian gave orders to lead the martyrs into the pagan temple and still yet another time he urged them to offer sacrifice to the idols. The valiant warriors of Christ cried out to God: &quot;O God All-Powerful, having once poured out fire on Sodom for its iniquity, destroy now this impious temple of idolatry, on account of Thine Truth&quot;. The idols fell down with a crash and a smash, and then all the temple was in ruins. The enraged governor gave orders to execute them; and the martyrs, glorifying God, put their necks beneathe the sword of the executioner.  	After the execution of the 36 martyrs, Fortunatian summoned before him Terence, Maximus, Africanus and Pompius, pointed out to them the executed and again urged them to offer sacrifice to the idols. The martyrs refused. The governor put heavy chains on them and gave orders to starve them to death in prison. by night an Angel of the Lord took the chains off the martyrs and fed them. In the morning the guards found the saints cheerful and strong. Then Fortunatian ordered sorcerers and conjurers to carry into the prison snakes and all kinds of viprous creatures. The guards through an opening in the prison ceiling glanced down into the jail-cell and saw the martyrs unharmed, praying, and the snakes crawling at their feet. When the snake-charmers in obeying the order opened the door of the prison-cell, the snakes disregarded the charms and struck and began to bite them. The furious Fortunatian gave orders to behead the holy martyrs. Christians took up their holy bodies and buried them with reverence outside the city. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="4">
Today the honored memorial/ of the martyrs Terence and his companions/ hath arrived, gladdening all things. Wherefore, let us hasten, that we may receive healing;/ for they have received from God the grace of the Holy Spirit,// for healing the infirmities of our souls.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>