<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Зосима, игумен Соловецкий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Преподобный Зосима, игумен Соловецкий, великий светильник русского Севера, основатель иноческого общежития на Соловец- ком острове, родился в Новгородской епархии, в селе Толвуе близ Онежского озера. С юных лет он воспитывался в благочестии, и после смерти родителей Гавриила и Варвары раздал имущество и принял постриг.    В поисках уединенного места преподобный отправился на по- бережье Белого моря и в устье Сумы встретился с преподобным Германом (память 30 июля), который поведал ему о пустынном морском острове, где он с преподобным Савватием (память 27 сен- тября) прожил 6 лет.    Около 1436 года отшельники, благополучно совершив морское плавание, пристали к Соловецким островам. Бог благословил ме- сто их поселения видением преподобному Зосиме прекрасной церк- ви на воздухе. Преподобные своими руками построили келью и ограду, начали возделывать и засевать землю. Однажды поздней осенью преподобный Герман отправился на материк за необходи- мыми припасами. Из-за осенней непогоды он не смог вернуться. Преподобный Зосима провел всю зиму один на острове. Много искушений он претерпел в борьбе с бесами. Ему угрожала голод- ная смерть, однако чудесно появившиеся два незнакомца оставили ему запас хлеба, муки и масла. Весной возвратился на Соловки преподобный Герман с рыбаком Марком и привез запас пищи и снасти для рыбной ловли.     Когда на острове собралось несколько отшельников, преподоб- ный Зосима устроил для них небольшую деревянную церковь в честь Преображения Господня с трапезной. По просьбе преподоб- ного Зосимы из Новгорода был прислан в новосозданную обитель игумен с антиминсом для соборного храма. Так было положено начало знаменитой Соловецкой обители. В суровых условиях отда- ленного острова иноки сумели организовать хозяйство. Но настоя- тели, которых присылали на Соловки из Новгорода, не выдержива- ли жизни в непривычно трудных условиях, и братия избрали игу- меном преподобного Зосиму.     Преподобный Зосима занялся устроением внутреннего быта обители, ввел строгое общежитие. В 1465 году он перенес на Со- ловки с реки Выг мощи преподобного Савватия. Обитель терпела притеснения от новгородских бояр, которые отнимали у иноков уловы рыбы. Преподобный вынужден был отправиться в Новго- род и искать защиты у архиепископа. По совету архиепископа он обходил дома бояр и просил их не допускать обитель до разо- рения. Влиятельная и богатая боярыня Марфа Борецкая прика- зала с бесчестьем выгнать преподобного Зосиму, но потом рас- каялась и пригласила его на обед, во время которого он вдруг увидел, что шесть знатнейших бояр сидят без голов. Преподобный Зосима поведал видение своему ученику Даниилу и предсказал боярам скорую смерть. Это предсказание исполнилось в 1478 го- ду, когда при взятии Новгорода Иоанном III (1462—1505) бояре были казнены.     Незадолго до кончины преподобный сам приготовил себе гроб, в котором был погребен за алтарем Преображенского храма (•\ 17 апреля 1478). Впоследствии над его могилой была устроена часовня. Мощи его совместно с мощами преподобного Савватия 8 августа 1566 года были перенесены в придел, освященный в их честь в Преображенском соборе.    Много чудес было засвидетельствовано, когда преподобный Зо- сима с преподобным Савватием являлись гибнувшим в морской пучине рыбакам. Преподобный Зосима также покровитель пче- ловодства и хранитель пчел, ему усвоено даже именование «пчель- ник». К преподобному Зосиме часто прибегают и в болезнях. Мно- жество больничных храмов, посвященных ему, свидетельствует о великой целительной силе его молитв пред Богом. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆зволе́нїемъ бж҃е́ственнагѡ ра́зꙋма всели́лсѧ є҆сѝ въ пꙋсты́ню, и҆ та́мѡ впери́въ ѹ҆́мъ тво́й въ нбⷭныѧ ѻ҆би́тєли, ра́вно а҆́гг҃лѡмъ житїѐ на землѝ пожи́въ, въ мл҃твахъ и҆ трꙋдѣ́хъ и҆ поще́нїихъ, ѡ҆́бразъ бы́лъ є҆сѝ твои҄мъ ѹ҆ченикѡ́мъ. ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже бг҃ъ ви́дѧ твоѐ бл҃го́е и҆зволе́нїе, ѹ҆мно́жи тебѣ̀ ча҄да въ пꙋсты́ни, сле́зъ твои́хъ тече́ньми напаѧ́емѣй: но ꙗ҆́кѡ и҆мѣ́ѧ дерзнове́нїе къ бг҃ꙋ, помина́й ста́до, є҆́же собра́лъ є҆сѝ мꙋ́дре, и҆ не забꙋ́ди ꙗ҆́коже ѡ҆бѣща́лсѧ є҆сѝ, посѣща́ѧ ча́дъ твои́хъ, зѡсї́мо прпⷣбне ѻ҆́тче на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Хрⷭто́вою любо́вїю ѹ҆ѧзви́всѧ прпⷣбне, и҆ тогѡ̀ крⷭтъ сла́вный на ра́мо взе́мъ поне́слъ є҆сѝ, бж҃е́ственнѣ воѡрꙋжи́всѧ, и҆ непреста҄нныѧ мл҃твы ꙗ҆́кѡ копїѐ въ рꙋцѣ̀ и҆мы́й, крѣ́пкѡ ссѣ́клъ є҆сѝ бѣсѡ́вскаѧ ѡ҆полчє́нїѧ. тѣ́мъ зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ прпⷣбне ѻ҆́тче зѡсї́мо, мона́хѡвъ ѹ҆добре́нїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Zosima, Hegumen of Solovki"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Zosima, Hegumen of Solovetsk, -- a great luminary of the RussianNorth, was the founder of monastic common-life on Solovetsk Island. He was born in Novgorod diocese, in the village of Tolvui near Lake Onega. From his early years he was raised in piety, and after the death of his parents Gavriil and Varvara he gave away his possessions and accepted monastic tonsure.  	In search of a solitary place the monk set off to the shores of the White Sea and at the mouth of the Suma he met the Monk German (Comm. 30 July), who told him about a desolate sea island, where formerly he had spent six years with the Monk Savvatii (Comm. 27 September). 	In about the year 1436 the hermits, felicitously having made the sea voyage, landed at the Solovetsk islands. God blessed the place of their settlement with a vision to the Monk Zosima of a beautiful church in the sky. The monks with their own hands built cells and an enclosure, and they began to cultivate and sow the land. One time in late Autumn the Monk German set off to the mainland for necessary provisions. Because of the Autumn weather he was not able to return. The Monk Zosima remained all Winter alone on the island. He suffered many a temptation in struggle with the devils. Death by starvation threatened him, but miraculously two strangers having appeared left him a supply of bread, flour and oil. In Spring the Monk German returned to Solovetsk together with the fisherman Mark, and he brought supplies of food and rigging-tackle for fish nets. 	When several hermits had gathered on the island, the Monk Zosima constructed for them a small wooden church in honour of the Transfiguration (Preobrazhenie) of the Lord, together with a refectory. At the request of the Monk Zosima, an hegumen was sent from Novgorod to the newly formed monastery with antimins for the church. Thus occurred the start of the reknown Solovetsk monastery. In the severe conditions of the remote island the monks knew how to arrange their economy. But the hegumens, sent from Novgorod to Solovetsk, could not withstand life in the unwontedly harsh conditions, and so the brethren chose as hegumen the Monk Zosima.  	The Monk Zosima concerned himself with the building up of the inner life of the monastery, and he introduced a strict life-in-common. In 1465 he transferred to Solovetsk from the River Vyg the relics of the Monk Savvatii. The monastery suffered vexation from the Novgorod boyars (nobles), who confiscated catches of fish from the monks. The monk was obliged to set off for Novgorod and seek the protection of the archbishop. On the advice of the archbishop, he made the rounds of homes of the boyars and requested them not to allow the ruin of the monastery. The influential and rich boyarina Martha Boretskaya impiously gave orders to throw out the Monk Zosima, but then repented her action and invited him to a meal, during the time of which he suddenly beheld, that six of the illustrious boyars sat without their heads. The Monk Zosima told about this vision to his disciple Daniel and predicted for the boyars an immanent death. The prediction was fulfilled in the year 1478, when during the taking of Novgorod by Ivan III (1462-1505) the boyars were executed. 	Shortly before death the monk prepared himself a grave, in which he was buried beyond the altar of the Transfiguration church (+ 17 April 1478). Later on, over his relics was built a chapel. His relics together with the relics of the Monk Savvatii were transferred on 8 August 1566 into a chapel consecrated in their memory at the Transfiguration cathedral. 	Many a miracle was witnessed to, when the Monk Zosima with the Monk Savvatii appeared to fishermen perishing in the depths of the sea. The Monk Zosima is likewise a patron of bee-keeping and preserver of bee-hives, and to him is even bestown the title &quot;Bee-keeper&quot; (&quot;Pchel&apos;nik&quot;). To the Monk Zosima often hasten those in sickness. The many hospital churches dedicated to him testify to the great curative power of his prayer before God. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
No english translation
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
No English translation
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>