<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой апостол Иаков Зеведеев"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святой апостол Иаков Зеведеев, один из 12 апостолов, был призван Господом Иисусом Христом к апостольскому служению вместе со своим братом апостолом Иоанном Богословом. Им и апостолу Петру Иисус Христос преимущественно перед дру- гими апостолами открывал Свои Божественные Тайны: при воскрешении дочери Иаира, на Фаворской горе и в Гефсиман- ском саду.    Святой Иаков, по сошествии Святого Духа, проповедовал в Испании и других странах, а потом возвратился в Иерусалим. Он открыто и смело учил об Иисусе Христе как Спасителе мира, сло- вами Священного Писания обличал фарисеев и книжников, уко- ряя их в жестокосердии и неверии. Иудеи были не в состоянии противостать апостольскому слову и за деньги наняли философа- волхва Гермогена, чтобы он вступил в диспут с апостолом и опро- верг его доводы о Христе как о пришедшем на землю обетованном Мессии. Волхв послал к святому апостолу своего ученика Филип- па, но он уверовал в Господа Иисуса Христа. Затем и сам Гермоген убедился в силе Божией, сжег свои волшебные книги, принял святое Крещение и сделался истинным последователем Христовым.    Неверующие иудеи убедили Ирода Агриппу (40—44) схватить апостола Иакова и осудить его на смерть. Святой Иаков спокойно выслушал смертный приговор и продолжал свидетельствовать о Христе. Один из доносчиков на апостола по имени Иосия был по- ражен мужеством святого Иакова. Он уверовал в истину слов о пришествии Христа-Мессии. Когда апостола повели на казнь, Иосия пал к его ногам, покаялся в своем грехе и молил о проще- нии. Апостол обнял, поцеловал его и сказал: «Мир тебе и проще- ние». Тогда Иосия исповедал всенародно веру во Христа и был обезглавлен вместе со святым Иаковом в 44 году в Иерусалиме. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
А҆пⷭле ст҃ы́й ї҆а́кѡве, молѝ млⷭтиваго бг҃а, да прегрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе пода́стъ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
А҆пⷭлъ хрⷭто́въ бы́лъ є҆сѝ и҆збра́нный, и҆ бг҃осло́вꙋ возлю́бленномꙋ бра́тъ є҆диноро́дный всехва́льне ї҆а́кѡве, пою́щымъ тѧ̀ грѣхѡ́въ ѡ҆ставле́нїе и҆спросѝ, и҆ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ ве́лїю млⷭть. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Гла́съ бж҃е́ственный слы́шавъ призыва́ющъ тѧ̀, любо́вь ѻ҆тца̀ презрѣ́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ прите́клъ є҆сѝ, ко хрⷭтꙋ̀, ї҆а́кѡве съ сро́дникомъ твои́мъ сла́вне: съ ни́мже сподо́билсѧ є҆сѝ ви́дѣти гдⷭне бж҃е́ственное преѡбраже́нїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Apostle James, Son of Zebedee"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Apostle James, Son of Zebedee, one of the 12 Apostles, was called by our Lord Jesus Christ for apostolic service together with his brother, the Apostle John the Theologian. It was to them and to the holy Apostle Peter pre-eminently over the other Apostles that Jesus Christ revealed His Divine Mysteries: at the Resuscitation of the Daughter of Jairus, on Mount Tabor (at the Transfiguration), and in the Garden of Gethsemane. 	Saint James, after the Descent of the Holy Spirit, preached in Spain and in other lands, and then he returned to Jerusalem. He openly and boldly taught about Jesus Christ as the Saviour of the world, and with the words of Holy Scripture he denounced the Pharisees and the Scribes [scholars], reproaching them with malice of heart and unbelief. The Jews had not the ability to refute the apostolic discourse and for money they hired the pseudo-philosopher and sorcerer Hermogenes, so that he would enter into a disputation with the apostle and confute his arguments about Christ as the Promised Messiah having come into the world. The sorcerer sent to the apostle his student Philip, who was converted to belief in Christ. Then Hermogenes himself became persuaded of the power of God, he burnt his books on magic, accepted holy Baptism and became a true follower of Christ. 	The unbelieving among the Jews persuaded Herod Agrippa (40-44) to arrest the Apostle James and sentence him to death. Saint James calmly heard out the death sentence and continued to bear witness about Christ. One of the false-witnesses against the apostle by the name of Josiah was struck by the courage of Saint James. He came to believe in the truth of the words about the coming of Christ the Messiah. When they led forth the apostle for execution, Josiah fell at his feet, repenting his sin and asking forgiveness. The apostle hugged him, gave him a kiss and said: &quot;Peace and forgiveness be unto thee&quot;. Then Josiah confessed before everyone his faith in Christ, and he was beheaded together with Saint James in the year 44 at Jerusalem.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
O holy apostle James/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
	Thou wast a chosen apostle of Christ/ and the only brother of the beloved Theologian,/ O most lauded James./ Ask thou remission of sins for those who hymn thee,// and great mercy for our souls.
	</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Hearing the voice of God calling thee,/ thou didst disdain the love of thy father,/ and with thy kinsman thou didst hasten after Christ, O glorious James./ And with him thou wast counted worthy to behold// the divine transfiguration of the Lord.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>