<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="                       еренесение мощей священномуче- ника Игнатия Богоносца"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   В этот день воспоминается перенесение мощей священномуче- ника Игнатия Богоносца (память 20 декабря).    После того как святой священномученик Игнатий, по повеле- нию императора Траяна (98—117), был в Риме брошен на растер- зание зверям и скончался в 107 году, христиане собрали его кости и хранили в Риме. В 108 году их перенесли в предместье города Антиохии. Второе перенесение — в самый город Антиохию — совер- шено было в 438 году. После взятия города Антиохии персами мощи священномученика были возвращены в Рим и положены в храме в честь святого священномученика папы Климента в 540 го- ду (по другим источникам, в 637 году). Священномученик Игнатий ввел в церковное Богослужение антифонное пение. Он оставил семь архипастырских посланий, в которых наставлял в вере, любви и добрых делах, призывал хранить единство веры и остерегаться еретиков, завещал повиноваться епископам и чтить их, «смотря на епископа как на Самого Христа».    «Внимайте епископу, дабы и Бог внимал вам... Крещение пусть остается с вами, как щит; вера — как шлем; любовь — как копье; терпение — как полное вооружение». 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆ нра́вѡмъ прича́стникъ, и҆ прⷭто́лѡмъ намѣ́стникъ а҆пⷭлѡмъ бы́въ, дѣѧ́нїе ѡ҆брѣ́лъ є҆сѝ бг҃одохнове́нне, въ видѣ́нїѧ восхо́дъ: сегѡ̀ ра́ди сло́во и҆́стины и҆справлѧ́ѧ, и҆ вѣ́ры ра́ди пострада́лъ є҆сѝ да́же до кро́ве, сщ҃енномч҃нче ї҆гна́тїе, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Ѿ восто́ка дне́сь возсїѧ́вый, и҆ тва́рь всю̀ просвѣти́вый ѹ҆че́ньми, мꙋ́ченичествомъ ѹ҆краси́сѧ, бг҃оно́сный и҆ бж҃е́ственный ї҆гна́тїй. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Transfer of the Relics of the PriestMartyr Ignatios the God-Bearer"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Transfer of the Relics of the PriestMartyr Ignatios the God-Bearer: (the account about him is located under 20 December). After the holy PriestMartyr Ignatios was thrown for devouring by wild beasts at Rome dying in the year 107 -- on orders of the emperor Trajan, Christians gathered up his bones and preserved them at Rome. Later in the year 108 they were transferred to the outskirts of Antioch. A second transfer -- into the city of Antioch itself, was done in the year 438. And after the taking of Antioch by the Persians, the relics of the PriestMartyr Ignatios were returned to Rome and placed into the church in honour of the holy PriestMartyr Pope Clement in the year 540 (but according to other histories, the year was 637). The PriestMartyr introduced antiphonal singing into Church Divine-services. He has left us seven archpastoral epistles in which he provided instruction on faith, love and good works, he urged likewise the preserving of the oneness of the faith and to beware of heretics, and he bid the obeying and honouring of bishops, &quot;looking upon the bishop as upon Christ Himself&quot;. 	&quot;Hearken ye unto the bishop, so that God in turn might hearken unto you... let Baptism remain with you, like a shield and buckler; faith -- like an helmet; love -- like a spear; patience -- like full armour&quot;. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
As thou didst share in the ways of the apostles/ and didst occupy their throne,/ thou didst find thine activity to be a passage to divine vision,/ O divinely inspired one./ Wherefore, ordering the word of truth,/ thou didst suffer for the Faith even to the shedding of thy blood.// O hieromartyr Ignatius, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Thou didst shine forth from the East today,/ illumining all creation with thy doctrines, O God-bearing and divine Ignatius,// and art adorned with martyrdom.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>