<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые мученики Феодор, мать его Филиппин, Диоскор, Сократ и Дионисий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святые мученики Феодор, мать его Филиппин, Диоскор, Сократ и Дионисий пострадали в царствование императора Антонина Пия (138—161) в Пергии Памфилийской. Когда для военной службы набирали красивых и здоровых юношей, то вместе с дру- гими к военачальнику Феодоту был приведен и юноша Феодор.     Военачальник стал принуждать юношу принести жертву идо- лам. Мученик не подчинился ни уговорам, ни угрозам, и воена- чальник приказал положить его на раскаленную сковороду и по- ливать расплавленной смолой. Тотчас совершилось чудо: нача- лось землетрясение, из трещины в земле хлынул поток воды и погасил огонь.    Оставшийся невредимым мученик Феодор воздал хвалу Богу и предложил военачальнику попытаться с помощью идолов повто- рить такое чудо.     Военачальник предложил языческому жрецу Диоскору лечь на раскаленную сковороду, призвав на помощь Зевса. Но святой Диоскор ответил, что он уверовал во Христа и готов бросить идо- ла Зевса в огонь. Тогда военачальник приказал ему взойти на сковороду. Мученик Диоскор припал к ногам святого Феодора и просил помолиться о нем. Затем он взошел на сковороду, гром-  ко взывая ко Господу: «Благодарю Тебя, Господи Иисусе Христе, что Ты сопричислил меня к числу рабов Твоих. Приими с миром  мою душу»,— и скончался, избавившись от тяжелых мук.     Святого Феодора продолжали мучить. Его привязали к диким  лошадям, которых стали гнать. Но у городской стены лошади упа-  ли и разбились, а мученик Феодор остался невредимым. Два вой- на, Сократ и Дионисий, увидели, как к святому Феодору сошла с небес огненная колесница, на которую был поднят влачимый мученик. Воины с изумлением воскликнули «Велик Бог христи- анский!» За это их тут же схватили и на другой день вместе с мучеником Феодором бросили в раскаленную печь. Но Небесная роса охладила печь, и святые остались живы. Наутро военачаль- ник приказал воинам пойти посмотреть кости сгоревших мучени- ков. Воины вернулись и с удивлением рассказали, что три юноши невредимы, а к мученику Феодору пришла его мать, Филиппия, которая теперь укрепляет мучеников в их подвиге.    Военачальник предложил святой Филиппин спасти сына, уго- ворив его принести жертву идолам. Но святая Филиппия ответила, что еще до рождения сына ей было открыто, что ее сын будет распят за Христа. Услышав это, военачальник приказал распять святого Феодора на кресте, а остальным мученикам отсечь голо- вы. В течение 3-х дней святой мученик Феодор висел на кресте, вознося молитвы Богу до своего преставления. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
Позна́нъ бы́въ, ѿ пеле́нъ ѡ҆сщ҃е́нъ, и҆ ꙗ҆́вльсѧ бл҃года́тей и҆спо́лненъ, чꙋдесы̀ мї́ръ ѡ҆зари́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ де́монѡвъ мно́жество ѿгна́лъ є҆сѝ, сщ҃еннодѣ́телю ѳео́дѡре: тѣ́мже ѡ҆ на́съ моли́сѧ гдⷭеви. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ на ѻ҆́гненнꙋю колесни́цꙋ, добродѣ́тельми бг҃оно́се возше́дъ, восте́клъ є҆сѝ на нбⷭнаѧ жили҄ща: ꙗ҆́кѡ а҆́гг҃лъ съ человѣ́ки пожи́лъ є҆сѝ: и҆ ꙗ҆́кѡ человѣ́къ со а҆́гг҃лы ѻ҆́крестъ ликовствꙋ́еши. сегѡ̀ ра́ди показа́лсѧ є҆сѝ чꙋде́съ бж҃е́ственное прїѧ́телище, ѳео́дѡре прпⷣбне. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyrs Theodore, his mother Philippia, Dioskoros, Sokrates and Dionysios"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyrs Theodore, his mother Philippia, Dioskoros, Sokrates and Dionysios suffered during the reign of the emperor Antoninus Pius (138-161) in Pamphylian Pergium. When they were conscripting for military service robust and healthy young men, then together with the others they led the youth Theodore to the military commander Theodotos. 	The military commander obliged the youth to offer sacrifice to idols. The martyr submitted neither to persuasion nor threats, and the military commander commanded to place him on a red-hot plate and to pour out liquid tar. Immediately there occurred a miracle: an earth-trembling began, and from a fissure in the ground gushed forth a torrent of water and extinguished the fire. 	Having remained unharmed, the martyr Theodore gave praise to God and suggested to the military commander to try with the help of the idols to repeat such a miracle. 	The military commander suggested to the pagan priest Dioskoros to lay upon the red-hot plate, calling on the help of Zeus. But Saint Dioskoros answered, that he believed in Christ and was prepared to throw the idol of Zeus into the fire. Then the military commander commanded him to get on the frying-pan. The martyr Dioskoros fell at the knees of Saint Theodore and pleaded that he pray for him. Then he got onto the frying-pan, loudly crying out to the Lord: &quot;I give Thee thanks, Lord Jesus Christ, that Thou hast included me in the number of Thine servants. Accept Thou my soul with peace&quot;, -- and he died, having been delivered from terrible torment. 	They continued to torture Saint Theodore. They tied him to wild horses, which began to run. But at the city walls the horses fell down and collapsed, and the martyr Theodore remained unharmed. Two soldiers, Sokrates and Dionysios, saw how there came down from the heavens a fiery chariot to Saint Theodore, on which was carried the dragged martyr. The soldiers with astonishment shouted out: &quot;Great God of the Christians!&quot; For this they seized hold of them and on the next day threw them together with the martyr Theodore into a red-hot furnace. But an Heavenly dew cooled the furnace, and the saints remained alive. In the morning the military commander commanded soldiers to go march to look upon the burnt bodies of the martyrs. The soldiers returned and with wonder reported that the three youths were unharmed, and to the martyr Theodore was come his mother, Philippia, who now encouraged the martyrs in their act. 	The military commander suggested to Saint Philippia to save her son, urging her to offer sacrifice to the idols. But Saint Philippia answered, that yet while at the time of the birth of her son it was revealed to her, that her son would be crucified for Christ. Hearing this, the military commander commanded to crucify Saint Theodore on a cross, and to cut off the heads of the remaining martyrs. During the course of 3 days the martyr Theodore hung on the cross, offering up prayer to God until he expired.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
No English translation
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
No English translation
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>