<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые апостолы Аристарх, Пуд и Трофим"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святые апостолы Аристарх, Пуд и Трофим были из числа 70-ти апостолов, которых Господь Иисус Христос послал перед Собою с Евангельским благовестием (Лк. 10, 1—24).     Святой апостол Аристарх, сотрудник святого апостола Павла, стал епископом сирийского города Апамеи. Имя его неоднократно упоминается в книге Деяний святых апостолов (Деян. 19, 29; 20, 4; 27, 2) и в Посланиях апостола Павла (Кол. 4, 10; Флп. 1, 24).     Святой апостол Пуд упоминается во 2-м Послании апостола Павла к Тимофею (2 Тим. 4, 21). Он занимал высокое положение члена римского Сената. В своем доме святой принимал первовер- ховных апостолов, собирал верующих христиан. Дом его был об- ращен в церковь, получившую название «Пастырской». В ней, по преданию, священнодействовал сам святой апостол Петр.    Святой апостол Трофим происходил из города Едессы. Имя его упоминается в Книге Деяний святых апостолов (Деян. 20, 4) и во 2-м Послании апостола Павла к Тимофею (2 Тим. 4, 20). Он был учеником и спутником святого апостола Павла, разделяя с ним все скорби и гонения.    Все три апостола приняли мученическую кончину в Риме при императоре Нероне (54—68), одновременно со святым апостолом Павлом ( { ок. 67).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Ꙗ҆ви́сѧ а҆по́стольскїй честны́й се́й пра́здникъ, просвѣща́ѧ на́съ, и҆ грѣхо́внꙋю мглꙋ̀ прогонѧ́ѧ, зовꙋ́щымъ: ꙗ҆ви́сѧ свѣ́тъ, и҆ прїи́де и҆збавле́нїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Disciples Aristarchus, Pudas and Trophymos"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Disciples Aristarchus, Pudas and Trophymos were from among the Seventy Disciples, whom the Lord Jesus Christ had sent before him with the good-news of the Gospel (Lk. 10: 1-24). 	The holy Disciple Aristarchus, a co-worker of the holy Apostle Paul, became bishop of the Syrian city of Apameia. His name is repeatedly mentioned in the book of the Acts of the Holy Apostles (Acts 19: 29, 20: 4, 27: 2) and in the Epistles of the Apostle Paul (Col. 4: 10, Philemon 1: 24). 	The holy Disciple Pudas is mentioned in the 2nd Epistle of the Apostle Paul to Timothy (2 Tim. 4: 21). He occupied high position as a member of the Roman Senate. At his home the saint took in the First-Ranked Apostles Peter and Paul, and believing Christians gathered. His house was converted into a church, receiving the name &quot;Pastorum&quot;. In it, according to tradition, the holy Apostle Peter himself served as priest. 	The holy Disciple Trophymos hailed from the city of Edessa. His name is mentioned in the book of the Acts of the Holy Apostles (Acts 20: 4) and in the 2nd Epistle of the Apostle Paul to Timothy (2 Tim. 4: 20). He was a student and companion of the holy Apostle Paul, sharing with him all the sorrows and persecution. 	All these three holy disciples accepted a martyr&apos;s death at Rome under the emperor Nero (54-68), concurrent with that of the Apostle Paul ( c. 67). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
This honored festival of the apostles hath appeared today,/ illumining us and dispelling the darkness of sin from those who cry:// Light hath appeared and deliverance hath come!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>