<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые апостолы от 70-ти: Архипп, Филимон и Апфия"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святые апостолы от 70-ти: Архипп, Филимон и Апфия (вторая память 22 ноября) были учениками и сподвижниками святого апо- стола Павла, В послании к Филимону апостол именует святого Архиппа своим сподвижником.    Апостол Архипп был епископом города Колоссы во Фригии. Апостол Филимон был именитым гражданином того же города, и в его доме собирались христиане, чтобы совершать Богослужение. Он был также рукоположен в сан епископа апостолом Павлом и обходил фригийские города, проповедуя Евангелие. Впоследствии он был архипастырем города Газы. Святая Апфия, супруга его, принимала в своем доме странников и больных, с усердием служа им. Она была верной сотрудницей супруга в благовестии Слова Божия.     В гонение на христиан императора Нерона (54—68) святые апо- столы Архипп, Филимон и равноапостольная Апфия были пре- даны суду градоначальника Артоклиса за проповедь веры во Хри- ста. Апостол Архипп был зверски изрезан ножами. После истя- заний Филимона и Апфию по пояс закопали в землю и били кам- нями, пока святые мученики скончались. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
А҆пⷭле ст҃ы́й а҆рхї́ппе, молѝ млⷭтиваго бг҃а, да прегрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе пода́стъ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ ѕвѣздꙋ̀ вели́кꙋю тѧ̀ цр҃ковь и҆мꙋ́щи а҆рхї́ппе, чꙋде́съ твои́хъ лꙋча́ми просвѣща́ема, зове́тъ тебѣ̀: сп҃сѝ вѣ́рою почита́ющыѧ па́мѧть твою̀. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Disciples from the Seventy: Archippos, Philemon and Apthea"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Disciples from the Seventy: Archippos, Philemon and Apthea (2nd Comm. 22 November) were students and companions of the holy Apostle Paul. In the Epistle to Philemon, the Apostle Paul names Saint Archippos as his companion.  	The Disciple Archippos was bishop of the city of Colossa in Phrygia. The Disciple Philemon was an eminent citizen of this city, and in his home the Christians gathered to celebrate Divine-services. He was likewise ordained to the dignity of bishop by the Apostle Paul and he went about the cities of Phrygia, preaching the Gospel. Later on, he became archpastor of the city of Gaza. Saint Apthea, his spouse, took into her home the sick and vagrants, zealously attending to them. She was indeed a veritable co-worker to her spouse in proclaiming the Word of God.  	During the persecution against Christians under the emperor Nero (54-68), the holy Disciples Archippos and Philemon and Equal-to-the-Apostles Apthea were brought to trial by the city-governor Artocles for confessing faith in Christ. The Disciple Archippos was brutally hacked at with knives. After torture, they buried Saints Philemon and Apthea up to the waist in the ground, and stoned them until the holy martyrs died.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
O holy apostle Archippus/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
The Church, possessing thee as a great star,/ O Archippus,/ and illumined by the rays of thy miracles,/ crieth out to thee:// Save those who honor thy memory with faith!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>