<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святая мученица Акилина"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святая мученица Анилина, уроженка финикийского города Библа, пострадала при императоре Диоклитиане (284—305). Ро- дители воспитали ее в христианском благочестии. Когда девочке было всего 12 лет, Акилина убеждала сверстниц-язычниц обра- титься ко Христу. Один из слуг царского наместника Волусиана донес, что она учит своих сверстниц не почитать религию отцов. Святая отроковица твердо исповедала перед наместником свою веру во Христа и сказала, что не отречется от Него. Волусиан пытался уговорами и лаской повлиять на юную исповедницу, но, видя ее твердость, велел предать истязаниям. Святую Акилину били по лицу, а потом, обнажив, бичевали. Издеваясь, мучитель спрашивал: «Где же твой Бог? Пусть придет и отнимет тебя из моих рук». Святая отвечала: «Господь невидимо со мною, и чем больше я страдаю, тем больше Он дает мне сил и терпения». Раскаленными прутьями мученице через уши просверлили го- лову. Святая мученица упала замертво. Мучитель решил, что Девочка действительно скончалась, и приказал выбросить ее тело на съедение псам за городом. Ночью святой Акилине явился Ан- гел, коснулся ее и сказал: «Встань и будь здорова. Иди и обличи Волусиана, ибо как он сам, так и намерения его ничтожны пред Богом». Мученица, воссылая хвалу Богу, поднялась невредимой, пошла к дворцу наместника и предстала перед Волусианом. Уви- дев святую Акилину, Волусиан в испуге позвал слуг и велел сто- рожить её до утра. Утром он вынес святой Акилине смертный при- говор как волшебнице,, не повиновавшейся царским указам. Когда святую вели на казнь, она молилась и благодарила Бога, удосто- ившего ее пострадать за Его Святое Имя. В ответ на молитву послышался глас, призывавший ее в Небесные обители, и вслед за тем мученица предала дух свой Богу {\ 293). Палач боялся на- рушить приказание правителя, и уже скончавшейся отсек ей го- лову. Христиане с честью погребли тело мученицы. Позднее ее мощи были перенесены в Константинополь и положены в создан- ном в ее честь храме. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
А҆́гница твоѧ̀ ї҆и҃се а҆кѷлї́на, зове́тъ ве́лїимъ гла́сомъ: тебѐ женишѐ мо́й люблю̀, и҆ тебѐ и҆́щꙋщи страда́льчествꙋю, и҆ сраспина́юсѧ, и҆ спогреба́юсѧ кр҃ще́нїю твоемꙋ̀, и҆ страждꙋ̀ тебѐ ра́ди, ꙗ҆́кѡ да ца́рствꙋю въ тебѣ̀, и҆ ѹ҆мира́ю за тѧ̀, да и҆ живꙋ̀ съ тобо́ю: но ꙗ҆́кѡ же́ртвꙋ непоро́чнꙋю прїими́ мѧ, съ любо́вїю поже́ршꙋюсѧ тебѣ̀. тоѧ̀ мл҃твами, ꙗ҆́кѡ ми́лостивъ сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Дѣ́вства твоегѡ̀ добро́тами, пред꙽ѡчи́стивши дꙋ́шꙋ твою̀, и҆ на высотꙋ̀ мꙋче́нїемъ востекла̀ є҆сѝ а҆кѷлї́но всечестна́ѧ, любо́вїю жениха̀ твоегѡ̀ хрⷭта̀ ѹ҆ѧзви́вшисѧ, є҆мꙋ́же со а҆́гг҃лы предстои́ши веселѧ́щисѧ: съ ни́миже не преста́й молѧ́сѧ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyress Acelina"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyress Acelina, a native of the Phoenician city of Byblos, suffered under the emperor Diocletian (284-305). Her parents raised her in Christian piety. When the girl was but 12 years of age, she persuaded a pagan friend to convert to Christ. One of the servants of the imperial governor Volusian made a denunciation, that she was teaching her peers not to honour the religion of their fathers. The girl firmly confessed her faith in Christ in front of the governor and said, that she would not renounce Him. Volusian tried by persuasion and by flattery to sway the young confessor, but seeing her assuredness, he then gave orders to hand her over for torture. They struck her upon the face, and then, having been stripped they whipped her. The torturer mockingly asked: &quot;Where then is thy God? Let Him come and take thee out of my hands&quot;. The saint answered: &quot;The Lord is invisibly here together with me, and the more I suffer, all the more shalt He give me strength and endurance&quot;. 	With red-hot rods they drilled at the head of the martyress at the ears. The holy martyress fell down as though dead. The torturer decided that the girl had actually died, and he gave orders to throw out her body outside the city for devouring by dogs. By night an holy Angel appeared to Saint Acelina, roused her and said: &quot;Arise and be well. Go and denounce Volusian, that he himself and his intent are thus come to naught before God&quot;. The martyress, offering up praise to God, and having been restored unharmed, went to the court of the governor and stood before Volusian. Seeing Saint Acelina, Volusian in fright called for his servants and ordered them to keep watch over her until morning. In the morning he delivered a death sentence against Saint Acelina on the grounds of being a sorceress and not obeying the imperial decrees. When they led the saint to execution, she prayed and gave thanks to God, for having granted her to suffer for His Holy Name. A voice was heard in answer to her prayer, summoning her to the Heavenly Kingdom, after which the martyress gave up her spirit to God (+ 293). The executioner feared to disobey the orders of the governor, and although already dead, he cut off her head. Christians piously buried the body of the martyress. Later on, her relics were taken to Constantinople and placed within a church named for her.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Thy ewe-lamb Aquilina crieth out to Thee with a loud voice, O Jesus:/ "I love Thee, O my Bridegroom,/ and, seeking Thee, I pass through many struggles:/ I am crucified and buried with Thee in Thy baptism,/ and suffer for Thy sake, that I may reign with Thee;/ I die for Thee that I might live with Thee./ As an unblemished sacrifice accept me,/ who sacrifice myself with love for Thee// By her supplications save Thou our souls, in that Thou art merciful.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Having utterly purified thy soul with the beauties of thy virginity/ and attained the heights by martyrdom, O most honored Aquilina,/ wounded with the love of Christ thy Bridegroom,/ thou standest before Him with the angels in gladness.// With them cease thou never to pray for us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>