<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Василий, епископ Амасийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Священномученик Василий, епископ Амасийский, жил в нача- ле IV века в Понтийском городе Амасии. Он поддерживал и уте- шал христиан, страдавших от гонений язычников. В то время Восточной частью Римской империи правил Ликиний (312—324), зять святого равноапостольного царя Константина Великого (306—337; память 21 мая). Ликиний лицемерно подписал его «Указ о веротерпимости» (313), который разрешал свободное ис- поведание христианства,, но в душе ненавидел христиан и продол- жал их преследовать, возвратившись к язычеству.    Ликиний воспылал страстью к служанке своей жены Констан- ции, праведной деве Глафире. Святая дева рассказала об этом царице и просила защиты. Переодев праведную Глафиру в муж- ское платье и снабдив деньгами, царица Констанция удалила ее из города в сопровождении преданных слуг. Императору сказали, что служанка сошла с ума и лежит при смерти. Праведная Гла- фира по пути в Армению остановилась в городе Амасии, где местный епископ, святитель Василий, дал ей приют.     В то время святитель строил в городе храм. Праведная Глафи- ра передала на его постройку все деньги, полученные от Кон- станции, и в письме к ней просила прислать еще средства на окончание храма. Царица исполнила ее просьбу. Но письмо пра- ведной Глафиры попало к императору. Разгневанный Ликиний потребовал от правителя Амасии выслать к нему святителя и служанку. Праведная Глафира скончалась ( ] 322), прежде чем                                             •• приказ дошел до Амасии. Святителя Василия направили к импе- ратору. За ним последовали два диакона, Парфений и Фе- стим, которые поселились вблизи темницы, куда заключили свя- тителя.     Благочестивый христианин Елпидифор подкупил тюремщиков к каждую ночь вместе с Парфением и Фестимом посещал святите- ля. Накануне дня суда святитель как обычно пел псалмы и слова «аще вселюся в последних моря и тамо рука Твоя наставит мя и удержит мя десница Твоя» (Пс. 138, 9—10) — трижды пропел со слезами. Диаконы усомнились, не испугался ли святитель бу- дущих мук, но он успокоил их.     На суде святитель Василий решительно отверг предложение императора стать верховным жрецом и был приговорен к смерти. Елпидифор деньгами задобрил воинов, и они позволили святите- лю помолиться и поговорить с друзьями перед казнью. После этого святитель сказал палачу: «Друг, делай, что тебе приказа- но»,— и спокойно встал под удар меча.     Когда мученик был обезглавлен,, Елпидифор пытался выку- пить у воинов его останки. Но воины опасались императора и бросили тело и главу святителя в море. После этого Елпидифору трижды во сне предстал Ангел Божий со словами: «Епископ Ва- силий в Синопе и ждет вас». Повинуясь этому зову, Елпидифор и диаконы отплыли в Синоп и там попросили рыбаков закинуть  сети. Когда закинули сеть «на счастье» диаконов Фестима и Пар-  фения, ничего не поймали. Тогда Елпидифор объявил, что он  просит закинуть сеть во Имя Бога, Которому он поклоняется.  На этот раз сеть вынесла тело святителя Василия. Голова при-  росла к нему, и только шрам на шее указывал на след меча.  Мощи святителя Василия были перевезены в Амасию и погребе-  ны в построенном им храме. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Царе́во повелѣ́нїе преѡби́дѣвъ, црⷭтво нбⷭное полꙋчи́лъ є҆сѝ васї́лїе, въ не́мже ликꙋ́ѧ, помина́й на́съ чтꙋ́щихъ па́мѧть твою̀ сщ҃енномч҃нче. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="riestMartyr Basil, Bishop of Amasea"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The PriestMartyr Basil, Bishop of Amasea, lived at the beginning of the IV Century in the Pontine city of Amasea. He encouraged and comforted the Christians, suffering persecution by the pagans. During this time the Eastern part of the Roman empire was ruled by Licinius (312-324), a relative by marriage to the holy Equal-to-the-Apostles emperor Constantine the Great (306-337, Comm. 21 May). Licinius deceitfully undersigned Constantine&apos;s &quot;Edict of Religious Toleration&quot; (313), which permitted the freely open confession of Christianity, but at heart he hated Christians and continued to persecute them to return to paganism. 	Licinius burned with passion for a maid-servant of his wife Constancia, -- the Righteous Virgin Galphyra. The holy maid reported about this to the empress and sought her intercession. Having dressed her in men&apos;s attire and provided her with money, the empress Constancia sent her away from the city in the company of a devoted servant. They told the emperor, that the maid-servant had gone mad and lay near death. Righteous Glaphyra on the road to Armenia remained in the city of Amasea, where the local bishop, Saint Basil, gave her shelter. 	At this time the saint was building a church in the city. Righteous Glaphyra for its construction gave over all the money that she had received from Constancia, and in a letter to the empress she besought her to send additional funds to complete the church. The empress fulfilled her request. But the letter of Righteous Galphyra fell into the hands of the emperor. The enraged Licinius demanded the governor of Amasea to send him the sainted-hierarch and the maid-servant. Righteous Galphyra died (+ 322) before the edict arrived in Amasea. They dispatched Saint Basil to the emperor. Two deacons, Parthenias and Thestimos, followed after him and lodged near the prison where they locked up the saint. 	The pious Christian Elpidyphoros bribed the jailer and each night together with Parthenias and Thestimos he visited the saint. On the eve of the trial day of the saint he sang psalms and the words &quot;if I be at the very depths of the sea, even there wilt Thy hand guide me and Thine right hand hold me&quot; (Ps. 138 [139]: 9-10) -- and thrice he broke down into tears. The deacons were apprehensive that the saint would be in distress over the coming torments, but he calmed them. 	At the trial Saint Basil resolutely refused the suggestion of the emperor to become a pagan high-priest, and therefore he was sentenced to death. Elpidyphoros got to the soldiers with money, and they allowed the saint to pray and to speak with his friends before the execution. After this, the saint said to the executioner: &quot;Friend, do what thou art ordered to&quot;, -- and calmly he bent beneathe the blow of the sword.  	When the martyr had been beheaded, Elpidyphoros tried to ransom his remains from the soldiers. But the soldiers were afraid of the emperor and they threw the body and head of the saint into the sea. After this, three times in a dream an Angel of God appeared before Elpidyphoros with the words: &quot;Bishop Basil is in Sinope and doth await you&quot;. Heeding this call, Elpidyphoros and the deacons sailed to Sinope and there they hired fishermen to lower their nets. When they lowered the net &quot;on the suggestion&quot; of the deacons Thestimos and Parthenias, they came up with nothing. Thereupon Elpidyphoros declared, that he would ask them to lower the net in the Name of the God, Whom he did worship. This time the net brought up the body of Saint Basil. The head had come back together with it, and only the gash on the neck indicated the strike of the sword. The relics of Saint Basil were conveyed to Amasea and buried in the church built by him.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Having spurned the imperial edict, O Basil,/ thou didst receive the kingdom of heaven;/ and joining the chorus therein,/ be thou mindful of us// who honor thy memory, O Hieromartyr.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>
