<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Воспоминание чуда святой Евфимии Всехвальной"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Воспоминание чуда святой Евфимии Всехвальной. Святая ве- ликомученица Евфимия (сведения о ней помещены 16 сентября) совершила мученический подвиг в городе Халкидоне в 304 году, во время гонения, воздвигнутого на христиан императором Ди- оклитианом (284—305). Полтора столетия спустя, когда Христи- анская Церковь стала господствующей в Римской империи, Бог сподобил Всехвальную Евфимию вновь явиться особенной свиде- тельницей и исповедницей чистоты православного учения. В 451 году в городе Халкидоне, в церкви, где почивали про- славленные чудесами мощи святой великомученицы Евфимии, происходили заседания IV Вселенского Собора (сведения о нем 16 июля). Собор был созван для определения точной формулиров- ки догмата Православной Церкви о природе Богочеловека Иисуса Христа, что было необходимо ввиду широко распространившейся ереси монофизитов, которые, вопреки православному учению о двух природах Иисуса Христа — Божественной и человеческой, ложно утверждали в Нем одну природу — Божественную, внося в Церковь смуту и раздоры. На Соборе присутствовали 630 пред- ставителей от всех Поместных Христианских Церквей. Со стороны православных в соборных деяниях принимали участие святитель Анатолий, Патриарх Константинопольский (память 3 июля), свя- титель Ювеналий, Патриарх Иерусалимский (память 2 июля), и представители святителя Льва, папы Римского (память 18 фев- раля). Монофизиты присутствовали в большом количестве во гла- ве с Диоскором, патриархом Александрийским, и Константино- польским архимандритом Евтихием. После долгих прений стороны так и не смогли придти к соглас- ному решению. Тогда святой Патриарх Константинопольский Анатолий пред- ложил Собору предоставить решение церковного спора Духу Свя- тому, чрез Его несомненную носительницу святую Евфимию Все- хвальную, у чудотворных мощей которой происходили соборные прения. Православные святители и их противники написали свое исповедание веры на отдельных свитках и запечатали своими печатями. Открыли гробницу святой великомученицы Евфимии и оба свитка положили на ее груди. Потом, в присутствии импера- тора Маркиана (450—457), участники Собора закрыли гробницу, приложили к ней императорскую печать и поставили стражу на три дня. В эти дни обе стороны наложили на себя строгий пост и совершали усиленные молитвы. Через три дня Патриарх и импе- ратор в присутствии всего Собора открыли ковчег с мощами: сви- ток с Православным исповеданием святая Евфимия держала в правой руке, а свиток еретический лежал у ее ног. Святая Евфи- мия, как живая, подняла руку и подала свиток Патриарху. После этого чуда многие из уклонившихся приняли Православное испо- ведание, а упорствовавшие в ереси были преданы соборному осуждению и отлучению. В VII столетии после нашествия персов мощи святой Евфимии были перенесены из Халкидона в Константинополь, во вновь построенную церковь, посвященную ее имени. Через много лет в период иконоборческой ереси ковчег с мощами святой по повеле- нию императора-иконоборца Льва Исавра (716—741) был брошен в море. Из моря ковчег был взят братьями-корабельщиками Сергием и Сергоном, которые передали его местному епископу. Святитель повелел хранить святые мощи тайно, под спудом, так как иконоборческая ересь продолжала свирепствовать, но все же над мощами была сооружена небольшая церковь, а на ковчег была положена доска с надписью, поясняющей, чьи мощи покоят- ся в нем. Когда иконоборческая ересь была окончательно осужде- на на святом Седьмом Вселенском Соборе (787 г.), при святителе Тарасии, Патриархе Константинопольском (784—806), и при им- ператоре Константине VI (780—797) и матери его святой Ирине (797—802) мощи святой великомученицы Евфнмии Все- хвальной были вновь торжественно перенесены в Константи- нополь. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
А҆́гница твоѧ̀ ї҆и҃се, є҆ѵѳи́мїа, зове́тъ ве́лїимъ гла́сомъ: тебѐ женишѐ мо́й люблю̀, и҆ тебѐ и҆́щꙋщи страда́льчествꙋю, и҆ сраспина́юсѧ, и҆ спогреба́юсѧ кр҃ще́нїю твоемꙋ̀, и҆ страждꙋ̀ тебѐ ра́ди, ꙗ҆́кѡ да ца́рствꙋю въ тебѣ̀, и҆ ѹ҆мира́ю за тѧ̀, да и҆ живꙋ̀ съ тобо́ю: но ꙗ҆́кѡ же́ртвꙋ непоро́чнꙋю прїими́ мѧ, съ любо́вїю поже́ршꙋюсѧ тебѣ̀. тоѧ̀ мл҃твами, ꙗ҆́кѡ ми́лостивъ сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Жениха̀ твоего̀ хрⷭта̀ возлюби́вши, и҆ свѣщꙋ̀ твою̀ свѣ́тлꙋ ѹ҆гото́вльши, добродѣ́тельми возсїѧ́вши, всехва́льнаѧ є҆ѵѳи́мїе: тѣ́мъ возшла̀ є҆сѝ съ ни́мъ на бра́къ, вѣне́цъ страда́нїѧ ѿ негѡ̀ прїе́мши: но ѿ бѣ́дъ и҆зба́ви на́съ, чтꙋ́щихъ вѣ́рою па́мѧть твою̀. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
По́двиги во страда́льчествѣ, по́двиги въ вѣ́рѣ положи́ла є҆сѝ те́плѣ за хрⷭта̀ жениха̀ твоего̀: но и҆ ны́нѣ ꙗ҆́коже є҆́рєси, и҆ врагѡ́въ шата́нїе под꙽ но́ги правосла́вныхъ царе́й покори́ти молѝ бцⷣею, ꙗ҆́же ѿ шестисѡ́тъ три́десѧти бг҃оно́сныхъ ѻ҆тє́цъ предѣ́лъ прїе́мшаѧ, и҆ хранѧ́щаѧ всехва́льнаѧ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Remembrance of the Miracle of Saint Euphemia the All-Praiseworthy"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The holy GreatMartyress Euphemia (the account about her is located under 16 September) suffered martyrdom in the city of Chalcedon in the year 304, during the time of the persecution against Christians by the emperor Diocletian (284-305). One and an half centuries later, -- at a time when the Christian Church had become victorious within the Roman empire, God deigned that Euphemia the All-Praiseworthy should again be an especial witness and confessor of the purity of the Orthodox teaching.  	In the year 451 in the city of Chalcedon, in the very church wherein rested the glorified relics of the holy GreatMartyress Euphemia -- there took place the sessions of the Fourth OEcumenical Council (the account about it is under 16 July). The Council was convened for determining the precise dogmatic formulae of the Orthodox Church concerning the nature-composition of the God-Man Jesus Christ. This had been necessitated because of the widely-dispersed heresy of the Monophysites [&quot;mono-phusis&quot; meaning &quot;one nature&quot;], who opposed the Orthodox teaching about the two natures in Jesus Christ -- the Divine and the Human natures [but in one Divine Person as Son of God within the Holy Trinity of three Divine Persons]. The Monophysites falsely affirmed that within Christ was only one nature -- the Divine [i.e. that Jesus is God but not man, bynature], causing discord and unrest within the Church. At the Council were present 630 representatives from all the Local Christian Churches. On the side of the Orthodox in the conciliar deliberations there participated Sainted Anatolios, Patriarch of Constantinople (Comm. 3 July), Sainted Juvenalios, Patriarch of Jerusalem (Comm. 2 July), and representatives of Sainted Leo, Pope of Rome (Comm. 18 February). The Monophysites were present in large numbers, headed by Dioscoros, the Alexandrian patriarch, and the Constantinople archimandrite Eutykhios.  	After prolonged discussions the two sides could not come to a decisive agreement. 	The holy Patriarch of Constantinople Anatolios thereupon proposed that the Council submit the decision of the Church dispute to the Holy Spirit, through His undoubted bearer Saint Euphemia the All-Praiseworthy, whose wonderworking relics had been discovered during the Council&apos;s discussions. The Orthodox hierarchs and their opponents wrote down their confessions of faith on separate scrolls and sealed them with their seals. They opened the tomb of the holy GreatMartyress Euphemia and placed both scrolls upon her bosom. Then, in the presence of the emperor Marcian (450-457), the participants of the Council sealed the tomb, putting on it the imperial seal and setting a guard to watch over it for three days. During these days both sides imposed upon themselves strict fast and made intense prayer. After three days the patriarch and the emperor in the presence of the Council opened the tomb with its relics: the scroll with the Orthodox confession was held by Saint Euphemia in her right hand, and the scroll of the heretics lay at her feet. Saint Euphemia, as though alive, raised her hand and gave the scroll to the patriarch. After this miracle many of the hesitant accepted the Orthodox confession, while those remaining obstinant in the heresy were consigned to the Council&apos;s condemnation and excommunication. 	After an invasion by the Persians during the VII Century, the relics of Saint Euphemia were transferred from Chalcedon to Constantinople, into a newly built church dedicated in her name. Many years later, during the period of the Iconoclast heresy, the reliquary with the relics of the saint was cast into the sea -- by order of the Iconoclast emperor Leo the Isaurian (716-741). The reliquary was rescued from the sea by the ship-owning brothers Sergios and Sergonos, who gave it over to the local bishop. The holy bishop ordered that the relics be preserved in secret, beneathe a crypt, since the Iconoclast heresy was continuing to rage. A small church was built over the relics, and over the reliquary was put a board with an inscription stating whose relics rested therein. When the Iconoclast heresy was finally condemned at the holy Seventh OEcumenical Council (in the year 787), -- during the time of Sainted Tarasios, Patriarch of Constantinople (784-806) and the emperor Constantine VI (780-797) and his mother Saint Irene (797-802), -- the relics of the holy GreatMartyress Euphemia were once again solemnly transferred to Constantinople.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Thy ewe-lamb Euphemia crieth out to Thee with a loud voice, O Jesus:/ "I love Thee, O my Bridegroom,/ and, seeking Thee, I pass through many struggles:/ I am crucified and buried with Thee in Thy baptism,/ and suffer for Thy sake, that I may reign with Thee;/ I die for Thee that I might live with Thee./ As an unblemished sacrifice accept me,/ who sacrifice myself with love for Thee// By her supplications save Thou our souls, in that Thou art merciful.
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
	Needs English translation
	</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
Feats in thy contest and struggles in the Faith/ didst thou fervently set for thyself for thy Bridegroom;/ and now through the Theotokos/ pray that the audacity of the foe and heresies/ be subdued beneath the feet of Orthodox hierarchs,// O all-praised one who accepted and preserved the definition of the six hundred and thirty God-bearing fathers.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>