<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Нил Столобенский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Преподобный Нил Столобенский преставился 7 декабря 1554 го- да (сведения о житии помещены в этот день).    Много лет спустя на остров озера Селигер, где подвизался свя- той подвижник, пришел иеромонах Герман и вслед за ним холмо- горец, странник Борис. Вместе они поселились на острове и пост- роили храм в честь Богоявления с приделом во имя святого блаженного Василия, Московского чудотворца. Со временем на месте подвигов преподобного Нила возникла обитель, названная его именем. Иноками Оршина монастыря была написана икона преподобного Нила, на месте погребения святого стали совершать- ся чудесные исцеления больных. Впоследствии живший в обители святитель Нектарий, архиепископ Сибирский и Тобольский, решил построить каменный храм вместо прежнего, деревянного. Во вре- мя закладки фундамента земля осыпалась и открылись нетленные мощи преподобного Нила. Обретение мощей произошло 27 мая 1667 года, одновременно было установлено празднование препо- добному в честь этого события. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ свѣти́льникъ всесвѣ́телъ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ во ѻ҆́стровѣ селиге́ра є҆́зера, прпⷣбне ѻ҆́тче нї́ле: ты́ бо крⷭтъ хрⷭто́въ ѿ ю҆́ности своеѧ̀ на ра́мо взе́мъ, ѹ҆се́рднѡ томꙋ̀ послѣ́довалъ є҆сѝ, чистото́ю бг҃ови прибли́живсѧ, ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже и҆ чꙋде́съ дарова́нїемъ ѡ҆богати́лсѧ є҆сѝ. тѣ́мъ и҆ мы̀ притека́юще къ ра́цѣ моще́й твои́хъ, ѹ҆ми́льнѡ глаго́лемъ: ѻ҆́тче прпⷣбне, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Ѻ҆те́чества, прпⷣбне, ѹ҆дали́всѧ, въ пꙋсты́ню всели́лсѧ є҆сѝ, и҆ на ѻ҆́стровъ селиге́ра є҆́зера возше́дъ, же́стоко житїѐ показа́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ мно́гихъ добродѣ́тельми ѹ҆диви́въ, дарова҄нїѧ чꙋде́съ ѿ хрⷭта̀ прїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ. помина́й на́съ чтꙋ́щихъ па́мѧть твою̀, да зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ, нї́ле ѻ҆́тче на́шъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Nil of Stolobensk"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Nil of Stolobensk reposed on 7 December 1554 (the account about his life is located under this day). 	Many years afterwards, on the Island of Lake Seliger, where the holy ascetic had asceticised, there came the priest-monk German and immediately after him the hill-dweller and wanderer Boris. They settled together on the island and built a church in honour of the Theophany, with a chapel in the name of Saint Vasilii (Basil) the Moscow Wonderworker. At this site where the Monk Nil had asceticised there in time grew up a monastery, named after him. An icon of the Monk Nil was written by the monks of the Orshin monastery, and numerous miracles of healings of the sick began to occur at the gravesite of the saint. Later at the monastery lived Sainted Nektarii, Archbishop of Sibirsk and Tobol&apos;sk, and he decided to build a stone church to replace the former wooden one. During the time of the laying of the foundations, the earth crumbled away and revealed the incorrupt relics of the Monk Nil. The Uncovering of the Relics occurred on 27 May 1667, and simultaneously with this was established a feastday to the monk in honour of the event.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Need English translation
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Need English translation
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>