<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Празднество Божией Матери в честь Ее святой иконы Владимирской"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Празднество Божией Матери в честь Ее святой иконы Влади- мирской совершается в благодарение за избавление Москвы от нашествия хана Ахмата. В 1480 году при великом князе Иоанне III Васильевиче (1462—-1505) хан Золотой Орды Ахмат с громадными полчищами подошел уже к реке Угре, которую называют «поя- сом Богоматери», охраняющим Московские владения. Целый день войска хана и Московского князя стояли друг против друга, не приступая к решительным действиям — «стояние на Угре». Вся Москва молилась своей Заступнице Пресвятой Богородице о спа- сении православной столицы. Митрополит Геронтий (1473—1489) и духовник князя, архиепископ Ростовский Вассиан, молитвой, благословением и советом подкрепляли русские войска. Митропо- лит писал князю соборное послание, в котором призывал его мужественно стоять против врага, уповая на помощь Матери Божией. Пресвятая Богородица заступилась за Землю русскую. Князь приказал своим войскам отступать от Угры, желая дождаться перехода татар, враги же решили, что русские заманивают их в засаду, и тоже стали отступать, сначала медленно, а ночью побе- жали, гонимые страхом. В благодарность за освобождение России от татар и был установлен праздник в честь Божией Матери. (Сведения о Владимирской иконе помещены 26 августа.) 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Дне́сь свѣ́тлѡ красꙋ́етсѧ сла́внѣйшїй гра́дъ москва̀, ꙗ҆́кѡ зарю̀ со́лнечнꙋю воспрїе́мши влⷣчце, чꙋдотво́рнꙋю твою̀ ї҆кѡ́нꙋ, къ не́йже ны́нѣ мы̀ притека́юще, и҆ молѧ́щесѧ тебѣ̀, взыва́емъ си́це: пречꙋ́днаѧ влⷣчце бцⷣе, моли́сѧ и҆з꙽ тебѐ воплоще́нномꙋ хрⷭтꙋ̀ бг҃ꙋ на́шемꙋ, да и҆зба́витъ гра́дъ се́й, и҆ всѧ҄ гра́ды и҆ страны҄ хрїстїа҄нскїѧ невреди́мы ѿ всѣ́хъ навѣ҄тъ вра́жїихъ, и҆ сп҃се́тъ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ ꙗ҆́кѡ милосе́рдъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Взбра́нной воево́дѣ побѣди́тєльнаѧ, ꙗ҆́кѡ и҆зба́вльшесѧ ѿ ѕлы́хъ прише́ствїемъ твоегѡ̀ честна́гѡ ѡ҆́браза, влⷣчце бцⷣе, свѣ́тлѡ сотворѧ́емъ празднество̀ срѣ́тенїѧ твоегѡ̀, и҆ ѻ҆бы́чнѡ зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ невѣ́сто неневѣ́стнаѧ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Feast of the Mother of God in honour of Her Holy Vladimir Icon"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Feast of the Mother of God in honour of Her Holy Vladimir Icon is celebrated in thanksgiving for the deliverance of Moscow from an invasion of khan Akhmat. In 1480 during the time of GreatPrince Ivan III Vasil&apos;evich (1462-1505), khan Akhmat of the Golden Horde approached with a vast host up to the River Ugra, which those guarding the Moscow domain called &quot;the Belt (Poyas) of the Mother of God&quot;. For an entire day the army of the khan and that of the Moscow prince stood opposite each other, not making the decision to act -- &quot;the standing at the Ugra&quot;. All Moscow prayed to its Patroness the MostHoly Mother of God for the safety of the Orthodox capital. Metropolitan Gerontii (1473-1489) and the father-confessor of the prince, Archbishop Vassion of Rostov, praying, strengthened the Russian army with blessing and counsel. The metropolitan wrote the prince a cathedral missive, in which he called on him to stand bravely against the enemy, trusting on the help of the Mother of God. 	The MostHoly Mother of God interceded for the Russian land. The prince commanded his army to fall back from the Ugra, hoping to await the passing over of the Tatars; the enemy decided, however, that the Russians were luring them into a trap, and they thus began to fall back, at first slowly, but by night they fled, driven by fear. In thanksgiving for the deliverance of Russia from the Tatars, this feast was established in honour of the Mother of God. (The account about the Vladimir Icon is located under 26August).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Today the most glorious city of Moscow is adorned, having received thy wonder-working icon like the radiance of the sun; and we, hastening to it and entreating thee, O Mistress, do thus cry out: O all-wondrous Mistress Theotokos, entreat Christ our God, Who became incarnate through thee, that He deliver this city, and all cities and lands where Christians dwell, unharmed by all the assaults of the enemy, and save thou our souls, in that thou art compassionate.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
As ones delivered from evils by the arrival of thy precious image, O Mistress Theotokos, do we splendidly chant hymns of victory to thee, the chosen leader, on the feast of thy meeting, and we cry to thee as is our wont: Rejoice, O Bride unwedded!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>