<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Девять святых мучеников Кизических"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Девять святых мучеников Кизических. Город Кизик находится в Малой Азии на берегу Дарданельского пролива. Христианство в нем начало распространяться еще со времен проповеди святого апостола Павла (память 29 июня). Но гонения язычников при- вели к тому, что одни из христиан убежали из города, другие же держали веру Христову в тайне. Поэтому в конце III века Кизик был в значительной мере языческим, хотя там и была христиан- ская церковь. Такое положение в городе огорчало истинных хри- стиан, стремившихся утвердить Христову веру. К ним принадле- жали и 9 святых мучеников — Феогнид, Руф, Антипатр, Феостих, Артема,, Магн, Феодот, Фавмасий и Филимон. Они происходили из разных местностей, были разного возраста: и юные, как святой Антипатр, и престарелые, как святой Руф, занимали разное поло- жение в обществе: среди них были и воины, и поселяне, и го- рожане, и клирики. Но всех их объединяла вера во Христа и горячее стремление к распространению и укреплению Истинной веры.    Оказавшись в городе Кизике, святые дерзновенно исповедовали Христа и безбоязненно обличали языческое нечестие. Их схватили и представили на суд правителю города. В течение нескольких дней их пытали, заключали в темницу и снова выводили из нее, обещая свободу за отречение от Христа. Но доблестные воины Христовы продолжали славить Имя Христово. Все девять мучени- ков были усечены мечом ( } ок. 284—292), и тела их погребли близ                         •• города.    Когда в 324 году Восточной половиной империи стал править святой Константин Великий (306—337; память 21 мая) и прекра- тились гонения на христиан, кизические христиане извлекли из земли нетленные тела 9-ти мучеников и положили их в храме, построенном в их честь.    От святых мощей происходили различные чудеса: исцелялись больные, приходили в разум безумные. Вера Христова утвержда- лась в городе заступлением святых мучеников, многие из язычни- ков обращались в христианство.    Когда воцарился Юлиан Отступник (361—363), язычники Ки- зика обратились к нему с жалобой на христиан за разорение язы- ческих храмов. Юлиан приказал восстановить языческие храмы и заключить в темницу епископа Елевсия. После гибели Юлиана епископ Елевсий получил свободу, и снова в Кизике воссиял свет Христовой веры под покровительством святых мучеников.     В России недалеко от города Казани был устроен монастырь в честь 9-ти мучеников Кизических иеродиаконом Стефаном, кото- рый принес с собой из Палестины часть мощей святых. Этот мо- настырь был основан в уповании избавления их предстательством и молитвами от различных недугов и болезней, особенно горячки, свирепствовавшей в Казани в 1687 году, «ибо, — пишет святитель Димитрий Ростовский (+1709; память 21 сентября), автор службы 9-ти мученикам, — этим святым далась обильная благодать ко прогнанию трясавичных болезней». Святитель Димитрий также описал страдания святых мучеников и составил слово на день их памяти. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Тве́рдый и҆ всесвѣ́тлый ли́къ мч҃нкъ девѧтѝ, трисо́лнечнагѡ бж҃ества̀ и҆сповѣ҄дницы, на сꙋди́щи томꙋ̀ нача́льнѡ взыва́хꙋ: кро́вь и҆ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ съ тѣлесы̀, ꙗ҆́кѡ непоро́чнꙋю же́ртвꙋ прино́симъ тебѣ̀ влⷣко: въ ли́цѣхъ нбⷭныхъ твои́хъ сопричтѝ, ꙗ҆́кѡ бг҃ъ млⷭтивый. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Nine Holy Martyrs of Kyzika"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Nine Holy Martyrs of Kyzika: The city of Kyzika is located in Asia Minor at the coast of the Dardenelles (Hellespont) Straits. Christianity there began to spread about already during the time of the preaching of the Apostle Paul (Comm. 29 June). But under the times of persecutions by the pagans events came to this -- that some of the Christians fled the city, while others kept their faith in Christ in secret. Therefore by the time of the end of the III Century Kyzika was still basically a pagan city, although there was also a Christian church there. The situation in the city distressed true Christians, who sought to uphold the Christian faith. From there were also the Nine holy Martyrs: Theognides, Ruphos, Antipater, Theostikhos, Artemon, Magnos, Theodotos, Thaumasios and Philemon. They hailed from various places, and were of different ages: both the young like Saint Antipater, and the very old like Saint Ruphos, and they came from various positions in society: among them were soldiers, countryfolk and city-people, and clergy. But all of them declared their faith in Christ and were all the more intense in their yearning for the spread and strengthening of the True Faith. 	Having shown up in the city of Kyzika, the saints boldly confessed Christ and fearlessly denounced the pagan impiety. They were arrested and brought to trial before the city governor. Over the course of several days they were tortured, locked up in prison and again led out from it, and promised their freedom for a renunciation of Christ. But the valiant martyrs of Christ continued to glorify the Name of Christ. All nine martyrs were beheaded by the sword (+ c. 284-292), and their bodies buried nearby the city.  	In the year 324, -- when the Eastern half of the Roman empire came under the rule of Saint Constantine the Great (306-337, Comm. 21 May), and the persecutions against Christians ended, the Kyzika Christians removed the undecayed bodies of the 9 martyrs from the ground and placed them in a church, built in their honour.  	Various miracles occurred from the holy relics: the sick were healed, and the mentally aberrant brought to their senses. The faith of Christ grew within the city through the intercession of the holy martyrs, and many of the pagans were converted to Christianity. 	When Julian the Apostate (361-363) came to rule, the pagans of Kyzika turned to him with a complaint against the Christians for the destruction of pagan temples. Julian gave orders to rebuild the pagan temples and to lock up in prison bishop Eleusios. Bishop Eleusios was set free after the death of Julian, and the light of the Christian faith shined anew through the assist of the holy martyrs.  	In Russia not far from the city of Kazan was built a monastery in honour of the Nine Martyrs of Kyzika. It was built by the monk-deacon Stefan, who brought with him from Palestine part of the relics of the saints. This monastery was built in the hope of deliverance through their intercession and prayers from various infirmities and ills, particularly the fever which raged through Kazan in the year 1687, &quot;since, -- writes Sainted Dimitrii of Rostov (+ 1709, Comm. 21 September), the compiler of the service to the 9 Martyrs, -- by these saints was given abundant grace for the dispelling of feverish and trembling sicknesses&quot;. Saint Dimitrii likewise described the sufferings of the holy martyrs and compiled a sermon on the day of their memory.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
The steadfast and most splendid choir of the nine martyrs,/ who confessed the three-Sunned Godhead,/ cried out to Him at the tribunal:/ "O Master, we offer our blood, souls and bodies to thee as an unblemished sacrifice!// Number us among Thy heavenly choir, in that Thou art our merciful God!"
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>