<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Virgin Martyrs Cyriaca and Theotima of Nicomedia († 311)" Short="Virgin Martyrs"/>
<SERVICE Type="0"/><LIFE Id="dunbar" Copyright="Dunbar, Agnes B.C. A dictionary of saintly women, Volume 1. (Bell, 1904) pg 216">
&lt;p&gt;St. Cyriaca, in Africa, with five other holy virgins, one of whom was Theotima, sister of Philetærus. Cyriaca was burnt, and Theotima was slain with a sword.  When Diocletian was in Nicomedia, some time after the publication of his edict for the extermination of Christianity, he was told of a Christian who worshipped God openly with impunity. He was very angry, and ordered him to be brought before him. He had a very white skin and golden beard, and the Emperor was so struck by his youth, beauty, and gentleness, that he thought he was a god, and afterwards tried to persuade him to renounce his religion and accept honours among the heathen. Philetærus rebuked him, and wrought a miracle in the name of Jesus Christ, which made Diocletian again say that Philetærus was one of the gods. When he had seen some more miracles he ordered Philetærus to be set at liberty. Soon afterwards Diocletian died, but the persecution was continued under Maximian, and Philetærus was brought before him as an irrepressible Christian. Hearing that he had a sister younger and more beautiful than himself, who was hiding among the mountains with other Christian virgins, Maximian ordered them all to be brought to him, and offered them the greatest honours, promising to treat them as his daughters on condition that they should sacrifice to his gods. Theotima answered, “What honour can you (yourself worthy of no honour) confer on us, who are servants of the true God?” The Emperor commanded those that stood by to strike her on the face. Whereupon Cyriaca told him he ought to be ashamed of his brutality. Maximian then had Cyriaca beaten until she was quite exhausted.  As Philetærus prayed that she might have strength and courage to undergo these sufferings for her Master”s sake, she revived. Maximian ordered her to be tortured in many cruel ways, and finally burnt. Philetærus and the six surviving virgins were condemned to hard labour in the island of Prceconesum. On the journey the women entreated Aristides, the captain of their guard, to have their fetters taken off, promising to make no attempt to escape, and saying that the fatigue was greater than they could bear. He hesitated to comply with their request, and, when they had gone a little further, the holy maidens suddenly disappeared from before his eyes, and were never seen or heard of more. St. Philetærus, after many miracles and sufferings, received the crown of martyrdom. R.M. AA.SS.&lt;/p&gt;</LIFE></SAINT>
