<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Repose of the Great Prince Alexander Nevsky, tonsured Alexei, Wonderworker of All Russia († 1263)" Short="St. Alexander Nevsky"/>
<SERVICE Type="3"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman’s Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
&lt;p&gt; The Holy Noble Born Prince Alexander Nevsky (in monastic-schema Alexei) died on the return journey from the Horde at Gorodtsa on the Volga, on November 14&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 1263, and on November 23&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt;(under this day is located the account about him) in 1263 he was buried in the Cathedral Church of the Nativity Monastery in the city of Vladimir (there is set up there now a memorial to the holy prince; yet another memorial is set up in the city of Pereslavl′-Zalessk). Veneration of the noble born prince started right at his burial, whereof was a remarkable miracle: the saint himself extended his hand for the absolving prayer. Great Prince John Ioannovich (1353-1359) in his spiritual testament written in the year 1356, left to his son Demetrius (1363-1389), the future victor of the Battle of Kulikovo, “an icon of Saint Alexander.” The undecayed relics of the noble born prince were opened, on account of a vision, before the Kulikovo Battle—in the year 1380, and then were set forth for local feast-celebration. For the prayers of the holy prince, glorified by defence of the Fatherland, Russian commanders resorted to in all the following times. On August 30&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 1721, Peter I, after a lengthy and exhausting war with the Swedes, concluded the Treaty of Nystad. This day was decided upon to hallow by the transfer of the relics of the Noble Born Prince Alexander Nevsky from Vladimir to the new northern capital, Peterburg, arranged on the banks of the Neva. Withdrawn from Vladimir on August 11&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 1723, the holy relics were greeted at Shlissel′burg on September 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; of that year and remained there until 1724, when on August 30&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; they were placed in the Trinity Cathedral of the Alexander Nevsky Lavra (Monastery), where now also they rest. By an edict (ukaz)  on September 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt;, 1724 there was established a feast day on August 30&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; (in 1727 the feast was discontinued by reason of non-church matters, and involved clique-struggles at the imperial court. In 1730 the feast was again re-established).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Archimandrite Gabriel Buzhinsky (later Bishop of Riazan, † April 27&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 1731) compiled a special service in remembrance of the Treaty of Nystad, combining with it a service to Saint Alexander Nevsky.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The name of the Defender of the borders of Russia and the Patron of Soldiers is famous far from the regions of our Native Land. The testimony to this: the numerous temples dedicated to Saint Alexander Nevsky. The most famous of them: the Patriarchal Cathedral at Sofia, the Cathedral church in Tallinn, and a church in Tbilisi. These churches are a pledge of friendship of the Russian National-Liberator with brother nations.&lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
Recognize thy brethren, O right-believing Prince Alexander, thou Russian Joseph who reignest not in Egypt, but in heaven; and accept their entreaties, increasing the harvests of thy people through the fertility of thy land, and protecting the cities of thy dominion by thy supplications. And together with our Orthodox hierarchs do battle against all heresies.
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="4">
As thy kinsmen Boris and Gleb appeared to thee, bringing thee help from heaven when thou didst battle against Velgar the Swede and his warriors, so now, O blessed Alexander, come to the aid of thy kinfolk, and contend thou against those who wage war against us.
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>
