<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Holy Wonderworkers and Unmercenaries Cosmas and Damian of Mesopotamia, and their mother, Saint Theodotia (3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; C)" Short="Unmercenaries"/>
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Fr. Eugene Tarris">
<p>Brothers by birth, they were born in Asia. Their father                    was a Greek pagan, and their mother, Theodotia, confessed the                    Christian faith. She became widowed in her youth and led a                    pious life, accustoming her children to a charitable life and                    teaching them good works. Brought up in strict piety, Cosmas                    and Damian from infancy tried to fulfill the law of God, and                    having come of age, like two candlesticks shone with good                    deeds. In order to better bring benefits to their neighbor, they were occupied with medical science, learned the healing properties of herbs and plants, and became skilful physicians. From their success of healing the infirm, they "neither received anything from anyone for doing this, for they did this not for the sake of their estate, to enrich themselves with gold and silver, but for the sake of God". They "helped not only people, but also cattle". Having lived in peace and hardworking, they quietly departed to the Lord, and were buried in Fereman in Mesopotamia and "in accordance with their holy repose granting healing flowing in abundance to all"2. The commemoration of the Unmercenaries on July 1 and October 17 are separate from them.</p>
</LIFE>
<SERVICE Type="2">
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="8" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
<p>O Holy Unmercenaries and Wonderworkers Cosmas and Damian, visit our infirmities. Freely have you received; freely grant to us. </p>
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="2" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
<p>Having received the grace of healings, you extend health to those in need, O Physicians [and] Most Glorious Wonderworkers. But by your visitation, destroy the insolence of the enemies, healing the world through your wonders. </p>
</KONTAKION>
</LITURGY>
</SERVICE>
</SAINT>
