<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Synaxis of the Commander Michael and the Other Bodiless Powers"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
       Commander Michael, whose name in Hebrew means "Who is like God? ", or
"Who is Equal to God? ", is the leader of heavenly Powers and is why in Holy
Scriptures he is called the Commander of the Powers of the Lord (Joshua 5:14)," "One
of the chief princes" (Dan. 10:13) "Your great prince" (Dan. 10:21; 12: 1). In church
hymns he is hymned as "leader of the angelic choir", "Intercessor to the Tri-solar
Divinity". Celebrating him, the Holy Church celebrates also all the bodiless Powers,
and is why the same feast is called the Synaxis. This feast was established in the
Fourth Century. The reason why the Holy Angels is commemorated in November is
that November is the ninth month from March (which originally was the first month
of the year) and there are nine orders of angels. These nine orders, according to the
teaching of the Holy Church, are divided into three hierarchies: the highest, the middle
and the lowest; each hierarchy has three ranks. To the highest hierarchy belong (1) the
six-winged Seraphim (Is. 6: 2), (2) the many-eyed Cherubim (Gen. 3:24) and (3) the
God-bearing Thrones (Col. 1: 16); to the middle hierarchy belong (1) the Dominions
(Col. 1:16), (2) the Powers (1 Pet. 3: 22) and (3) the Authorities (1 Pet. 3:22; Col.
1:16); to the lowest hierarchy belong the (1) Principalities (Col. 1:16), (2) the
Archangels (1 Thess. 4:16) and (3) the Angels (1 Pet. 3:22). Besides the Archangels
Michael and Gabriel (Mar. 26 and July 13) the following archangels are known both
in the Holy Scriptures and Holy Tradition: Raphael, the physician of God (Tobit 3:17;
12:15), Uriel, the fire or light of God (3 Esdras 5:16), Salaphiel, the prayer of God (3
Esdras 5:16), Jegudiel, the glorifier of God, Barachiel, the blessing of God, and
Jeremiel, the exaltation of God (3 Esdras 4:36).

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
Supreme commanders of the armies of Heaven,/ we, the unworthy, do ever entreat you,/ that by your prayers ye ever surround us/ with the protection of the wings of your immaterial glory,/ preserving us that earnestly fall down before you and cry aloud:/ Deliver us from misfortunes,// in that ye are the leaders of the hosts on high.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
O ye chief commanders of God,/ ministers of glory divine, captains of the angels and instructors of men:/ beg ye great mercy and that which is profitable for us,/ for ye are the supreme commanders of the bodiless hosts.
</KONTAKION>

</SAINT>