<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Venerable Nikon, Abbot of Radonezh, and disciple of Venerable Sergius (+1426)" Short="Venerable Nikon,"/>
<SERVICE Type="3"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
     Born in Yuriev Povolzhsky, in his youth he, "having scorned earthly beauty and glory as being nothing", came to the Venerable Sergius, but he reassigned him to his disciple the Venerable Athanasius Vysotsky (to Serpukhov, the eminent). When the Venerable Nikon under the direction of this great ascetic achieved the rank of priest, the Venerable Sergius accepted him in the monastery in 1375. The Venerable Sergius loved the Venerable Nikon so much because of his habits and his life that he lived with him in the same cell and finally shortly before his death assigned him to be the Hegumen. Because of his love for solitude the Venerable Nikon for a time gave up being Hegumen in the monastery and departed from it for the exercise of ascetical efforts of silence. In 1422 he was granted the privilege to open the uncorrupt relics of his director (see July 5). "Pointing out the paradigm of your good deeds to all, having the grace of God Who loves mankind deeply within you", "serving the Lord with purity of conscience", he lived "on earth as an angel" and died in peace on Nov. 17 in 1427 or 1428. The Council of 1547 numbered him among the saints. In 1548 a church was built over his grave, and in 1623 in place of this church the new St. Sergius Laura was built, existing to the present time. In the northwest corner of church, along the northern wall, there is a monument (gravestone) over the relics of the Venerable Nikon, which are found in the ground or in a hidden place. 
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="1">
 Having been a good zealot of obedience, O ever-memorable and venerable Nikon, in praise of thy father you erected a church to the Holy Trinity. Therefore we thy children lovingly cry out to thee: Glory to Him who has given thee strength. Glory to Him who has crowned thee. Glory to Him who through thee works healings for all.
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="4">
 Having cleaved to thy spiritual superior in all things, O Father Nikon, and being instructed by him, thou didst enslave thyself to Christ. Thou wast a superior of monks and co-dweller with the venerable ones. With them beseech Christ God incessantly for us all.
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>