<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Repose of Saint Peter, Metropolitan of Moscow and Wonderworker of All Russia († 1326)" Short="St. Peter"/>
<SERVICE Type="4"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
He was born in Volhynia and since childhood was nurtured by his parents in the awe of God. When he was 12 years old, St. Peter, moved with love for asceticism, accepted monasticism and soon showed himself a paradigm of high virtue and piety, for which at a mature age was ordained a presbyter. He loved to read the Holy Bible and write icons.      After many years of asceticism, St. Peter founded the Monastery of the Savior on the Rata River in which he became the Rector, (now village of Dvorets (Palace)). As Hegumen of the monastery St. Peter became glorified by his own life, and became known to the princes and noblemen and on a broader scale to the whole country.      In 1308 St. Peter was installed as the Metropolitan Kiev and all Russia and settled in Vladimir on the Kliazma. The hierarch worked much to build up piety in his extensive flock: he himself went throughout the diocese, instructing the people in the faith and holy life, built temples, reconciled princes warring among themselves, himself went to the Horde to intercede for the clergy before the khan and so forth.      In 1325 St. Peter transferred his see to Moscow that promoted its exaltation, since it then was yet insignificant as a city and to uniting all the Rus about him. Having set the foundation of the famous Dormition (Uspensky) Cathedral, St. Peter died in peace in 1326. Glorified while yet alive with the gift of insight, St. Peter after his death also became glorified for numerous miracles and healings.      The Holy Church hymns him, as “the joy of the heavenly ranks, and on earth the praise of bishops, the glory of priests, the rule of monastics and confirmation of the church,” “comfort of the needy, advocate of widows and orphans and great defender of the Russian land.”        His relics repose in the Moscow Dormition (Uspensky) Cathedral. In their presence local princes kissed the cross in loyalty to the Grand Prince of Moscow. Russian hierarchs were elected and named here.        Concerning the transfer of his relics see Aug. 24. 
</LIFE>
</SAINT>
