<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Venerable Tryphon of Pechenga and Kolsk (+1583)" Short="Venerable Tryphon"/>
<SERVICE Type="0"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
 In the world called Metrophanes, the son of a priest, who lived near the city of Torzhok within the Novgorod Province, was born in about 1485. Trained by literate parents, he loved to visit God&apos;s temple, and sang and read in it, and, from youth he was brought up in piety, and from time to time liked to leave the vain world to a deserted place to pray alone and to talk with the Lord. Fervently desiring to remain in this deserted place forever, he once while praying heard a wonderful voice: &quot;this is not your place, an uninhabited and thirsting world is waiting for you&quot;. Having accepted this voice as instruction from above, Trypho decided to devote himself to homiletic works for those not knowing the One God. Having decided this, he went to an unknown country for him and after wandering for a long time in the wilderness, and taught by God, he reached the western part of Lapland occupied by nomadic tribes of pagans, the Lopars. The heaviest work of apostleship among the rough idolaters without human help or protection against rage of pagans stood ahead of the preacher of Christ. But the heart of the preacher burned with love for Christ for their conversion to the faith in Christ, and he for 20 years wandered alone among the dwellings of the Lopars, scattered on various sides of the vast expanse of the tundra, the bogs and the mountains, without means, and sometimes without hope for kind acceptance of him in one dwelling so that he goes to another to meet the same situation. Quite often the kebuns, pagan priests, subjected the Venerable Trypho to severe tortures and beatings because of his sacred work. The kebuns more than once rose up against the holy preacher to challenge him with pride and hope, &quot;spinning with the preacher of God and raging like beasts and playing dirty tricks on him behind his back, pulling his hair and throwing him to the ground and beating him, and pushing him, calling him an unknown wanderer and fool, shouting at him without limit, and for him to continue to live with them there will bring bitter torments and hating him until his very death&quot;. But the holy adherent of heavenly truth with meekness endured the abuse and beatings, and for a while went to the mountains and caves, and when the rage and the anger of pagans quieted down, he again went there to preach, and the Lord protected His servant. After 20-years of hard work the Venerable Trypho converted the rough idolaters, and a significant number of them accepted the Lord and were ready to receive baptism. But, being a layman with humility, the preacher would not do holy baptism by himself, and meanwhile in all Lapland there was no priest who could baptize the Lopars, and no temple to receive the newly illumined children into the bosom of Church. This forced Trypho to go to Novgorod to Archbishop Macarius to request a sacred charter to build a church and to assign a priest to it. Having received the charter, he led carpenters to the Pechenga River, and carrying wood on his shoulders built a church in 1532, which, however, remained 3 years unconsecrated, and without a priest. Such new difficulty forced Trypho to go to the Kola village, in which he by chance met Hieromonk Elias going there, and whom he invited to go with him to the Pechenga River. The Hieromonk Elias baptized the Lopars, consecrated his church and tonsured Trypho into monasticism. Having taken advantage of the services of the Hieromonk Elias, the Venerable Trypho started the foundation of his church of the holy monastery in the name of the Holy Life-originating Trinity. The Lord obviously blessed the work of the Venerable One: a considerable number of brothers soon gathered near the lonely church, and within 20 years a large monastery with many brothers was founded and services were performed. During this time all the Lopar tribes of western Lapland accepted sacred baptism. In 1556 St. Trypho went to Moscow to the Tsar Ivan the Terrible with a petition for the protection and the security of the monastery in the future. Being graciously accepted by the tsar, he received from him rich gifts for the church and the imperial charter for the possession of the land areas, the necessary streams and the sea bay for eternity. In memory of the imperial generosity, in carrying this out in 1565 he built a temple in the name of the Saints Princes Boris and Gleb for the Lopars on the Pazreke River, which and until now stands as guards on our border with Norway. On a primitive, lonely place of his residence on the Manna Rivulet, which runs into the Pechenga River, the Venerable One constructed a small temple in the name of Dormition of the Mother of God. The extensive, favorable river and sea industry delivered sufficient means for external accomplishment and protection of the monastery, for the special growth in the number of the brothers with postulants. And the holy monastery under the skilled management of the Venerable Trypho blossomed as a garden of belief and piety, as a brightly burning lamp illuminating and recovering all desert areas. The newly illumined children of the Venerable One are the nomadic Lopars who so loved the holy monastery that some began to give it money, some arable land, and others entered the monastery to work for it, and became so strong in the Orthodox faith, that during 300 years there was no instance of anyone converting to another faith or schism among them. Having built his monastery, the Venerable Trypho spent most of his last years in solitude at his favorite place near the Dormition Church. Having lived in Lapland for 70 years and having reached a very old age, the Venerable Trypho became seriously ill. Before his end he taught his brothers consolation and received the Holy Sacraments. He turned over his soul to the Lord on December 15, 1583, being 98 years old, and was buried in a place ordered by him, and his relics rest even up to now in a little hermitage. (See the Archangel Diocese). 
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="1">
 
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="1">
 
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>