<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Holy Monastic Fathers slain in Sinai and Raithu (4th-5th C): Isaiah, Savva, Moses and his disciple Moses, Jeremiah, Paul, Adam, Sergius, Domnus, Proclus, Hipatius, Isaac, Macarius, Mark, Eusibius, Benjamin, Elijah, and others [their service is sung on the 13th]" Short="Holy Monastic"/>
<SERVICE Type="1"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
 The Monastic Fathers, Murdered at Sinai and Raipha, asceticised at the monasteries and caves of Mount Sinai, where previously the Ten Commandments had been given through Moses; near to it also was the Raipha monastic wilderness (on the shores of the Red Sea). They suffered under the Saracens and under nomadic brigands from among the Arab tribes. The first massacre occurred in about the year 312. It was recorded by Ammon, an Egyptian monk, who witnessed the murder of the 40 holy fathers in Sinai. During this time the Arabs also killed 39 fathers at Raipha. The second period of the massacres occurred nearly an hundred years later, and was likewise recorded by an eye-witness who himself in the process miraculously escaped -- the Monk Nilos the Faster (Comm. 12 November). 	The Sinai and Raipha ascetics lived a particularly strict lifestyle: they spent the whole week in their cells at prayer, on Saturday they gathered for the all-night vigil, and on Sunday they communed the Holy Mysteries. Their only food was dates and water. Many of the wilderness ascetics were glorified by wonderworking -- the elders Moses, Joseph and others. By name, remembered in the service to these monastic fathers are commemorated: Isaiah, Sava, Moses and his student Moses, Jeremiah, Paul, Adam, Sergios, Domnos, Proklos, Ipatios, Isaac, Makarios, Mark, Benjamin, Eusebios and Elias.
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
 O God of our fathers,/ deal with us ever according to Thy meekness./ Deprive us not of Thy mercy,/ but through their supplications// direct our life in peace.
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="2">
 Ye fled from the tumult of the world/ and have found rest in the calm haven,/ crowned with the blood of martyrdom/ and the labors of asceticism.// Wherefore, ye have been shown to dwell together with the martyrs and the venerable.
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>