<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Martyr Hieron and the other 32 Martyrs of Melitene: Hieron, Hysichius, Nicander, Athanasius, Mamantus, Barachius, Callinicus, Theogenes, Nikon, Longinus, Theodore, Valerius, Xantheius, Theodulus, Callimachus, Eugene, Theodochus, Ostrichius, Epiphanius, Maximian, Duceitius, Claudian, Theophilus, Gigantius, Dorotheus, Theodotus, Castrichius, Anikita, Themelius, Eutichius, Hilarion, Diodotus, and Amonitus (3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; C)" Short="Martyr Hieron"/>
<SERVICE Type="1"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
&lt;p&gt;Hieron, Hesychius, Nicander, Athanasius, Mamas, Barachias, Callinicus, Theogenes, Nikon, Longinus, Theodore, Galerius, Xanthius, Theodulus, Callimachus, Eugene, Theodochus, Ostrychius, Epiphanius, Maximian, Ducitius, Claudian, Theophilus, Gigantius, Dorotheus, Theodotus, Castrychius, Anicletus, Theomelius, Eutychius, Hilarion, Diodotus and Amonitus suffered for Christ during the reign of Emperor Diocletian in Melitene. St. Hieron was born in Tyana, Cappadocia and was glorified for his courage and strength. Not wishing to enter into the ranks of the warriors as in an army it was impossible to hide his faith. He was seized by force and, for his confession of Christ, they cut off his hands and imprisoned him together with other Christians. After being tortured all the Holy Martyrs were beheaded. All these holy martyrs are mentioned in the services by name. &lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
&lt;p&gt;In their sufferings, O Lord, * Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God; * for, possessed of Thy might, * they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons. ** By their supplications save Thou our souls.&lt;/p&gt;
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="0" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
&lt;p&gt;The radiant choir of martyrs, the luminous company, * descending to us nœtically, hath illumined the Church today with wondrous rays. * Wherefore, celebrating their honored memory, we ask of Thee, O our Savior: * through their supplications deliv­er us from misfortunes, ** that we may chant unto Thee: Alleluia! &lt;/p&gt;
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>
