<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Saint John the Merciful, Patriarch of Alexandria († 612)" Short="Saint John"/>
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
&lt;p&gt; Born on the island of Cyprus, son of a prince, he devoted his whole life to prayer and virtue and for his piety he was chosen to be the patriarch. In this post St. John even more cared for the poor, the suffering and the captives, not leaving anyone without bountiful grants. St. John gave alms to everyone who asked. Once among the poor gathering for a handout there were well-dressed girls who approached and asked the hierarch whether they should give alms in the same way. St. John answered: “if you are servants of Christ, give as Christ has enjoined, not looking at the person for we do not give of our own but of Christ’s”. One rich noblewoman, who visited the hierarch and saw on his bed a thin coverlet, sent him a silk one, costing 36 gold coins (zlatnitsa). The hierarch respected her zeal and put on the coverlet presented to him, but in that same night he woke up, and repented and said: “wœ to you, the condemned! You are covered with an expensive blanket, and the brothers in Christ, the poor, freeze in the cold. Let this costly gift cover some of the poor”. In the morning he sent to sell the coverlet and gave the money to the needy. The noblewoman again gave him a coverlet, but the hierarch did not want to take advantage of the gift and turned the noblewoman”s attachment to him into a means of philanthropy. So that no one from the needy would be set aside, St. John on Wednesday and Friday sat all day at the church gate so that all having business with him would not be forbidden to come to him. When they expressed surprise at his patience, the hierarch answered: “ if I always have access to my Lord Jesus Christ, in prayer I talk to Him and I ask Him everything that I want: how I can forbid my neighbor to come to me?” And it is true that no urgent business could force St. John to postpone acts of mercy. One widow approached him when he went to church. Accompanying him she listened to his advice after the service. But the hierarch answered: “but would God listen to me if I do not want to listen to her?” Then he analyzed the situation and satisfied the widow. Being “meek, the good compassionate one was also gentle”. St. John once for the defense of poor people was deeply offended by one secular leader and on the same day, before sunset, sent a message to his offender: “soon the sun will set: let us reconcile”. The leader was so touched with these words, that he not only reconciled with the peace loving hierarch, but also promised to flee from conflicts with anyone in his life. During an attack of the Persians in Egypt, St. John left for the island of Cyprus where he died in 620. His relics repose in city of Bratislava, Slovakia. &lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE>
<SERVICE Type="2">
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="0">
In thy patience, O venerable father, thou didst acquire thy reward, * having endured in prayers without ceasing, and loved the poor and provided for them. ** Beseech Christ God, O blessed almsgiver John, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="2">
Thou didst distribute thy wealth to the destitute, * and hast now received heavenly riches, O John most wise. * Wherefore, celebrating thy memory, ** we all honor thee, O namesake of almsgiving.
</KONTAKION>
</LITURGY>
</SERVICE>
</SAINT>
