<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Our Venerable Father Barlaam of Khutin, Wonderworker of Novgorod"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
       The Ven. Barlaam, in the world Alexis, was born in 1156 of pious and rich
parents living in Novgorod. Having found an inclination for the monastic life in his
youth, he distributed his estate to the poor after the death of his parents, and, with the
name Barlaam, accepted tonsure in the Lisitsi Monastery. Wishing to practice
asceticism in strict solitude, he left for Khutin, about 10 versts (6.6 miles) from
Novgorod. Having built a small cell there for himself he was entirely given to prayer,
fasting and labor. The glory of the asceticism of St. Barlaam soon spread in the
vicinity. Both princes and boyars, monks and laymen began to come to him for
conversation, and he gave each one long instruction. And many lovers of the monastic
way of life wished to conduct their life under his leadership and settled around him.
Ven. Barlaam built for them the Transfiguration of the Lord Monastery and cells (see
the Novgorod Diocese). St. Gregory, Archbishop of Novgorod, ordained the Ven.
Barlaam to the priesthood and appointed him the hegumen of the monastery. Being
the hegumen of the monastery, the Ven. Barlaam "standing all night in continual
prayer" set the high example of virtue through his life. Being taught "in the
commandments of the Lord day and night" his "exhaustion" of the flesh through
fasting "and vigil", suppressing in himself "all carnal subtleties" and being glorified by
the Lord with the gift of wonders and insight, the Ven. Barlaam was very much
respected by princes and hierarchs. He died in 1192. His relics, discovered to be
incorrupt in 1452, repose in a hidden place in his monastery.

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
Thou who, by reclining on earth, fasting and vigils didst put to death every fleshly subtlety,  O Righteous one, and didst appear an inexhaustible stream of healings unto those that with faith hasten to thy relics, O Barlaam, our father; pray thou to Christ God that our souls may be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
As a second Elias, O Father, thou didst bring down rain from the heavens. For he brought down fire and awed the king, but thou didst gladden thy people and didst cause them to keep festival. Great Novgorod is thus greatly praised in thee, having thy relics in it. Do thou keep it unshaken from enemies that we may cry unto thee: Rejoice, O Righteous Barlaam, our father.
</KONTAKION>

</SAINT>