<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Hieromartyr Ignatius the God-Bearer, Bishop of Antioch (+107)" Short="Hieromartyr Ignatius"/>
<SERVICE Type="2"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
 As the &quot;brightly shining lamp of the church&quot;, &quot;the pillar of patience and the rule of courage and the confirmation of faith&quot;, he was the disciple of the Holy Apostle John the Theologian and the second (after St. Evodius) Bishop of Antioch. He ruled his own flock for 40 years, showing himself an example of a highly virtuous life. He was the first to establish antiphonal singing in the church. During the Dometian persecution, the holy shepherd &quot;with the rudder of prayer and fasting, with indefatigableness in doctrine and zealousness of spirit, counteracted the turmoil in order that none would sink from lack of courage or inexperience&quot;, and from his side he expressed full readiness to accept the crown of martyrdom. This was his desire, and to his sincere joy it was soon fulfilled. During the reign of Trajan, St. Ignatius for his confession and propagation of the Christian faith was sent to Rome in fetters where for the entertainment of the people he was given to be torn apart by wild beasts in the Coliseum in the year 107. On the way to Rome, St. Ignatius wrote seven epistles. He was called God-bearer because in his childhood, according to tradition, he was taken into the hands of Jesus Christ Himself. But also because he became so used to feeding his heart with the memory of the sweet name of Jesus Christ, that this deep spiritual seal with sensitive images was stamped on this bodily organ and when, after his martyr&apos;s death, when his heart was cut asunder, the name of Jesus Christ was seen alphabetically represented in it. See Jan. 29.
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
 As thou didst share in the ways of the apostles/ and didst occupy their throne,/ thou didst find thine activity to be a passage to divine vision,/ O divinely inspired one./ Wherefore, ordering the word of truth,/ thou didst suffer for the Faith even to the shedding of thy blood.// O hieromartyr Ignatius, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="3">
 The luminous day of thy radiant struggles/ proclaimeth beforehand to all Him Who hath been Born in the cave;/ for thirsting to delight in His love,/ thou didst hasten to be devoured by the wild beasts.// Wherefore, thou hast been called the God-bearer, O most wise Ignatius.
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>