<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Sunday before the Nativity of Christ, of the Fathers" Short="Sunday before the Nativity"/>
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
In the services of this week are glorified the Old Testament saints, from whose human family came our Lord Jesus Christ. Therefore in the Gospel appointed for this Sunday is read the “genealogy” of Jesus Christ. Together with these on this Sunday, as well as on the Sunday of the Forefathers (see Dec. 11), are commemorated all those living in faith and all the Old Testament saints who have come to the Savior, who are listed in the Epistle reading for this Sunday.         In the church hymns for this day the Holy Church primarily sings “of the beginning fathers Abraham, Isaac and Jacob,” “together with the Three Youths, who quench the fiery flames with the dew of the Spirit” and “the physical images of the hidden mysteries of God revealed to the world,” and the prophet Daniel, who, “foretold the birth of the Christ from a virgin” and “foresaw that the cruel world would be counted among those with deep spiritual peace by the coming of Christ, having sometimes stopped the mouths of lions in the pit.”         Together with this the Holy Church in the hymns for the present day as well as for the Forefeast of the Nativity of Christ, exclaims: “Come let us all faithfully celebrate the Nativity of Christ,” “Skip, O hills and mountains; Dance, O prophets who spoke of God! Clap your hands, O peoples and nations! The salvation and the enlightenment of all draw near. He comes to be born in the city of Bethlehem”; “The never setting Sun arises from the bedding of the Virgin to enlighten all those under the sun. Let us hasten with chaste eyes and pure deeds to meet Him.”
</LIFE>
<SERVICE Type="1">
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Tone="2" Type="1">
Great are the accomplishments of faith, * for the Three Youths rejoiced in the fountain of flames as though in the waters of rest; * and the prophet Daniel appeared * a shepherd to the lions as though they were sheep. ** So by their prayers O Christ God save our souls
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1" Podoben="2" Type="1">
Rejoice O Bethlehem! Prepare yourself O Ephratha! * The Lamb is on her way to give birth to the Chief Shepherd she carries in her womb. * The God-bearing forefathers will rejoice beholding Him ** and the shepherds will glorify her nursing Him.
</KONTAKION>
</LITURGY>
</SERVICE>
</SAINT>
