<COMMEMORATION>

<NAME>The Eve (Paramony) of the Theophany</NAME>
<SERVICE>
	<ROYALHOURS><!-- The verses for the Idiomels are the same in all the hours -->
	<IDIOMEL Type="11" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8&lt;BR&gt;The Work of Sophronios, the Patriarch of Jerusalem" Author="Sophronios, the Patriarch of Jerusalem">
Today the nature of water is sanctified, and the Jordan is cloven, and its waters shall be withheld from flowing; the Master being shown washed therein.
	</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<VERSE Type="1" >
Therefore will I remember Thee from the land of the Jordan and Hermoniem. The waters saw Thee, O God, the waters saw Thee and were afraid.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="12" Tone="3" Header="Tropar, Tone 3">
Thou didst come to the river like a man, O Christ King. Thou dost hasten, O good One, to receive baptism as a servant at the hands of the Forerunner, for our sins, O Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="2">
The waters saw Thee, O God; the waters saw Thee and were afraid.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="13" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Toward the voice in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord. Thou didst come taking the
likeness of a servant, seeking baptism, O Thou Who knowest no sin. The waters saw Thee and
were afraid, and the Forerunner trembled and cried, saying, How shall the Light seek to be
lighted for the lamp? How shall the servant place His hand upon the Master? Wherefore, sanctify
me and the waters, O Savior, carrying the sin of the world.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="1P" Tone="4" Header="Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The voice of the Lord is upon many waters; the voice of Thy thunder was in heaven.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="1P" >
I will love Thee, O Lord, my strength; the Lord is my support, refuge and deliverer.
</VERSE><!-- The last 3 words of these verse are not found in the Church Slavonic -->

<IDIOMEL Type="31" Tone="8" Header="Тropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Verily, the right hand of the Forerunner, Baptizer, and Prophet, exceeding all Prophets in honor,
did tremble when he beheld Thee, O Lamb of God that beareth the sins of the world. And being
encompassed with fear, shouted, saying, I dare not touch Thy head, O Word. Sanctify Thou me
and enlighten me, O compassionate One; for Thou art the Life, the Light, and the Safety of the
world.
</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<IDIOMEL Type="32" Tone="8" Header="Troparion, Tone 8">
Our God the Trinity hath revealed Himself to us today as free from division; for the Father
uttered the clear testimony to His Son, and the Spirit descended from heaven in the likeness of a
dove, and the Son bowed His pure head to the Forerunner, and being baptized did save mankind
from captivity, since He is the Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="33" Tone="3" Header="Tropar, Tone 3" Author="">
O Life-giving Lord, when Thou didst come to the Jordan in the flesh, in the likeness of man,
willing to be baptized to lighten us who have erred, delivering us from all the wiles of the dragon
and his gins, since Thou art compassionate, the Father testified of Thee, and the divine Spirit did
come to Thee in the likeness of a dove. Dwell Thou, therefore, in our souls, O Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="3P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The waters saw Thee, O God; the waters saw Thee and were afraid.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="3P">
The voice of the Lord is upon the waters; the God of glory thundered, the Lord is upon many waters.
</VERSE><!-- This does not quite match the Church Slavonic version -->
	
<IDIOMEL Type="61" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Thus sayeth the Lord to John, Come, O Prophet, and baptize me, Who have created Thee, the
Illuminator and Purifier of all by grace. Touch my divine head and falter not, O Prophet. Let be
now; for I have come to fulfill all justice. Be not doubtful, therefore, at all; for verily, I have
come to destroy the Archon of darkness, the Contender, who hideth in the waters, now rescuing
the world from his traps, and granting eternal life, since I am the Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="62" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6">
Today it is the time for the prophecy of the Psalms to take effect; for it sayeth that the sea beheld
and ran away; and Jordan turned back from the face of the Lord, from the face of the God of
Jacob, Who cometh to accept baptism from a servant, so that having been washed from
abominable idolatry, our souls may be illuminated by Him.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="63" Tone="5" Header="Tropar, Tone 5" Author="">
Why are thy waters troubled, O Jordan, and why turnest thou backward, not proceeding forward
according to thy natural flow? It shall answer, saying, I cannot bear a consuming fire. Therefore,
do I marvel and tremble at Thine exceeding condescension; for I am not accustomed to wash the
Pure; I have not learned to purify the sinless One, but to purify impure vessels. Christ, who
January 05 Royal Hours 15 Theophany of Christ
baptized in me, doth teach me to burn the thorns of sins. And John, the voice of the Word, doth
testify with me, crying, Behold the Lamb of God Who beareth the sin of the world. Let us believers
therefore cry unto Him, saying, O God that hath appeared for our salvation, glory to Thee.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="6P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The voice of the Lord is upon the waters; the God of glory thundered, the Lord is upon many waters.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="6P" >
Bring unto the Lord, ye sons of God, bring unto the Lord glory and honor.
</VERSE>

<IDIOMEL Type="91" Tone="7" Header="Tropar, Tone 7" Author="">
It is an astonishing thing how the Maker of heaven and earth is seen naked in the river, accepting
like a servant baptism from a servant for our salvation. Therefore, the ranks of the angels were
astonished in fear and rejoicing. With them therefore, we worship Thee. Save us, O Lord.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="92" Tone="2" Header="Tropar, Tone 2">
Verily, the Forerunner, seeing the Lord of glory coming towards him, cried, saying, Behold the
Redeemer of the world cometh from corruption. Behold, He rescueth us from sorrow. Behold,
He Who granteth forgiveness of sins hath come to the earth from a pure Virgin, of His own
mercy. Wherefore, He maketh us sons of God instead of servants; and instead of darkness He
illuminateth mankind with the water of His divine baptism. Let us, therefore, glorify Him in
unison with the Father and the Holy Spirit.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.1" Tone="5" Header="Tropar, Tone 5" Author="">
Thy hand which touched the head of the Master, free of corruption
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.2" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
the same with which thou didst point Him to us by the pointing of the finger, raise thou it to
Him for our sakes, O Forerunner. Thou hast attained great favor, since it was testified of thee by
Him that thou art the greatest of all the Prophets. And thine eyes also, which did behold the All-
Holy Spirit descending in the likeness of a dove, raise to Him, O Baptizer, granting mercy for us.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.3" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
Come, thou, and stand with us
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.4" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
concluding our praise and beginning the celebration of the Feast.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.5" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
And the bridegroom of the Church calleth the Magi.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="9P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The Lord is my light and my salvation; whom shall I fear?
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="9P">
The Lord is the defender of my life; of whom shall I be afraid?
</VERSE>

	</ROYALHOURS>
</SERVICE>

</COMMEMORATION>