<!-- service file for SID P_163 (The Paramony of Theophany) (The 3 days before Theophany) -->
<!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="Commemeration.xsl" ?>-->

<COMMEMORATION>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME>The Eve (Paramony) of the Theophany</NAME>
<SERVICE>
	<ROYALHOURS><!-- The verses for the Idiomels are the same in all the hours -->
	<IDIOMEL Type="11" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8&lt;BR&gt;The Work of Sophronios, the Patriarch of Jerusalem" Author="Sophronios, the Patriarch of Jerusalem">
Today the nature of water is sanctified, and the Jordan is cloven, and its waters shall be withheld from flowing; the Master being shown washed therein.
	</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<VERSE Type="1" >
Therefore will I remember Thee from the land of the Jordan and Hermoniem. The waters saw Thee, O God, the waters saw Thee and were afraid.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="12" Tone="3" Header="Tropar, Tone 3">
Thou didst come to the river like a man, O Christ King. Thou dost hasten, O good One, to receive baptism as a servant at the hands of the Forerunner, for our sins, O Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="2">
The waters saw Thee, O God; the waters saw Thee and were afraid.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="13" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Toward the voice in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord. Thou didst come taking the
likeness of a servant, seeking baptism, O Thou Who knowest no sin. The waters saw Thee and
were afraid, and the Forerunner trembled and cried, saying, How shall the Light seek to be
lighted for the lamp? How shall the servant place His hand upon the Master? Wherefore, sanctify
me and the waters, O Savior, carrying the sin of the world.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="1P" Tone="4" Header="Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The voice of the Lord is upon many waters; the voice of Thy thunder was in heaven.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="1P" >
I will love Thee, O Lord, my strength; the Lord is my support, refuge and deliverer.
</VERSE><!-- The last 3 words of these verse are not found in the Church Slavonic -->

<IDIOMEL Type="31" Tone="8" Header="Тropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Verily, the right hand of the Forerunner, Baptizer, and Prophet, exceeding all Prophets in honor,
did tremble when he beheld Thee, O Lamb of God that beareth the sins of the world. And being
encompassed with fear, shouted, saying, I dare not touch Thy head, O Word. Sanctify Thou me
and enlighten me, O compassionate One; for Thou art the Life, the Light, and the Safety of the
world.
</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<IDIOMEL Type="32" Tone="8" Header="Troparion, Tone 8">
Our God the Trinity hath revealed Himself to us today as free from division; for the Father
uttered the clear testimony to His Son, and the Spirit descended from heaven in the likeness of a
dove, and the Son bowed His pure head to the Forerunner, and being baptized did save mankind
from captivity, since He is the Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="33" Tone="3" Header="Tropar, Tone 3" Author="">
O Life-giving Lord, when Thou didst come to the Jordan in the flesh, in the likeness of man,
willing to be baptized to lighten us who have erred, delivering us from all the wiles of the dragon
and his gins, since Thou art compassionate, the Father testified of Thee, and the divine Spirit did
come to Thee in the likeness of a dove. Dwell Thou, therefore, in our souls, O Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="3P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The waters saw Thee, O God; the waters saw Thee and were afraid.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="3P">
The voice of the Lord is upon the waters; the God of glory thundered, the Lord is upon many waters.
</VERSE><!-- This does not quite match the Church Slavonic version -->
	
<IDIOMEL Type="61" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Thus sayeth the Lord to John, Come, O Prophet, and baptize me, Who have created Thee, the
Illuminator and Purifier of all by grace. Touch my divine head and falter not, O Prophet. Let be
now; for I have come to fulfill all justice. Be not doubtful, therefore, at all; for verily, I have
come to destroy the Archon of darkness, the Contender, who hideth in the waters, now rescuing
the world from his traps, and granting eternal life, since I am the Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="62" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6">
Today it is the time for the prophecy of the Psalms to take effect; for it sayeth that the sea beheld
and ran away; and Jordan turned back from the face of the Lord, from the face of the God of
Jacob, Who cometh to accept baptism from a servant, so that having been washed from
abominable idolatry, our souls may be illuminated by Him.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="63" Tone="5" Header="Tropar, Tone 5" Author="">
Why are thy waters troubled, O Jordan, and why turnest thou backward, not proceeding forward
according to thy natural flow? It shall answer, saying, I cannot bear a consuming fire. Therefore,
do I marvel and tremble at Thine exceeding condescension; for I am not accustomed to wash the
Pure; I have not learned to purify the sinless One, but to purify impure vessels. Christ, who
January 05 Royal Hours 15 Theophany of Christ
baptized in me, doth teach me to burn the thorns of sins. And John, the voice of the Word, doth
testify with me, crying, Behold the Lamb of God Who beareth the sin of the world. Let us believers
therefore cry unto Him, saying, O God that hath appeared for our salvation, glory to Thee.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="6P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The voice of the Lord is upon the waters; the God of glory thundered, the Lord is upon many waters.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="6P" >
Bring unto the Lord, ye sons of God, bring unto the Lord glory and honor.
</VERSE>

<IDIOMEL Type="91" Tone="7" Header="Tropar, Tone 7" Author="">
It is an astonishing thing how the Maker of heaven and earth is seen naked in the river, accepting
like a servant baptism from a servant for our salvation. Therefore, the ranks of the angels were
astonished in fear and rejoicing. With them therefore, we worship Thee. Save us, O Lord.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="92" Tone="2" Header="Tropar, Tone 2">
Verily, the Forerunner, seeing the Lord of glory coming towards him, cried, saying, Behold the
Redeemer of the world cometh from corruption. Behold, He rescueth us from sorrow. Behold,
He Who granteth forgiveness of sins hath come to the earth from a pure Virgin, of His own
mercy. Wherefore, He maketh us sons of God instead of servants; and instead of darkness He
illuminateth mankind with the water of His divine baptism. Let us, therefore, glorify Him in
unison with the Father and the Holy Spirit.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.1" Tone="5" Header="Tropar, Tone 5" Author="">
Thy hand which touched the head of the Master, free of corruption
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.2" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
the same with which thou didst point Him to us by the pointing of the finger, raise thou it to
Him for our sakes, O Forerunner. Thou hast attained great favor, since it was testified of thee by
Him that thou art the greatest of all the Prophets. And thine eyes also, which did behold the All-
Holy Spirit descending in the likeness of a dove, raise to Him, O Baptizer, granting mercy for us.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.3" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
Come, thou, and stand with us
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.4" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
concluding our praise and beginning the celebration of the Feast.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.5" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
And the bridegroom of the Church calleth the Magi.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="9P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The Lord is my light and my salvation; whom shall I fear?
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="9P">
The Lord is the defender of my life; of whom shall I be afraid?
</VERSE>

	</ROYALHOURS>
</SERVICE>
</LANGUAGE>

<!-- The Greek Texts -->
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == -2"> 
<SERVICE>
	<ROYALHOURS>
<IDIOMEL Type="11" Tone="5" Header="Ἦχος πλ. δ'&lt;BR&gt;Ποίημα Σωφρονίου Πατριάρχου Ἱεροσολύμων" Author="Σωφρονίου Πατριάρχου Ἱεροσολύμων">
Σήμερον τῶν ὑδάτων ἁγιάζεται ἡ φύσις· καὶ ῥήγνυται ὁ Ἰορδάνης, καὶ τῶν ἰδίων ναμάτων ἐπέχει τὸ ῥεῦμα, Δεσπότην ὁρῶν ῥυπτόμενον.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="1" >
Διὰ τοῦτο μνησθήσομαί σου ἐκ γῆς Ἰορδάνου καὶ Ἐρμωνιείμ. 
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="12" Tone="3" Header="Ἦχος πλ. γ'">
Ὡς ἄνθρωπος ἐν ποταμῷ ἦλθες Χριστὲ Βασιλεῦ, καὶ δουλικὸν Βάπτισμα λαβεῖν, σπεύδεις ἀγαθέ, ὑπὸ τῶν τοῦ Προδρόμου χειρῶν, διὰ τὰς ἁμαρτίας ἡμῶν φιλάνθρωπε.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="2">
Εἴδοσάν σε ὕδατα ὁ Θεός, εἴδοσάν σε ὕδατα καὶ ἐφοβήθησαν.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="13" Tone="8" Header="Ἦχος πλ. δ'" Author="">
Πρὸς τὴν φωνὴν τοῦ βοῶντος ἐν τῇ ἐρήμῳ, ἑτοιμάσατε τὴν ὁδὸν τοῦ Κυρίου, ἦλθες Κύριε, μορφὴν δούλου λαβών, Βάπτισμα αἰτῶν, ὁ μὴ γνοὺς ἁμαρτίαν. Εἴδοσάν σε ὕδατα καὶ ἐφοβήθησαν· σύντρομος γέγονεν ὁ Πρόδρομος, καὶ ἐβόησε λέγων· Πῶς φωτίσει ὁ λύχνος τὸ Φῶς; πῶς χειροθετήσει ὁ δοῦλος τὸν Δεσπότην; Ἁγίασον ἐμὲ καὶ τὰ ὕδατα Σωτήρ, ὁ αἴρων τοῦ κόσμου τὴν ἁμαρτίαν.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="1P" Tone="4" Header="Προκείμενον τῆς Προφητείας. Ἦχος δ'">
Ἑβρόντησε Κύριος ἐπὶ ὑδάτων πολλῶν.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="1P" >
Ἀγαπήσω σε, Κύριε, ἡ ἰσχύς μου.
</VERSE>

<IDIOMEL Type="31" Tone="4" Header="Ἦχος πλ. δ'" Author="">
Ἡ τοῦ Προδρόμου καὶ Βαπτιστοῦ, τοῦ Προφήτου, καὶ ὑπὲρ πάντας τιμηθέντος τοὺς Προφήτας, ἐτρόμαξε νῦν χεὶρ δεξιά, ὅτε ἐθεάσατό σε τὸν Ἀμνὸν τοῦ Θεοῦ, τόν καθαίροντα κόσμου ἁμαρτήματα, καὶ ἀγωνίᾳ συσχεθεὶς ἐβόα· Οὐ τολμῶ προσψαῦσαι Λόγε τῆς κορυφῆς σου· αὐτὸς ἁγίασόν με, καὶ φώτισον οἰκτίρμον· αὐτὸς γὰρ εἶ ἡ ζωὴ καὶ τὸ φῶς, καὶ ἡ εἰρήνη τοῦ κόσμου.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="32" Tone="4" Header="Ἦχος δ'">
Ἡ Τριὰς ὁ Θεὸς ἡμῶν, ἑαυτὴν ἡμῖν σήμερον, ἀδιαιρέτως πεφανέρωκεν· ὁ μὲν γὰρ Πατήρ, ἐναργῆ μαρτυρίαν τῷ συγγενεῖ ἐπεφώνησε, τὸ Πνεῦμα περιστερᾶς ἐν εἰκόνι κατέπτη οὐρανόθεν· ὁ Υἱὸς τὴν ἄχραντον κορυφὴν τῷ Προδρόμῳ ὑπέκλινε, καὶ βαπτισθείς, τὸ ἀνθρώπινον ἐκ δουλείας ἐρρύσατο, ὡς φιλάνθρωπος.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="33" Tone="8" Header="Ἦχος πλ. α’" Author="">
Ἐρχόμενος μετὰ σαρκός, πρὸς Ἰορδάνην Κύριε, βαπτισθῆναι θέλων, ἐν σχήματι ἀνθρώπου ζωοδότα, ἵνα τοὺς πλανηθέντας ἡμᾶς ὡς εὔσπλαγχνος, πάσης μηχανῆς καὶ παγίδος τοῦ δράκοντος, ῥυσάμενος φωτίσῃς, ἐκ Πατρὸς μεμαρτύρησαι, τὸ δὲ θεῖον Πνεῦμα, περιστερᾶς ἐν εἴδει σοι ἐπέστη. Ἀλλ᾽ οἴκισον ψυχαῖς ἡμετέραις σαυτόν, φιλάνθρωπε. 
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="3P" Tone="4" Header="Προκείμενον τῆς Προφητείας. Ἦχος δ'">
Εἴδοσάν σε ὕδατα ὁ Θεός, εἴδοσάν σε ὕδατα καὶ ἐφοβήθησαν.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="3P" >
Φωνὴ Κυρίου ἐπὶ τῶν ὑδάτων. 
</VERSE>

<IDIOMEL Type="61" Tone="2" Header="Ἦχος α'" Author="">
Τάδε λέγει Κύριος πρός, Ἰωάννην. Προφῆτα δεῦρο βάπτισόν με, τὸν δημιουργήσαντα· τὸν φωτίζοντα χάριτι, καὶ καθαίροντα ἅπαντας, ἅψαι θείας κορυφῆς μου, καὶ μὴ διστάσῃς. Προφῆτα, ἄφες ἄρτι· καὶ γὰρ πληρῶσαι παραγέγονα, δικαιοσύνην πᾶσαν. Σὺ οὖν μὴ διστάσῃς ὅλως· καὶ γὰρ τὸν κεκρυμμένον τοῖς ὕδασι πολέμιον, τόν ἄρχοντα τοῦ σκότους, ἐπείγομαι ὀλέσαι· λυτρούμενος τὸν κόσμον, ἐκ τῶν αὐτοῦ παγίδων νῦν, παρέχων ὡς φιλάνθρωπος, ζωὴν τὴν αἰώνιον. 
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="62" Tone="7" Header="Ἦχος πλ. β᾽">
Σήμερον ἡ ψαλμικὴ Προφητεία, πέρας λαβεῖν ἐπείγεται· ἡ θάλασσα γὰρ φησιν, εἶδε καὶ ἔφυγεν· ὁ Ἰορδάνης ἐστράφη εἰς τὰ ὀπίσω, ἀπὸ προσώπου Κυρίου, ἀπὸ προσώπου τοῦ Θεοῦ Ἰακώβ, ἐλθόντος ὑπὸ δούλου δέξασθαι Βάπτισμα· ἵνα ἡμεῖς, εἰδωλικῆς ἀκαθαρσίας ἐκπλυθέντες, φωτισθῶμεν τὰς ψυχὰς δι᾽ αὐτοῦ.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="63" Tone="1" Header="Ἦχος πλ. α'" Author="">
Τὶ ἀναχαιτίζεις σου τὰ ὕδατα ὦ Ἰορδάνη; τὶ ἀναποδίζεις τὸ ῥεῖθρον, καὶ οὐ προβαίνεις τὴν κατὰ φύσιν πορείαν. Οὐ δύναμαι φέρειν, φησί, πῦρ καταναλίσκον· ἐξίσταμαι, καὶ φρίττω τὴν ἄκραν συγκατάβασιν· ὅτι οὐκ εἴωθα τὸν καθαρὸν ἀποπλύνειν, οὐκ ἔμαθον τὸν ἀναμάρτητον ἀποσμήχειν, ἀλλὰ τὰ ῥερυπωμένα σκεύη ἐκκαθαίρειν. Ἀκάνθας φλέγειν με ἁμαρτημάτων διδάσκει, ὁ ἐν ἐμοὶ βαπτιζόμενος Χριστός· ὁ Ἰωάννης συμμαρτυρεῖ μοι· ἡ Φωνὴ τοῦ Λόγου βοᾷ· ἴδε ὁ Ἀμνὸς τοῦ Θεοῦ, ὁ αἴρων τὴν ἁμαρτίαν τοῦ κόσμου. Αὐτῷ πιστοὶ βοήσωμεν· ὁ ἐπιφανεὶς Θεός, εἰς τὴν ἡμῶν σωτηρίαν, δόξα σοι.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="6P" Tone="4" Header="Προκείμενον τῆς Προφητείας. Ἦχος πλ. δ'">
Φωνὴ Κυρίου ἐπὶ τῶν ὑδάτων.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="6P" >
Ενέγκατε τω Κυρίω υιοί Θεού, ενέγκατε τω Κυρίω δόξαν και τιμήν.
</VERSE>

<IDIOMEL Type="91" Tone="" Header="Ἦχος βαρὺς" Author="">
Θάμβος ἦν κατιδεῖν, τὸν οὐρανοῦ καὶ γῆς Ποιητήν, ἐν ποταμῷ γυμνωθέντα, Βάπτισμα ὑπὸ δούλου, εἰς ἡμῶν σωτηρίαν, δεχόμενον ὡς δοῦλον, καὶ χοροὶ Ἀγγέλων ἐξεπλήττοντο, φόβῳ καὶ χαρᾷ. Μεθ᾽ ὧν προσκυνοῦμέν σε, σῶσον ἡμᾶς Κύριε.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="92" Tone="2" Header="Ἦχος β'">
Ὅτε πρὸς αὐτὸν ἐρχόμενον ὁ Πρόδρομος, τὸν Κύριον τῆς δόξης, ἐβόα θεωρῶν· ἴδε, ὁ λυτρούμενος τὸν κόσμον παραγέγονεν ἐκ φθορᾶς· ἴδε, ῥύεται ἡμᾶς ἐκ θλίψεως· ἰδού, ὁ ἁμαρτημάτων ἄφεσιν χαριζόμενος, ἐπὶ γῆς ἐκ Παρθένου Ἁγνῆς ἐλήλυθε δι᾽ ἔλεον, καὶ ἀντὶ δούλων, υἱοὺς Θεοῦ ἐργάζεται, ἀντὶ δὲ σκότους φωτίζει τὸ ἀνθρώπινον, διὰ τοῦ ὕδατος τοῦ θείου Βαπτισμοῦ αὐτοῦ. Λοιπὸν δεῦτε συμφώνως αὐτὸν δοξολογήσωμεν, σὺν Πατρὶ καὶ Ἁγίῳ Πνεύματι.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.1" Tone="1" Header="Ἦχος πλ. α'" Author="">
Τὴν χεῖρά σου τὴν ἁψαμένην, τὴν ἀκήρατον κορυφὴν τοῦ Δεσπότου
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.2" Tone="1" Header="Ἦχος πλ. α'" Author="">
 μεθ᾽ ἧς καὶ δακτύλῳ αὐτόν, ἡμῖν καθυπέδειξας, ἔπαρον ὑπὲρ ἡμῶν, Βαπτιστά, ὡς παρρησίαν ἔχων πολλήν· καὶ γὰρ μείζων τῶν Προφητῶν ἁπάντων, ὑπ᾽ αὐτοῦ μεμαρτύρησαι. Τοὺς ὀφθαλμούς σου πάλιν δέ, τοὺς τὸ Πανάγιον Πνεῦμα κατιδόντας, ὡς ἐν εἴδει περιστερᾶς κατελθόν, ἀναπέτασον πρὸς αὐτὸν Βαπτιστά, ἵλεων ἡμῖν ἀπεργασάμενος.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.3" Tone="1" Header="Ἦχος πλ. α'" Author="">
Καὶ δεῦρο στῆθι μεθ᾽ ἡμῶν (ἐκ γ´)
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.4" Tone="1" Header="Ἦχος πλ. α'" Author="">
ἐπισφραγίζων τὸν ὕμνον, καὶ προεξάρχων τῆς πανηγύρεως.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="9P" Tone="3" Header="Προκείμενον τῆς Προφητείας. Ἦχος γ'">
Κύριος φωτισμός μου και Σωτήρ μου.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="9P" >
Κύριος υπερασπιστής της ζωής μου.
</VERSE>
</ROYALHOURS>
</SERVICE>
	
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 2 || LS == 3">
<NAME></NAME>
<SERVICE>
<!-- The verses for the Idiomels are the same in all the hours -->	
<ROYALHOURS>
<IDIOMEL Type="11" Tone="7" Header="Тропарь Гла́съ и҃ &lt;BR&gt;Творе́нїе сѡфро́нїа патрїа́рха ї҆ерꙋсали́мскагѡ" Author="сѡфро́нїа патрїа́рха ї҆ерꙋсали́мскагѡ">
Дне́сь во́дъ ѡ҆сщ҃а́етсѧ є҆стество̀, и҆ раздѣлѧ́етсѧ ї҆ѻрда́нъ, и҆ свои́хъ во́дъ возвраща́етъ стрꙋи҄, влⷣкꙋ зрѧ̀ кр҃ща́ема.
</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<VERSE Type="1" >
Сегѡ̀ ра́ди помѧнꙋ́хъ тѧ̀ ѿ землѝ ї҆ѻрда́нски и҆ є҆рмѡнїи́мски. 
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="12" Tone="3" Header="Тропарь Гла́съ г҃">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ чл҃вѣ́къ на рѣкꙋ̀ прише́лъ є҆сѝ, хрⷭтѐ цр҃ю̀, и҆ ра́бское кр҃ще́нїе прїѧ́ти тщи́шисѧ, бл҃же, ѿ прⷣте́чевꙋ рꙋкꙋ̀, грѣ҄хъ ра́ди на́шихъ, чл҃вѣколю́бче.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="2">
Ви́дѣша тѧ̀ во́ды, бж҃е, ви́дѣша тѧ̀ во́ды, и҆ ѹ҆боѧ́шасѧ.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="13" Tone="8" Header="Тропарь Гла́съ и҃ " Author="">
Ко гла́сꙋ вопїю́щагѡ въ пꙋсты́ни, ѹ҆гото́вайте пꙋ́ть гдⷭнь, прише́лъ є҆сѝ гдⷭи, зра́къ ра́бїй прїи́мъ, кр҃ще́нїѧ просѧ̀, не вѣ́дый грѣха̀. ви́дѣша тѧ̀ во́ды, и҆ ѹ҆боѧ́шасѧ. тре́петенъ бы́сть прⷣте́ча, и҆ возопѝ глаго́лѧ: ка́кѡ просвѣти́тъ свѣти́льникъ свѣ́та; ка́кѡ рꙋ́кꙋ положи́тъ ра́бъ на влⷣкꙋ; ѡ҆ст҃ѝ менѐ и҆ во́ды, сп҃се, взе́млѧй мї́ра грѣ́хъ.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="1P" Tone="4" Header="прокї́менъ, гла́съ д҃ ">
И҆ возгремѣ̀ съ нб҃сѐ гдⷭь, и҆ вы́шнїй дадѐ гла́съ.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="1P" >
Возлюблю̀ тѧ̀, гдⷭи, крѣ́посте моѧ̀: гдⷭь ѹ҆твержде́нїе моѐ.
</VERSE>

<IDIOMEL Type="31" Tone="8" Header="Тропарь Гла́съ и҃" Author="">
Прⷣте́чи и҆ крⷭти́телѧ и҆ прⷪро́ка, и҆ па́че всѣ́хъ почте́на прⷪро́къ, трепета́ше ны́нѣ рꙋка̀ десна́ѧ, є҆гда̀ ви́дѣ тебѐ а҆́гнца бж҃їѧ, ѡ҆чища́ющаго мї́рꙋ согрѣшє́нїѧ, и҆ по́двигомъ ѡ҆держи́мь вопїѧ́ше: не смѣ́ю прикоснꙋ́тисѧ, сло́ве, верхꙋ̀ твоемꙋ̀. са́мъ мѧ̀ ѡ҆свѧтѝ, и҆ просвѣтѝ, ще́дре, ты́ бо є҆сѝ живо́тъ и҆ свѣ́тъ, и҆ ми́ръ мї́рови.
</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<IDIOMEL Type="32" Tone="4" Header="Тропарь Гла́съ д҃">
Трⷪца бг҃ъ на́шъ, себѐ на́мъ дне́сь нераздѣ́льно ꙗ҆вѝ: и҆́бо ѻ҆ц҃ъ ꙗ҆вле́ннымъ свидѣ́тельствомъ сро́дства возгласѝ: дх҃ъ же голꙋби́нымъ ѡ҆́бразомъ сни́де съ нб҃съ: сн҃ъ, пречⷭтый ве́рхъ сво́й прⷣте́чи приклонѝ, и҆ кре́щьсѧ, человѣ́чество ѿ рабо́ты и҆зба́ви, ꙗ҆́кѡ чл҃вѣколю́бецъ.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="33" Tone="5" Header="Тропарь Гла́съ є҃" Author="">
Грѧды́й съ пло́тїю ко ї҆ѻрда́нꙋ, гдⷭи, крⷭти́тисѧ хотѧ̀ во ѡ҆́бразѣ чл҃вѣ́ка, животода́вче, да прельсти́вшихсѧ на́съ, ꙗ҆́кѡ бл҃гоꙋтро́бенъ, всѧ́кїѧ ко́зни и҆ сѣ́ти ѕмї́евы и҆зба́вивъ просвѣти́ши, ѿ ѻ҆ц҃а̀ свидѣ́тельствꙋемь: бж҃е́ственный же дх҃ъ голꙋби́нымъ ви́домъ тебѣ̀ предста̀: но вселѝ въ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ того̀, чл҃вѣколю́бче.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="3P" Tone="6" Header="прокї́менъ, гла́съ ѕ҃">
Ви́дѣша тѧ̀ во́ды, бж҃е, ви́дѣша тѧ̀ во́ды, и҆ ѹ҆боѧ́шасѧ.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="3P" >
Гла́сомъ мои́мъ ко гдⷭꙋ воззва́хъ, гла́сомъ мои́мъ къ бг҃ꙋ, и҆ внѧ́тъ мѝ.
</VERSE>
	
<IDIOMEL Type="61" Tone="8" Header="Тропарь Гла́съ и҃" Author="">
Та́кѡ глаго́летъ гдⷭь ко ї҆ѡа́ннꙋ: прⷪро́че, грѧдѝ крⷭти́ти менѐ, тебѐ созда́вшаго, и҆ просвѣща́ющаго бл҃года́тїю, и҆ ѻ҆чища́ющагѡ всѣ́хъ: прикосни́сѧ бж҃е́ственномꙋ моемꙋ̀ верхꙋ̀, и҆ не ѹ҆сꙋмни́сѧ. про́чее ѡ҆ста́ви ны́нѣ, и҆́бо и҆спо́лнити прїидо́хъ пра́вдꙋ всѧ́кꙋю. ты́ же не ѹ҆сꙋмни́сѧ ѿню́дъ, и҆́бо таѧ́щагосѧ въ вода́хъ бори́телѧ, кнѧ́зѧ тьмы̀ тщꙋ́сѧ погꙋби́ти, и҆збавлѧ́ѧ мї́ръ ѿ є҆гѡ̀ сѣ́тей ны́нѣ, подаѧ̀ ꙗ҆́кѡ чл҃вѣколю́бецъ живо́тъ вѣ́чный.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="62" Tone="6" Header="Тропарь гла́съ ѕ҃">
Дне́сь ѱало́мское прⷪро́чество коне́цъ прїѧ́ти спѣши́тъ: мо́ре бо, речѐ, ви́дѣ, и҆ побѣжѐ, ї҆ѻрда́нъ возврати́сѧ вспѧ́ть, ѿ лица̀ гдⷭнѧ, ѿ лица̀ бг҃а ї҆а́кѡвлѧ, прише́дша ѿ раба̀ прїѧ́ти кр҃ще́нїе: ꙗ҆́кѡ да и҆ мы̀ ї҆́дѡльскїѧ и҆змы́вшесѧ нечⷭтоты̀, просвѣти́мсѧ дꙋша́ми є҆гѡ̀ ра́ди.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="63" Tone="5" Header="Тропарь гла́съ є҃ " Author="">
Что̀ возвраща́еши твоѧ҄ во́ды, ѽ ї҆ѻрда́не; что̀ воспѧща́еши стрꙋи҄, и҆ не прехо́диши є҆́же по є҆стествꙋ̀ хожде́нїе; не мо́щно мѝ терпѣ́ти, речѐ, ѻ҆гнѧ̀ поѧда́ющагѡ мѧ̀. ѹ҆дивлѧ́юсѧ и҆ ѹ҆жаса́юсѧ кра́йнемꙋ схожде́нїю: ꙗ҆́кѡ не ѡ҆быко́хъ чи́стаго и҆змыва́ти, ни навыко́хъ безгрѣ́шнаго ѡ҆тира́ти: но ѡ҆сквернє́нныѧ сосꙋ́ды ѻ҆чища́ти, тє́рнїѧ попалѧ́ти мѝ согрѣше́нїй ѹ҆чи́тъ, и҆́же во мнѣ̀ кр҃ща́емый хрⷭто́съ. ї҆ѡа́ннъ свидѣ́тельствꙋетъ мѝ гла́съ сло́ва, вопїѧ̀: сѐ а҆́гнецъ бж҃їй взе́млѧй грѣхѝ мї́ра. томꙋ̀ вѣ́рнїи возопїи́мъ: ꙗ҆вле́йсѧ, бж҃е, въ на́ше сп҃се́нїе, сла́ва тебѣ̀.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="6P" Tone="4" Header="прокї́менъ, гла́съ д҃ ">
Въ мо́ри пꙋтїѐ твоѝ, и҆ стєзѝ твоѧ҄ въ вода́хъ мно́гихъ.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="6P" >
Гла́съ гро́ма твоегѡ̀ въ колесѝ.
</VERSE>

<IDIOMEL Type="91" Tone="7" Header="Тропарь Гла́съ з҃ " Author="">
Ѹ҆́жасъ бѣ̀ ви́дѣти, нб҃сѐ и҆ землѝ творца̀ на рѣцѣ̀ ѡ҆бна́жшагосѧ, и҆ кр҃ще́нїе ѿ раба̀ за на́ше сп҃се́нїе прїе́млющагѡ, ꙗ҆́кѡ раба̀, и҆ ли́цы а҆́гг҃льстїи дивлѧ́хꙋсѧ, стра́хомъ и҆ ра́достїю. съ ни́миже покланѧ́емсѧ тебѣ̀, сп҃сѝ на́съ гдⷭи.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="92" Tone="2" Header="Тропарь гла́съ в҃ ">
Є҆гда̀ къ себѣ̀ грѧдꙋ́ща предте́ча гдⷭа сла́вы, вопїѧ́ше, зрѧ̀: се́й и҆збавлѧ́ѧй мї́ра прїи́де, ѿ и҆стлѣ́нїѧ: се́й и҆збавлѧ́етъ на́съ ѿ ско́рби: се́й согрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе да́рꙋетъ ꙗ҆́кѡ бг҃ъ на землѝ, ѿ дв҃ы чтⷭыѧ прїи́де ми́лости ра́ди, и҆ вмѣ́стѡ рабѡ́въ, сы́ны бж҃їѧ содѣ́ловаетъ: вмѣ́стѡ же тьмы̀, просвѣща́етъ человѣ́чество водо́ю бж҃е́ственнагѡ кр҃ще́нїѧ є҆гѡ̀. про́чее прїиди́те, согла́снѡ того̀ да славосло́вимъ, со ѻ҆ц҃е́мъ и҆ со ст҃ы́мъ дх҃омъ.
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.1" Tone="5" Header="Тропарь гла́съ є҃" Author="">
Рꙋ́кꙋ твою̀ прикоснꙋ́вшꙋюсѧ пречⷭтомꙋ верхꙋ̀ влⷣчню,
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.2" Tone="5" Header="Тропарь гла́съ ѕ҃ " Author="">
съ не́юже и҆ пе́рстомъ того̀ на́мъ показа́лъ є҆сѝ, воздѣжѝ ѡ҆ на́съ къ немꙋ̀, крⷭти́телю, ꙗ҆́кѡ дерзнове́нїе и҆мѣ́ѧ мно́го: и҆́бо бо́лїй прⷪрѡ́къ всѣ́хъ ѿ негѡ̀ свидѣ́тельствованъ є҆сѝ. ѻ҆́чи же твоѝ па́ки всест҃а́го дх҃а ви́дѣвшыѧ, ꙗ҆́кѡ въ ви́дѣ голꙋби́нѣ соше́дша, воздви́гни къ немꙋ̀ крⷭти́телю, и҆ ми́лостива на́мъ содѣ́лай:
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.3" Tone="5" Header="Тропарь гла́съ ѕ҃ " Author="">
и҆ прїидѝ, ста́ни съ на́ми,
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.4" Tone="5" Header="Тропарь гла́съ ѕ҃ " Author="">
запеча́таѧй пѣ́нїе, и҆ предначина́ѧй торжество̀.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="9P" Tone="3" Header="прокї́менъ, гла́съ г҃">
Гдⷭь просвѣще́нїе моѐ, и҆ спаси́тель мо́й, когѡ̀ ѹ҆бою́сѧ;
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="9P">
Гдⷭь защи́титель живота̀ моегѡ̀, ѿ когѡ̀ ѹ҆страшꙋ́сѧ;
</VERSE>

</ROYALHOURS>
</SERVICE>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 1">
<SERVICE>
<ROYALHOURS>
</ROYALHOURS>
</SERVICE>
</LANGUAGE>
</COMMEMORATION>