<SERVICES>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<TEXT Value="<center><b>Then the Prayer of the First Hour:</b></center>
</br>
<b>Priest</b>:  O Christ, the True Light, Who enlightenest and sanctifiest every man that cometh into the world: Let the Light of Thy countenance be signed upon us, that in it we may see the Unapproachable Light, and guide our steps in the doing of Thy commandments, through the intercessions of Thy most pure Mother, and of all Thy saints.  Amen. 
</br>
<b>Choir <i>(Tone 8)</i></b>: To Thee, the Champion Leader, we Thy servants dedicate a feast of victory and of thanksgiving as ones rescued out of sufferings, O Theotokos: but as Thou art one with might which is invincible, from all dangers that can be do Thou deliver us, that we may cry to Thee: Rejoice, Thou Bride Unwedded!
</br>
Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen.
</br>	
Lord, have mercy. Lord, have mercy. Lord, have mercy.
</br>
Father (Master), bless.
</br>
<b>Priest</b>: May Christ our true God, through the intercessions of His most pure Mother, of our holy and God-bearing fathers, and of all the saints, have mercy on us and save us, for He is good and the Lover of mankind.
</br>
<b>Choir</b>:  Amen. Lord, have mercy. Lord, have mercy. Lord, have mercy."/>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 1">
<TEXT Value="<center><b>Prière de Prime</b></center>
</br>
<b>Priest</b>:  O Christ, the True Light, Who enlightenest and sanctifiest every man that cometh into the world: Let the Light of Thy countenance be signed upon us, that in it we may see the Unapproachable Light, and guide our steps in the doing of Thy commandments, through the intercessions of Thy most pure Mother, and of all Thy saints.  Amen. 
</br>
<b>Choir <i>(Tone 8)</i></b>: To Thee, the Champion Leader, we Thy servants dedicate a feast of victory and of thanksgiving as ones rescued out of sufferings, O Theotokos: but as Thou art one with might which is invincible, from all dangers that can be do Thou deliver us, that we may cry to Thee: Rejoice, Thou Bride Unwedded!
</br>
Gloire au Père et au Fils et au Saint-Esprit,
maintenant et toujours et aux siècles des siècles. Amen.
</br>	
Kyrie eleison. Kyrie eleison. Kyrie eleison.
</br>
Au nom du Seigneur, Père, bénis.
</br>
<b>Priest</b>: May Christ our true God, through the intercessions of His most pure Mother, of our holy and God-bearing fathers, and of all the saints, have mercy on us and save us, for He is good and the Lover of mankind.
</br>
<b>Choir</b>:  Amen. Kyrie eleison. Kyrie eleison. Kyrie eleison."/>
</LANGUAGE>
</SERVICES>