<SERVICES>
<!-- The Paschal Hours are invariant and the same for all of the Bright Week. They replace the First, Third, Sixth, and Ninth Hours, the Compline, and the Midnight Office -->
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<TEXT Value="&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;PASCHAL HOURS&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;BR&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;I&gt;Comment: This service replaces the First, Third, Sixth, and Ninth Hours, the Compline, and the Midnight Office during Bright Week.&lt;BR&gt;Source: http://www.orthodox.net/pascha/paschalhours.html&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;BR&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;B&gt;PRIEST:&lt;/B&gt; Blessed is our God, always, now and ever, and unto the ages of ages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;I&gt;&lt;small&gt;But a layman sayeth: Through the prayers of our holy fathers, O Lord Jesus Christ, our God, have mercy on us.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;&lt;B&gt;Choir: &lt;/B&gt;Amen. Christ is risen from the dead, conquering death by death, and on those in the tombs bestowing life.&lt;dd&gt;&lt;t&gt;Christ is risen from the dead, conquering death by death, and on those in the tombs bestowing life.&lt;dd&gt;Christ is risen from the dead, conquering death by death, and on those in the tombs bestowing life.
&lt;dd&gt;Having beheld the resurrection of Christ, let us worship the holy Lord Jesus, the only Sinless One. We worship Thy cross, O Christ, and Thy holy Resurrection we hymn and glorify; for Thou art our God, and we know none other beside Thee, and we call upon Thy name. O come, all ye faithful, let us worship Christ's holy Resurrection, for behold, through the Cross joy hath come to all the world. Ever blessing the Lord, we hymn His Resurrection; for, having endured crucifixion, He hath destroyed death by death.
&lt;dd&gt;Having beheld the resurrection of Christ, let us worship the holy Lord Jesus, the only Sinless One. We worship Thy cross, O Christ, and Thy holy Resurrection we hymn and glorify; for Thou art our God, and we know none other beside Thee, and we call upon Thy name. O come, all ye faithful, let us worship Christ's holy Resurrection, for behold, through the Cross joy hath come to all the world. Ever blessing the Lord, we hymn His Resurrection; for, having endured crucifixion, He hath destroyed death by death.
&lt;dd&gt;Having beheld the resurrection of Christ, let us worship the holy Lord Jesus, the only Sinless One. We worship Thy cross, O Christ, and Thy holy Resurrection we hymn and glorify; for Thou art our God, and we know none other beside Thee, and we call upon Thy name. O come, all ye faithful, let us worship Christ's holy Resurrection, for behold, through the Cross joy hath come to all the world. Ever blessing the Lord, we hymn His Resurrection; for, having endured crucifixion, He hath destroyed death by death.&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;B&gt;The Hypakoe (Tone 8)&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Forestalling the dawn, the women came with Mary, and found the stone rolled away from the sepulchre, and heard from the angel: why seek ye among the dead, as though He were a mortal, Him Who liveth in everlasting light? Behold the grave-clothes. Go quickly and proclaim to the world that the Lord is risen and hath slain death. For He is the Son of God Who saveth mankind.&lt;center&gt;&lt;B&gt;Kontakion (Tone 8)
&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;BR&gt;Though Thou didst descend into the grave, O Immortal One, yet didst Thou destroy the power of hades. And didst arise as victor, O Christ God, calling to the myrrh-bearing women: Rejoice! And giving peace unto Thine apostles: Thou Who dost grant resurrection to the fallen. &lt;center&gt;&lt;B&gt;Troparia (Tone 8)&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;BR&gt;In the grave bodily, but in hades with Thy soul as God: in Paradise with the thief, and on the throne with the Father and the Spirit wast Thou Who fillest all things, O Christ the Inexpressible.
&lt;BR&gt; Glory to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit.&lt;BR&gt;How life-giving, how much more beautiful than Paradise, and truly more resplendent than any royal palace was Thy tomb shown to be, O Christ, the source of our resurrection.&lt;BR&gt;Both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen.
&lt;BR&gt; O sanctified and divine tabernacle of the Most High, rejoice! For through thee, O Theotokos, joy is given to them that cry: Blessed art thou among women, O all-spotless Lady.&lt;BR&gt; Lord, have mercy. &lt;I&gt;(Forty times.)&lt;/I&gt;
&lt;BR&gt;Glory to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen.&lt;BR&gt;
More honourable than the Cherubim, and beyond compare more glorious than the Seraphim, who without corruption gavest birth to God the Word, the very Theotokos, thee do we magnify.&lt;BR&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;&lt;I&gt;If a Priest Serves: &lt;/I&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;B&gt;Reader:&lt;/B&gt; In the name of the Lord, Father bless.&lt;dd&gt;&lt;B&gt;PRIEST&lt;/B&gt;: O Lord Jesus Christ our God, for the sake of the prayers of Thy most pure Mother, of our holy and God-bearing fathers, and of all the saints, have mercy on us.&lt;dt&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;I&gt;If a Reader's service: &lt;/I&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;B&gt;Reader:&lt;/B&gt; O Lord bless.&lt;BR&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;&lt;B&gt;Choir:&lt;/B&gt;Amen. Christ is risen from the dead, conquering death by death, and on those in the tombs bestowing life. &lt;dd&gt; Christ is risen from the dead, conquering death by death, and on those in the tombs bestowing life.&lt;dd&gt;Christ is risen from the dead, conquering death by death, and on those in the tombs bestowing life. &lt;dd&gt;Glory to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen.&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;&lt;dt&gt;&lt;I&gt;If a Priest Serves: &lt;/I&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;B&gt;Reader:&lt;/B&gt; Father bless.&lt;dd&gt;&lt;B&gt;PRIEST:&lt;/B&gt; May Christ our true God, Who rose from the dead, and conquered death by death and on those in the tombs bestowed life, through the intercessions of His most Pure Mother, and of all the saints have mercy on us and save us, for He is good and the Lover of mankind.&lt;dt&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;I&gt;If a Reader's service:&lt;/I&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;B&gt;Reader:&lt;/B&gt; O Lord bless!&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/dl&gt;" />
</LANGUAGE>
</SERVICES>