<COMMONPRAYER>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<HEADER Value="Psalm 5" />
<TEXT Value="Unto my words give ear, O Lord, hear my cry. Attend unto the voice of my supplication, O my King and my God; for unto Thee will I pray, O Lord. In the morning shalt Thou hear my voice. In the morning shall I stand before Thee, and Thou shalt look upon me; for not a God that wiliest iniquity art Thou. He that worketh evil shall not dwell near Thee nor shall transgressors abide before Thine eyes.  Thou hast hated all them that work iniquity; Thou shalt destroy all them that speak a lie.  A man that is bloody and deceitful shall the Lord abhor.  But as for me, in the multitude of Thy mercy shall I go into Thy house; I shall worship toward Thy holy temple in fear of Thee.  O Lord, guide me in the way of Thy righteousness; because of mine enemies, make straight my way before Thee, For in their mouth there is no truth; their heart is vain. Their throat is an open sepulcher, with their tongues have they spoken deceitfully; judge them, O God.  Let them fall down on account of their own devisings; according to the multitude of their ungodliness, cast them out, for they have embittered Thee, O Lord. And let all them be glad that hope in Thee; they shall rejoice, and Thou shalt dwell among them. And all shall glory in Thee that love Thy name, for Thou shalt bless the righteous. O Lord, as with a shield of Thy good pleasure hast Thou crowned us."/>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 1">
<HEADER Value="Psaume 5" />
<TEXT Value="Prête l’oreille à mes paroles, Seigneur, comprends mon cri. Sois attentif à la voix de ma supplication, ô mon Roi et mon Dieu, car c’est toi que je prie, Seigneur. Au matin, tu exauceras ma voix ; au matin, je me présenterai devant toi, et tu poseras sur moi ton regard. Car tu n’es pas un Dieu qui aime l’iniquité,
le méchant n’habitera pas auprès de toi, et les pécheurs ne tiendront pas devant ton regard. Tu hais tous ceux qui commettent l’iniquité, et tu fais périr ceux qui disent le mensonge ; L’homme de sang et de ruse, le Seigneur le hait. Pour moi, en l’abondance de ta miséricorde, j’entrerai dans ta maison ; vers ton saint temple j’adorerai, pénétré de ta crainte. Seigneur, conduis-moi dans ta justice, à cause de mes ennemis : rends droite ma voie en ta présence. Car la vérité n’est pas dans leur bouche, leur cœur est vain ; leur gosier est un sépulcre béant, ils rusent avec leur langue. Juge-les, ô Dieu, qu’ils échouent dans leurs desseins. Selon la multitude de leurs impiétés, chasse-les, car ils t’ont irrité, Seigneur. Et qu’ils se réjouissent, tous ceux qui espèrent en toi, éternellement ils seront dans l’allégresse et tu habiteras en eux ; et tous ceux qui aiment ton Nom se glorifieront en toi. Car tu béniras le juste ; Seigneur, comme d’un bouclier tu nous as couronnés de ta enveillance."/>
</LANGUAGE>
</COMMONPRAYER>