<SERVICES>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<TEXT Value="Lord, have mercy. <b><i>(Forty times.)</i></b>
</br>
<center><b>And the Prayer of the Hours:</b></center>
<p>Thou Who at all times and at every hour, in heaven and on earth, art worshipped and glorified, O Christ God, Who art long-suffering, plenteous in mercy, most compassionate, Who lovest the righteous and hast mercy on sinners; Who callest all men to salvation through the promise of good things to come: Receive, O Lord, our prayers at this hour, and guide our life toward Thy commandments. Sanctify our souls, make chaste our bodies, correct our thoughts, purify our intentions, and deliver us from every sorrow, evil, and pain.  Compass us about with Thy holy angels, that, guarded and guided by their array, we may attain to the unity of the faith and to the knowledge of Thine unapproachable glory: For blessed art Thou unto the ages of ages. Amen.</p>
Lord, have mercy. Lord, have mercy. Lord, have mercy.
</br>
Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen.
<p>More honorable than the cherubim and beyond compare more glorious than the seraphim; who without corruption gavest birth to God the Word, the very Theotokos, thee do we magnify.</p> 
In the name of the Lord, father (master) bless.
</br>
<b>Priest</b>: God be gracious unto us and bless us, and cause Thy face to shine upon us and have mercy on us.
</br>
<b>Reader</b>: Amen.<BR>"/>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 1">
<TEXT Value="Kyrie eleison. <b><i>(Quarante fois.)</i></b>
</br>
<center><b>Prière des heures</b></center>
<p>En tout temps et à toute heure, au ciel et sur terre,
tu es adoré et glorifié, ô Christ notre Dieu,
le longanime, le riche en pitié, le très miséricordieux.
Toi qui aimes les justes et qui fais grâce aux pécheurs,
et qui appelles tous les hommes au salut
par la promesse des biens à venir,
toi-même, Seigneur, à cette heure, accueille nos requêtes
et dirige notre vie selon tes commandements.
Sanctifie nos âmes, rends chastes nos corps ;
redresse nos raisonnements, purifie nos pensées ;
et délivre-nous de toute tribulation, de tout mal et de toute douleur.
Entoure-nous de tes saints anges afin que,
gardés sous leur protection et guidés par eux,
nous parvenions à l'unité de la foi et à la connaissance de ta gloire inaccessible ;
car tu es béni dans les siècles des siècles. Amen.</p>
Kyrie eleison. Kyrie eleison. Kyrie eleison.
</br>
Gloire au Père et au Fils et au Saint-Esprit,
maintenant et toujours et aux siècles des siècles. Amen.
<p>Toi plus vénérable que les Chérubins,
et incomparablement plus glorieuse que les Séraphins,
qui sans tache enfantas Dieu le Verbe,
toi véritablement la Mère de Dieu, nous t'exaltons.</p> 
Au nom du Seigneur, Père, bénis.
</br>
<b>Prêtre </b>:<i>(Le Prêtre donne sa bénédiction.)</i>
</br>
<b>Reader</b>: Amen. 
</br>"/>
</LANGUAGE>
</SERVICES>