<SERVICES>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<TEXT Value="Both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen.
</br>
<center><b>Theotokion</b></center>
<p>What shall we call thee, O thou who art full of grace? Heaven, for from thee hast dawned forth the Sun of Righteousness. Paradise, for from thee bath blossomed forth the flower of immortality. Virgin, for thou hast remained incorrupt. Pure Mother, for thou hast held in thy holy embrace the Son, the God of all. Do thou entreat Him to save our souls.</p>
<p>My steps do Thou direct according to thy saying, and let no iniquity have dominion over me. Deliver me from the false accusations of men, and I will keep Thy commandments. Make Thy face to shine upon Thy servant, and teach me Thy statutes.</p>
<p>Let my mouth be filled with Thy praise, that I may hymn Thy glory and Thy majesty all the day long.</p>
Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us.</br>
Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us.</br> 
Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us.</br> 
Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen. 
</br> 
<p>O Most Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Lord, blot out our sins. O Master, pardon our iniquities. O Holy One, visit and heal our infirmities for Thy name's sake.</p>
Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy.
</br> 
Glory to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen. 
<p>Our Father, Who art in the Heavens, hallowed be Thy Name. Thy Kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily bread, and forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors; and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.</p> 
</br> 
<b>Priest</b>:  For Thine is the kingdom and the power, and the glory: of the Father and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, now and ever, and unto the ages of ages.
</br>
<b>Reader</b>: Amen." Cmd="!(nday > -50 &amp;&amp; nday < 0)"/>
<TEXT Value="Both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen.
</br>
<center><b>Theotokion</b></center>
<p>What shall we call thee, O thou who art full of grace? Heaven, for from thee hast dawned forth the Sun of Righteousness. Paradise, for from thee bath blossomed forth the flower of immortality. Virgin, for thou hast remained incorrupt. Pure Mother, for thou hast held in thy holy embrace the Son, the God of all. Do thou entreat Him to save our souls.</p>
<p>My steps do Thou direct according to thy saying, and let no iniquity have dominion over me. My steps do Thou direct according to thy saying, and let no iniquity have dominion over me.</p><p>Deliver me from the false accusations of men, and I will keep Thy commandments. Deliver me from the false accusations of men, and I will keep Thy commandments.</p><p>Make Thy face to shine upon Thy servant, and teach me Thy statutes. Make Thy face to shine upon Thy servant, and teach me Thy statutes.</p>
<p>Let my mouth be filled with Thy praise, that I may hymn Thy glory and Thy majesty all the day long. Let my mouth be filled with Thy praise, that I may hymn Thy glory and Thy majesty all the day long. Let my mouth be filled with Thy praise, that I may hymn Thy glory and Thy majesty all the day long.</p>
<p>Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us.</br>
Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us.</br> 
Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us.</br> 
Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen. </p>
<p>O Most Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Lord, blot out our sins. O Master, pardon our iniquities. O Holy One, visit and heal our infirmities for Thy name's sake.</p>
Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy.
</br> 
Glory to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen. 
<p>Our Father, Who art in the Heavens, hallowed be Thy Name. Thy Kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily bread, and forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors; and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.</p> 
</br> 
<b>Priest</b>:  For Thine is the kingdom and the power, and the glory: of the Father and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, now and ever, and unto the ages of ages.
</br>
<b>Reader</b>: Amen." Cmd="(nday > -50 &amp;&amp; nday < 0)"/><!-- It looks like a certain part of the Theotokion is repeated more time during Lent. -->
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 1">
<TEXT Value="Maintenant et toujours et aux siècles des siècles. Amen.
</br>
<center><b>Théotokion</b></center>
<p>What shall we call thee, O thou who art full of grace? Heaven, for from thee hast dawned forth the Sun of Righteousness. Paradise, for from thee bath blossomed forth the flower of immortality. Virgin, for thou hast remained incorrupt. Pure Mother, for thou hast held in thy holy embrace the Son, the God of all. Do thou entreat Him to save our souls.</p>
<p>My steps do Thou direct according to thy saying, and let no iniquity have dominion over me. Deliver me from the false accusations of men, and I will keep Thy commandments. Make Thy face to shine upon Thy servant, and teach me Thy statutes.</p>
<p>Let my mouth be filled with Thy praise, that I may hymn Thy glory and Thy majesty all the day long.</p>
Saint Dieu, Saint Fort, Saint Immortel, aie pitié de nous.</br>
Saint Dieu, Saint Fort, Saint Immortel, aie pitié de nous.</br> 
Saint Dieu, Saint Fort, Saint Immortel, aie pitié de nous.</br> 
Gloire au Père et au Fils et au Saint-Esprit,
maintenant et toujours et aux siècles des siècles. Amen. 
</br> 
<p>Trinité toute-sainte, aie pitié de nous.
Seigneur, agrée l'expiation de nos péchés.
Maître, pardonne-nous nos iniquités.
Saint, visite-nous et guéris nos infirmités, à cause de ton nom.</p>
Kyrie eleison. Kyrie eleison. Kyrie eleison.
</br> 
Notre Père qui es aux cieux, que ton nom soit sanctifié,
que ton règne arrive, que ta volonté soit faite sur la terre comme au ciel.
Donne-nous aujourd'hui notre pain substantiel, remets-nous nos dettes
comme nous remettons aussi à nos débiteurs,
et ne nous soumets pas à l'épreuve, mais délivre-nous du malin.</p> 
</br> 
<b>Prêtre </b>:  Car c'est à toi qu'appartiennent le règne, la puissance et la gloire,
Père, Fils et Saint-Esprit, maintenant et toujours et aux siècles des siècles. 
</br>
<b>Lecteur </b>: Amen."/>
</LANGUAGE>
</SERVICES>