<SERVICES>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<TEXT Value="<B><center> Prayer of St. Ephraim </center>Priest:</B> O Lord and Master of my life, a spirit of idleness, despondency, ambition, and idle talking give me not.<I> (Prostration)</I><BR>But rather a spirit of chastity, humble-mindedness, patience, and love bestow upon me Thy servant.<I> (Prostration)</I><BR>Yea, O Lord King, grant me to see my own failings and not condemn my brother; for blessed art Thou unto the ages of ages.Amen.<I> (Prostration)</I><BR>O God, cleanse me a sinner.  <I>(Twelve times, with a bow after each.)</I><BR>O Lord and Master of my life, a spirit of idleness, despondency, ambition, and idle talking give me not.  But rather a spirit of chastity, humble-mindedness, patience, and love bestow upon me Thy servant.  Yea, O Lord King, grant me to see my own failings and not condemn my brother; for blessed art Thou unto the ages of ages.<I> (Prostration)</I><BR><B>Reader:</B>  Amen.  Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us. Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us. Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, have mercy on us.<BR>Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen. <BR>
O Most Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Lord, blot out our sins. O Master, pardon our iniquities. O Holy One, visit and heal our infirmities for Thy name's sake. <BR>Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy.<BR>Glory to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy Spirit, both now and ever, and unto the ages of ages. Amen. <BR>Our Father, Who art in the Heavens, hallowed be Thy Name. Thy Kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily bread, and forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors; and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one. <BR><B>Priest:</B> For Thine is the Kingdom, and the power, and the glory; of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit, now and ever, and unto the ages of ages.<BR><B>Reader:</B> Amen. Lord, have mercy. <I>(Twelve times)</I>"/>
</LANGUAGE>
</SERVICES>