<!-- service file for SID B_3174 (The Forefeast of Christmas) (The days before Christmas) -->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="Commemeration.xsl" ?>

<COMMEMORATION>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME>Forefeast of the Nativity</NAME>
<SERVICE>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4" Author="Unknown" Header="Tropar of the Forefeast, Tone 4">
And it came to pass that Mary was enrolled with Joseph the old man, in Bethlehem, since she was
of the seed of David, and was great with the Lamb, without seed. And when the time for delivery
drew near, and they had no place in the village, the cave did appear to the Queen as a delightful
palace. Verily, Christ shall be born, raising the likeness that fell of old.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="3" Author="Unknown" Header="Kondak of the Forefeast, Tone 3">
Today the Virgin cometh to the cave where she will give birth in an ineffable manner to the Word
Who is before all the ages. Rejoice, therefore, O universe, when thou hearest it heralded: Glorify
Him, with the angels and the shepherds, Who chose to be seen as a new-born babe, the God Who
is before all the ages.
</KONTAKION>
</SERVICE>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 2 || LS == 3">
<NAME>Предпра́зднство</NAME>
<SERVICE>
	<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4" Author="Traditional" Header="Тропа́рь предпра́зднства, гла́съ д҃ ">
Написова́шесѧ и҆ногда̀ со ста́рцемъ ї҆ѡ́сифомъ, ꙗ҆́кѡ ѿ сѣ́мене дв҃дова, въ виѳлее́мѣ мр҃їа́мъ, чревоносѧ́щи безсѣ́менное рожде́нїе: наста́ же вре́мѧ ржⷭтва̀, и҆ мѣ́сто ни є҆ди́но же бѣ̀ ѻ҆бита́лищꙋ: но ꙗ҆́коже кра́снаѧ пала́та, верте́пъ цр҃и́цѣ показа́шесѧ. хрⷭто́съ ражда́етсѧ, пре́жде па́дшїй воскр҃си́ти ѡ҆́бразъ. 
	</TROPARION>
	<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="3" Header="Конда́къ предпра́зднства, гла́съ г҃ ">
Дв҃а дне́сь превѣ́чное сло́во въ верте́пѣ грѧде́тъ роди́ти неизрече́ннѡ: ликꙋ́й вселе́ннаѧ ѹ҆слы́шавши, просла́ви со а҆́гг҃лы и҆ па́стырьми хотѧ́щаго ꙗ҆ви́тисѧ, ѻ҆троча̀ мла́до превѣ́чнаго бг҃а.
	</KONTAKION>
</SERVICE>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == -2">
<!-- Greek -->
<SERVICE>
	<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4" Author="Traditional" Header="Ἦχος πλ. δ'">
Ἀπεγράφετο ποτέ, σὺν τῷ πρεσβύτῃ Ἰωσήφ, ὡς ἐκ σπέρματος Δαυΐδ, ἐν Βηθλεὲμ ἡ Μαριάμ, κυοφοροῦσα τὴν ἄσπορον κυοφορίαν. Ἐπέστη δὲ καιρὸς ὁ τῆς γεννήσεως, καὶ τόπος ἦν οὐδεὶς τῷ καταλύματι· ἀλλ' ὡς τερπνὸv παλάτιοv, τὸ Σπήλαιοv τῇ Βασιλίδι ἐδείκνυτο. Χριστὸς γεννᾶται, τὴν πρὶv πεσοῦσαν, ἀναστήσων εἰκόνα.
	</TROPARION>
	<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="3" Header="">
H παρθένος σήμερον, τὸν προαιώνιον Λόγον, ἐν σπηλαίῳ ἔρχεται, ἀποτεκεῖν ἀπορρήτως. Χόρευε ἡ οἰκουμένη ἀκουτισθεῖσα· δόξασον μετὰ Ἀγγέλων καὶ τῶν Ποιμένων, βουληθέντα ἐποφθῆναι, παιδίον νέον, τὸν πρὸ αἰώνων Θεόν.
	</KONTAKION>
</SERVICE>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 1">
<SERVICE>
<ROYALHOURS>
</ROYALHOURS>
</SERVICE>
</LANGUAGE>
</COMMEMORATION>