<COMMONPRAYER>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<HEADER Value="Psalm 89" />
<TEXT Value="Lord, Thou hast been our refuge in generation and generation.  Before the mountains came to be and the earth was formed and the world, even from everlasting to everlasting art Thou.  Turn not man away unto lowliness; yea, Thou hast said: Turn back ye sons of men.  For a thousand years in Thine eyes, O Lord, are but as yesterday that is past, and as a watch in the night. Things of no account shall their years be; in the morning like grass shall man pass away.  In the morning shall he bloom and pass away. In the evening shall he fall and grow withered and dry.  For we have fainted away in Thy wrath, and in Thine anger have we been troubled.  Thou hast set our iniquities before us; our lifespan is in the light of Thy countenance.  For all our days are faded away, and in Thy wrath are we fainted away; our years have, like a spider, spun out their tale.  As for the days of our years, in their span, they be threescore years and ten.  And if we be in strength, mayhap fourscore years; and what is more than these is toil and travail.  For mildness is come upon us, and we shall be chastened.  Who knoweth the might of Thy wrath? And out of fear of Thee, who can recount Thine anger?  So make Thy right hand known to me, and to them that in their heart are instructed in wisdom.  Return, O Lord; how long? And be Thou entreated concerning Thy servants.  We were filled in the morning with Thy mercy, O Lord, and we rejoiced and were glad.  In all our days, let us be glad for the days wherein Thou didst humble us, for the years wherein we saw evils.  And look upon Thy servants, and upon Thy works, and do Thou guide their sons.  And let the brightness of the Lord our God be upon us, and the works of our hands do Thou guide aright upon us, yea, the works of our hands do Thou guide aright."/>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 1">
<HEADER Value="Psaume 89" />
<TEXT Value="Seigneur, tu as été pour nous un refuge de génération en génération. 
Avant que les montagnes soient nées, que la terre et le monde aient été formés, de l’éternité à l’éternité tu es. Ne rejette pas l’homme dans l’humiliation, mais dis : Revenez, fils des hommes. Car mille ans sont à tes yeux comme le jour d’hier qui n’est plus comme une veille de la nuit. C’est peu de choses que les années de l’homme ; en un matin elles passent comme l’herbe, le matin elle fleurit, et elle passe, le soir elle se flétrit, durcit et se dessèche. Car nous avons défailli sous ta colère,
nous avons été troublés par ta fureur. Tu as mis nos iniquités devant toi, notre existence à la lumière de ta face. C’est pourquoi tous nos jours se sont évanouis,
et nous avons défailli sous ta colère ; nos années sont comme une toile d’araignée. Le temps de nos années fait soixante dix ans, pour les plus robustes, quatre-vingts,
et le surplus n’est que peine et douleur ; mais la douceur du Seigneur nous visite et nous enseigne. Qui connaît la puissance de ta colère, et, dans ta crainte, mesure ton courroux ? Fais-nous connaître ta droite, et qu’ainsi tes leçons rendent sages nos cœurs. Reviens, Seigneur ; jusques à quand ? Sois enclin à la pitié envers tes serviteurs. Nous avons été comblés de ta miséricorde au matin, et nous avons été dans la joie et l’allégresse, tous les jours de notre vie. Nous avons été remplis de joie,
à la place des jours où tu nous as humiliés, des années où nous connûmes le malheur. Jette les yeux sur tes serviteurs et sur tes œuvres, et guide leurs fils. Que la splendeur du Seigneur notre Dieu soit sur nous ; dirige d’en haut les œuvres de nos mains, dirige le travail de nos mains."/>
</LANGUAGE>
</COMMONPRAYER>