<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="   Воспоминание явления на небе Креста Господня в Иерусалиме (351)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   После кончины первого христианского благоверного императо- ра Константина Великого императорский престол занял его сын Констанций, который уклонился в ересь Ария, отрицавшего еди- носущие Сына Божия с Отцом. В утверждение святого Правосла- вия Господь явил в Иерусалиме дивное знамение. В дни Святой Пятидесятницы, 7 мая 351 года, в третьем часу утра на небе яви- лось изображение равноконечного Креста Господня, сиявшее неиз- реченным светом, превосходившим свет солнца. Свидетелем был весь народ, пораженный великим ужасом и удивлением. Явление знамения Креста началось над святой Голгофской горой, на кото- рой был распят Господь (Мф. 27, 32—33; Ин. 19, 17, 41; Евр. 13, 12), и достигало горы Елеонской (Ин. 8, 1; 18, 2), отстоящей от Голгофы на расстоянии 15 стадий. Знамение переливалось всеми цветами радуги и привлекло к себе взоры всех людей. Многие люди, оставив свои дела, выходили из домов и со страхом созер- цали чудное явление. Потом многочисленные толпы жителей Иеру- салима с трепетом и радостью поспешили ко святому храму Воск- ресения.    О совершившемся чудесном явлении знамения Креста Святей- ший Патриарх Иерусалимский Кирилл (350—387) известил посла- нием императора Констанция, увещевал его обратиться к право- славной вере. Историк Древней Церкви Созомен свидетельствует, что через это явление Святого Креста многие иудеи и еллины при- шли к истинной вере, покаявшись Христу Богу, и приняли Святое Крещение. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Крⷭта̀ твоегѡ̀ ѡ҆́бразъ ны́нѣ па́че со́лнца возсїѧ̀, є҆го́же горы̀ ст҃ы́ѧ да́же до ло́бнагѡ мѣ́ста просте́рлъ є҆сѝ, и҆ въ не́мъ твою̀ сп҃се, крѣ́пость ѹ҆ѧсни́лъ є҆сѝ, си́мъ ѹ҆крѣплѧ́ѧ и҆ вѣ҄рныѧ на́шѧ царѝ: ꙗ҆̀же и҆ сп҃са́й вы́нꙋ въ ми́рѣ, мл҃твами бцⷣы хрⷭтѐ бж҃е, и҆ сп҃сѝ на́съ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Ѿве́рзый нб҃са̀ заключє́ннаѧ, на нб҃сѝ пресвѣ҄тлыѧ лꙋчѝ, на землѝ возсїѧ̀ пречⷭтый крⷭтъ: тѣ́мже сїѧ́нїе є҆гѡ̀ дѣ́йства прїе́мше, къ незаходи́момꙋ наставлѧ́емсѧ свѣ́тꙋ, и҆ во бране́хъ и҆́мамы є҆го̀ ѻ҆рꙋ́жїе ми́ра непобѣди́мꙋю побѣ́дꙋ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Remembrance of the Appearance in the Heavens of the Cross of the Lord at Jerusalem (351)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Remembrance of the Appearance in the Heavens of the Cross of the Lord at Jerusalem (351): After the death of the first Christian emperor, Constantine the Great, the imperial throne was occupied by his son Constantius, who inclined towards the heresy of Arius, which denied the one self-same essence of the Son of God with the Father. In the reaffirming of holy Orthodoxy, the Lord manifest at Jerusalem a wondrous sign. On the day of Holy Pentecost, 7 May 351, at the third hour of the morning in the heavens there appeared the image of the equal-proportioned Cross of the Lord, shining with an inexpressible light, and brighter than the light of the sun. All the people were eye-witness to this, and they were struck with great dread and amazement. The appearance of the Sign of the Cross began over holy Mount Golgotha, whereupon it was that the Lord had been crucified (Mt. 27: 32-33; Jn. 19: 17, 41; Heb. 13: 12), and it reached to the Mount of Olives (Jn. 8: 1; 18: 1-2), extending from Golgotha a distance of 15 stadia. The Sign was transfused with all the colours of the rainbow and it caught the sight of all the people. Many of the people, leaving off from whatever they were doing, went outside the houses and with awe stood contemplating the wondrous sign. Then a numerous throng of the people of Jerusalem with trembling and joy hastened to the holy Church of the Resurrection. 	The holy Jerusalem Patriarch Cyril (350-387) advised the emissary of the emperor Constantius about this miraculous occurrence of the appearance of the Sign of the Cross, and he urged him to return to the Orthodox faith. And Sozomen, an historian of the Ancient Church, likewise testifies, that through this appearance of the Holy Cross many of the Jews and pagan Greeks came to the true faith, repenting in Christ God, and accepted Holy Baptism.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
The image of Thy Cross hath now shone forth more brightly than the sun,/ and Thou hast extended it from the holy mountain to the place of the skull,/ and therein hast revealed Thy might, O Savior./ Strengthening all faithful Orthodox Christians thereby, O Christ God,// save them ever in peace, and by the supplications of the Theotokos do Thou also save us.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
The all-pure Cross, which opened the heavens which were shut,/ hath shed upon the earth all-radiant heavenly beams;/ wherefore, receiving the effulgence of its activity/we are guided to the never-waning Light;// and amid battles we have it as a weapon of peace, and invincible trophy.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>