<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой мученик Христофор"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
    Святой мученик Христофор жил в III веке и пострадал около 250 года, при императоре Декии (249—251). О жизни и чудесах его существует много различных сказаний, память его чтится ив Восточной, и в Западной Церквах. (Память мученика Христофора особенно чтится в Испании, где к его молитвам прибегают при заразных болезнях.) О происхождении его говорится по-разному. По одним источникам — он происходил из хананеев, по другим — киноцефалов.     Святой Христофор был человеком высокого роста и необычай- ной силы, лицо же его было зверообразно. По преданию, святой Христофор первоначально имел красивую наружность, но, желая избегнуть соблазнов для себя и окружающих, просил Господа дать ему безобразное лицо, что и исполнилось. До своего Крещения он носил имя Репрев (негодный), что было связано с его обезоб-  раженной внешностью. Еще до Крещения Репрев исповедовал веру во Христа и обличал тех, кто преследовал христиан. За это он однажды был избит неким Вакхом и принял побои со смире-  нием. Вскоре после этого были присланы 200 воинов, чтобы при-  вести его, известного силача, к императору Декию. Репрев подчи-  нился без сопротивления. В пути произошли чудеса: сухая трость  в руке святого расцвела, по молитве его умножились хлебы, кото-  рых недоставало у путников, подобно умножению хлебов Спаси-  телем в пустыне. Воины, сопровождавшие Репрева, были пораже-  ны чудесами, уверовали во Христа и вместе с Репревом были кре-  щены антиохийским епископом Вавилой.      Когда святой Христофор был приведен к императору, тот ужас-  нулся его наружности и решил заставить его отречься от Христа  не насилием, а хитростью. Он призвал двух женщин-блудниц, Кал-  линикию и Акилину, приказал им склонить Христофора к отре-  чению от Христа и добиться согласия его принести жертву идолам.  Но женщины были сами обращены святым Христофором к вере  во Христа и, вернувшись к императору, объявили себя христиан-  ками, за что были подвергнуты жестоким истязаниям и скончались  мученицами. Декий приговорил к казни также посланных за свя-  тым Христофором воинов, которые уверовали во Христа. Импера-  тор приказал бросить мученика в медный раскаленный ящик  Однако святой Христофор не испытывал страданий и остался не-  вредим. После многих жестоких истязаний мученику наконец от- секли голову мечом. Это произошло в 250 году в Ликин. Своими чудесами святой мученик Христофор обратил ко Христу^ до 50 ты- сяч язычников, о чем свидетельствует святой Амвросий. Впослед- ствии мощи святого Христофора были перенесены в Толедо, а позд- нее—в аббатство Сен-Дени во Франции. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Ѻ҆де́ждами ѿ крове́й ѹ҆краша́ѧйсѧ гдⷭеви предстои́ши цр҃ю̀ си́лъ, хрїстофо́ре приснопа́мѧтне: ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже со безпло́тными и҆ мч҃нки пое́ши трист҃ы́мъ и҆ стра́шнымъ сладкопѣ́нїемъ. тѣ́мже мл҃твами твои́ми сп҃са́й ста́до твоѐ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyr Christopher"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyr Christopher lived during the III Century and suffered in about the year 250, during the reign of the emperor Decius (249-251). About his life and miracles there exist many various accounts, and his memory is venerated in both the Western and Eastern Churches. (The memory of the Martyr Christopher is especially venerated in Italy, where they recourse to him in prayer during times of contagious diseases). Various are the suggestions about his descent. According to some historians, he was descended from the Canaanites, according to others -- from &quot;Cynoscephalai&quot; [literally &quot;Dog-heads&quot;, located in Thessaly]. 	Saint Christopher was a man of great stature and unusual strength, and his face was brutish. By tradition, Saint Christopher at first possessed an handsome appearance, but wishing to avoid temptation for himself and others, he besought the Lord to give him an unseemly face, which was done. Until Baptism he had the name Reprebus (Reprobate) which was connected with his disfigured outer appearance. Even before Baptism, Reprebus confessed his faith in Christ and denounced those who persecuted Christians. For this he was once given a beating by a certain Bacchus, and he took the beating with humility. Because of his reknown strength, soon after this there came after him 200 soldiers, so as to bring him before the emperor Decius. Reprebus submitted without resistance. On the way miracles occurred: a dry stick blossomed in the hand of the saint, by his prayer bread-loaves were multiplied, and the travellers had no lack thereof, similar to the multiplication of loaves in the wilderness by the Saviour. The soldiers surrounding Reprebus were astonished at the miracles, -- they came to believe in Christ and together with Reprebus they were baptised by the Antioch Bishop Babylos. 	When Saint Christopher was brought before the emperor, the emperor became terrified by his appearance and decided to coerce him into renouncing Christ, not by force but by cunning. He summoned two profligate women, Callinika and Acelina, and commanded them to sway Christopher into a renunciation of Christ and gain his consent to offer sacrifice to idols. But the women were themselves converted by Saint Christopher to the faith in Christ, and having returned to the emperor, they declared themselves Christians, for which they were subjected to fierce beatings and died as martyrs. Decius sentenced to execution also the soldiers who had been sent after Saint Christopher, but who now believed in Christ. The emperor gave orders to throw the martyr into a red-hot metal box. But Saint Christopher did not experience any suffering and he remained unharmed. After many fierce torments they finally beheaded the martyr with a sword. This occurred in the year 250 in Lycia. By his miracles the holy Martyr Christopher converted to Christ as many as 50 thousand pagans, about which Saint Ambrose (of Milan) testifies to. The relics of Saint Christopher were later transferred to Toledo (Spain), and even later -- to the abbey of Sainte Denis in France.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Arrayed in vesture dyed with thine own blood,/ thou standest before the King of hosts, O ever-memorable Christopher;/ therefore, with the incorporeal ones and the martyrs thou dost sing thrice-holy and awesome melodies.// Wherefore, by thy supplication save thou thy flock.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>