<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой апостол Симон Зилот"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святой апостол Симон Зилот происходил из Каны Галилейской, был сыном святого Обручника Иосифа, по плоти братом Господа, и одним из 12-ти апостолов. Первое чудо, которое сотворил Спа- ситель,— претворение воды в вино, произошло в доме Симона: во время пира для гостей недостало вина. Тогда Господь, по пред- стательству Пресвятой Богоматери, претворил воду в вино. Пора- женный чудом, Симон всем сердцем и душой уверовал в Господа Иисуса как обетованного Мессию и, все оставив, последовал за Ним. Симон получил наименование «зилота», т. е. ревнителя. В день Пятидесятницы он принял вместе с другими Апостолами дар Святого Духа. Святой апостол Симон проповедовал учение Христово в Иудее, Египте, Ливии, Киринее и Британии. В Абхазии принял мученическую кончину, был распят на кресте. Погребен в городе Никопсии около Сухуми. Впоследствии (в XIX в.) на месте подвигов святого Апостола, близ Иверской горы, был соору- жен Новоафонский монастырь Симона Кананита. Доныне сохра- нилась пещера, в которой подвизался святой Апостол. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
А҆пⷭле ст҃ы́й сї́мѡне, молѝ млⷭтиваго бг҃а, да прегрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе пода́стъ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
И҆звѣ́стнѡ премꙋ́дрости ѹ҆чє́нїѧ въ дꙋша́хъ бл҃гоче́ствꙋющихъ поло́жшаго, во хвале́нїи ѹ҆бл҃жи́мъ, ꙗ҆́кѡ бг҃оглаго́ливаго всѝ сї́мѡна: прⷭто́лꙋ бо сла́вы ны́нѣ предстои́тъ, и҆ со безпло́тными весели́тсѧ, молѧ́сѧ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Apostle Simon Zelotes"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Apostle Simon Zelotes hailed from Cana of Galilee. He was a son of Joseph the Betrothed, and hence a brother of the Lord after the flesh, and he was also one of the 12 Apostles. The first miracle which the Saviour worked, -- the transforming of water into wine, occurred at the house of Simon: at the time of a wedding-feast there was insufficient wine for the guests. Then the Lord, at the prompting of the MostHoly Mother of God, transformed water into wine. Struck by the miracle, Simon with all his heart and soul believed in the Lord Jesus as the Promised Messiah and, having left behind everything, he followed after Him. Simon received the title &quot;Zelotes&quot;, i.e. a zealot, meaning a person who is zealous. On the day of Pentecost he received the gift of the Holy Spirit together with the other Apostles. The holy Apostle Simon preached the teaching of Christ at Judea, Egypt, Libya, Cyrenia and Britain. At Abkhazia he accepted a martyr&apos;s death, and was crucified on a cross. He was buried at the city of Nikopsia around Sukhum. Afterwards (in the XIX Century), at the place where the holy Apostle Simon asceticised near Mount Iveria, there was established the Novoathonite monastery of Simon the Canaanite. To the present day is preserved the cave wherein the holy Apostle Simon asceticised. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
O holy apostle Simon/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
In laudations let us all bless the divinely eloquent Simon,/ who hath diligently set the doctrines of wisdom in the hearts of the pious;/ for he standeth now before the throne of glory and dwelleth with the incorporeal ones,// praying unceasingly for us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>