<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой Мокий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
    Святой Мокий был пресвитером в Македонии, в городе Амфи- поле. Во время гонения на христиан императора Диоклитиана  (284—305) святой Мокий убеждал язычников, собравшихся для празднования языческому божеству Дионису (Бахусу), оставить беззаконные и скверные обычаи, сопровождавшие&apos;это торжество, покаяться, обратиться к Господу Иисусу Христу и очиститься во святом крещении. Святой был приведен на суд к правителю Лао- дикию, исповедал перед ним истинную веру, а на угрозы отвечал: «Смерть за Христа — великое приобретение для &quot;меня». Святого Мокия подвергли истязаниям, которые он переносил с дивным тер- пением, не переставая обличать нечестие идолопоклонников. При- веденный в капище Диониса, святой Именем Иисуса Христа сокру- шил идола, после чего был ввергнут в раскаленную печь, где ос- тался невредимым, а пламенем, вышедшим из печи, был сожжен правитель. Вновь назначенный начальник подверг святого Мокия жестоким истязаниям, которые он при помощи Божией стойко перенес; отданный на растерзание диким зверям, он остался не- вредимым—львы ложились у ног святого. Народ, вразумившись такими чудесами, стал требовать, чтобы мученика отпустили на сво- боду. Правитель распорядился отослать святого в город Перинф, а оттуда в Византию, где святой Мокий был казнен. Перед смертью он в молитве благодарил Господа, давшего ему силу до конца пройти мученический подвиг. «Господи, приими в мире дух мой», — были его последние слова, после чего ему отсекли голову. Святой Мокий скончался около 295 года. Впоследствии император Константин построил в честь священномученика Мокия храм и перенес в него святые мощи страстотерпца. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆ нра́вѡмъ прича́стникъ, и҆ прⷭто́лѡмъ намѣ́стникъ а҆пⷭлѡмъ бы́въ, дѣѧ́нїе ѡ҆брѣ́лъ є҆сѝ бг҃одохнове́нне, въ видѣ́нїѧ восхо́дъ: сегѡ̀ ра́ди сло́во и҆́стины и҆справлѧ́ѧ, и҆ вѣ́ры ра́ди пострада́лъ є҆сѝ да́же до кро́ве, сщ҃енномч҃нче мѡкї́е, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Воѡрꙋжи́всѧ щито́мъ вѣ́ры, нечести́выхъ ѡ҆полчє́нїѧ сте́рлъ є҆сѝ сщ҃енномч҃нче, и҆ вѣне́цъ ѿ хрⷭта̀ взѧ́лъ є҆сѝ мѡкї́е: тѣ́мъ и҆ со а҆́гг҃лы ра́дꙋѧсѧ, сп҃са́й ѿ бѣ́дъ пою́щыѧ тѧ̀, молѧ̀ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Saint Mokios"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Saint Mokios was a presbyter in Macedonia in the city of Amphypolis. During a time of persecution against Christians under the emperor Diocletian (284-305), Saint Mokios exhorted the pagans -- who had assembled for the pagan feast to the divinity Dionysos (Bacchus), to forsake iniquity and  the vile customs which accompanied this solemnity, and to repent and be converted to the Lord Jesus Christ and be cleansed through holy baptism. The saint was brought to trial to the governor of Laodiceia; he confessed before him the true faith, and against the threats he answered: &quot;My death for Christ -- is a great accomplishment for me&quot;. Saint Mokios was subjected to torture, which he bore with marvelous endurance, and in no wise ceasing to denounce the idol-worshippers. Taken to the pagan temple of Dionysos, the saint shattered the idols with the Name of Jesus Christ. After this he was put into a red-hot oven, where he remained unharmed, but the flames coming out of the oven scorched the governor. And again the assigned commander subjected Saint Mokios to fierce torture, which with the help of God he stoically endured; given for devouring by wild beasts, he remained unharmed -- the lions but lay down at the feet of the saint. The people, having witnessed such miracles, began to urge that the saint be set free. The governor ordered the saint to be sent to the city of Perinth, and from there to Byzantium, where Saint Mokios was executed. Before his death he gave thanks to the Lord, for having bestown upon him the strength to go to the very end with the act of martyrdom. &quot;Lord, receive my spirit in peace&quot;, -- were his last words, after which he was beheaded. Saint Mokios died in about the year 295. Later on, the emperor Constantine built a church in honour of the Priestmartyr Mokios and transferred his holy passion-bearing relics into it.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
As thou didst share in the ways of the apostles/ and didst occupy their throne,/ thou didst find thine activity to be a passage to divine vision,/ O divinely inspired one./ Wherefore, ordering the word of truth,/ thou didst suffer for the Faith even to the shedding of thy blood.// O hieromartyr Mocius, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Armed with the shield of faith,/ thou didst cut down legions of the ungodly,/ O hieromartyr Mocius,/ and hast received a crown from Christ;/ wherefore, rejoicing with the angels,/ from misfortunes save those who hymn thee,// praying unceasingly in beHalf of us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>