<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Иона, митрополит Московский и всея России"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святитель Иона, митрополит Московский и всея России чудо- творец ( { 31 марта 1461). Сведения о нем помещены 31 марта. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Ѿ ю҆́ности твоеѧ̀ ве́сь са́мъ себѐ гдⷭеви возложи́въ, въ мл҃твахъ, и҆ трꙋдѣ́хъ, и҆ въ постѣ́хъ ѡ҆́бразъ бы́въ добродѣ́тели: ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже ви́дѣвъ бг҃ъ твоѐ бл҃го́е произволе́нїе, а҆рхїере́а тѧ̀ и҆ па́стырѧ це́ркви свое́й ѹ҆строѧ́етъ. тѣ́мже и҆ по преставле́нїи, честно́е тѣ́ло твоѐ цѣ́ло и҆ нетлѣ́нно соблюде́сѧ, ї҆ѡ́но ст҃и́телю, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, да сп҃се́тъ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ ѿ младе́нства гдⷭеви порабо́тивъ себѐ мꙋ́дре, посто́мъ и҆ бдѣ́нїемъ тѣ́ло твоѐ ѹ҆дрꙋча́ѧ. тѣ́мже сосꙋ́дъ чи́стъ, и҆ до́мъ дх҃ꙋ прест҃о́мꙋ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ: сегѡ̀ ра́ди и҆ це́ркви свое́й тебѐ а҆рхїере́а и҆ па́стырѧ ѹ҆строѧ́етъ, ю҆́же до́брѣ ѹ҆па́съ ко гдⷭꙋ ѿхо́диши, є҆го́же возлюби́лъ є҆сѝ. тѣ́мъ мо́лимъ тѧ̀: помина́й на́съ, вѣ́рою чтꙋ́щихъ ст҃ꙋ́ю па́мѧть твою̀, да всѝ зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ ѻ҆́тче ї҆ѡ́но, ст҃и́телю всечестны́й. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Jona, Metropolitan of Moscow and Wonderworker of All Russia"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Jona, Metropolitan of Moscow and Wonderworker of All Russia (+31 March 1461) -- the account about him is located under 31 March.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Having dedicated thyself wholly to the Lord from thy youth, thou becamest a model of virtue in prayers, labors and fasting; wherefore, beholding thy goodly intent, God appointed thee the hierarch and pastor of His Church: and for this cause, thy precious body hath been preserved whole and incorrupt after thy repose. O holy hierarch Jonah, entreat Christ God, that He save our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
From childhood thou didst enslave thyself unto the Lord, O wise one, laying waste to thy body through fasting and the keeping of vigils; wherefore, thou wast shown to be the pure vessel and abode of the all-holy Spirit. For this cause He ordained thee as hierarch and pastor for His Church, and having tended it well, thou didst depart unto the Lord Whom thou didst love. We therefore beseech thee: Be thou mindful of us who honor thy holy memory with faith, that we may all cry aloud unto thee: Rejoice, O father Jonah, most honored and holy hierarch!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>