<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Иона Новгородский, архиепископ"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov">
В миру Иоанн. Родился в Новгороде в конце XIV в., рано осиротел. Еще в детстве он получил предсказание о своем святительстве от блаженного Михаила Клопского (+ ок. 1453-1456 гг.; память 11/24 января), которое исполнилось через пятьдесят лет.

Достигнув совершенного возраста, Иоанн принял монашество в Отенской пустыни. За святую жизнь братия избрала его игуменом, а в 1458 г. новгородцы пожелали иметь Иону своим архиепископом. Для своих пасомых святитель был пастырем и отцом и особенно заботился святой о вдовах и сиротах. Пользуясь любовью и уважением сограждан, не раз ходатайствовал святитель о мятежных новгородцах перед московским великим князем, утоляя его гнев, удерживал Новгород от союза с Литвой.
Святитель много заботился и о духовном просвещении своей паствы, и о строительстве храмов, не забыл он и Отенской пустыни. Он оказал большую помощь и содействие устройству Соловецкого монастыря: преподобному Зосиме (+ 1478 г.; память 17/30 апреля) святитель Иона выдал грамоту, по которой вместе с мирскими властями отдавал во владение новой обители весь Соловецкий остров.

Архиепископ Иона почил о Господе 5 ноября 1470 г. Нетленные мощи святителя прославились многочисленными чудотворениями.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆справле́нїе вѣ́ры, и҆ ѡ҆́бразъ кро́тости, и҆ ꙗ҆́коже са́дъ посредѣ̀ раѧ̀, прпⷣбными дѣ́лы твои́ми мї́ръ просвѣща́еши. и҆ сегѡ̀ ра́ди къ честнѣ́й ра́цѣ твое́й любо́вїю прикаса́емсѧ, и҆ вѣ́рнѡ вопїе́мъ: предста́ни въ по́мощь воспѣва́ющымъ па́мѧть твою̀ свѣтоно́снꙋю, ѻ҆́тче ї҆ѡ́но, и҆ молѝ сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Свы́ше прїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ бж҃е́ственнꙋю бл҃года́ть, хода́тайствовати бг҃ꙋ и҆ человѣ́кѡмъ, ꙗ҆́кѡ а҆рхїере́й возноше́нїе возносѧ̀, и҆ ми́ръ лю́демъ твои҄мъ сносѧ̀, и҆ ѻ҆би́лїе плодѡ́въ, ї҆ѡ́но бл҃же́нне: ты́ бо є҆сѝ вели́кагѡ нова́града похвала̀, и҆ сꙋ́щихъ ѡ҆ не́мъ ра́дость. 
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Repose of Our Father among the Saints Jonah, Archbishop of Novgorod, Wonderworker"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
       St. Jonah, in the world John, was born in Novgorod, in 14th Century and, having
been an orphan since childhood, was turned over to a certain deacon for his education.
In childhood he liked to read the Holy Scriptures more than to play with his friends.
Having reached maturity, John decided to take the way of salvation, according to
which he steadily went during all his life, and was tonsured in the Otensk Hermitage
(about 50 versts (33 miles) from Novgorod). Because of his holy life the monks of this
hermitage selected him to be their hegumen, and in 1458 the Novgorodians selected
him to be their archbishop. Having become the Archbishop of Novgorod, Jonah
wisely led his flock and was the good shepherd, "leading his flock to faith by true
words", "father-like providing for widows and orphans, taking out affronts, softening
enmity, making peace". His "meekness and good nature" surprised pious autocrats and
he received their love and respect, so they "always were ready to follow" the bishop
"needing prayers and blessings" from him. St. Jonah reposed in peace in 1470.
Wonderful was the deep respect of contemporaries for St. Jonah. Considering his
holiness and wonderworking, they left his coffin open, and the body of the hierarch
remained uncorrupt. His relics now rest in the Otensk Monastery (see Novgorod
Diocese). The Moscow Council in 1540 established the feast day for St. Jonah. The
Holy Church glorifies him, as "the intercessor for orphans and widows, the comforter
of the grieving, the helper of those coming to him and the warm defender and instiller
of tranquility and mercy to the novices and autocratic sovereigns calling on him".

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
A rule of faith and an image of meekness, and like the garden in the middle of paradise thou enlightenest the world by thy righteous deeds, and therefore we lovingly venerate thine honoured bier and faithfully cry out:
intercede for those who hymn your light-bearing memory, O Father Jonah, and pray that our souls may be saved.

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
Thou didst accept from on high divine grace to intercede between God and men, as a bishop raising up offerings and bringing down peace and an abundance of fruits to thy people, O blessed Jonah,
for thou art the praise of Great Novgorod and the joy of those who dwell therein.

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>
