<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Пахомий Великий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
         Р П    бНЫЙ (па1 т °н                Пахомий Великий, наряду с Антонием Великим Евин,/           января), Макарием Великим (память 19 января) и                В е л и к и м     п а м я т ь 2 0 «ыннож^                        &lt;                 января), является столпом пу-      нножительства и основателем монашеского общежития в Егип-             ЛСЯ п    еп       бный Егип?тГ           Р °Д°               Пахомий в III веке в Фиваиде (Верхний Разов!» ° Т с Р ° д и т е л е й язычников и получил хорошее светское об- М г ш , „                   юности он имел задатки доброю нрава, был цело-   --Ч&gt;и1 и рассудителен. Когда Пахомию исполнилось 20 лет он был призван в войска императора Константина (по-видимому, в 315 году). Новобранцев разместили в здании городской темницы под охраной стражи. Местные христиане пришли с запасами пи- щи, кормили воинов и усердно им служили. Когда юноша узнал, что эти люди так поступают ради своего Бога, исполняя Его запо- ведь о любви к ближним, это глубоко запало в его чистую душу. Пахомий дал обещание сделаться христианином. Вернувшись из войска после победы, Пахомий принял святое Крещение, поселил- ся в уединенном селении Шенесит и сразу же стал вести строгую подвижническую жизнь. Почувствовав необходимость в духовном руководителе, он обратился к Фиваидскому пустыннику Паламо- ну, был принят старцем с любовью и стал ревностно проходить мо- нашеские подвиги по примеру своего наставника.     Однажды, после 10 лет пустынной жизни, преподобный Пахо- мий, идя по пустыне, остановился у развалин селения Тавенниси и услышал Голос, приказавший ему построить на этом месте оби- тель. Пахомий рассказал об этом старцу Паламону, и оба, при- няв услышанные слова за указание Божие, отправились в Тавен- ниси и начали строить небольшое иноческое жилище. Святой ста- рец Паламон благословил начало основания обители и предсказал будущую ее славу. Вскоре преподобный Паламон отошел ко Гос- поду. Тогда святому Пахомию явился Ангел Божий в образе схим- ника и вручил ему устав монашеской жизни. Вскоре к преподоб- ному пришел его старший брат Иоанн и поселился вместе с ним.    Преподобный Пахомий терпел много искушений и нападений от врага рода человеческого, но все искушения преподобный Па- хомий доблестно отражал молитвой к Богу и терпением.    Постепенно к преподобному Пахомию стали собираться учени- ки. Всех их поражало трудолюбие наставника, который успевал исполнять все монастырские работы: возделывал сад, беседовал с приходящими, просившими наставления, и служил больным. Пре- подобный Пахомий ввел устав общего жития, установив единооб- разие для всех в пище и одежде. Иноки обители должны были трудиться в назначенных им послушаниях на общую пользу оби- тели. В числе послушаний было переписывание книг. Иноки не должны были иметь собственных денег или принимать что-нибудь от своих родственников. Преподобный считал, что послушание, исполняемое с усердием, выше поста и молитвы, и требовал от ино- ков точного соблюдения устава, строго наказывая нарушителей.     Однажды к преподобному Пахомию пришла его сестра Мария, которая давно желала увидеть брата. Но строгий подвижник от- казал ей в свидании и через привратника передал ей благослове- ние вступить на путь монашеской жизни, обещая в этом свою по- мощь. Мария заплакала, но поступила согласно указанию брата. Тавеннисские иноки построили для нее жилище на противополож- ном берегу Нила. К Марии стали собираться инокини, и вскоре создалась женская обитель со строгим уставом, который был пере- дан преподобным Пахомием.     Число иноков монастыря быстро возрастало, что вызвало необ- ходимость постройки еще 7-ми монастырей поблизости. Количество иноков доходило до 7000, и все они находились под руководством преподобного Пахомия, который посещал все монастыри и управ- лял ими. В то же время преподобный Пахомий оставался глубо- ко смиренным иноком, который всегда готов был повиноваться и принимать замечания от каждого брата.     Суровый и строгий к себе, преподобный Пахомий имел вели- кое милосердие и снисхождение к недостаточно зрелым духовно инокам. Один из иноков стремился к подвигу мученичества, но преподобный отвращал его от этих стремлений и наставлял без- молвно исполнять монашеское послушание, укрощая в себе гор- дость и приучаясь к смирению. Однако инок не послушал настав- ника и ушел из обители, после чего подвергся нападению разбой- ников, которые под страхом смерти принудили его принести жерт- ву языческим богам. В полном отчаянии инок вернулся в обитель. Преподобный велел ему усиленно молиться днем и ночью, соблю- дать строгий пост и жить в полном молчании. Инок последовал наставлению преподобного, и это спасло его душу от отчаяния.     Преподобный учил всячески опасаться осуждения других и сам  боялся даже в мыслях осудить кого-либо.     С особой любовью относился преподобный Пахомий к больным  инокам. Он посещал их, ободрял унывающих, убеждал благода-  рить Бога и возлагать надежду на Его святую волю. Больным он  ослаблял пост, если это было необходимо для их выздоровления.  Однажды, в отсутствие преподобного, повар не готовил монахам  вареной пищи, ссылаясь на то, что братия любят поститься. Вме-  сто своего послушания он сплел 500 рогож, но преподобный не  одобрил его поступка; и в наказание за непослушание велел сжечь  все изготовленные поваром рогожи.     Преподобный Пахомий всегда поучал иноков иметь надежду  только на помощь и милость Божию. В обители как-то случился  недостаток пшеницы. Целую ночь святой провел в молитве, а ут-  ром привезли от начальника города большое количество хлеба для  монастыря, не взяв ничего в уплату. Господь сподобил преподоб-  ного Пахомия дара чудотворения и исцеления болезней.      Ему были открыты Господом последующие судьбы монашества.  Святой знал, что последние монахи не будут иметь такой ревности  к подвигам, как первые, будут ходить как во тьме, не имея опыт-  ных руководителей. Простершись на земле, преподобный Пахомий  горько плакал, взывая к Господу и прося милости к ним. В ответ  он услышал Голос: «Пахомий, помни о милосердии Божием. О по-  следних монахах знай, что и они получат награду, ибо им придет-  ся страдать от тяжкой для инока жизни».      Под конец своей жизни преподобный Пахомий тяжко заболел  от бывшей в тех местах моровой болезни. За ним с сыновней лю-  бовью ухаживал его ближайший и любимый ученик преподобный  Феодор (память 17 мая). Скончался преподобный Пахомий около 348 года в возрасте 53-х лет и был погребен у горы возле обители. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Сле́зъ твои́хъ тече́ньми пꙋсты́ни безпло́дное воздѣ́лалъ є҆сѝ, и҆ и҆̀же и҆з꙽ глꙋбины̀ воздыха́ньми, во сто̀ трꙋдѡ́въ ѹ҆плодоноси́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ бы́лъ є҆сѝ свѣти́льникъ вселе́ннѣй, сїѧ́ѧ чꙋдесы̀, пахѡ́мїе ѻ҆́тче на́шъ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Свѣти́льникъ свѣ́телъ показа́лсѧ є҆сѝ въ концѣ́хъ: пꙋсты́ню же гра́ды сотвори́лъ є҆сѝ мно́жествы мона́шескими, са́мъ себѐ распе́нъ, крⷭтъ тво́й на ра́мо взе́мъ, и҆ воздержа́нїемъ тѣ́ло и҆знꙋри́лъ є҆сѝ, молѧ̀ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Pachomios the Great"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Pachomios the Great, together with Anthony the Great (Comm. 17January), Makarios the Great (Comm. 19 January), and Euthymios the Great (Comm. 20 January), was both an exemplar of wilderness dwelling, and a founder of the monastic &quot;life-in-common&quot; coenobitism in Egypt. The Monk Pacholios was born in the III Century in the Thebaid (Upper Egypt). His parents were pagans and he received an excellent secular education. From youth he had the traits of good character, he was prudent of sensible in mind. When Pacholios reached age 20, he was called up into the army of the emperor Constantine (apparently, in the year 315). They settled the new conscripts into the edifice of a city prison under a guard of sentries. The local Christians came with supplies of food, they fed the soldiers and they took sincere care of them. When the youth learned, that these people acted thus for the sake of their God, fulfilling His commandment about love for neighbour, this made a deep impression upon his pure soul. Pacholios made a vow to become a Christian. Having returned from the army after the victory, Pacholios accepted holy Baptism, resettled himself into the lonely settlement of Shenesit and immediately he began to lead a strict ascetic life. Sensing the need for spiritual guidance, he turned to the Thebaid wilderness dweller Palamon. He was fondly accepted by the elder, and he began to proceed through monastic efforts on the example of his instructor. 	One time, after 10 years of wilderness life, the Monk Pacholios was making his way through the desert, when he halted at the ruins of the former village of Tabennis and here he heard a Voice, ordering him to form at this place a monastery. Pachomios reported about this to the elder Palamon, and they both considered the words heard to be a command from God. They set out to Tabennis and began by building there a small monastic hovel. The holy elder Palamon blessed the beginning foundations of the monastery and made a prediction of its future glory. But soon also the Monk Palamon expired to the Lord. An Angel of God then appeared to Saint Pacholios in the form of a schemamonk and entrusted to him an ustav-rule of monastic life. And soon his own elder brother John came and settled there together with him. 	The Monk Pachomios underwent many a temptation and assault from the enemy of the race of man, but the Monk Pachomios bravely warded off all the temptations by his prayer to God and endurance.  	Gradually there began a gathering of followers to the Monk Pachomios. Their teacher impressed everyone by his love for work, whereby he managed to accomplish all kinds of monastic tasks: he cultivated a garden, he conversed with those that arrived seeking guidance, and he tended to the sick. The Monk Pachomios introduced a monastic rule of &quot;life-in-common&quot;, making everything the same for everyone in food and attire. The monks of the monastery were to toil at the obediences assigned them for the common good of the monastery. Among the various obediences was the re-copying of books. The monks were not to possess their own money nor to accept anything from their kinsfolk. The Monk Pachomios considered that an obedience, fulfilled with zeal, was higher than fasting or prayer, and he demanded from the monks an exact observance of the monastic rule, strictly chastising flaggards. 	To the Monk Pachomios one time came his sister Maria, who for a long time had wanted to see her brother. But the strict ascetic refused seeing her and via the gate-keeper he gave her the blessing to enter upon the path of monastic life, promising his help with this. Maria wept, but did as her brother had ordered. The Tabennis monks built her an hut on the opposite side of the River Nile. And to Maria also there began to gather nuns, and soon there was formed a women&apos;s monastery with a strict monastic rule, provided by the Monk Pachomios. 	The number of monks at the monastery grew quickly, and it necessitated the building of 7 more monasteries in the vicinity. The number of monks reached 7,000, -- all under the guidance of the Monk Pachomios, who visited at all the monasteries and administered them. But at the same time Saint Pachomios remained a deeply humble monk, who was always ready to comply with and accept the remarks of each brother. 	Severe and strict towards himself, the Monk Pachomios had great kindness and condescension towards the spiritually immature deficiencies of monks. One of the monks was ardent for the deed of martyrdom, but the Monk Pachomios swayed him from this yearning and instructed him quietly to fulfill his monastic obedience, taming the pride in himself and training him in humility. One time a monk would not heed his advice and went off from the monastery, during which time he was set upon by brigands, who under the threat of death forced him to offer sacrifice to the pagan gods. Filled with despair, the monk returned to the monastery. The Monk Pachomios ordered him to pray intensely night and day, keep strict fast and live in complete solitude. The monk followed his advice, and this saved his soul from despair. 	The monk taught to avoid against judging others and he himself feared to be judgemental of anyone even in thought.  	It was with an especial love that the Monk Pachomios concerned himself over the sick monks. He visited them, he cheered up the disheartened, he urged them to be thankful to God and put their hope in His holy will. For the sick he lightened the fasting, if this should aid in their recovery of health. One time in the absence of the monk, the cook did not prepare the monks any cooked food, on the presumption that the brethren loved to fast. Instead of doing his obedience, this monk plaited 500 mats, something which the Monk Pachomios had not encouraged. In punishment for the disobedience, all the mats prepared by the cook were ordered burnt. 	The Monk Pachomios always taught the monks to have hope only upon the help and mercy of God. At the monastery it happened that there was an insufficiency of grain. The saint spent the whole night at prayer, and in the morning there came from the main city a large quantity of bread for the monastery, at no expense. The Lord granted the Monk Pachomios the gift of wonderworking and healing the sick.  	The Lord revealed to him the ultimate fate of monasticism. The monk learned, that successive monks would not have such zeal in their efforts as did the first, and they would walk in the darkness of not having experienced guides. Prostrating himself upon the ground, the Monk Pachomios wept bitterly, calling out to the Lord and imploring mercy for them. In answer he heard a Voice: &quot;Pachomios, be mindful of the mercy of God. About the monks to come, know that they shalt receive recompense, since that they too shalt have occasion to suffer the life burdensome for the monk&quot;. 	Towards the end of his life the Monk Pachomios likewise fell ill from a pestilence that afflicted the region. His closest and beloved disciple, the Monk Theodore (Comm. 17May), tended to him with a filial love. The Monk Pachomios died in about the year 348 at age 53, and he was buried on an hill near the monastery.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
With the streams of thy tears thou didst irrigate the barren desert,/ and with sighs from the depths of thy soul thou didst render thy labors fruitful an hundredfold./ Thou wast a beacon for the whole world, radiating miracles.// O our father Pachomius, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Thou wast shown to be a radiant luminary for the ends of the earth,/ and didst populate the desert with multitudes of monastics, as with cities./ And crucifying thyself, taking thy cross upon thy shoulders,/ thou didst lay waste to thy body with asceticism,// praying unceasingly for us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>