<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Ферапонт, епископ Сардийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Священномученик Ферапонт, епископ Сардийский (город Сар- дис (Сарды) находился в малоазийской области Лидии), постра- дал за Христа в III веке. Исполняя свое святительское служение, святой Ферапонт просветил светом христианской веры и крестил многих язычников-еллинов. За это он предстал перед судом пра- вителя Юлиана и бесстрашно объявил себя христианским епис- копом. Его бросили в темницу, где долгое время томили голодом и жаждой, потом предали жестоким истязаниям, но мучения не поколебали мужественного исповедничества святителя. В оковах святого повели в город Синаон во Фригии, оттуда в Анкиру. В этих городах его снова пытали. Затем привели святого Фера- понта к реке Астале, обнаженного растянули крестообразно на земле, привязав к четырем кольям, вбитым в землю, и жестоко избили. После этого истязания страстотерпца Христова привели в пределы Саталийской епископии, подчинявшейся Сардийской митрополии, и здесь после долгих избиений святитель Ферапонт закончил свой мученический подвиг. Сухие колья, к которым был привязан святой, напитанные его кровью, дали зеленые ростки и выросли в большие деревья, листья которых обрели целебные свой- ства и многим людям подавали благодатные исцеления. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆ нра́вѡмъ прича́стникъ, и҆ прⷭто́лѡмъ намѣ́стникъ а҆пⷭлѡмъ бы́въ, дѣѧ́нїе ѡ҆брѣ́лъ є҆сѝ бг҃одохнове́нне, въ видѣ́нїѧ восхо́дъ: сегѡ̀ ра́ди сло́во и҆́стины и҆справлѧ́ѧ, и҆ вѣ́ры ра́ди пострада́лъ є҆сѝ да́же до кро́ве, сщ҃енномч҃нче ѳерапо́нте, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="PriestMartyr Therapontos, Bishop of Sardis"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The PriestMartyr Therapontos, Bishop of Sardis suffered for Christ during the III Century (the city of Sardis, or Sarda, was situated in the Asia Minor district of Lydia). In fulfilling his priestly service, Saint Therapontos enlightened with the light of the Christian faith and baptised many of the pagan-Hellenes (Greeks). For this, he was brought to trial before the governor Julian and fearlessly declared himself a Christian bishop. They threw him into prison, where for a long time he languished with hunger and thirst, and then they gave him over to cruel tortures, but the torments did not break the saint&apos;s valiant confessing of faith. In chains they led off the saint to the city of Sinaion in Phrygia, and thence to Ancyra. In these cities they again tortured him. They took him to the River Astala, where they stretched him cross-form and bare upon the ground, fastened to four posts driven into the ground, and they beat him fiercely. After this torture, they took the passion-bearer of Christ off to the outskirts of the Satalia diocese, part of the Sardis metropolitanate, and here after long beatings Saint Therapontos ended with his martyr&apos;s deed. The dry posts, to which the saint had been tied, and having soaked up his blood, gave forth green shoots and grew into large trees, the leaves of which were found to have curative powers through which many people received graced healing. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Need English translation
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>