<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой мученик Ермий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
    Святой мученик Ермий пострадал за Христа в городе Команы во время гонений при императоре Антонине Пии (138—161). Пра- витель Севастиан, прибывший в Каппадокию для исполнения при- каза о преследовании христиан, предложил святому принести жертву языческим богам, обещая за это почести и милость импе- ратора. Но убеленный сединами воин мужественно исповедал свою веру во Христа. После долгих уговоров правитель повелел мучить святого. Его били по лицу так, что содрали с лица кожу, а потом бросили в раскаленную печь. Когда через 3 дня печь открыли, мученик Ермий вышел из нее невредимым. Правитель Севастиан приказал волхву отравить святого Ермия ядом. Отравленное питье не принесло святому никакого вреда. Так же и второй кубок с сильнейшим ядом не умертвил мученика. Волхв уверовал, принес покаяние Христу Спасителю и был немедленно обезглавлен, кре- стившись собственной кровью и восприняв мученический венец. А святой Ермий был предан еще более жестоким мукам: из него вытягивали жилы, бросали в кипящее олово, выкололи глаза, но он смиренно благодарил Господа Иисуса Христа. Потом мученика Ермия повесили головой вниз. Три дня висел он в таком положе- нии. Люди, посланные правителем удостовериться в смерти мучени- ка, нашли его живым. Пораженные чудом, они ослепли от ужаса и начали взывать к святому, чтобы он помог им. Святой мученик велел подойти ослепшим к нему, возложил на них руки и исцелил Именем Иисуса Христа. В ярости правитель приказал содрать с тела святого всю кожу, но страстотерпец по-прежнему оставался живым. Тогда обезумевший Севастиан собственноручно отрезал ему голову ножом. Христиане тайно погребли тело мученика Ермия, от святых мощей которого подавались многочисленные исцеления. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нкъ тво́й гдⷭи, є҆рме́й, во страда́нїи свое́мъ вѣне́цъ прїѧ́тъ нетлѣ́нный ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мѣ́ѧй бо крѣ́пость твою̀, мꙋчи́телей низложѝ, сокрꙋшѝ и҆ де́монѡвъ немощны́ѧ де́рзѡсти: тогѡ̀ мл҃твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
И҆́же по хрⷭтѣ̀ ѹ҆се́рднѡ подвиза́всѧ, въ сѣди́нахъ до́блихъ мꙋ́жество стѧжа́лъ є҆сѝ мч҃нче є҆рмї́е, беззако́нныхъ ѕлоꙋмышле́нїе попра́въ хрⷭто́вою си́лою, ѿ чаро́вныхъ напое́нїй невреди́мь пребы́сть, зовы́й: бг҃ъ є҆́сть со мно́ю, и҆ никто́же на мѧ̀. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyr Hermias"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyr Hermias suffered for Christ in the city of Komana during the time of persecution under the emperor Antoninus Pius (138-161). The governor Sebastian, having arrived in Cappadocia to carry out a commission to chase down Christians, urged the saint to offer sacrifice to the pagan gods, promising for this both honours and the mercy of the emperor. But the soldier grey with age bravely confessed his faith in Christ. After long exhortation the governor gave orders to torture the saint. They beat him on the face such that the skin peeled from his face, and they threw him into a red-hot oven. When the oven was opened after 3 days, the Martyr Hermias emerged from it unharmed. The governor Sebastian ordered a sorcerer to poison Saint Hermias with a potion. The poisonous drink did the saint no harm. So likewise a second goblet with even stronger poison failed to kill the saint. The sorcerer believed and offered repentance to Christ the Saviour and was immediately beheaded, baptised by his own blood and receiving a martyr&apos;s crown. But Saint Hermias was subjected to even more terrible torturings: they tore at his sinews, threw him in boiling oil, dug out his eyes, but he humbly gave thanks to the Lord Jesus Christ. Then they suspended the Martyr Hermias head downwards. For three days he hung in such a position. People, sent by the governor to verify his death, found him alive. Struck by the miracle, they were blinded with fright and began to call out to the saint that he should help them. The holy martyr ordered the blind to approach to him, laid hands on and healed them in the Name of Jesus Christ. In anger the governor ordered to flay the skin on the body of the saint, but as before he remained alive. Then the crazed Sebastian by his own hand beheaded him. Christians secretly buried the body of the Martyr Hermias, from whose relics numerous relics were bestowed.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In his suffering, O Lord,/ Thy martyr Hermias received an imperishable crown from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ he set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By his supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
Having struggled eagerly for Christ,/ thou didst acquire courage at an advanced age, O martyr Hermias;/ and having trampled the machinations of the iniquitous underfoot by the power of Christ,/ thou didst remain unharmed by sorcerous potions, crying:/ "God is with me!// Who then can stand against me?"
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>