<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые мученики Лукиллиан, отроки Клавдий, Ипатий, Павел и Дионисий и Павла дева"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Лукиллиан был языческим жрецом при римском императоре Аврелиане (270—275). В старости он убедился в ложности язы- ческой религии, всей душой обратился к вере во Христа-Спасителя и крестился.     Под влиянием его проповеди многие язычники стали обра- щаться к христианству. Тогда иудеи за распространение веры в распятого ими Христа донесли на Лукиллиана градоначальнику Никомидии Сильвану. Тот стал принуждать старца возвратиться к идолослужению. За отказ святому Лукиллиану сокрушили челю- сти, били палками и повесили вниз головой, а затем заключили в темницу, где он встретил четырех отроков-исповедников Христо- вых—Клавдия, Ипатия, Павла и Дионисия. Святой Лукиллиан убеждал их твердо стоять за веру, не бояться мучений и смерти. Через некоторое время все они были приведены на судилище и брошены в раскаленную печь, но внезапно пролившийся дождь угасил пламя, и святые мученики остались невредимы. Правитель приговорил, их к смертной казни, отправив для исполнения приго- вора в Византию. Святые отроки были усечены мечом, а святой мученик Лукиллиан многочисленными гвоздями пригвожден ко кресту.     Свидетельницей подвига святых мучеников была святая дева Павла, посвятившая себя служению страдавшим за веру во Хр-и- ста. Она доставляла пищу узникам-христианам, омывала их&apos; раны, приносила лекарства и погребала тела мучеников. После кончины святого Лукиллиана и четырех отроков она возвратилась в Нико- мидию и продолжала свое святое служение. Святая дева была схвачена и брошена в печь, однако силою Божиею осталась невре- дима. Тогда ее отослали в Византию, где святая мученица была усечена мечом. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyrs Lucillian, the Lads Claudius, Ipatius, Dionysius, and Paula the Virgin"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyrs Lucillian, the Lads Claudius, Ipatius, Dionysius, and Paula the Virgin: Lucillian was a pagan priest during the time of the Roman emperor Aurelian (270-275). In his old age he became persuaded of the falseness of the pagan religion, and with all his heart he turned to the faith in Christ the Saviour, and was baptised. 	Under the influence of his preaching many a pagan was converted to Christianity. Then certain Jews, out of concern for his spreading faith in the Christ crucified by them, reported against Lucillian to the Nicomedia city-governor Sylvanus, who thereupon urged the elder to return to idol-worship. For his refusal, they smashed the jawbone of Saint Lucillian, beat him with canes and suspended him head downwards, and then they locked him away in prison. Here he met up with four lads that were confessors of Christianity -- Claudius, Ipatius, Paul and Dionysius. Saint Lucillian urged them to stand firm in the faith, and to fear neither tortures nor death. After a certain while they brought them to trial and then thrown into a red-hot furnace, but suddenly rain poured down extinguishing the flames, and the martyrs remained unharmed. The governor sentenced them to death by execution, sending them off to Byzantium for carrying out the sentence. The holy lads were beheaded by the sword, and the holy Martyr Lucillian was nailed to a cross with quite many nails. 	Witness to the deed of the holy martyrs was the holy Virgin Paula, who had dedicated herself to the service of those suffering for the faith in Christ. She provided food to Christian prisoners, washed their wounds, brought medications and also buried the bodies of martyrs. After the death of Saint Lucillian and the four lads, she returned to Nicomedia and continued on with her holy service. The holy virgin was arrested and cast into a furnace, but by the power of God she remained unharmed. Then they sent her off to Byzantium, where the holy martyress was beheaded by the sword. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>