<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Иларион Новый"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Преподобный Иларион Новый родился от благочестивых роди- телей Петра и Феодосии, которые воспитали его в добродетели и наставили в Священном Писании. В двадцатилетнем возрасте свя- той Иларион постригся в монашество в Исихийской обители вбли- зи Византии, а оттуда перешел в Далматскую обитель, где при- нял великую схиму и стал учеником преподобного Григория Де- каполита (память 20 ноября). Преподобный глубоко почитал свое- го Богоносного соименника — преподобного Илариона Великого (память 21 октября), он стремился подражать его жизни, потому и был прозван Иларионом Новым. В Далматской обители его по- святили во пресвитера. После смерти игумена братия хотели из- брать на это место святого Илариона, но он, узнав об этом, тайно удалился в Византию.    Тогда монахи Далматской обители прислали святителю Па- триарху Никифору ходатайство о назначении преподобного Ила- риона игуменом. Патриарх призвал святого и убедил его дать согласие. Преподобный Иларион из святого послушания подчи- нился. В течение 8 лет он мирно управлял монастырем. В 813 году императорский престол занял иконоборец Лев Армянин (813— 820). Преподобный отказался хулить святые иконы и дерзновенно обличил императора в ереси, за что претерпел много истязаний. Несколько раз его заключали в темницу, морили голодом и жаж- дой. Нечестивый патриарх Феодот, занявший место изгнанного Патриарха Никифора, учинил преподобному много мучений, доби- ваясь отречения от Православия. Монахи Далматской обители явились к императору и просили его отпустить святого, обещая по- виноваться императорской воле. Но, возвратившись в монастырь, преподобный Иларион и все далматские иноки продолжали чтить святые иконы. Разгневанный император вновь заключил препо- добного в темницу. Всеми силами добиваясь отречения, он пре- давал святого на истязания и заточал в темницы.    Но кара Божия постигла злочестивого императора: он был изрублен своими же воинами в храме, на том самом месте, где когда-то в первый раз низринул святую икону. Новый император Михаил II Косноязычный (820—829) освободил преподобного Илариона из заточения, и святой поселился в уединенной келлии. Когда отошел ко Господу преподобный Феодор Студит, также по- страдавший за святые иконы (память 11 ноября), преподобный Иларион удостоился видеть Ангелов, возносивших на Небо святую душу Феодора.    При императоре-иконоборце Феофиле (829—842) преподобного Илариона вновь взяли под стражу и, жестоко избив, заточили на острове Афусии.    После смерти Феофила святая императрица Феодора (842— 855) повелела возвратить исповедников из ссылки. Преподобный Иларион вернулся в Далматскую обитель, вновь принял в ней игуменство и мирно скончался в 845 году. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е ѻ҆тє́цъ на́шихъ, творѧ́й при́снѡ съ на́ми по твое́й кро́тости, не ѡ҆ста́ви млⷭть твою̀ ѿ на́съ, но мл҃твами и҆́хъ въ ми́рѣ ѹ҆пра́ви живо́тъ на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Ѡ҆гра́ды живоно́сныѧ твоеѧ̀ па́жити па́стырски невреди́мо ста́до соблю́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ высото́ю дѣ́лъ вели́къ, но́вый ї҆ларїѡ́не, по бл҃гоче́стїи мнѡ́ги мꙋ҄ки и҆ скѡ́рби прїе́мъ. тѣ́мъ во всера́достный живо́тъ всели́лсѧ є҆сѝ го́рнѧгѡ сїѡ́на, молѝ за ны̀ прпⷣбне. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Ilarion (Hilary) the New"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Ilarion (Hilary) the New was born of pious parents, Peter and Theodosia, who raised him in the virtues and instructed him in Holy Scripture. At twelve years of age Saint Ilarion was tonsured into monasticism at the Isykhia monastery near Byzantium, and from there he transferred to the Dalmatia monastery, where he took on the great schema and became a disciple of the Monk Gregory Dekapolites (Comm. 20November). The monk deeply venerated his God-bearing patronal-name saint -- the Monk Ilarion the Great (Comm. 21 October), and he strove to imitate his life, whereby he came to be called Ilarion the New. At the Dalmatia monastery they ordained him presbyter. After the death of the hegumen the brethren wanted to elect Saint Ilarion to this position, but learning of this, he secretly withdrew away to Byzantium.  	Then the monks of Dalmatia monastery sent off a petition to Sainted Patriarch Nikephoros, asking that the Monk Ilarion be assigned as hegumen. The Patriarch summoned the saint and persuaded him to give his assent. The Monk Ilarion submitted out of holy obedience. Over the course of eight years he peacefully guided the monastery. But in the year 813 the iconoclast Leo the Armenian (813-820) occupied the imperial throne. The monk refused to blaspheme holy icons and he boldly accused the emperor of heresy, for which he endured many torments. They locked him up in prison for awhile, and vexed him with hunger and thirst. The impious patriarch Theodotos, having replaced the exiled Patriarch Nikephoros, caused the monk much suffering in demanding a rejection of Orthodoxy. The monks of the Dalmatia monastery went to the emperor and besought him to release the saint, promising to submit to the imperial will. But having returned to the monastery, the Monk Ilarion and all the monks continued to venerate holy icons. The enraged emperor again locked up the monk in prison. With all the powers at his disposal to demand a renunciation, he gave the saint over to torture and confined him in prison. 	But the wrath of God overtook the wicked emperor: he was cut down by his own soldiers in church at that very spot, where once before he had thrown down an holy icon. The new emperor Michael II the Stammerer (820-829) set free the Monk Ilarion from his imprisonment, and the saint settled into a solitary cell. Upon the death of the Monk Theodore the Studite (Comm. 11 November) -- who likewise had suffered for holy icons, the Monk Ilarion was vouchsafed to behold holy Angels lifting up to Heaven the holy soul of  Saint Theodore.  	Under the iconoclast emperor Theophilos (829-842), the Monk Ilarion was again put under guard, and beaten terribly, and they confined him on the island of Athysia. 	After the death of Theophilos, the holy empress Saint Theodora (842-855) gave orders to restore the confessors from exile. The Monk Ilarion returned to the Dalmatia monastery, again accepting to be hegumen at it, and he peacefully died in the year 845. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O God of our fathers,/ deal with us ever according to Thy meekness./ Deprive us not of Thy mercy,/ but through their supplications// direct our life in peace.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Like a shepherd didst thou preserve within thy fold/ the flock of thy life-bearing pasture,/ and wast shown to be great by the loftiness of thy works, O Hilarion the New,/ having undergone much suffering and sorrow in thy piety./ Wherefore, thou hast made thine abode in the most joyful life in heavenly Sion.// Pray for us, O venerable one!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>