<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Трифиллий, епископ Левкуссийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святитель Трифиллий, епископ Левкуссийский, родился в Кон- стантинополе, образование получил в Верите (Бейрут, в Сирии). Он был очень учен и красноречив. Несмотря на это, святитель избрал себе наставника не книжного и не ученого, но мужа высо- кой святости — святителя Спиридона, епископа Тримифунтского {\ 348, память 12 декабря). Император Констанций II (337—340) тяжело заболел и, не получив помощи от врачей, обратился с усердной молитвой к Богу. Во сне он увидел Ангела,, показавшего ему собор святителей. Указав на двух из них, Ангел сказал, что только через них он может получить исцеление. Констанций разо- слал по всем областям империи указ, повелевавший собраться епископам. Это повеление получил и святитель Спиридон. Вместе со своим учеником святым Трифиллием он отправился к импе- ратору. Больной сразу узнал в пришедших указанных ему Анге- лом целителей, поклонился им и просил помолиться о его исце- лении. Святитель Спиридон с молитвой прикоснулся к голове им- ператора, и он стал здоров. Святой Трифиллий восхитился красо- той дворца, величественным видом императора, пышностью двор- цовой жизни. Святитель Спиридон сказал на это: «Зачем ты удив- ляешься? Разве этот блеск делает царя более праведным? Все они — цари и вельможи — одинаково с последним нищим умрут и предстанут на суд Божий. Следует искать вечных благ и Небесной славы». Вскоре святой Трифиллий был поставлен епископом города Левкуссии на Кипре. Он часто навещал святителя Спиридона. Однажды они вместе проходили по отличавшейся красотой и изо- билием виноградников и садов местности, называемой Паримна. Святитель Трифиллий, привлеченный красотой природы, стал ду- мать о том, чтобы приобрести эту землю. Святитель Спиридон прозрел мысли Трифиллия и сказал: «Зачем ты непрестанно ду- маешь о земных и суетных благах? Наше жилище и богатство на Небесах, к ним и нужно стремиться». Так святитель Спиридон постепенно возводил своего ученика к духовному совершенству, которого святой Трифиллий достиг по молитвам своего наставни- ка. Святитель Трифиллий имел милостивую душу, незлобивое сердце, правую веру, любовь ко всем и многие другие добродетели. Однажды на Кипре проходил Собор епископов. Отцы Собора просили святителя Трифиллия, известного своей ученостью и красноречием, произнести поучение народу. Говоря об исцелении Господом расслабленного (Мк. 2. 11), он вместо слова «одр» упо- требил «ложе». Не терпя неточной передачи Евангельского текста, святитель Спиридон возмутился и сказал святителю Трифиллию: «Неужели ты лучше Сказавшего «одр», что стыдишься слова Его?» — и немедленно покинул храм. Так святитель Спиридон дал святителю Трифиллию урок смирения, чтобы он не возгордился данным ему талантом красноречия. Святитель Трифиллий мудро пас свое стадо. На средства, доставшиеся ему после матери, он построил в Левкуссии монастырь. Скончался святитель в глубокой старости около 370 года. В начале XII века мощи святителя Трифиллия видел на Кипре русский паломник игумен Даниил. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Пра́вило вѣ́ры и҆ ѡ҆́бразъ кро́тости, воздержа́нїѧ ѹ҆чи́телѧ ꙗ҆ви́ тѧ ста́дꙋ твоемꙋ̀, ꙗ҆́же веще́й и҆́стина: сегѡ̀ ра́ди стѧжа́лъ є҆сѝ смире́нїемъ высѡ́каѧ, нището́ю бога҄таѧ, ѻ҆́тче трїфѵ́ллїе, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
И҆зрѧ́дствомъ житїѧ̀ чистотꙋ̀ дѣ́вства прїе́мъ трїфѵ́ллїе, первопресто́льникъ показа́лсѧ є҆сѝ леѵкꙋсї́и: и҆ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ тѣ҄мъ провозвѣсти́тель и҆ бг҃оразꙋ́мїѧ наста́вникъ. сегѡ̀ ра́ди ра́достнѡ взыва́емъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ ст҃и́телей ѹ҆краше́нїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Triphyllios, Bishop of Leukyssa"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Triphyllios, Bishop of Leukyssa, was born in Constantinople, and he received his education at Berit (Beirut, in Lebanon). He was very intelligent and eloquent. In spite of this, the saint chose as his guide a man not bookish nor learned, but of profound holiness -- Sainted Spyridon of Trimiphunteia (+ 348, Comm. 12 December). The emperor Constantine II (337-340) fell grievously ill and, having received no help from the doctors, he turned with fervent prayer to God. In a dream he saw an Angel, directing him to a gathering of saintly hierarchs. Pointing out two of them, the Angel said that only through them could he receive healing. Constantine circulated an imperial edict throughout all the districts, commanding the bishops to gather. Saint Spyridon also received this order. Together with his disciple Saint Triphyllios, he set out to the emperor. The sick one immediately recognised them as the healers pointed out by the Angel. He bowed to them and asked them to pray for his health. Saint Spyridon with a prayer touched the head of the emperor, and he became well. Saint Triphyllios was charmed by the beautiful palace, the majestic figure of the emperor, and the pomp of palace life. Saint Spyridon said to this: &quot;Why art thou astonished? Doth then this lustre make the emperor any more righteous? All of them -- emperors and dignitaries -- will alike die and stand together with the very poorest before the judgement-seat of God. One ought to seek after the eternal blessings and Heavenly glories&quot;. 	Soon Saint Triphyllios was made bishop of the city of Leukyssa on Cyprus. He often visited with Saint Spyridon. One time they passed together through an area of vineyards and gardens of especial beauty and abundance, named Parimnos. Saint Triphyllios, attracted by the beauty of nature, began to consider how they might explore this land. Saint Spyridon discerned the thoughts of Saint Triphyllios and said: &quot;Why dost thou incessantly think about earthly and transitory blessings? Our habitation and riches art in Heaven, to which we ought to strive&quot;. Thus did Saint Spyridon constantly lead his student towards spiritual perfection, which Saint Triphyllios attained through the prayers of his preceptor. Saint Triphyllios had a charitable soul, an heart without malice, right faith and love towards all, and many other virtues. 	One time a Council of bishops assembled on Cyprus. The father of the Council requested that Saint Triphyllios, known for his erudition and eloquence, give an edifying speech to the people. Speaking about the healing of the paralytic by the Lord (Mk. 2 : 11). in place of the word &quot;cot&quot; he used the word &quot;bed&quot;. Impatient with the imprecise rendering of the Gospel text, Saint Spyridon roused himself and said to Saint Triphyllios: &quot;Art thou better than He that spake &quot;cot&quot;, that thou be ashamed of His wording?&quot; -- and abruptly he left the church. Thus did Saint Spyridon give Saint Triphyllios a lesson in humility, so that he would not get puffed up with pride over the talent of eloquence bestown on him. Saint Triphyllios wisely shepherded his flock. From the means left him by his mother, he built a monastery at Leukyssa. The saint died in old age in about the year 370. 	At the beginning of the XII Century the Russian pilgrim Hegumen Daniel saw the relics of Saint Triphyllios on Cyprus.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
The truth of things revealed thee to thy flock as a rule of faith,/ a model of meekness and a teacher of abstinence/ wherefore thou hast attained the heights through humility/ and riches through poverty.// O hierarch Triphyllius our father, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Receiving the purity of virginity through the excellence of thy life, O Triphyllius,/ thou wast the first hierarch of Leucosia/ and wast shown to be its evangelizer and instructor in the knowledge of God.// Wherefore, with joy we cry out to thee: Rejoice, O adornment of hierarchs!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>