<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Мефодий, Патриарх Константинопольский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святитель Мефодий, Патриарх 435 Константинопольский, родился в Сицилии, в богатой семье. По призванию Божию,, еще в моло- дости, ушел в монастырь на острове Хиос и обновил его на свои средства. В царствование иконоборца Льва Армянина (813—820) святой Мефодий занимал высокую должность апокрисиария при святейшем Патриархе Никифоре (память 2 июня). Был послан патриархом в Рим с поручением к папе и задержался там. В это время Лев Армянин сверг святителя Никифора с престола и воз- вел на него иконоборца Феодота Мелиссинского, по прозванию Касситер (815—822). После смерти Льва Армянина святой Ме- фодий возвратился и в сане пресвитера неустанно боролся про- тив иконоборческой ереси. Император Михаил Косноязычный (820—829) вначале показывал себя милостивым и освободил мно- гих заключенных его предшественником за почитание икон, но после возобновил гонение на Православие. Святой Мефодий был заключен в темницу в Акрите. После смерти Михаила Косноязыч- ного воцарился сын его Феофил (829—842), также иконоборец. Более образованный, чем его отец, он освободил святого Мефодия, как человека ученого, превосходно сведущего в делах не только церковных, но и гражданских. Получив свободу, святой Мефодий возобновил борьбу с еретиками; император некоторое время терпел. После поражения в войне против арабов Феофил обрушил свой гнев на святого Мефодия, говоря, что Бог покарал его за то, что он приблизил к себе «идолопоклонника» (так иконоборцы на- зывали почитателей святых икон). Святой Мефодий возразил, что Господь прогневался на него за поругание Своей святой иконы. Святого предали истязаниям, ему нанесли множество ударов по щекам, отчего челюсть его была раздроблена. На его лице остался безобразный шрам. Святой Мефодий был сослан на остров Анти- гон и вместе с двумя разбойниками заключен в глубокой пещере. В мрачной темнице, куда не проникал солнечный свет, святой Ме- фодий томился 7 лет до смерти императора Феофила. В то время, изгоняемые в заточение святые иноки-исповедники Феодор и Феофан Начертанные (память 27 декабря) послали свя- тому Мефодию приветствие в стихах,, узник тоже ответил стихо- творным приветствием. После смерти Феофила воцарился его сын Михаил III (842— 867), но ввиду его малолетства Византийской империей правила его мать, блаженная царица Феодора, почитательница икон. Императрица старалась уничтожить иконоборческую ересь, по- велела освободить заключенных за почитание икон исповедников. Занимавший патриарший престол еретик Анний был изгнан, а из- бран святой Мефодий. В Константинополе был созван Поместный Собор под председательством святого Мефодия (842). Собор вос- становил иконопочитание и постановил ежегодно торжествовать по- беду Православия. Составленный святым Мефодием «Чин право- славия» совершается в первую неделю Великого поста. Стремясь подорвать авторитет святого Мефодия, любовь и ува- жение к нему паствы, еретики оклеветали его в нарушении цело- мудрия. Клевета была обнаружена, и враги святителя посрамлены. Последние годы жизни святителя прошли мирно, он много тру- дился, мудро управлял Церковью и своей паствой, восстанавливал разрушенные еретиками храмы, собирал мощи святых, уничтожен- ные иконоборцами, перенес мощи патриарха Никифора из места его заточения в Константинополь. Скончался- святитель Мефодий в 846 году. Святой Мефодий был духовно близок с преподобным Иоанникием (память 4 ноября), предсказавшим ему патриарше- ство и время кончины. Кроме «Чина православия», Святитель со- ставил также правила для обращающихся к вере, три чина бра- ков и несколько пастырских поучений и церковных песнопений. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Пра́вило вѣ́ры и҆ ѡ҆́бразъ кро́тости, воздержа́нїѧ ѹ҆чи́телѧ ꙗ҆ви́ тѧ ста́дꙋ твоемꙋ̀, ꙗ҆́же веще́й и҆́стина: сегѡ̀ ра́ди стѧжа́лъ є҆сѝ смире́нїемъ высѡ́каѧ, нището́ю бога҄таѧ, ѻ҆́тче меѳо́дїе, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
На землѝ подвиза́лсѧ є҆сѝ ꙗ҆́кѡ безпло́тный, и҆ нб҃са̀ наслѣ́довалъ є҆сѝ меѳо́дїе, ꙗ҆́кѡ и҆з꙽ѧсни́вый въ концѣ́хъ ї҆кѡ́нъ поклоне́нїе: въ трꙋдѣ́хъ бо и҆ болѣ́знехъ вѧ́щше пребы́въ, не преста́лъ є҆сѝ дерзнове́нїемъ ѡ҆блича́ѧ ѿмета́ющыѧсѧ ї҆кѡ́ны хрⷭто́вы. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Methodios, Patriarch of Constantinople"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Methodios, Patriarch of Constantinople, was born in Sicily into a rich family. Having a vocation to God, he went while still in his youth off to a monastery on the island of Chios and renovated it with his means. During the reign of the iconoclast Leo the Armenian (813-820), Saint Methodios held the high position of &quot;apokrisiaros&quot; (&quot;advocate for Church matters&quot;) under the holy Patriarch Nicephoros (Comm. 2 June). He was dispatched by the patriarch to Rome on a mission to the papacy and he remained there. During this period Leo the Armenian removed Nicephoros from the patriarchal throne and put on it the iconoclast Theodotos of Melissinea, given the nickname &quot;Kassiter&quot; (&quot;Tinman&quot;) (815-822). After the death of Leo the Armenian, Saint Methodios returned, and in the dignity of presbyter he struggled incessantly against the Iconoclast heresy. The emperor Michael the Stammerer (820-829) at first was noted for his benevolence and he set free many imprisoned by his predecessor for their veneration of icons, but after a while he renewed the persecution against Orthodoxy. Saint Methodios was locked up in prison in Akrita. After the death of Michael the Stammerer, the ruler was Theophilos (829-842), who also was an iconoclast. More refined a man than his father, he set free Saint Methodios, who likewise was a man of learning, superbly skilled in matters not only ecclesial, but also civil. Having received his freedom, Saint Methodios renewed the struggle with the heretics, and for a while the emperor tolerated this. 	But after defeat in a war with the Arabs, Theophilos vented his anger against Saint Methodios, saying, that God had punished him because he had let come close to him an &quot;icon-worshipper&quot; (such was what the iconoclasts called those who venerate holy icons). Saint Methodios objected, saying that the Lord was angry with him for the insults upon His holy icons. They gave the saint over to tortures, and struck him much about the face, from which his jaw was broken. On his face remained ugly scars. Saint Methodios was sent off to the island of Antigonos and he was locked up there with two robbers in a deep cave. In this dark prison where the light of day penetrated not, Saint Methodios languished for 7 years until the death of the emperor Theophilos. 	During this time, the holy Icon-Confessors Theodore and Theophanes the LetteredUpon (Comm. 27 December), likewise banished to prison, sent Saint Methodios greetings in verse, and the prisoner likewise answered with greetings in verse.  	After the death of Theophilos, his son Michael III (842-867) began to rule, but not being of mature age, the Byzantine empire was actually ruled by his mother, the empress Blessed Theodora, a venerator of icons. 	The empress tired to extirpate the Iconoclast heresy, and gave orders to free the confessors imprisoned for icon veneration. The heretic Annios occupying the patriarchal throne was banished, and Saint Methodios chosen in his place. At Constantinople was convened a Local Council with Saint Methodios presiding (842). The Council restored icon veneration and established an annual celebration of the triumph of Orthodoxy. The &quot;Rite of Orthodoxy&quot; compiled by Saint Methodios is done on the First Sunday of the Great Lent. 	Attempting to undermine the authority of Saint Methodios, and also the love and esteem of his flock for him, the heretics slandered him as having transgressed chastity. The slandering was exposed as such, and the enemies of the saint put to shame. The final years of the saint passed peacefully, he toiled much, wisely guided the Church and his flock, renovated temples ruined by the heretics, gathered up the relics of saints scattered about by the heretics, and transferred the relics of Patriarch Nicephoros from the place of his imprisonment back to Constantinople. Saint Methodios died in the year 846. He was spiritually close to the Monk Ioannikos (Comm. 4 November), who had foretold him his becoming patriarch and also the time of his end. Besides the &quot;Rite of Orthodoxy&quot;, the holy hierarch also compiled a rule for those converted to the faith, three rites of marriage and several pastoral sermons and church songs.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
The truth of things revealed thee to thy flock as a rule of faith,/ a model of meekness and a teacher of abstinence/ wherefore thou hast attained the heights through humility/ and riches through poverty.// O hierarch Methodius our father, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Thou didst struggle on earth like an incorporeal being, O Methodius,/ and hast inherited the heavens,/ as one who explained the veneration of icons to the ends of the earth;/ for subjected all the more to labors and pangs,// thou didst not cease boldly to denounce those who cast aside the icons of Christ.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>