<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Алексий, митрополит Московский и всея России"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Святитель Алексий, митрополит Московский и всея России чу-  дотворец (в миру Елевферий) родился в 1292 году (по другим данным, 1304) в Москве в семье боярина Феодора Бяконта, выход-  ца из Черниговского княжества.     Господь рано открыл будущему святителю его высокое пред- назначение. На двенадцатом году жизни Елевферий раскинул сети для ловли птиц, незаметно для самого себя задремал и вдруг  явственно услышал голос: «Алексий! Что напрасно трудишься? Ты будешь ловить людей». С этого дня отрок стал уединяться, часто посещать церковь и в пятнадцать лет решился стать иноком. В 1320 году он вступил в Московский Богоявленский монастырь, где провел более двадцати лет в строгих иноческих подвигах. Ру- ководителями его и друзьями были замечательные подвижники этой обители — старец Геронтий и Стефан, брат преподобного Сер- гия Радонежского. Затем митрополит Феогност повелел будущему святителю оставить монастырь и заведовать судебными делами Церкви. Эту должность святой исполнял 12 лет со званием митро- поличьего наместника. В конце 1350 года владыка Феогност посвя- тил Алексия во епископа Владимирского, а по смерти митрополи- та он стал его преемником в 1354 году. В то время Русская Цер- ковь раздираема была великими нестроениями и распрями, в част- ности из-за претензий митрополита Литвы и Волыни Романа. В 1356 году, чтобы положить конец смутам и тревогам, святитель отправился в Константинополь к Вселенскому Патриарху. Патри- арх Каллист дал Алексию право считаться архиепископом Киева и великой России с титулом «всечестнаго митрополита и экзарха». На обратном пути во время бури на море кораблю грозила гибель. Алексий молился и дал обет построить храм святому того дня, в который корабль пристанет к берегу. Буря утихла, корабль при- стал 16 августа. Восторженно встретила святителя Москва.     Несмотря на все смуты, святитель Алексий всячески заботился о своей пастве — ставил епископов, устраивал общежительные монастыри (по образцу Троицкого, основанного Преподобным Сергием), налаживал отношения с ордынскими ханами. Не раз святому и самому приходилось путешествовать в Золотую Орду. В 1357 году хан потребовал у великого князя, чтобы святитель прибыл к нему и исцелил слепую Тайдулу — его супругу. «Про- шение и дело превышает меру сил моих, — сказал святой Алек- сий, — но я верю Тому, Который дал прозреть слепому, — не пре- зрит Он молитвы веры». И действительно, по его молитве,, окроп- ленная святой водой, супруга хана исцелилась.    Когда скончался великий князь Иоанн, святитель взял под свою опеку малолетнего его сына Димитрия (будущего Донского). Много пришлось святому владыке потрудиться, дабы примирять и смирять строптивых князей, не желавших признавать власть Москвы. Вместе с тем не оставлял митрополит и трудов по уст- ройству новых обителей. Им основаны в 1361 году Спаса Неруко- творенного Образа монастырь на Яузе в Москве (Андроников, по имени ученика преподобного Сергия, первого игумена монастыря) по обету, который он дал, когда корабль во время его поездки в Константинополь терпел бедствие; Чудов — в Московском Кремле, восстановлены и две древние обители — Благовещенская в Ниж- нем Новгороде и Константино-Еленинская во Владимире. В 1361 году также была построена женская общежительная обитель его имени (Алексеевская).    Святитель Алексий достиг глубокой старости — 78 лет, пробыв на митрополичьей кафедре 24 года. Почил он 12 февраля 1378 года и погребен по завещанию в Чудовом монастыре. Мощи его были обретены через 50 лет чудесным образом, после чего стали чтить память великого святителя и молитвенника за Русскую землю. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ а҆пⷭлѡмъ сопресто́льна, и҆ врача̀ предо́бра, и҆ слꙋжи́телѧ бл҃гопрїѧ́тна, къ ра́цѣ твое́й честнѣ́й притека́юще ст҃и́телю а҆леѯсї́е, бг҃омꙋ́дре чꙋдотво́рче, соше́дшесѧ любо́вїю въ па́мѧть твою̀ свѣ́тлѡ пра́зднꙋемъ, въ пѣ́снехъ и҆ пѣ́шихъ ра́дꙋющесѧ, и҆ хрⷭта̀ сла́вѧще, таковꙋ́ю бл҃года́ть тебѣ̀ дарова́вшаго и҆сцѣле́нїй, и҆ гра́дꙋ твоемꙋ̀ вели́кое ѹ҆твержде́нїе. 
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
А҆пⷭльскихъ догма҄тъ ѻ҆па́сна храни́телѧ, цр҃кве рѡссї́йскїѧ па́стырѧ и҆ ѹ҆чи́телѧ, пребл҃же́ннагѡ а҆леѯсї́а ст҃и́телѧ па́мѧть пра́зднꙋюще, славосло́вимъ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а на́шего пѣ́сньми достодо́лжными, дарова́вшаго на́мъ ѹ҆го́дника своего̀ ꙗ҆́кѡ ѻ҆би́льный и҆сто́чникъ точа́щь врачева҄нїѧ, гра́дꙋ же москвѣ̀ похвалꙋ̀ и҆ ѹ҆твержде́нїе. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Бж҃е́ственнаго и҆ пречестна́го ст҃и́телѧ хрⷭто́ва, но́ваго чꙋдотво́рца а҆леѯсї́а, вѣ́рнѡ всѝ пою́ще лю́дїе, любо́вїю да ѹ҆бл҃жи́мъ, ꙗ҆́кѡ па́стырѧ вели́каго, слꙋжи́телѧ же и҆ ѹ҆чи́телѧ премꙋ́дра землѝ рѡссї́йстѣй: дне́сь въ па́мѧть є҆гѡ̀ прите́кше, ра́достнѡ возопїе́мъ пѣ́снь бг҃оно́сномꙋ: ꙗ҆́кѡ и҆мѣ́ѧ дерзнове́нїе къ бг҃ꙋ, многоѡбра́зныхъ на́съ и҆зба́ви ѡ҆бстоѧ́нїй, да зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ ѹ҆твержде́нїе гра́дꙋ на́шемꙋ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Alexei, Metropolitan of Moscow and All Russia the Wonderworker"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Alexei, Metropolitan of Moscow and All Russia the Wonderworker, (in the world Elevtherii), was born in the year 1292 (or by another source 1304) at Moscow into the family of the boyar-noble Theodore (Feodor) Byakont, a descendant of the Chernigov princely line. 	The Lord early on revealed to the future saint his lofty destiny. At twelve years of age Elevtherii ha set a snare for the netting of birds, and imperceptibly he dozed off and suddenly he heard quite distinctly a voice: &quot;Alexei! Why toilest thou in vain? Thou art to be a netter of people&quot;.From this day on the lad tended towards seclusion, he frequently visited church, and at age fifteen he decided to become a monk. In 1320 he entered the Moscow Theophany monastery, where he spent more than twelve years at strict monastic efforts. As guides for him and his companions there were the reknown ascetics of the monastery, the startsi-elders Gerontii and Stefan, brother of the Monk Sergei of Radonezh. Metropolitan Theognist then bade the future saint to leave the monastery and manage the juridical affairs of the Church. The saint fulfilled this office for 12 years as vicar of the metropolitan. Towards the end of 1350 Vladyka Theognist had Alexei ordained as bishop of Vladimir; upon the death of the metropolitan he became his successor in the year 1354. During this period the Russian Church was torn amidst great rifts and quarrels, in part because of the pretensions of the metropolitan of Lithuania and Volynia, Roman. In 1356, in order to put an end to the troubles and disturbances, the saint set off to Constantinople to the OEcumenical Patriarch. Patriarch Kallistos gave Saint Alexei the right to both be called and to consider himself Archbishop of Kiev and Great Russia with the title, &quot;All-Venerable Metropolitan and Exarch&quot;. On the return journey during the time of a storm at sea the ship was in danger of shipwreck. Saint Alexei prayed and gave a vow to build a temple to the saint of that day, when the ship should come to shore. The storm subsided, and the ship arrived on 16 August. Moscow delightedly came out to meet the saint. 	In spite of problems on every side, Saint Alexei concerned himself everywhere over his flock: he sent forth bishops, he established life-in-common monasteries (on the model of the Trinity Lavra, founded by the Monk Sergei), and he brought order to relations with the khans of the Horde. The saint himself occasioned more than once to journey to the Golden Horde. In 1357 the khan demanded of the greatprince, that the saint should come to him and heal the blindness of Taidul, his spouse. &quot;The request and the matter is beyond my powers, -- said Saint Alexei, -- but I do believe in Him That gaveth the blind man to see, and that He shalt not disdain my prayers of faith&quot;. And actually, through his prayer, and being sprinkled with holy water, the wife of the khan was healed. 	When Greatprince Ioann died, his young son Dimitrii (the future Donskoy), still in age a minor, was taken under the saint&apos;s guardianship. The holy vladyka had much toil in reconciling and appeasing  princes obstinate against accepting the authority of Moscow. Nor did the metropolitan neglect the work of organising new monasteries. In 1361 he founded the Saviour Image Not-Wrought-by-Hand monastery at the Yauza in Moscow (the disciple of the Monk Sergei -- Andronikov by name -- was the first hegumen of the monastery), from the vow he had given back on his return journey from Constantinople, when the ship had suffered woe. There was also the Chudov monastery -- in the Moscow Kremlin; likewise, ancient monasteries were restored: the Annunciation monastery at Nizhni-Novgorod, and the Konstantino-Eleninsk [Constantine and Helen] at Vladimir. And in 1361 there was built a women&apos;s life-in-common monastery after his name (the Alekseev). 	Saint Alexei reached the advanced age of 78, having spent 24 years upon the metropolitan cathedra-seat. He reposed on 12 February 1378 and was buried in accord with his last-wishes at the Chudov monastery. His relics were uncovered in a miraculous manner 50 years later, after which there began the veneration of the memory of the great Sainted-Hierarch and Man of Prayer for the Russian Land. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Hastening to thy precious shrine, O holy hierarch Alexis, divinely wise wonder-worker, assembling with love, we celebrate with splendor the memory of thee who art equally enthroned with the apostles, the all-good physician, the right pleasing servant; and we rejoice with songs and hymns, glorifying Christ Who hath given thee such grace to heal and bestowed upon thy city so great a bulwark.
</TROPARION>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
	Celebrating the memory of the all-blessed and holy hierarch Alexis, the careful preserver of the dogmas of the apostles, the shepherd and teacher of the Church of Russia, let us glorify with right fitting hymnody Christ our God Who hath given us His favored one as an abundant well-spring pouring forth healings, the boast and confirmation of the city of Moscow.
	</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
O all ye people, hymning with faith the new wonder-worker Alexis, the godly and all-honorable hierarch of Christ, let us bless him with love, as a great pastor, an all-wise minister and teacher of the land of Russia. And hastening today to his memorial, let us joyfully give utterance to a hymn to the God-bearer: As thou hast boldness before God, deliver us from multifarious evil circumstances, that we may cry to thee: Rejoice, O confirmation of our city!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>