<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой мученик Иулиан Тарсийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святой мученик Иулиан Тарсийский родился в малоазийской провинции Киликия. Он был сыном сенатора-язычника, мать его исповедовала христианство. После смерти мужа мать святого Иулиана переселилась в город Таре, где крестила сына и вос- питала в христианском благочестии. Когда святому исполнилось 18 лет, император Диоклитиан (284—305) начал гонение на хри- стиан. В числе других был схвачен и святой Иулиан. Его привели к правителю Маркиану на суд, где долго уговаривали отречься от Христа. Ни истязания, ни угрозы, ни обещания даров и почестей не могли склонить благочестивого юношу к принесению языческих жертв и отречению от Христа. Святой исповедник оставался непо- колебимым в твердой вере. Целый год мученика водили по горо- дам Киликийской области, в каждом из них подвергая допросам и жестоким истязаниям, после чего бросили в темницу. Мать свя- того Иулиана следовала за сыном и молилась, чтобы Господь еще более укрепил его в вере и подвиге. В городе Эгее под предлогом убедить сына принести жертву идолам, она просила правителя разрешить ей посещать темницу. Три дня она провела в темнице со святым Иулианом, умоляя его быть твердым до конца. Святой Иулиан вновь предстал перед правителем. Думая, что мать убедила сына повиноваться императорскому указу, прави- тель стал хвалить ее благоразумие. Неожиданно святая смело ис- поведала себя христианкой. Святой мученик Иулиан все так же бесстрашно и мужественно обличал языческое многобожие. Тогда правитель приказал отрубить матери святого Иулиана ступни ног за то, что она сопровождала сына из Тарса. Святая мученица скончалась от нанесенных ран. Мученика Иулиана зашили в ме- шок, наполненный песком и ядовитыми гадами, и бросили в море. Тело страдальца было вынесено волнами на берег около Алек- сандрии и с честью погребено одной благочестивой александрий- ской христианкой. Мученическая кончина его последовала около 305 года. Впоследствии мощи святого мученика перенесли в город Антиохию. Святитель Иоанн Златоуст почтил память святого му- ченика Иулиана похвальным словом. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нкъ тво́й гдⷭи, ї҆ꙋлїа́нъ, во страда́нїи свое́мъ вѣне́цъ прїѧ́тъ нетлѣ́нный ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мѣ́ѧй бо крѣ́пость твою̀, мꙋчи́телей низложѝ, сокрꙋшѝ и҆ де́монѡвъ немощны́ѧ де́рзѡсти: тогѡ̀ мл҃твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="4">
Бл҃гоче́стїѧ непобѣди́маго во́ина, и҆ и҆́стины согла́сника и҆ ѻ҆рꙋ́жника, всѝ досто́йнѡ восхва́лимъ ї҆ꙋлїа́на дне́сь, и҆ къ немꙋ̀ возопїи́мъ: молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyr Julian of Tarsis"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyr Julian of Tarsis was born in the Asia Minor province of Cilicia. He was the son of a pagan senator, but his mother confessed Christianity. After the death of her husband the mother of Saint Julian resettled to Tarsis, where the son was baptised and raised in Christian piety. When Julian reached age 18, a persecution against Christians started under the emperor Diocletian (284-305). Among others arrested was also Saint Julian. They brought him before the governor Marcian for trial, where for a long time they urged him to renounce Christ. Neither tortures nor threats, nor promises of gifts and honours could convince the pious youth to offer pagan sacrifice and a denial of Christ. The holy confessor remained steadfast in his firm faith. For a whole year they led the martyr through the cities of Cilicia, in each of them subjecting him to interrogation and tortures, after which they threw him in prison. The mother of Saint Julian followed after her son and prayed, that the Lord would strengthen him yet more in faith and act. In the city of Aegea under the pretext of urging her son to offer sacrifice to idols, she besought the governor to permit her to visit the prison. She spent three days in prison with Saint Julian, beseeching him to be strong to the end. 	Saint Julian was again brought to stand before the governor. Thinking, that the mother had persuaded her son to submit to the imperial decree, the governor began to praise her prudence. But suddenly the saint boldly confessed himself a Christian. And the holy Martyr Julian all the more fearlessly and boldly denounced the pagan polytheism. The governor then gave orders to cut off the feet of the mother of Saint Julian, since she had accompanied her son from Tarsis. They tied the Martyr Julian into a sack, filled with sand and poisonous vipers, and threw it into the sea. The body of the sufferer was carried by the waves to the shores of Alexandria, and with reverence was buried by a certain pious Alexandrian Christian. The martyr&apos;s death occurred in about the year 305. Afterwards the relics of the holy martyr were transferred to Antioch. Saint John Chrysostom honoured the memory of the holy Martyr Julian with a sermon of laudation.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In his suffering, O Lord,/ Thy martyr Julian received an imperishable crown from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ he set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By his supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="4">
As is meet, let us all praise Julian today,/ the invincible warrior of piety,/ the true counselor and soldier of the Truth,/ and let us cry aloud unto him:/ Entreat Christ God in behalf of us all!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>