<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой папа Римский Сильвестр"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святой папа Римский Сильвестр (314—335) родился в Риме от родителей-христиан Руфина и Иусты. Вскоре отец его скончался, и святой остался на попечении матери. Учитель Сильвестра, пре- свитер Квирин, дал ему хорошее образование и воспитал как ис- тинного христианина. Достигнув совершеннолетия, Сильвестр стал исполнять заповедь Господа о служении ближним, особенно забо- тясь о приеме странников, предоставляя им в своем доме приют и отдых. Во время гонения на христиан Сильвестр не убоялся при- нять святого исповедника епископа Тимофея, который прожил у него более года и своей проповедью обратил многих ко Христу. После мученической кончины Тимофея, Сильвестр тайно взял тело святого и с честью предал его погребению. Это стало известно гра- доначальнику Тарквинию; святой был схвачен и предстал перед судом. Тарквиний принуждал его отречься от Христа, грозя мука- ми и смертью. Святой Сильвестр, однако, не устрашился, остался тверд в исповедании веры и был заключен в темницу. Когда же Тарквиний после суда скоропостижно умер, святой получил сво- боду и стал бесстрашно благовествовать язычникам, многих обра- тив в христианство. В тридцатилетнем возрасте святой Сильвестр был принят в клир Римской Церкви и рукоположен в сан диакона, а потом и пресвитера, папой Марцеллином (296—304). После смер- ти папы Мельхиада (311—314) святой Сильвестр был избран епи- скопом Римским. Он ревностно заботился о чистоте жизни паствы, следил за тем, чтобы пресвитеры строго исполняли свое служение, не отягощаясь мирскими делами.     Святитель Сильвестр славился как глубокий знаток Священно- го Писания и непоколебимый защитник христианской веры. В цар- ствование императора Константина Великого, когда для Церкви  кончился период гонений, иудеи устроили диспут об истинной вере,  на котором присутствовали святой равноапостольный царь Кон-  стантин, его мать — святая царица Елена и многочисленная свита.  Со стороны христиан выступил папа Сильвестр, а от иудеев —  множество ученых раввинов, во главе с Замврием, чернокнижни-  ком и чародеем. На основании Священных книг Ветхого Завета  святой Сильвестр убедительно доказал, что всеми пророками было  предсказано Рождество Иисуса Христа от Неискусобрачной Девы,  Его вольное страдание, смерть для искупления падшего рода чело-  веческого и славное Воскресение. В этом словесном состязании  святитель был признан победителем. Тогда Замврий пытался при-  бегнуть к чародейству, но святой воспрепятствовал злу, призывая  Имя Господа Иисуса Христа. Замврий и остальные иудеи уверо-  вали во Христа и просили совершить над ними святое Крещение.  Святой папа Сильвестр управлял Римской Церковью более двад-  цати лет, пользуясь глубоким уважением христиан. Он мирно скон-  чался в глубокой старости в 335 году. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Пра́вило вѣ́ры и҆ ѡ҆́бразъ кро́тости, воздержа́нїѧ ѹ҆чи́телѧ ꙗ҆ви́ тѧ ста́дꙋ твоемꙋ̀, ꙗ҆́же веще́й и҆́стина: сегѡ̀ ра́ди стѧжа́лъ є҆сѝ смире́нїемъ высѡ́каѧ, нището́ю бога҄таѧ, ѻ҆́тче сїлве́стре, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Во сщ҃е́нницѣхъ сщ҃е́нникъ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ цр҃ѧ̀ и҆ бг҃а бг҃оно́се, по́стникѡмъ собесѣ́дникъ бы́въ: ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже сра́дꙋешисѧ ны́нѣ ликѡ́мъ а҆́гг҃льскимъ, ѻ҆́тче, веселѧ́сѧ въ нбⷭныхъ, сїлве́стре сла́вне па́стырю, сп҃са́й любо́вно соверша́ющыѧ па́мѧть твою̀.
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Holy Pope of Rome Sylvester"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Pope of Rome Sylvester (314-335) was born at Rome of Christian parents named Rufinus and Justa. His father soon died, and the saint remained in the care of his mother. Sylvester&apos;s teacher, the presbyter Quirinus, gave him a fine education and raised him as a true Christian. Having reached the age of maturity, Sylvester set about fulfilling the command of the Lord about service to neighbour, and particularly concerned himself with the taking in of vagrants, offering them in his own house shelter and respite. During a time of persecution against Christians, Sylvester did not hesitate to take in the holy confessor Bishop Timothy, who dwelt with him for more than a year and who by his preaching converted many to Christ. After the Martyr&apos;s death of Timothy, Sylvester secretly took up the body of the saint and reverently gave it burial. This however came to the attention of the city-head Tarquinius, and the saint was arrested and brought to trial. Tarquinius demanded him to renounce Christ, threatening him with torture and death. Saint Sylvester was however not intimidated, and he remained steadfast in his confession of faith, and was then thrown into prison. When Tarquinius suddenly died after the trial, the saint was set free and fearlessly he evangelised amongst the pagans, converting many to Christianity. At thirty years of age Saint Sylvester was accepted into the clergy of the Roman Church and was ordained to the dignity of deacon, and then also presbyter, by Pope Marcellinus (296-304). After the death of Pope Militiades (or Melchiades, 311-314), Saint Sylvester was chosen bishop of Rome. He zealously concerned himself about the purity of life in his flock, and he insisted that presbyters strictly fulfill their duty, and not be overwhelmed with worldly matters. 	Saint Sylvester became reknown as a profound expert on Holy Scripture and as a staunch defender of the Christian faith. During the reign of the emperor Saint Constantine the Great, when the periods of persecution had ended for the Church, the Jews arranged a debate about the true faith, at which were present the holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Emperor Constantine and his mother -- the holy Empress Helen, together with a numerous retinue. On the side of the Christians Pope Sylvester stood forth, and on the side of the Jews -- a number of learned rabbis, headed by Zambrius, a magician and sorcerer. On the basis of the Sacred books of the Old Testament, Saint Sylvester convincingly demonstrated, that all the prophets foretold the Birth of Jesus Christ from the Immaculate Virgin, and also His voluntary Suffering and Death for the Redemption of the fallen race of mankind, and His glorious Resurrection. In this verbal confrontation the saint was declared the victor. Then Zambrius tried to resort to sorcery, but the saint obstructed the evil by calling on the Name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Zambrius and the other Jews came to believe in Jesus Christ, and they besought that there be made over them the holy Baptism. Pope Saint Sylvester directed the Roman Church for more than twenty years, and earning deep esteem as a Christian. He died peacefully in old age in the year 335.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
The truth of things revealed thee to thy flock as a rule of faith,/ a model of meekness and a teacher of abstinence/ wherefore thou hast attained the heights through humility/ and riches through poverty.// O hierarch Sylvester our father, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
As a conversor with the ascetics, thou becamest a priest among the priests of God the King; wherefore, thou rejoicest now with the angelic choirs. O father Sylvester, thou God-bearing shepherd, dwelling in the heavens, save those who with love celebrate thy memory.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>