<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Собор святых славных и всехвальных 12-ти Апостолов"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Собор святых славных и всехвальных 12-ти Апостолов Хри- стовых является древним праздником. Святая Церковь, чествуя каждого из 12-ти апостолов в разное время года, с давних времен установила общее празднование им на следующий день после па- мяти славных и первоверховных апостолов Петра и Павла ({ ок. &quot;• 67). Сведения о каждом апостоле в день его сугубой памяти: апостол Петр (^ ок. 67; память 29 июня); апостол Андрей Пер- возванный (1&quot; 62; память 30 ноября); апостол Иаков Зеведеев ( } 44; память 30 апреля); апостол и Евангелист Иоанн Богослов • • (+ нач. II в.; память 26 сентября); апостол Филипп (I; память 14 ноября); апостол Варфоломей (I; память 11 июня); апостол Фома (I; память 6 октября); апостол и Евангелист Матфей (+60; память 16 ноября); апостол Иаков Алфеев (I; память 9 ок- тября); апостол Иуда, брат Господень (•$ ок. 80; память 19 июня); апостол Симон Зилот (I; память 10 мая); апостол Матфий а ок. 63; память 9 августа). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
А҆пⷭлѡвъ первопресто́льницы, и҆ вселе́нныѧ ѹ҆чи́телїе, влⷣкꙋ всѣ́хъ моли́те, ми́ръ вселе́ннѣй дарова́ти, и҆ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ ве́лїю млⷭть. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Ка́мень хрⷭто́съ, ка́менѧ вѣ́ры прославлѧ́етъ свѣ́тлѡ, ѹ҆ч҃нкѡ́въ преизрѧ́дна, и҆ съ па́ѵломъ ве́сь дванадесѧточи́сленный собо́ръ дне́сь: и҆́хже па́мѧть соверша́юще вѣ́рнѡ си́хъ просла́вльшаго прославлѧ́емъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Synaxis of the Twelve Glorious and All-Praised Apostles"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Sobor (Assemblage) of the Glorious and All-Praiseworthy 12 Apostles of Christ appears an ancient feast. Holy Church, -- honouring each of the 12 Apostles at a separate time of the year, from ancient times established a general commemoration of them on the day following after the commemoration of the Glorious and First-Ranked among the Apostles Peter and Paul (+ c. 67). An account about each of the Apostles is on the day of his individual commemoration: the Apostle Peter (+ c. 67; Comm. 29 June); the Apostle Andrew the First-Called (+ 62, Comm. 30 November); the Apostle James son of Zebedee (+ 44, Comm. 30 April); the Apostle and Evangelist John the Theologian (+ early II Century, Comm. 26 September); Apostle Philip (Comm. 14 November); Apostle Bartholomew (Comm. 11 June); Apostle Thomas (Comm. 6 October); Apostle and Evangelist Matthew (+ 60, Comm. 16 November); Apostle James Alphaeus (Comm. 9October); Apostle Jude, brother of the Lord (+ c. 80, Comm. 19 June); Apostle Simon Zelotes (Comm. 10 May); Apostle Matthias (+ c. 63, Comm. 9 August). 	The holy nobleborn emperor Constantine the Great (306-337) built at Tsar&apos;grad a temple in the name of the holy Twelve Apostles. Directions for the celebrating of this feast are encountered from the IV Century.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O first enthroned among the apostles/ and teachers of the whole world;/ entreat the Master of all,/ that He grant peace to the world// and great mercy to our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Christ the Rock doth radiantly glorify the rock of Faith,/ the most excellent of His disciples,/ as He doth Paul and the assembly of the twelve today;/ and, faithfully celebrating their memory,// we glorify Him Who glorified them.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>