<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Сщмч. Феопемпт, еп. Никомидийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Святые мученики Феопемпт и Феона пострадали в Никомидии в 303 году. Святой Феопемпт был епископом в Никомидии при Дио- клитиане. Выступая против идолопоклонства, он защищал веру Христову. Призванный к царю, он отказался выполнить его требо- вание поклониться идолу Аполлону. Святого Феопемпта бросили в раскаленную печь, но он, силой Божией, остался жив. Ночью царь с отрядом воинов пошел к печи и там действительно увидел святого живым и молящимся Богу. Приписывая свершившееся чудо действию волхвования, Диоклитиан приказал морить святого Фео- пемпта голодом и жаждой в течение 22 дней, но и тут волей Бо- жией мученик был сохранен.    Тогда царь призвал известного волшебника Феону, взявшегося разрушить «чары», которыми, как они предполагали, обладает святой епископ Феопемпт. Феона приготовил для святого Феопемпта яд, вложенный в лепешку, и предложил ему съесть ее. Яд нисколь- ко не повредил святому Феопемпту. Феона во второй раз испытал на мученике действие еще более сильного яда, но, видя, что святой Феопемпт остается невредим, сам уверовал во Христа. Его бросили в темницу вместе со святым епископом, который огласил его и кре- стил, дав ему имя Синесий (что значит «исполненный разума»).     Утром Диоклитиан призвал святого Феопемпта и вновь убеж- дал отречься от Христа, но, видя непреклонную твердость святого мужа, предал его многим и тяжким мукам, после чего святой был обезглавлен. Святой мученик Феона, отказавшийся принести жерт- ву идолам, был живым закопан в глубокий ров. Это произошло в Никомидии в 303 году. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Holy Martyrs Theopemptos and Theon"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
 	The Holy Martyrs Theopemptos and Theon suffered in Nicomedia in the year 303. Saint Theopemptos was bishop in Nicomedia during the time of Diocletian. Speaking out against idol-worship, he defended the faith in Christ. Summoned to the emperor, he refused to carry out his demand to worship an idol of Apollo. They threw Saint Theopemptos into a red-hot furnace, but by the power of God he remained alive. The emperor came by night with a detachment of soldiers to the furnace and there actually saw the saint alive and praying to God. Ascribing the miracle accomplished to be a work of magic, Diocletian gave orders to wear down Saint Theopemptos by hunger and thirst during the course of 22 days, but here also by the will of God the martyr was preserved. 	The emperor then summoned the famous sorcerer Theon, brought in to overcome the magical power which, as they supposed, was possessed by the holy bishop Theopemptos. Theon prepared a poison for Saint Theopemptos -- put into a little cake, and offered it to him to eat. The poison did no harm at all to Saint Theopemptos. A second time, Theon tried out the effect of a still stronger poison on the martyr; but seeing, that Saint Theopemptos remained unharmed, he himself came to believe in Christ. They threw him into prison together with the holy bishop, who taught and baptised him, giving him the name Synesios (which means &quot;fulfillment of understanding&quot;). 	In the morning Diocletian summoned Saint Theopemptos and again contended with him to recant from Christ; but, seeing the unbending rigour of the holy man, he subjected him to many grievous tortures, after which the saint was beheaded. The holy martyr Theon, having refused to offer sacrifice to idols, was buried alive in a deep ditch. This occurred at Nicomedia in the year 303.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>