<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобная Синклитикия"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобная Синклитикия родом из Александрии, дочь богатых родителей, прекрасная собой, с юных лет помышляла только об угождении Богу. Возлюбив чистоту девства, она отказалась всту- пить в брак и всё время проводила в посте и молитве. После смер- ти родителей она раздала нищим имущество и со своей слепой се- строй, приняв иночество, скрылась в одной из гробниц, принадле- жавших ее родственникам. Слава о ее подвигах быстро распро- странилась в окрестностях, и много благочестивых жен и дев при- шли к ней, чтобы жить под ее руководством. В продолжение своей подвижнической жизни святая усердно словом и делом поучала сестер. На 80-м году жизни ее постигла тяжелая и мучительная болезнь. Преподобная с истинно христианским терпением перено- сила ниспосланное ей испытание. Скончалась святая около/350 го- да, в возрасте 83-х лет. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Nun Syncleticea"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Nun Syncleticea was a native of Alexandria, the daughter of rich parents, pretty, and from her early years she thought only about things pleasing to God. Loving the purity of virginity, she declined to enter into marriage, and spent all her time in fasting and prayer. After the death of her parents she distributed her inheritance to the poor, and having accepted monasticism together with her blind sister, she withdrew into one of the crypts belonging to her kin. News about her ascetic deeds quickly spread throughout the vicinity, and many pious women and girls came to her to live under her guidance. During the course of her ascetic life the saint zealously instructed her sisters by word and by deed. In her 80th year of life she was struck by an intense and grievous illness. The nun bore the outcome of her ordeal with true christian endurance. The saint died in about the year 350, at age 83.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>