<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Никон Радонежский, игумен"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov">
Ученик преподобного Сергия Радонежского. Родился в Юрьев-Польском. В юном возрасте, услышав об ангельской жизни преподобного Сергия и желая последовать ему, святой пришел к преподобному Сергию и просил приобщения к лику монашествующих. Преподобный Сергий, провидя в нем будущего великого подвижника и испытывая его смирение и терпение, отослал св. Никона к своему ученику преподобному Афанасию Высоцкому. Здесь преподобный Никон учился умному деланию, изучал Священное Писание и преуспевал в добродетели и чистоте.

Возведенный в сан иеромонаха, преподобный Никон вернулся в Троице-Сергиеву лавру и стал любимым и близким учеником преподобного Сергия. Видя духовную зрелость и опытность преподобного Никона, преподобный Сергий перед смертью назначил его своим преемником.

Став игуменом, преподобный Никон поддерживал все, что было установлено учителем: любил молитву и пост, трудился наравне с братией, о которой постоянно с любовью заботился.

При преподобном Никоне 5 июля 1422 г., во время строительства нового храма во имя Живоначальной Троицы, были обретены нетленные мощи преподобного Сергия Радонежского.

После многих трудов и подвигов преподобный Никон скончался 17 ноября 1426 г. и был погребен близ раки своего учителя. В 1560 г. над могилой преподобного был построен храм во имя его. Мощи преподобного Никона, почивающие здесь под гробницей, отделяются от раки великого Сергия одной каменной стеной.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Послꙋша́нїѧ до́брый рачи́тель бы́въ, преподо́бне нї́кѡне приснопа́мѧтне: цр҃ковь бо прекра́снꙋ ст҃ы́ѧ трⷪцы, въ похвалꙋ̀ ѻ҆ц҃ꙋ̀ твоемꙋ̀ воздви́глъ є҆сѝ. тѣ́мже и҆ мы̀ ча҄да твоѧ҄ любо́вїю вопїе́мъ тѝ: сла́ва да́вшемꙋ тѝ крѣ́пость, сла́ва вѣнча́вшемꙋ тѧ̀, сла́ва дѣ́йствꙋющемꙋ тобо́ю всѣ҄мъ и҆сцѣлє́нїѧ.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Дх҃о́вномꙋ твоемꙋ̀ настоѧ́телю, ѻ҆́тче нї́кѡне, всѧ́чески прилѣпи́всѧ, и҆ ѿ негѡ̀ наставлѧ́емь, во все́мъ хрⷭто́ви порабо́тивсѧ, мона́хѡвъ бы́лъ є҆сѝ чинонача́льникъ, и҆ прпⷣбныхъ сожи́тель, съ ни́миже хрⷭта̀ бг҃а молѝ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Our Venerable Father Nikon Wonderworker, disciple of St. Sergius"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
    Born in Yuriev Povolzhsky, in his youth he, "having scorned earthly beauty and
glory as being nothing", came to the Venerable Sergius, but he reassigned him to
his disciple the Venerable Athanasius Vysotsky (to Serpukhov, the eminent).
When the Venerable Nikon under the direction of this great ascetic achieved the
rank of priest, the Venerable Sergius accepted him in the monastery in 1375. The
Venerable Sergius loved the Venerable Nikon so much because of his habits and
his life that he lived with him in the same cell and finally shortly before his death
assigned him to be the Hegumen. Because of his love for solitude the Venerable
Nikon for a time gave up being Hegumen in the monastery and departed from it for
the exercise of ascetical efforts of silence. In 1422 he was granted the privilege to
open the uncorrupt relics of his director (see July 5). "Pointing out the paradigm of
your good deeds to all, having the grace of God Who loves mankind deeply within
you", "serving the Lord with purity of conscience", he lived "on earth as an angel"
and died in peace on Nov. 17 in 1427 or 1428. The Council of 1547 numbered him
among the saints. In 1548 a church was built over his grave, and in 1623 in place
of this church the new St. Sergius Laura was built, existing to the present time. In
the northwest corner of church, along the northern wall, there is a monument
(gravestone) over the relics of the Venerable Nikon, which are found in the ground
or in a hidden place.

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Having been a good zealot of obedience, O ever-memorable and venerable Nikon, in praise of thy father you erected a church to the Holy Trinity. Therefore we thy children lovingly cry out to thee:
Glory to Him who has given thee strength. Glory to Him who has crowned thee. Glory to Him who through thee works healings for all.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Having cleaved to thy spiritual superior in all things, O Father Nikon, and being instructed by him, thou didst enslave thyself to Christ. Thou wast a superior of monks and co-dweller with the venerable ones. With them beseech Christ God incessantly for us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>
