<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Панкратий, епископ Тавроменийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Священномученик Панкратий, епископ Тавроменийский, родил- ся в то время, когда Господь наш Иисус Христос жил на земле. Родители Панкратия были родом из Антиохии. Услышав о бла- говестии Иисуса Христа, отец Панкратия, взяв с собой юного сына, отправился в Иерусалим, чтобы лично видеть великого Учи- теля. Его потрясли чудеса, и, когда он услышал Божественное учение, то уверовал во Христа как Сына Божия. Он сблизился с учениками Господа, особенно со святым апостолом Петром. С тех пор юноша Панкратий стал известен святому апостолу Петру. После Вознесения Спасителя один из апостолов пришел в Антиохию и крестил родителей Панкратия и весь их дом. Когда родители Панкратия скончались, он, оставив свое имение, ушел в Понтийские горы и стал жить в пещере, проводя дни в молитве и глубоком духовном размышлении. Святой апостол Петр, однаж- ды проходя по тем местам, встретил Панкратия в Понте, взял его с собой в Антиохию, а затем в Киликию, где находился святой апостол Павел. Там святые апостолы Петр и Павел рукоположили Панкратия во епископа сицилийского города Тавромении. Святитель Панкратий усердно трудился над христианским про- свещением народа. В течение одного месяца он построил храм, где совершал Богослужения. Число верующих быстро росло, и вскоре почти все жители Тавромении и окрестных городов приняли христианскую веру. Много лет святой Панкратий мирно управлял своей паствой Однажды язычники восстали на святителя и, выбрав подходящее время, внезапно напали на него и побили камнями. Так мучени- чески окончил свою жизнь святитель Панкратий (I). Мощи свя- тителя покоятся в храме его имени, в Риме. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆ нра́вѡмъ прича́стникъ, и҆ прⷭто́лѡмъ намѣ́стникъ а҆пⷭлѡмъ бы́въ, дѣѧ́нїе ѡ҆брѣ́лъ є҆сѝ бг҃одохнове́нне, въ видѣ́нїѧ восхо́дъ: сегѡ̀ ра́ди сло́во и҆́стины и҆справлѧ́ѧ, и҆ вѣ́ры ра́ди пострада́лъ є҆сѝ да́же до кро́ве, сщ҃енномч҃нче пагкра́тїе, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Свѣ́тлаѧ таѵроменї́ѡмъ пагкра́тїе, ѕвѣзда̀ показа́лсѧ є҆сѝ, и҆ сщ҃еннострада́лецъ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ за хрⷭта̀: є҆мꙋ́же ны́нѣ предстоѧ̀ молѝ за чтꙋ́щыѧ тѧ̀ бл҃же́нне. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="PriestMartyr Pankratios, Bishop of Tauromeneia"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The PriestMartyr Pankratios, Bishop of Tauromeneia, was born at a time, when our Lord Jesus Christ yet lived upon the earth. 	The parents of Pankratios were natives of Antioch. Hearing about the good-news of Jesus Christ, the father of Pankratios took his young son with him and set off to Jerusalem, in order to see for himself personally the great Teacher. The miracles astonished him, and when he heard the Divine teaching, he then believed in Christ as the Son of God. He became close with the disciples of the Lord, especially with the holy Apostle Peter. And it was during this period that young Pankratios got to know the holy Apostle Peter. 	After the Ascension of the Saviour one of the Apostles came to Antioch and baptised the parents of Pankratios together with all their household. When the parents of Pankratios died, he left behind his inherited possessions and went to a Pontine mountain and began to live in a cave, passing his days in prayer and deep spiritual contemplation. The holy Apostle Peter, one time passing through these parts, made a visit to Pankratios at Pontus, and took him along to Antioch, and then to Cilicia, where the holy Apostle Paul then was. And there the holy Apostles Peter and Paul ordained Saint Pankratios as bishop of the Cilician city of Tauromeneia. 	Saint Pankratios toiled zealously for the Christian enlightenment of the people. Over the course of a single month he built a church, where he celebrated Divine-services. The number of believers quickly grew, and soon almost all the people of Tauromeneia and the surrounding cities accepted the Christian faith. 	Saint Pankratios governed his flock peacefully for many years. But one time pagans connived against the saint, and seizing an appropriate moment, they fell upon him and stoned him. Thus did Saint Pankratios end his life as a martyr (I). The relics of the saint rest in the church named for him, at Rome.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
As thou didst share in the ways of the apostles/ and didst occupy their throne,/ thou didst find thine activity to be a passage to divine vision,/ O divinely inspired one./ Wherefore, ordering the word of truth,/ thou didst suffer for the Faith even to the shedding of thy blood.// O hieromartyr Pancratius, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Thou wast shown to be a brilliant star for the people of Taormina, O Pancratius,/ and wast shown also to be a sufferer for Christ.// Standing now before Him pray thou for them that honor thee, O blessed one.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>