<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="   Поклонение честным веригам святого и всехвального апостола Петра"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Поклонение честным веригам святого и всехвального апостола Петра. Около 42 года апостол Петр по повелению Ирода Агриппы был заключен в темницу за проповедь о Христе Спасителе. В тем- нице он был связан двумя железными цепями. Ночью, накануне суда над ним, Ангел Господень снял с апостола эти цепи и чудесно вывел его из темницы (Деян. 12, 1—11). Христиане, услышав о чу- де, взяли вериги (цепи) и хранили их как драгоценность. Одержи- мые разными болезнями, приходя к ним с верою, получали исцеле- ния. Вериги святого апостола Петра хранились в Иерусалиме до Патриарха Ювеналия, который подарил их Евдокии, супруге импе- ратора Феодосия Младшего, а она в 437 и 439 годах перенесла их из Иерусалима в Царьград. Одну веригу Евдокия послала в Рим своей дочери Евдоксии, которая построила храм во имя апостола Петра и положила в нем веригу. В Риме были также и другие ве- риги, в которых находился апостол перед своей кончиной при им- ператоре Нероне.     16 января вериги апостола Петра выносятся на поклонение на- роду. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Ри́ма не ѡ҆ста́вль къ на́мъ прише́лъ є҆сѝ, честны́ми вери́гами, ꙗ҆̀же носи́лъ є҆сѝ, а҆по́столѡвъ первопресто́льнѣ. и҆̀мже вѣ́рою покланѧ́ющесѧ, мо́лимсѧ: твои́ми къ бг҃ꙋ мл҃твами, да́рꙋй на́мъ ве́лїю млⷭть. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Ка́мень хрⷭто́съ, ка́менѧ вѣ́ры, прославлѧ́етъ свѣ́тлѡ ѹ҆ченикѡ́въ первопресто́льника: созыва́етъ бо всѧ҄ пра́здновати пе́тре, чꙋдесѝ твоеѧ̀ чⷭтны́ѧ вери́ги и҆ подае́тъ согрѣше́нїй проще́нїе. 
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="4">
Верхо́внаго и҆ пе́рваго а҆по́столѡвъ, и҆́стины бж҃е́ственнаго ѹ҆ченика̀, петра̀ вели́каго восхва́лимъ, и҆ тогѡ̀ вѣ́рою цѣлꙋ́емъ вери҄ги, прегрѣше́нїй разрѣше́нїе прїе́млюще. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Veneration of the Venerable Shackles of the Holy and All-Praiseworthy Apostle Peter"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Veneration of the Venerable Shackles of the Holy and All-Praiseworthy Apostle Peter: On the orders of Herod Agrippa, in about the year 42 the Apostle Peter was thrown into prison for preaching about Christ the Saviour. In prison he was held secure by two iron chains. By night, on the eve of his trial, an Angel of the Lord removed these chains from the Apostle Peter and miraculously led him out from the prison (Acts12: 1-11). Christians who learned of the miracle took the chains and kept them as precious keepsakes. Those afflicted with illness and approaching them with faith received healing. The Chains of the holy Apostle Peter were kept at Jerusalem until the time of Patriarch Juvenalios, who presented them to Eudocia, spouse of the emperor Theodosius the Younger, and she in turn transferred them from Jerusalem to Constantinople in either the year 437 or 439. Eudocia sent one Chain to Rome to her daughter Eudoxia, who built a church in the name of the Apostle Peter and put within it the Chain. At Rome were also other Chains, in which the Apostle Peter found himself before his death under the emperor Nero. 	On 16 January the Chains of the Apostle Peter are brought out for veneration by the people.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Without leaving Rome thou art come to us in the precious chains which thou didst bear, O first-enthroned of the apostles; and, bowing down before them with faith we pray: through thy supplications unto God grant us great mercy!
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Christ the Rock most splendidly glorifieth the rock of faith, the first-enthroned of His disciples; for He summoneth all to celebrate the wonders of thy precious chains, O Peter, and granteth forgiveness of offenses.
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="4">
Let us praise the great Peter, the chief and first among the apostles, the divine disciple of the Truth, and with faith let us kiss his chains, receiving release from our transgressions.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>