<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Серафим Саровский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобный Серафим Саровский, великий подвижник Русской Церкви, родился 19 июля 1754 года. Родители преподобного, Иси- дор и Агафия Мошнины,, были жителями Курска. Исидор был куп- цом и брал подряды на строительство зданий, а в конце жизни начал постройку собора в Курске, но скончался до завершения работ. Младший сын Прохор остался на попечении матери, воспи- тавшей в сыне глубокую веру.    После смерти мужа Агафия Мошнина, продолжавшая построй- ку собора, взяла однажды туда с собой Прохора, который, осту- пившись, упал с колокольни вниз. Господь сохранил жизнь буду- щего светильника Церкви: испуганная мать, спустившись вниз, на- шла сына невредимым.    Юный Прохор, обладая прекрасной памятью, вскоре выучился грамоте. Он с детства любил посещать церковные службы и чи- тать своим сверстникам Священное Писание и Жития святых, но  больше всего любил молиться или читать Святое Евангелие в уеди- нении.     Как-то Прохор тяжело заболел, жизнь его была в опасности. Во сне мальчик увидел Божию Матерь, обещавшую посетить и ис- целить его. Вскоре через двор усадьбы Мошниных прошел крест- ный ход с иконой Знамения Пресвятой Богородицы; мать вынесла Прохора на руках, и он приложился к святой иконе, после чего стал быстро поправляться.     Еще в юности у Прохора созрело решение всецело посвятить жизнь Богу и уйти в монастырь. Благочестивая мать не препятст- вовала этому и благословила его на иноческий путь распятием, которое преподобный всю жизнь носил на груди. Прохор с палом- никами отправился пешком из Курска в Киев на поклонение Пе- черским угодникам.     Схимонах старец Досифей, которого посетил Прохор, благосло- вил его идти в Саровскую пустынь и спасаться там. Вернувшись ненадолго в родительский дом, Прохор навсегда простился с ма- терью и родными. 20 ноября 1778 года он пришел в Сэров, где настоятелем тогда был мудрый старец, отец Пахомий. Он ласково принял юношу и назначил ему в духовники старца Иосифа. Под его руководством Прохор проходил многие послушания в мона- стыре: был келейником старца, трудился в хлебне, просфорне и столярне, нес обязанности пономаря, и всё исполнял с ревностью и усердием, служа как бы Самому Господу. Постоянной работой он ограждал себя от скуки — этого, как позже он говорил, «опас- нейшего искушения для новоначальных иноков, которое врачуется молитвой, воздержанием от празднословия, посильным рукоделием, чтением Слова Божия и терпением, потому что рождается оно от малодушия, беспечности и празднословия».     Уже в эти годы Прохор, по примеру других монахов, удаляв- шихся в лес для молитвы, испросил благословение старца в сво- бодное время тоже уходить в лес, где в полном одиночестве творил Иисусову молитву. Через два года послушник Прохор заболел во- дянкой, тело его распухло, он испытывал тяжкие страдания. На- ставник, отец Иосиф, и другие старцы, любившие Прохора, ухажи- вали за ним. Болезнь длилась около трех лет, и ни разу никто не услышал от него слова ропота. Старцы, опасаясь за жизнь больного, хотели вызвать к нему врача, однако Прохор просил этого не делать, сказав отцу Пахомию: «Я предал себя, отче свя- тый, Истинному Врачу душ и телес — Господу нашему Иисусу Христу и Пречистой Его Матери...», и желал, чтобы его причастили Святых Тайн. Тогда же Прохору было видение: в несказанном свете явилась Матерь Божия в сопровождении святых апостолов Петра и Иоанна Богослова. Указав рукой на больного, Пресвятая Дева сказала Иоанну: «Сей — от рода нашего». Затем она косну- лась жезлом бока больного, и тотчас жидкость, наполнявшая тело, стала вытекать через образовавшееся отверстие, и он быстро по- правился. Вскоре на месте явления Божией Матери была построе- на больничная церковь, один из приделов которой был освящен во имя преподобных Зосимы и Савватия Соловецких. Престол для придела преподобный Серафим соорудил своими руками из кипа- рисового дерева и всегда приобщался Святых Тайн в этой церкви.     Пробыв восемь лет послушником в Саровской обители, Прохор принял иноческий постриг с именем Серафим, столь хорошо выра- жавшим его пламенную любовь ко Господу и стремление ревност- но Ему служить. Через год Серафим был посвящен в сан иеродиа- кона. Горя духом, он ежедневно служил в храме, непрестанно со- вершая молитвы и после службы. Господь сподобил преподобного благодатных видений во время церковных служб: неоднократно он видел святых Ангелов, сослужащих братии. Особенного благодат- ного видения преподобный сподобился во время Божественной литургии в Великий Четверг, которую совершали настоятель отец Пахомий и старец Иосиф. Когда после тропарей преподобный произнес «Господи, спаси благочестивыя» и, стоя в царских вра- тах, навел орарь на молящихся с возгласом «и во веки веков», вне- запно его осенил светлый луч. Подняв глаза, преподобный Сера- фим увидел Господа Иисуса Христа, идущего по воздуху от запад- ных дверей храма, в окружении Небесных Бесплотных Сил. Дойдя до амвона, Господь благословил всех молящихся и вступил в мест- ный образ справа от царских врат. Преподобный Серафим, в ду- ховном восторге взирая на дивное явление, не мог ни слова про- говорить, ни сойти с места. Его увели под руки в алтарь, где он простоял еще три часа, меняясь в лице от озарившей его великой благодати. После видения преподобный усилил подвиги: днем он трудился в обители, а ночи проводил в молитве в лесной пустын- ной келлии. В 1793 году, в возрасте 39 лет, преподобный Серафим был рукоположен в сан иеромонаха и продолжал служение в хра- ме. После смерти настоятеля, отца Пахомия, преподобный Сера- фим, имея ег.о предсмертное благословение на новый подвиг — пустынножительство, взял также благословение у нового настоя- теля— отца Исайи — и ушел в пустынную келлию в нескольких  километрах от монастыря, в глухом лесу. Здесь стал он преда- ваться уединенным молитвам, приходя в обитель лишь в субботу, перед всенощной и, возвращаясь к себе в келлию после литургии, за которой причащался Святых Тайн. Преподобный проводил жизнь в суровых подвигах. Свое келейное молитвенное правило он совершал по уставу древних пустынных обителей; со Святым Еван-  гелием никогда не расставался, прочитывая в течение недели весь  Новый Завет, читал также святоотеческие и Богослужебные книги.  Преподобный выучил наизусть много церковных песнопений и вос-  певал их в часы работы в лесу. Около келлии он развел огород  и устроил пчельник. Сам себе добывая пропитание, преподобный  держал очень строгий пост, ел один раз в сутки, а в среду и пят-  ницу совершенно воздерживался от пищи. В первую неделю Свя-  той Четыредесятницы он не принимал пищи до субботы, когда  причащался Святых Тайн.    Святой старец в уединении настолько иногда погружался во внутреннюю сердечную молитву, что подолгу оставался неподвиж- ным, ничего не слыша и не видя вокруг. Навещавшие его изредка пустынники —• схимонах Марк Молчальник и иеродиакон Алек- сандр, застав святого в такой молитве, с благоговением тихо уда- лялись, чтобы не нарушать его созерцания.    В летнюю жару преподобный собирал на болоте мох для удобрения огорода; комары нещадно жалили его, но он благодуш- но терпел это страдание, говоря: «Страсти истребляются страда- нием и скорбью, или произвольными, или посылаемыми Промыс- лом». Около трех лет преподобный питался только одной травой снитью, которая росла вокруг его келлии. К нему всё чаще стали приходить, кроме братии, миряне — за советом и благословением. Это нарушало его уединение. Испросив благословение настоятеля, преподобный преградил к себе доступ женщинам, а затем и всем остальным, получив знамение, что Господь одобряет его мысль о полном безмолвии. По молитве преподобного, дорогу в его пустын- ную келлию преградили огромные сучья вековых сосен. Теперь только птицы, слетавшиеся во множестве к преподобному, и дикие звери посещали его. Преподобный из рук кормил медведя хлебом, когда из монастыря приносили ему хлеб.    Видя подвиги преподобного Серафима, враг рода человеческого вооружился против него и, желая принудить святого оставить без- молвие, решил устрашать его, но преподобный ограждал себя молитвой и силой Животворящего Креста. Диавол навел на свято- го «мысленную брань» — упорное продолжительное искушение. Для отражения натиска врага преподобный Серафим усугубил труды, взяв на себя подвиг столпничества. Каждую ночь он под- нимался на огромный камень в лесу и молился с воздетыми рука- ми, взывая: «Боже, милостив буди мне грешному». Днем же он молился в келлии, также на камне, который принес из леса, сходя с него только для краткого отдыха и подкрепления тела скудной пищей. Так молился преподобный 1000 дней и ночей. Диавол, по- срамленный преподобным, задумал умертвить его и наслал граби- телей. Подойдя к святому, работавшему на огороде, разбойники стали требовать от него деньги. У преподобного в это время был в руках топор, он был физически силен и мог бы обороняться, но не захотел этого делать, вспомнив слова Господа: «Взявшие меч мечом погибнут» (Мф. 26, 52). Святой, опустив топор на землю, сказал: «Делайте, что вам надобно». Разбойники стали бить пре- подобного, обухом проломили голову, сломали несколько ребер, потом, связав его, хотели бросить в реку, но сначала обыскали келлию в поисках денег. Всё сокрушив в келлии и ничего не найдя в ней, кроме иконы и нескольких картофелин, они устыдились сво- его злодеяния и ушли. Преподобный, придя в сознание, дополз до келлии и, жестоко страдая, пролежал всю ночь. Наутро с вели- ким трудом он добрел до обители. Братия ужаснулись, увидев израненного подвижника. Восемь суток пролежал преподобный, страдая от ран; к нему были вызваны врачи, удивившиеся тому, что Серафим после таких побоев остался жив. Но преподобный не от врачей получил исцеление: Царица Небесная явилась ему в тонком сне с апостолами Петром и Иоанном. Коснувшись головы преподобного, Пресвятая Дева даровала ему исцеление. После это- го случая преподобному Серафиму пришлось провести около пяти месяцев в обители, а затем он опять ушел в пустынную келлию. Оставшись навсегда согбенным, преподобный, ходил, опираясь на посох или топорик, однако своих обидчиков простил и просил не наказывать. После смерти настоятеля отца Исайи, бывшего с юно- сти преподобного его другом, он взял на себя подвиг молчальни- чества, совершенно отрекаясь от всех житейских помыслов для чистейшего предстояния Богу в непрестанной молитве. Если свя- тому в лесу встречался человек, он падал ниц и не вставал, пока прохожий не удалялся. В таком безмолвии старец провел около трех лет, перестав даже посещать обитель в воскресные дни. Пло- дом молчания явилось для преподобного Серафима стяжание мира души и радости о Святом Духе. Великий подвижник так впослед- ствии говорил одному из монахов монастыря: «...радость моя, молю тебя, стяжи дух мирен, и тогда тысячи душ спасутся около тебя». Новый настоятель, отец Нифонт, и старшая братия обители пред- ложили отцу Серафиму или по-прежнему приходить в монастырь по воскресеньям для участия в богослужении и причащения в оби- тели Святых Тайн, или вернуться в обитель. Преподобный избрал последнее, так как ему стало трудно ходить из пустыни в мона-  стырь. Весной 1810 года он возвратился в обитель после 15 лет  пребывания в пустыни. Не прерывая молчания, он к этому под- вигу прибавил еще и затвор и, никуда не выходя и никого у себя  не принимая, непрестанно находился в молитве и Богомыслии.  В затворе преподобный Серафим приобрел высокую душевную чи- стоту и сподобился от Бога особых благодатных даров — прозор- ливости и чудотворения. Тогда Господь поставил Своего избран-  ника на служение людям в самом высшем монашеском подвиге—•  старчестве. 25 ноября 1825 года Матерь Божия вместе с празднуе-  мыми в этот день двумя святителями явилась в сонном видении  старцу и повелела ему выйти из затвора и принимать у себя не-  мощные души человеческие, требующие наставления, утешения,  руководства и исцеления. Благословившись у настоятеля на изме-  нение образа жизни, преподобный открыл двери своей келлии для  всех. Старец видел сердца людей, и он, как духовный врач, исце-  лял душевные и телесные болезни молитвой к Богу и благодатным  словом. Приходившие к преподобному Серафиму чувствовали его  великую любовь и с умилением слушали ласковые слова, с кото-  рыми он обращался к людям: «радость моя, сокровище мое».  Старец стал посещать свою пустынную келлию и родник, называ-  емый Богословским, около которого ему выстроили маленькую  келлейку. Выходя из келлии, старец всегда нес за плечами котом-  ку с камнями. На вопрос, зачем он это делает, святой смиренно отвечал: «Томлю томящего меня». В последний период земной жизни преподобный Серафим особенно заботился о своем люби- мом детище — Дивеевской женской обители. Еще в сане иеродиа- кона он сопровождал покойного настоятеля отца Пахомия в Ди- веевскую общину к настоятельнице монахине Александре, великой подвижнице, и тогда отец Пахомий благословил преподобного всег- да заботиться о «Дивеевских сиротах». Он был подлинным отцом для сестер, обращавшихся к нему во всех своих духовных и жи- тейских затруднениях. Ученики и духовные друзья помогали свя- тому окормлять Дивеевскую общину — Михаил Васильевич Ман- туров, исцеленный преподобным от тяжкой болезни и по совету старца принявший на себя подвиг добровольной нищеты; Елена Васильевна Мантурова, одна из сестер Дивеевских, добровольно согласившаяся умереть из послушания старцу за своего брата, который был еще нужен в этой жизни; Николай Александрович Мотовилов, также исцеленный преподобным. Н. А. Мотовилов за- писал замечательное поучение преподобного Серафима о цели христианской жизни. В последние годы жизни преподобного Сера- фима один исцеленный им видел его стоявшим на воздухе вовре- мя молитвы. Святой строго запретил рассказывать об этом ранее его смерти.     Все знали и чтили преподобного Серафима как великого под- вижника и чудотворца. За год и десять месяцев до своей кончины, в праздник Благовещения, преподобный Серафим еще раз сподо- бился явления Царицы Небесной в сопровождении Крестителя Господня Иоанна, апостола Иоанна Богослова и двенадцати дев, святых мучениц и преподобных. Пресвятая Дева долго беседовала с преподобным, поручая ему Дивеевских сестер. Закончив беседу, Она сказала ему: «Скоро, любимиче Мой, будешь с нами». При этом явлении, при дивном посещении Богоматери, присутствовала одна Дивеевская старица, по молитве за нее преподобного.     В последний год жизни преподобный Серафим стал заметно слабеть и говорил многим о близкой кончине. В это время его часто видели у гроба, стоявшего в сенях его келлии и приготов- ленного им для себя. Преподобный сам указал место, где следова- ло похоронить его, — близ алтаря Успенского собора. 1 января  1833 года преподобный Серафим в последний раз пришел в боль- ничную Зосимо-Савватиевскую церковь к литургии и причастился Святых Тайн, после чего благословил братию и простился, сказав: «Спасайтесь, не унывайте, бодрствуйте, днесь нам венцы готовят- ся». Второго января келейник преподобного, отец Павел, в шестом часу утра вышел из своей келлии, направляясь в церковь, и почув- ствовал запах гари, исходивший из келлии преподобного; в келлии святого всегда горели свечи, и он говорил: «Пока я жив, пожара не будет, а когда я умру, кончина моя откроется пожаром». Когда двери открыли, оказалось, что книги и другие вещи тлели, а сам преподобный стоял на коленях перед иконой Божией Матери в молитвенном положении, но уже бездыханный. Его чистая душа во время молитвы была взята Ангелами и взлетела к Престолу Бога Вседержителя, верным рабом и служителем Которого преподоб- ный Серафим был всю жизнь. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Ѿ ю҆́ности хрⷭта̀ возлюби́лъ є҆сѝ бл҃же́нне, и҆ томꙋ̀ є҆ди́номꙋ рабо́тати пла́меннѣ вожделѣ́въ, непреста́нною мл҃твою и҆ трꙋдо́мъ пꙋсты́ни подвиза́лсѧ є҆сѝ, ѹ҆миле́ннымъ же се́рдцемъ любо́вь хрⷭто́вꙋ стѧжа́въ, и҆збра́нникъ возлю́бленъ бж҃їѧ мт҃ре ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ. сегѡ̀ ра́ди вопїе́мъ тѝ: сп҃са́й на́съ мл҃твами твои́ми, серафї́ме, прпⷣбне ѻ҆́тче на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2">
Мї́ра красотꙋ̀ и҆ ꙗ҆̀же въ не́мъ тлѣ҄ннаѧ ѡ҆ста́вивъ, прпⷣбне, въ саро́вскꙋю ѻ҆би́тель всели́лсѧ є҆сѝ: и҆ та́мѡ а҆́гг҃льски пожи́въ, мнѡ́гимъ пꙋ́ть бы́лъ є҆сѝ ко сп҃се́нїю: сегѡ̀ ра́ди и҆ хрⷭто́съ тебѐ, ѻ҆́тче серафї́ме, просла́ви и҆ да́ромъ и҆сцѣле́нїй и҆ чꙋде́съ ѡ҆богатѝ. тѣ́мже вопїе́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ, серафї́ме, прпⷣбне ѻ҆́тче на́шъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Monk Seraphim of Sarov"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Seraphim of Sarov, a great ascetic of the Russian Church, was born on 19 July 1754. His parents, Isidor and Agathia Moshnin, were inhabitants of Kursk. Isidor was a merchant involved in the construction of buildings, and towards the end of his life he began construction of a cathedral in Kursk, but he died before the completion of the work. His little son Prokhor -- the future Seraphim, remained in the care of his widowed mother, who raised her son in deep faith. 	After the death of her husband, Agathia Moshnina continued with the construction of the cathedral, and one time when she took Prokhor along with her there, he stumbled and fell down from the belfry. But the Lord watched over the life of the future luminary of the Church: the terrified mother, running down, found her son unharmed. 	Young Prokhor, endowed with an excellent memory, soon mastered his reading and writing. From the time of his childhood he loved to visit church-services and to read with his fellow students both the Holy Scripture and the Lives of the Saints, but most of all he loved to pray or to read the Holy Gospel in private.  	At one point Prokhor fell grievously ill, and his life was in danger. In a dream the boy saw the Mother of God, promising to visit and heal him. Soon through the courtyard of the Moshnin home there came a church procession with the Znamenie (Sign) Icon of the Mother of God; his mother carried out Prokhor in her arms, and he kissed the holy icon, after which he speedily recovered.  	While still in his youth Prokhor matured his plans to entirely devote his life to God and to go off to a monastery. His pious mother did not object to this and she blessed him on his monastic path with a cross, which the monk all his life wore on his chest. Prokhor set off on foot with pilgrims going from Kursk to Kiev to venerate the Pechersk Saints.  	The starets-elder schema-monk Dosiphei, whom Prokhor visited, blessed him to go off to the Sarovsk wilderness-monastery and there seek his salvation. Returning briefly to his parental home, Prohkor bid a final farewell to his mother and kinsfolk. On 20November 1778 he arrived at Sarov, where the monastery then was headed by a wise starets-elder, Father Pakhomii. He amiably accepted him and put him under the spiritual guidance of the starets-elder Joseph. And under his direction Prokhor passed through many obediences at the monastery: he was the cell-attendant of the elder, he toiled in the making of bread and prosphora and at carpentry, he did duty as a church-attendant, and he did everything with zeal and fervour, just as though serving the very Lord Himself. By constant work he hedged himself in against boredom -- this being, as he later said, &quot;the most dangerous temptation for newly-become monks, which is doctored by prayer, abstaining from idle chatter, exertive handwork, by reading of the Word of God and by patience, since that it is engendered by pettiness of soul, neglectfulness and idle talk&quot;. 	Prokhor already in these years, on the example of the other monks that went off into the forest for prayer, besought the blessing of the elder for free time likewise to withdraw into the woods, where in complete isolation he made the Jesus Prayer. After two years as a novice, Prokhor fell ill with dropsy, his body became swollen, and he was beset with suffering. His instructor Father Joseph and the other startsi-elders were fond of Prokhor, and they provided him care. The illness dragged on for about three years, and not once did anyone hear from him a word of complaint. The elders, fearing for his very life, wanted to call a doctor for him, but Prokhor asked that this not be done, in saying to Father Pakhomii: &quot;I have given myself over, holy father, to the True Physician of soul and body -- our Lord Jesus Christ and His All-Pure Mother...&quot;, and he besought, that they might commune him with the Holy Mysteries. Prokhor then had a vision: in an inexpressible light there appeared the Mother of God accompanied by the holy Apostles Peter and John the Theologian. Pointing with Her hand towards he that was sick, the MostHoly Virgin said to Saint John: &quot;This one -- is of our lineage&quot;. Thereupon with Her staff She touched the side of the sick man, and immediately the fluid that had swelled up his body began to flow through a sort of opening made, and he quickly became well. Soon at the place of the appearance of the Mother of God there was built an infirmary-church for the sick, and one of the side-chapels was dedicated in the name of the Monks Zosima and Savvatii of Solovetsk. The altar-table for the chapel was fashioned by the MonkSeraphim with his own hands from cypress wood, and he always communed the Holy Mysteries in this church. 	Being eight years an obedient (novice) at the Sarov monastery, Prokhor accepted monastic tonsure with the name Seraphim, a name so finely expressive of his fiery love for the Lord and the desire zealously to serve Him. After a year, Seraphim was ordained to the dignity of monk-deacon. Earnest in spirit, he daily served in temple, incessantly praying even after the service. The Lord vouchsafed the monk graced visions during the time of church-services: repeatedly he beheld holy Angels, concelebrating with the brethren. The monk was vouchsafed one particularly graced vision during the time of Divine Liturgy on Holy Great Thursday, which was celebrated by the monastery-head Father Pakhomii and by Father Joseph. When after the Little Entrance with the Gospel, the Monk-deacon Seraphim pronounced the words &quot;O Lord, save the God-fearing, and hear us&quot;, and standing in the royal doorway, he lifted his orarion (deacon&apos;s stole) with the exclamation prayer &quot;And unto ages of ages&quot;, suddenly a bright ray of light blinded him. [trans. note: this prayer &quot;O Lord, save the God-fearing...&quot; in Divine Liturgy falls between the priest&apos;s exclamation &quot;For holy art Thou...&quot; and the choir&apos;s beginning of the &quot;Holy God, Holy Mighty...&quot;. To Orthodox believers in the West, this is likely unfamiliar (even though found in Hapgood): its use apparently ceased in Russia after the Revolution, and was restored only recently with the demise of the Soviet Union, with other liturgical changes, such as the adding of Saint Seraphim of Sarov to the commemoration of the 6th rank of saints in Proskomedia, a particle being taken from the third prosphora for the rank of the Monastics.]  Looking upwards, the Monk Seraphim beheld the Lord Jesus Christ, coming through the air from the western doors of the temple, surrounded by the Heavenly Bodiless Hosts. Reaching the amvon, the Lord blessed all the praying and entered into HisImage located there to the right of the royal doors. The Monk Seraphim, in spiritual rapture viewing this miraculous vision, was able to utter neither a word, nor to move from the spot. They led him by the hand into the altar, where he just stood for another three hours, his face having changed colour from the great grace that shone upon him. After the vision the saint intensified his efforts: by day he toiled at the monastery, and nights he spent at prayer in the forest wilderness cell. 	In 1793, at age 39, the Monk Seraphim was ordained to the dignity of priestmonk and he continued at serving in the temple. After the death of the monastery head Father Pakhomii, the Monk Seraphim, -- having before this received deathbed blessing for the new exploit of wilderness-dwelling, and having likewise received blessing of the new monastery-head Father Isaiah, -- went off to a wilderness cell some several kilometers from the monastery, in the deep forest. Here he devoted himself to solitary prayer, arriving at the monastery only on Saturday before the all-night vigil, and returning to his cell after Liturgy, at which he communed the Divine Mysteries. The monk spent his time at severe efforts. His cell rule of prayer he made according to the ustav-rule of the ancient wilderness-monasteries; from the Holy Gospel he never parted, reading through the course of the week all the New Testament, and he read likewise the holy fathers and the Divineservice books. The monk learned by heart many of the Church songs and sang them during his hours at work in the forest. Around his cell he cultivated a garden and set up a bee-hive. Having seen to his subsistence, the monk kept to a very strict fast, he ate only once during the entire day, and on Wednesdays and Fridays he completely abstained from food. On the first Sunday of the Holy Forty-Days (Lent)he did not partake of food at all until Saturday, when he communed the Holy Mysteries.  	The holy elder in his solitude was sometimes so immersed in his inner prayer of the heart, that at length he remained without stirring, neither hearing nor seeing anything around him. The schema-monk Mark the Silent and the monk-deacon Aleksandr, also wilderness-dwellers, would visit him every now and then, and finding the saint immersed in suchlike prayer, in reverent quiet they would leave, so as not to disrupt his contemplation.  	In the heat of Summer the monk gathered moss in a swamp as fertilizer for his garden; the gnats relentlessly bit at him, but he good-naturedly endured this vexation, saying: &quot;Passions are destroyed by suffering and by sorrow, either arbitrarily or as sent by Providence&quot;. For about three years the monk ate only a certain vegetable, which grew about his cell. All the more frequently there began to come not only monks, but also laypeople, -- for advice and blessing. This disrupted his solitude. Having besought the blessing of the monastery head, the monk at first barred the admittance of women to him, and then all the rest, having received a sign that the Lord approved of his intent for complete silence. Through the prayer of the monk, the pathway to his wilderness cell was blocked by huge branches blown down from ancient pine trees. Now only the birds, flocking to him in throngs, and the wild beasts, paid him visit. The monk fed a bear with bread from his hand, when they happened to bring him bread from the monastery. 	Seeing the efforts of the Monk Seraphim, the enemy of the race of man roused up against him, and wanting to force the saint to foresake his silence, he decided to frighten him, but the monk shielded himself by prayer and by the power of the Life-Creating Cross. The devil conducted against the saint &quot;mental warfare&quot; -- persistent and continous temptation. For repulsing the onslaughts of the enemy the Monk Seraphim intensified his toil, and took upon himself the exploit of pillar-dwelling. Each night he climbed up upon an immense rock in the forest and he prayed with up-raised hands, crying out: &quot;God, be merciful to me a sinner&quot;. By day he prayed in his cell and likewise upon a stone, which he had brought from the forest, coming down from it only for brief rest and to refresh his body with a scant bit of food. The monk prayed thus for 1,000 days and nights. The devil, shamed by the monk, hatched a plan to kill the saint and sent out robbers. Coming upon him while working in his garden, the robbers began to demand money from him. The monk had in his hands at this time an axe, he was physically strong and could have put up a fight, but he did not want to do this, having called to mind the words of the Lord: &quot;Those taking up the sword wilt perish by the sword&quot; (Mt. 26: 52). The monk, dropping his axe to the ground, said: &quot;Do what ye intend to&quot;. The robbers began to beat the monk, with the butt-end of the axe they bloodied his head, broke several of his ribs, and then having tied him, they wanted to throw him in the river, but first they searched the cell for money. Having trashed everything in the cell and finding nothing in it besides icons and a few potatoes, they were shamed in their wicked deed and left. The monk, gaining consciousness, got to his cell, and suffering terribly, he lay there all night. In the morning with great difficulty he reached the monastery. The brethren were horrified, seeing the ascetic all bruised with wounds. For eight whole days the monk just lay there, suffering from his wounds; doctors were called for him, who were amazed that after such a beating he even remained alive. But the monk did not receive his healing from the physicians: the Queen of Heaven appeared to him in a subtle dream vision together with the Apostles Peter and John. Touching the head of the monk, the MostHoly Virgin granted him healing. After this instance the Monk Seraphim had to spend about five months at the monastery, and then he again went off to his wilderness cell. Left in posture stooped over always henceforth, the monk walked, leaning upon his staff or small axe, and he indeed forgave his abusers and asked that they not be punished. 	After the death of the monastery head, Father Isaiah, -- a friend of the monk since his youth, -- the Monk Seraphim took upon himself the deed of silence, being completely cut off from any worldly ponderings for a most purified being in the presence of God in unceasing prayer. If the saint encountered a man in the forest, he fell face downwards and did not rise up, until the passerby had moved on. In such a manner of silence the staretselder spent about three years, ceasing even to visit the monastery on Sundays. The fruit of silence for the Monk Seraphim was the acquisition of peace of soul and joy in the Holy Spirit. The great ascetic afterwards spoke thus to one of the monks of the monastery: &quot;...my joy, I pray thee, acquire a spirit at peace, and then a thousand souls wilt be saved around thee&quot;.  	The new monastery head, Father Nyphont, and the elder brethren of the monastery suggested to Father Seraphim that either as before he show up at the monastery on Sundays for participation in Divine-services and communing the Holy Mysteries at the monastery, or that he return to the monastery. The monk chose the latter course, since it had become difficult for him to walk from the wilderness to the monastery. In Spring of the year 1810 he returned to the monastery after 15 years of living in the wilderness. Not breaking off with his silence, he added onto it also that of hermit enclosure, neither coming out anywhere nor admitting anyone, he dwelt in unceasing prayer and meditation on God. In his hermitage the Monk Seraphim discovered an height of spiritual purity and was vouchsafed of God the special gifts of grace -- perspicacity and wonderworking. Then the Lord sent His chosen one to serve people in an utmost monastic exploit -- &quot;Starchestvo&quot; (&quot;being an elder&quot;). On 25 November 1825 the Mother of God accompanied by the two sainted-hierarchs celebrated this day (i.e. PriestMartyr Clement, Pope of Rome, and Peter, Archbishop of Alexandria), appeared to the elder in a dream-vision and bid him emerge from his hermitage, so as to receive infirm human souls, needful of instruction, consolation, guidance and healing. The monastery head gave blessing to this change in the manner of his life, and the monk opened the doors of his cell to everyone. The starets saw into the hearts of people, and as a spiritual physician, he healed the infirmities of soul and body with a prayer to God and by words of grace. Those coming to the Monk Seraphim sensed his great love and with tenderness they hearkened to his amiable words, with which he turned to people: &quot;my joy, my precious&quot;. The starets began to visit his own wilderness cell and water-spring, called Bogoslovsk, around which they built him a small cell. Coming out from the cell, the starets always carried on his shoulders a knapsack with stones. To the question as to why he did this, the saint humbly answered: &quot;I oppress that which oppresseth me&quot;. 	In the final period of his earthly life the Monk Seraphim especially concerned himself about his spiritual children -- the Diveevo women&apos;s monastery. While still in the dignity of monk-deacon he had accompanied the belated monastery head Father Pakhomii to the Diveevo community to its monastic leader, the nun Mother Alexandra -- a great woman ascetic, and then Father Pakhomii blessed the Monk Seraphim to concern himself always for the &quot;Diveevo orphans&quot;. He was a genuine father for the sisters, who turned to him with all their spiritual and material difficulties. His students and spiritual friends helped the saint to feed and nourish the Diveevo community: -- Mikhail Vasil&apos;evich Manturov, healed by the monk from grievous illness and on the advice of the elder having taken upon himself the exploit of voluntary poverty; Elena Vasil&apos;evna Manturovna, one of the Diveevo sisters, voluntarily consenting to die out of obedience to the elder for her brother, who was still needed in this life; Nikolai Aleksandrovich Motovilov, who likewise was healed by the monk. N. A. Motovilov recorded in writing the remarkable teachings of the MonkSeraphim about the goals of Christian life. In the last year of the life of the MonkSeraphim, one of those healed by him saw him standing in the air during the time of prayer. The saint strictly forbade this to be told of before his death.  	Everyone knew and esteemed the Monk Seraphim as a great ascetic and wonderworker. A year and ten months before his end, on the feast of the Annunciation, the Monk Seraphim was vouchsafed yet once more to have appear the Queen of Heaven in the company of the Baptist of the Lord John, the Apostle John the Theologian and twelve virgins, martyrs and monastics. The MostHoly Virgin conversed at length with the monk, entrusting the Diveevo sisters to him. Concluding the conversation, She said to him: &quot;Soon, My dear one, thou shalt be with us&quot;. During this vision with the miraculous visit of the Mother of God, a certain Diveevo eldress was present, through the prayer of the monk for her. 	During the final year of his life the Monk Seraphim became noticeably weaker and he spoke much about his approaching end. During this time they often saw him at his grave, set at the approaches to his cell, and which he had prepared for himself. The monk himself had pointed out the place, where finally they would bury him -- near the altar of the Uspenie-Dormition cathedral. On 1 January 1833 the Monk Seraphim one last time came to the Zosimo-Savvatiev church for liturgy and he communed the Holy Mysteries, after which he blessed the brethren and bid farewell, saying: &quot;Ye seeking salvation, be not discouraged, but take heart, the day of crowns is prepared for us&quot;. On 2 January, the cellattendant of the monk, Father Pavel, at six in the morning left his own cell heading for church, and he caught the smell of burning coming from the cell of the Monk Seraphim; in the cell of the monk candles always burned, and he had said: &quot;While I yet live, there wilt be no fire, but when I die, my end shalt reveal itself with a fire&quot;. When they opened the doors, it appeared that the books and the other things had burned, but the monk himself remained upright on his knees before an icon of the Mother of God in a position of prayer, but was already lifeless. His pure soul at the time of prayer was taken by the Angels and had flown off to the Throne of the All-Mighty God, to Whom the Monk Seraphim had been a faithful servant all his life.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>