<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Праведный Симеон Богоприимец"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Праведный Симеон Богоприимец был, по свидетельству святого евангелиста Луки, одним из избранников Божиих, ожидавших утешения Израилева, и Дух Святой пребывал на нем (Лк. 2, 25). Ему было возвещено от Бога, что он не умрет до того времени, пока в мир не придет обещанный Мессия — Христос Господь.    Древние историки сообщают, что египетский царь Птоломей II Филадельф (285—247 до Рождества Христова) пожелал пополнить свою знаменитую александрийскую библиотеку текстами Священ- ных книг. Он пригласил из Иерусалима книжников. Синедрион послал своих мудрецов. Среди 72 ученых прибывших в Александ- рию для перевода Священного Писания на греческий язык, был приглашен и праведный Симеон. (Работа была выполнена и по- лучила название «Перевод 72-х толковников». Именно с него в дальнейшем Ветхий Завет был переведен на славянский язык для Болгарской, Сербской и Русской Православных Церквей.) Пра- ведный Симеон переводил книгу пророка Исайи. Прочтя в под- линнике слова «Се, Дева во чреве приимет и родит Сына» (Ис. 7, 14), он решил, что слово «Дева» здесь употреблено оши- бочно, вместо слова «Жена», и хотел исправить текст. В этот мо- мент ему явился Ангел и удержал его руку, говоря: «Имей веру написанным словам, ты сам убедишься, что они исполнятся, ибо не вкусишь смерти, доколе не увидишь Христа Господа, Который родится от Чистой и Пренепорочной Девы».     С того дня праведный Симеон стал ожидать пришествия Обе- тованного Мессии.     И вот однажды праведный Симеон, ведомый Духом Божиим, пришел в Иерусалимский храм. Это было в тот самый день (соро- ковой по Рождестве Христовом), когда Пречистая Дева Мария и Ее Обручник Иосиф пришли туда, чтобы совершить обряд, поло- женный по иудейскому закону, — представить пред Господом свое- го Божественного Первенца и принести положенную жертву.     Как только праведный Симеон увидел пришедших, Дух Святой открыл ему, что Богомладенец, Которого держала Пречистая Дева Мария, и есть ожидаемый Мессия, Спаситель мира. Старец принял на свои руки Младенца Христа и произнес свои пророче- ские слова: «Ныне отпущаеши раба Твоего, Владыко, по глаголу Твоему, с миром, ибо видели очи мои спасение Твое, которое Ты уготовал пред лицем всех людей. Свет к просвещению языч-ников и славу людей Твоих Израиля». Он благословил Пречистую Деву и праведного Иосифа и, обращаясь к Богородице, сказал: «Се, лежит Сей на падение и на восстание многих в Израиле и в пред- мет пререканий, — И Тебе Самой оружие пройдет душу, — да откроются помышления многих сердец» (Лк. 2, 22—35).     Далее святой евангелист повествует: «Тут была также Анна пророчица, дочь Фануилова, от колена Асирова, достигшая глубо- кой старости, прожив с мужем от девства своего семь лет, вдова лет восьмидесяти четырех, которая не отходила от храма, постом и молитвою служа Богу день и ночь. И она в то время, подойдя, славила Господа и пророчествовала о Нем всем, ожидавшим из- бавления в Иерусалиме» (Лк. 2, 36—38).     О святом и праведном Симеоне Богоприимце известно, что он скончался, прожив 360 лет. В VI веке святые мощи его были пере- несены в Константинополь. В 1200 году его гроб видел русский паломник святитель Антоний, будущий архиепископ Новгородский  (1212—1220; 1&quot; 1232; память 8 октября). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Ста́рецъ дне́сь ѿрѣши́тисѧ ѿ ю҆́зъ молѧ́шесѧ сегѡ̀ житїѧ̀ тлѣ́ннагѡ, хрⷭта̀ воспрїѧ́тъ на рꙋ́ки зижди́телѧ и҆ гдⷭа. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Righteous Simeon the God-Receiver and Anna the Prophetess"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Righteous Simeon the God-Receiver (Bogopriimets) was, according to the testimony of the holy Evangelist Luke, one of the chosen of God in expectation of the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit dwelt upon him (Lk 2:25). It was announced to him from God, that he would not die until that time, when the Promised Messiah -- Christ the Lord -- would be come into the world. 	Ancient historians relate that the Egyptian emperor Ptolemy II Philadelphos (285-247 BC) wished to add to the famous Library at Alexandria with texts of Holy Scripture. He invited scholars from Jerusalem, and the Sanhedrin sent their wise men. Righteous Simeon was also among the 72 scholars in Alexandria for the translation of the Sacred Scriptures into the Greek language. (The work was accomplished and received the title &quot;Translation of the 72 Interpreters&quot;. With this also further on in the future, the New Testament was translated into the Slavonic language for the Bulgarian, Serbian and Russian Orthodox Churches.) Righteous Simeon translated a book of the Prophet Isaiah, having read in the original the words: &quot;Behold, a Virgin shalt conceive and give birth to a Son&quot; (Is 7: 14). He decided, that the word &quot;Virgin&quot; was incorrectly used here in place of the word &quot;Woman&quot;, and he wanted to correct the text. At that moment an Angel appeared to him and held back his hand saying: &quot;Have faith in the words written down; thou thyself shalt be persuaded that they will be fulfilled, whereof thou shalt not taste of death until thou behold Christ the Lord, Who shall be born of a Pure and Immaculate Virgin&quot;. 	From this day righteous Simeon began to await the coming of the Promised Messiah. 	And here one day righteous Simeon, knowing of it by the Holy Spirit, was come to the Jerusalem Temple. It was on that very same day (the fortieth after the Birth of Christ), when the All-Pure Virgin Mary and Her Betrothed Joseph had come there in order to perform the ritual set down by Jewish Law -- to present before the Lord His Own Divine First-Born and to offer the established sacrifice. 	When righteous Simeon beheld their arrival, the Holy Spirit revealed to him that the God-Infant Whom the All-Pure Virgin Mary held, -- was the Promised Messiah, the Saviour of the world. The elder took into his arms the Infant Christ and pronounced his prophetic words: &quot;Now lettest Thou Thy servant depart, O Lord, with peace according to Thy word, wherefore hath mine eyes beheld Thy salvation, which Thou hast prepared before the face of all peoples, a light to the enlightening of gentiles and the glory of Thy people Israel&quot;. He blessed the All-Pure Virgin and Righteous Joseph and, having turned to the Mother of God he said: &quot;Behold, This One is set for the fall and rising up of many in Israel and for the sign spoken against, and for Thee thyself a sword shalt pierce the soul, so that the thoughts of many hearts might be revealed&quot; (Lk 2: 22-35). 	The holy Evangelist relates further: &quot;Here also was Anna the Prophetess, daughter of Phanuel from the tribe of Aser, having reached extreme old age, having lived with her husband for seven years, she was a widow for eighty-four years, who went not out from the temple, serving God both day and night by fasting and prayer. And she having approached at this time, glorified the Lord and prophesied about Him to all awaiting deliverance at Jerusalem&quot; (Lk 2: 36-38). 	About the righteous and holy Simeon the God-Receiver is known that he died in extreme old age. In the VI Century his holy relics were transferred to Constantinople. In the year 1200 his grave was seen by the Russian pilgrim Saint Antonii, future archbishop of Novgorod (1212-1220. +1232, Comm. 8 October).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Today the elder asked to be loosed/ from the bonds of this life of corruption,// receiving in his arms Christ, the Creator and Lord.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>