<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Антоний"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобный Антоний, величайший подвижник, основатель пус- тынножительства и отец монашества, получивший от Святой Церк- ви наименование Великий, родился в Египте, в селении Кома, близ Фиваидской пустыни, в 251 году. Родителями его были благочести- вые христиане знатного происхождения. Антоний с юности был всегда серьезным, сосредоточенным. Он любил посещать церков- ные службы и слушал Священное Писание с таким глубоким вни- манием, что запоминал слышанное на всю жизнь. С юности руковод- ствовался он заповедями Господними. Святому Антонию было око- ло двадцати лет, когда он лишился родителей, и на его попечении осталась малолетняя сестра. Посещая церковные службы, юноша проникся благоговейным чувством к тем христианам, которые, как повествуется в Деяниях апостольских, продавали свои имения, а цену их полагали к ногам Апостолов. Услышав в церкви Евангель- ские слова Христа, обращенные к богатому юноше: «Если хочешь быть совершенным, пойди, продай имение твое и раздай нищим; и будешь иметь сокровище на небесах; и приходи и следуй за Мною» (Мф. 19, 21), Антоний воспринял их как сказанные лично ему. Он продал имение, оставшееся ему после смерти родителей, роздал деньги нищим, оставил сестру на попечении благочестивых девственниц в монастыре, покинул родительский дом и, поселив- шись недалеко от своего селения в бедной хижине, начал подвиж- ническую жизнь. Трудами рук своих он зарабатывал на пропита- ние и на милостыню бедным. Иногда святой юноша посещал и других подвижников, живших в окрестностях, и от каждого старал- ся получить наставления и пользу. К одному из подвижников он обратился за руководством в духовной жизни. В этот период жиз- ни преподобный Антоний подвергся тяжким искушениям от диаво- ла. Враг рода человеческого смущал молодого подвижника помыс- лами, сомнениями в избранном пути, тоской по сестре, пытался склонить Антония к плотскому греху, но преподобный хранил твер- дую веру, непрестанно творил молитву и усилил подвиги. Антоний молился, чтобы Господь указал ему путь спасения, и ему было явлено видение. Подвижник увидел человека, который поперемен- но то совершал молитву, то начинал трудиться — это был Ангел, которого Господь послал для вразумления Своего избранника. Тог- да преподобный установил строгий порядок своей жизни. Он при- нимал пищу один раз в сутки, а иногда один раз в два-три дня; все ночи проводил в молитве, предаваясь краткому сну лишь на третью или четвертую ночь после непрерывного бдения. Но диавол не оставлял своих ухищрений и, пытаясь устрашить преподобного, являлся под видом чудовищ, но святой с непоколебимой верой ограждал себя Животворящим Крестом. Наконец враг явился ему в виде страшного черного отрока и лицемерно признал себя побеж- денным, рассчитывая склонить святого к тщеславию и гордости. Но преподобный отогнал врага молитвой. Для большего уединения святой поселился вдалеке от селения, в гробнице. В определенные дни его друг приносил ему скудную пищу. И здесь бесы, напав на подвижника с намерением убить его, нанесли ему тяжкие побои. Однако Господь не допустил смерти Антония. Друг святого, при- несший по обычаю пищу, увидел его замертво лежащим на земле и отнес в селение. Святого сочли умершим и стали готовиться к погребению. Но преподобный глубокой ночью пришел в сознание и умолил своего друга отнести его обратно в гробницу. Твердость святого Антония была сильнее ухищрений врага. Приняв вид ди- ких зверей, бесы вновь пытались принудить святого покинуть  избранное им место, но он опять отогнал их силой Животворящего  Креста. Господь подкрепил силы Своего угодника: в разгар борь-  бы с темными силами преподобный увидел спускавшийся к нему  с неба светлый луч и воскликнул: «Где был Ты, милосердный  Иисусе?., почему с самого начала не явился исцелить мои раны?»  Господь ответил: «Антоний! Я был здесь, но ждал, желая видеть  твое мужество; теперь же, после того, как ты твердо выдержал  борьбу, Я буду всегда помогать тебе и прославлю тебя во всем  мире». После этого явления преподобный Антоний встал исцелен-  ный от ран и готовый к новым подвигам. В это время ему было  35 лет. Приобретя духовный опыт в борьбе с диаволом. преподоб-  ный задумал уйти в глубь Фиваидской пустыни и в полном уеди-  нении служить Господу трудом и молитвой. Он просил старца-  подвижника (к которому обращался в начале своего иноческого  пути) удалиться вместе с ним в пустыню, но старец, благословив  преподобного на новый, до тех пор неизвестный вид подвига —  отшельничество, по старческой немощи, не решился ему сопутст-  вовать. Преподобный Антоний ушел в пустыню один. Диавол  пытался остановить его, бросая перед преподобным драгоценности  и золото, но святой, не обращая на них внимания, прошел мимо.  Дойдя до одной горы, преподобный увидел какое-то заброшенное  огороженное строение и поселился в нем, заложив камнями вход.  Тот же верный друг приносил ему дважды в год хлеб, а вода  имелась внутри ограды. В полном молчании принимал преподоб-  ный приносимую пищу. В полном уединении и непрестанной борь-  бе с бесами преподобный Антоний прожил 20 лет и обрел, наконец,  спокойствие духа и мир в помыслах. Когда- настало время, Гос-  подь открыл людям Своего великого подвижника. Преподобному  предстояло наставить многих мирян и монахов и руководить ино-  ками. Собравшиеся к ограде преподобного люди разобрали за-  граждавшие вход камни, проникли к святому Антонию и просили  взять их под свое руководство. Вскоре гора, на которой подвизал-  ся святой Антоний, была окружена целым поясом монастырских  обителей, и преподобный с любовью наставлял насельников, уча  духовной жизни тех, кто пришел в пустыню спасаться. Он учил  прежде всего постоянству в принятом на себя подвиге, неослаб-  ному стремлению угодить Господу, щедрому и бескорыстному  отношению к трудам, понесенным ранее. Он убеждал не страшить-  ся бесовских нападений и прогонять врага силой Животворящего  Креста Господня. В 311 году Церковь постигло испытание — жес- токое гонение на христиан, воздвигнутое императором Максими-  ном. Желая пострадать вместе со святыми мучениками, преподоб- ный Антоний покинул пустыню и пришел в Александрию. Он от- крыто служил мученикам в их заточении, присутствовал на суде  и допросах, но мучители к нему даже не прикоснулись! Господу угодно было сохранить его на пользу христианам. По оконча- нии гонения преподобный вернулся в пустыню и продолжал под- виги. Господь даровал Своему избраннику дар чудотворений: пре- подобный изгонял бесов и исцелял больных силой своей молитвы. Множество Приходящих к нему людей препятствовало его уеди- нению, и преподобный ушел еще дальше, в так называемую «внутреннюю пустыню», и поселился на вершине горы. Однако братия из пустынных монастырей разыскали преподобного и умо- лили его хоть изредка посещать их обители.     Еще раз преподобному Антонию пришлось покинуть пустыню и прийти к христианам в Александрию, чтобы защитить право- славную веру от ересей манихеев и ариан. Зная, что имя преподоб- ного Антония почитается всей Церковью, ариане возвели на него клевету — якобы он придерживается их еретического учения. При- быв в Александрию, преподобный Антоний всенародно, в присут- ствии епископа, проклял арианство. Во время своего недолгого пребывания в Александрии он обратил ко Христу великое множе- ство язычников. К преподобному приходили языческие философы, желая своими умствованиями поколебать его твердую веру, но он простыми, убедительными речами привел их к молчанию. Равно- апостольный царь Константин Великий (^ 337, память 21 мая) и его сыновья глубоко почитали преподобного Антония и просили его посетить их в столице, но преподобный не пожелал оставить своих братьев-пустынников. В ответном послании он убеждал им- ператоров не гордиться высоким положением и помнить, что и над ними есть Нелицеприятный Судия — Господь Бог. 85 лет сво- ей жизни провел преподобный Антоний в пустынном уединении. Незадолго до своей смерти преподобный поведал братии, что вскоре он будет взят от них. Еще и еще раз поучал он их в чисто- те хранить православную веру, избегать всякого общения с ерети- ками, не ослабевать в иноческих подвигах. «Старайтесь же паче пребывать всегда в единении между собою, а преимущественно с Господом, и потом со святыми, да примут они и вас по смерти в вечные свои кровы, как друзей и знаемых»,— так передано пред- смертное слово преподобного в его житии. Преподобный завещал двум из своих учеников, находившимся при нем последние 15 лет его жизни, похоронить его в пустыне и не устраивать торжествен- ного погребения его останков в Александрии. Из двух своих ман- тий одну преподобный завещал святителю Афанасию Александ- рийскому (память 18 января), другую — святителю Серапиону Тмунтскому. Преподобный Антоний мирно скончался в 356 году, в возрасте 105 лет, и погребен своими учениками в прославленной им пустыне в сокровенном месте.    Жизнь прославленного подвижника, преподобного Антония Ве- ликого, подробно описана отцом Церкви святителем Афанасием Александрийским. Это творение святителя Афанасия — первый памятник православной агиографии — считается одним из лучших его писаний; святитель Иоанн Златоуст говорит, что это житие нужно читать всем христианам. «Повествование сие мало значи- тельно в сравнении с Антониевыми добродетелями,— пишет святой Афанасий, — однако же и из сего заключайте, каков был Божий человек Антоний. С юных лет и до такого возраста соблюдавший равное усердие к подвижничеству, ни по старости не обольщав- шийся дорогими снедями, ни по немощи тела своего не изменяв- ший вида своей одежды, ни в чем однако же не потерпел он вреда. Глаза у него были здоровы и невредимы и видел он хорошо. Не выпало у него ни одного зуба, а только ослабли они в деснах от преклонных лет старца. Здоров он был руками и ногами (...). А что всюду говорили о нем, все удивлялись ему, даже не видав- шие любили его — это служит доказательством его добродетели и Боголюбивой души»/ Из творений самого преподобного Антония До нас дошли: 1) Речи его, числом 20, трактующие о христиан- ских добродетелях, особенно монашеских, 2) Семь посланий к мо- настырям— о стремлении к нравственному совершенству и духов- ной борьбе и 3) Правила жизни и увещания к монахам.     В 544 году мощи преподобного Антония Великого были пере- несены из пустыни в Александрию, а затем, по завоевании Египта сарацинами в VII веке, в Константинополь. Из Константинополя в    X—XI вв. святые мощи перенесены в епархиальный округ Вьенский, а в XV веке — в Арис (Франция), в храм святого Иулиана. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Ревни́телѧ и҆лїю̀ нра́вы подража́ѧ, крⷭти́телю пра́выми стезѧ́ми послѣ́дꙋѧ, ѻ҆́тче а҆нтѡ́нїе, пꙋсты́ни бы́лъ є҆сѝ жи́тель, и҆ вселе́ннꙋю ѹ҆тверди́лъ є҆сѝ мл҃твами твои́ми. тѣ́мже молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, спасти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Житє́йскїѧ молвы̀ ѿри́нꙋвъ, безмо́лвнѡ житїѐ сконча́лъ є҆сѝ, крⷭти́телѧ подража́ѧй всѧ́кимъ ѡ҆́бразомъ прпⷣбнѣйшїй: съ ни́мъ ѹ҆́бѡ тѧ̀ почита́емъ, ѻ҆тцє́въ нача́льниче а҆нтѡ́нїе.
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Anthony"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Anthony, a very great ascetic, the founder of wilderness-monastery life and as such the father of monasticism, is entitled &quot;the Great&quot; by Holy Church. He was born in Egypt in the village of Coma, near the Thebaid wilderness, in the year 251. His parents were pious Christians of illustrious lineage. From his youth Anthony was always serious and given over to concentration. He loved to visit church services and he hearkened to the Holy Scripture with such deep attention, that he remembered what he heard all his entire life. The commandments of the Lord guided him from the time of his very youth. When Saint Anthony was about twenty years old, he lost his parents, but in his care remained his sister, a minor in age. Visiting the church services, the youth was pierced through by a reverent feeling towards those Christians who, as it relates in the Acts of the Apostles, sold off their possessions and the proceeds thereof they applied in following after the Apostles. He heard in church the Gospel passage of Christ, spoken to the rich young man: &quot;If thou wouldst be perfect, sell what thou hast and give it to the poor; and thou wilt have treasure in heaven; and come follow after Me&quot; (Mt. 19: 21). Anthony understood this as spoken to him personally. He sold off his property that remained to him after the death of his parents, he distributed the money to the poor, he left his sister in the care of pious virgins in a monastic setting, he left his parental home, and having settled not far from his village in a wretched hut, he began his ascetic life. He earned his livelihood by working with his hands, and alms also for the poor. Sometimes the holy youth also visited other ascetics living in the surrounding areas, and from each he sought to receive direction and benefit. And to a particular one of these ascetics he turned for guidance in the spiritual life. 	In this period of his life the Monk Anthony was subjected to terrible temptations by the devil. The enemy of the race of man troubled the young ascetic with thoughts, and with doubts about his chosen path, with anguish over his sister, and he attempted to incline Anthony towards fleshly sin. But the monk preserved his firm faith, he incessantly made prayer and intensified his efforts. Anthony prayed that the Lord would point out to him the path of salvation. And he was granted a vision. The ascetic beheld a man, who by turns alternately finished a prayer, and then began to work -- this was an Angel, which the Lord had sent to instruct His chosen one. The monk thereupon set up a strict schedule for his life. He partook of food only once in the entire day, and sometimes only once every second or third day; he spent all night at prayer, giving himself over to a short sleep only on the third or fourth night after unbroken vigil. But the devil would not desist with his tricks, and trying to scare the monk, he appeared under the guise of monstrous phantoms. The saint however with steadfast faith protected himself with the Life-Creating Cross. Finally the enemy appeared to him in the guise of a frightful looking black lad, and hypocritically declaring himself beaten, he reckoned to sway the saint into vanity and pride. But the monk expelled the enemy with prayer.  	For yet greater solitude, the saint re-settled farther away from the village, in a graveyard. On designated days his friend brought him a scant bit of food. And here the devils, pouncing upon the saint with the intent to kill him, inflicted upon him terrible beatings. But the Lord would not allow the death of Anthony. The friend of the saint, on schedule taking him his food, saw him as though dead laying upon the ground, and he took him away back to the village. They thought the saint was dead and began to prepare for his burial. But the monk in the deep of night regained consciousness and besought his friend to take him back to the graveyard. The staunchness of Saint Anthony was greater than the wile of the enemy. Taking the form of ferocious beasts, the devils again tried to force the saint to forsake the place chosen by him, but he again expelled them by the power of the Life-Creating Cross. The Lord strengthened the power of His saint: in the heat of the struggle with the dark powers the monk saw coming down to him from the sky a luminous ray of light, and he cried out: &quot;Where hast Thou been, O Merciful Jesus?.. Why hast Thou not healed my wounds at the very start?&quot; The Lord replied: &quot;Anthony! I was here, but did wait, wanting to see thine valour; and now after this, since thou hast firmly withstood  the struggle, I shalt always aid thee and glorify thee throughout all the world&quot;. After this vision the Monk Anthony was healed of his wounds and ready for renewed efforts. He was then 35 years of age.  	Having gained spiritual experience in the struggle with the devil, the Monk Anthony pondered going into the deeps of the Thebaid wilderness, and in full solitude there to serve the Lord by deed and by prayer. He besought the ascetic elder (to whom he had turned at the beginning of his monastic journey) to go off together with him into the wilderness, but the elder, while blessing him in the then as yet unheard of exploit of being suchlike an hermit, decided against accompanying him because of the infirmity of age. The Monk Anthony went off into the wilderness alone. The devil tried to stop him, throwing in front of the monk precious gems and stones, but the saint paid them no attention and passed them on by. Having reached a certain hilly spot, the monk caught sight of an abandoned enclosed structure and he settled within it, securing the entrance with stones. His faithful friend brought him bread twice a year, and water he had inside the enclosure. In complete silence the monk partook of the food brought him. The Monk Anthony dwelt for 20 years in complete isolation and incessant struggle with the devils, and he finally found tranquillity of spirit and peace in his mind. When it became appropriate, the Lord revealed to people about His great ascetic. The saint had to instruct many layfolk and monastics. The people gathering at the enclosure of the monk removed the stones sealing his entrance way, and they went to Saint Anthony and besought him to take them under his guidance. Soon the heights on which Saint Anthony asceticised was encircled by a whole belt of monastic communities, and the monk fondly directed their inhabitants, teaching about the spiritual life to everyone who came into the wilderness to be saved. He taught first of all the need to take up spiritual efforts, to unremittingly strive to please the Lord, to have a willing and unselfish attitude towards types of work shunned earlier. He urged them not to be afraid of demonic assaults and to repel the enemy by the power of the Life-Creating Cross of the Lord. 	In the year 311 the Church was beset by a trial -- a fierce persecution against Christians, set in motion by the emperor Maximian. Wanting to suffer together with the holy martyrs, the Monk Anthony left the wilderness and arrived in Alexandria. He openly rendered aid to the imprisoned martyrs, he was present at the trial and interrogations, but the torturers would not even bother with him! It pleased the Lord to preserve him for the benefit of Christians. With the close of the persecution, the monk returned to the wilderness and continued his exploits. The Lord bestowed upon His saint a gift of wonderworking: the monk cast out devils and healed the sick by the power of his prayer. The multitude of people coming to him disrupted his solitude, and the monk went off still farther, into the so-called &quot;interiour of the wilderness&quot;, and he settled atop an high elevation. But the brethren of the wilderness monasteries searched out the monk and besought him at least often to pay visits to their communities. 	Another time the Monk Anthony left the wilderness and arrived amidst the Christians in Alexandria, to defend the Orthodox faith against the Manichaean and Arian heresies. Knowing that the name of the Monk Anthony was venerated by all the Church, the Arians circulated a lie about him -- that he allegedly adhered to their heretical teaching. But actually being present in Alexandria, the Monk Anthony in front of everyone and in the presence of the bishop openly denounced Arianism. During the time of his brief stay at Alexandria he converted to Christ a great multitude of pagans. Pagan philosophers came to the monk, wanting by their speculations to test his firm faith, but by his simple and convincing words he reduced them to silence. The Equal-to-the-Apostles emperor Constantine the Great (+ 337, Comm. 21 May) and his sons deeply esteemed the Monk Anthony and besought him to visit them at the capital, but the monk did not want to forsake his wilderness brethren. In reply to the letter, he urged the emperor not to be overcome with pride by his lofty position, but rather to remember, that even over him was the Impartial Judge -- the Lord God.  	The Monk Anthony spent 85 years of his life in the solitary wilderness. Shortly before his death, the monk told the brethren, that soon he would be taken from them. Time and again he instructed them to preserve the Orthodox faith in its purity, to shun any association with heretics, and not to weaken in their monastic efforts. &quot;Strive the yet more to dwell ever in unity amongst ye, and most of all with the Lord, and then with the saints, so that upon death they should bring ye into eternity by their blood, as friends and acquaintances&quot;, -- thus were the death-bed words of the monk passed on in his Vita (Life). The monk bid two of his disciples, who had been together with him the final 15 years of his life, to bury him in the wilderness and not arrange any solemn burial of his remains in Alexandria. Of his two monastic mantles, the monk left one to Sainted Athanasias of Alexandria (Comm. 18 January), the other to Sainted Serapion of Tmunta. The Monk Anthony died peacefully in the year 356, at age 105, and he was buried by his disciples at a treasured spot glorified by him in the wilderness.  	The Vita (Life) of the famed ascetic the Monk Anthony the Great was written in detail by a father of the Church, Saint Athanasias of Alexandria. This work of Saint Athanasias is the first memorial of Orthodox hagiography, and is considered one of the finest of his writings; Saint John Chrysostom says, that this Vita should be read by every Christian. &quot;These narratives be significantly small in comparison with the virtues of Anthony, -- writes Saint Athanasias, -- but from them ye can conclude, what the man of God Anthony was like. From his youth into his mature years observing an equal zeal for asceticism, not being seduced by the avenues of filth, and not as regards infirmity of body altering his garb, nor the any worse for it in suffering harm. His eyes were healthy and unfailing and he saw well. Not one tooth fell out for him, and they only weakened at the gums from the advanced years of age. He was healthy of hand and of foot (...). And what they said about him everywhere, all being amazed at him, whereof even those that did not see him loved him -- this serves as evidence of his virtue and love for God in soul&quot;.  	Of the works of the Monk Anthony himself, there have come down to us: 1) his Discourses, 20 in number, treating of the virtues, primarily monastic, 2) Seven Letters to monasteries -- about striving for moral perfection and regarding the spiritual struggle, and 3) a Rule of life and consolation for monastics. 	In the year 544 the relics of the Monk Anthony the great were transferred from the wilderness to Alexandria, and later on with the conquest of Egypt by the Saracens in the VII Century, they were transferred to Constantinople. The holy relics were transferred from Constantinople in the X-XI Centuries to a diocese outside Vienna, and in the XV Century -- to Arles (in France), into the church of Saint Julian. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Emulating the demeanor of the zealous Elijah, and following the Baptist with forthright steps, O father Anthony, thou wast a dweller in the desert, and hast made the whole world steadfast by thy supplications. Wherefore, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Having cast off the tumults of life, thou didst live a life of stillness to the end, emulating the Baptist in every way, O all-venerable one. Wherefore, we honor thee with him, O Anthony, first among the fathers.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>