<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Антоний Киево-Печерский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Преподобный Антоний Киево-Печерский родился в 983 году недалеко от Чернигова, в местечке Любече. С юных лет имея страх Божий, он желал облечься в иноческий образ. Придя в возраст, он отправился странствовать и, достигнув Афона, возго- релся желанием подражать подвигам его святых насельников. Приняв здесь постриг, юный инок во всем благоугождал Богу и, подвизаясь на пути добродетели, особенно преуспевал в покорно- сти и послушании, так что все монахи радовались, глядя на его святую жизнь. Прозирая в Антонии великого будущего подвижника, игумен, по внушению от Бога, отправил его на родину, сказав: «Антоний! Пора тебе и других руководить во святой жизни. Возвратись в свою Русскую землю, да будет на тебе благословение Святой Афонской Горы, от тебя произойдет множество иноков». Вернувшись на Русь, Антоний начал обходить монастыри на Киевщине, но нигде не нашел такой строгой жизни, к которой он привык на Афоне. По смотрению Божию, на одном из холмов Киевских, на кру- том берегу Днепра, напоминавшем ему любимый Афон, в лесу, близ села Берестово, он увидел пещеру, выкопанную священником Иларионом (впоследствии святой Митрополит Киевский; память 21 октября). Он стал подвизаться там в молитве, посте, бдении и труде, вкушая через день немного пищи, иногда не ел по неделе. Люди начали приходить к подвижнику за благословением, сове- том, а иные решались навсегда остаться со святым. В числе пер- вых учеников преподобного Антония был святой Никон, который в 1032 году постриг пришедшего в обитель преподобного Феодо- сия Печерского (\ 1074; память 3 мая). Святая жизнь Преподобного Антония озарила всю Русскую зем- лю красотой монашеского подвига. Святой Антоний стремившихся к иночеству принимал с любовью. После наставлений, как должно следовать за Христом, он повелевал блаженному Никону постри- гать желающих. Когда около Преподобного собралось 12 человек братии, общими усилиями была выкопана большая пещера и в ней устроена церковь и келлии для иноков. Святой Антоний, по- ставив над братией игуменом блаженного Варлаама, сам удалил- ся из обители и, выкопав себе новую пещеру, затворился в ней. Но и там, около места его уединения, вскоре начали селиться иноки. Так образовались Ближний и Дальний пещерные монасты- ри. Впоследствии над Дальней пещерой была выстроена иноками небольшая деревянная церковь в честь Успения Божией Матери. Волею князя Изяслава игумен Варлаам удалился вДимитриев- ский монастырь. Благословением преподобного Антония и с обще- го согласия братии, на игуменство был избран кроткий и смирен- ный Феодосии. К тому времени число братии уже достигло ста человек. Великий киевский князь Изяслав (I 1078) подарил ино- кам гору, на которой был выстроен большой храм и келлии, а вокруг поставлен частокол. Так образовалась славная обитель, которая была названа Печерской, как основанная над пещерами. Ведя рассказ об этом, летописец замечает, что хотя и существуют многие монастыри, устроенные богатством царей и бояр, однако они не могут сравниться с теми, которые строятся молитвами святых, их слезами, пощением и бдением. Так и преподобный Антоний не имел золота, но своими трудами возрастил обитель, не- сравнимую с другими, которая явилась первым духовным центром Руси. За святую жизнь Бог прославил преподобного Антония даром прозрения и чудотворений. Особенно это проявилось при построе- нии им великой Печерской церкви. Сама Пресвятая Богородица предстала ему и преподобному Феодосию во Влахернском храме, куда они чудесно явились, были восхищены, не отлучаясь от Пе- черского монастыря. Получив от Матери Божией золото, святые наняли мастеров-каменщиков, которые, по повелению Царицы Небесной, пошли в Русскую землю для построения храма в Печер- ской обители. При этом явлении Матерь Божия предсказала близ- кую смерть преподобного Антония, которая последовала на 90-м году его жизни 7 мая 1073 года. Мощи преподобного Анто- ния, по Божию смотрению, остаются сокрытыми. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Ѿ мїрска́гѡ мѧте́жа и҆зше́дъ, ѿверже́нїемъ же мї́ра є҆ѵⷢльски хрⷭтꙋ̀ послѣ́довалъ є҆сѝ и҆ равноа́гг҃льное житїѐ пожи́въ, въ ти́хое приста́нище ст҃ы́ѧ горы̀ а҆ѳѡ́на дости́глъ є҆сѝ. ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже бл҃гослове́нїемъ ѻ҆тцє́въ въ го́рꙋ кї́ева прише́дъ, и҆ та́мѡ трꙋдолю́бнѡ жи́знь соверши́въ, ѻ҆те́чество твоѐ просвѣти́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ мно́жествꙋ мона́шествꙋющихъ стезю̀ ведꙋ́щꙋю къ нбⷭномꙋ црⷭтвїю показа́въ, хрⷭтꙋ̀ сїѧ҄ приве́лъ є҆сѝ: є҆го́же молѝ а҆нтѡ́нїе прпⷣбне, да сп҃се́тъ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Возложи́въ себѐ бг҃ꙋ, па́че всѣ́хъ возлю́бленномꙋ ѿ ю҆́ности прпⷣбне, томꙋ̀ ѿ всеѧ̀ дꙋшѝ любо́вїю послѣ́довалъ є҆сѝ: мї́ра же тлѣ҄ннаѧ нивочто́же вмѣни́въ, въ землѝ пеще́рꙋ содѣ́лалъ є҆сѝ, и҆ въ не́й до́брѣ проти́вꙋ неви́димагѡ врага̀ ко́зней подвиза́всѧ, ꙗ҆́кѡ свѣтоза́рное сл҃нце во всѧ҄ концы̀ землѝ возсїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ: ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже веселѧ́сѧ преше́лъ є҆сѝ къ нбⷭнымъ черто́гѡмъ. и҆ ны́нѣ со а҆́гг҃лы влⷣчню прⷭто́лꙋ предстоѧ̀, помина́й на́съ чтꙋ́щихъ па́мѧть твою̀, да зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ а҆нтѡ́нїе, ѻ҆́тче на́шъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Antonii (Anthony) of Pechersk"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Antonii (Anthony) of Pechersk was born in the year 983 not far from Chernigov, at the locale of Liubech. Possessing the fear of God from his youthful years, he desired to be clothed in the monastic form. Attaining maturity of age, he set off wandering, and having reached Athos, he burned with the desire to emulate the deeds of its holy inhabitants. Here he received monastic tonsure and in everything the young monk pleased God in his asceticising upon the path of virtue; he throve especially in humility and obedience, such that all the monks did rejoice to look upon his holy life. 	The hegumen foresaw within Saint Antonii the great future ascetic, and on an inspiration from God, he sent him off back to his native land, saying: &quot;Antonii! It is time for thee to guide others also into an holy life. Return to thine own Russian Land, and be thou upon thee the blessing of Holy Mount Athos, so that from thee shalt come a multitude of monks&quot;. 	Having returned to Rus&apos;, Antonii began to make the rounds of the monasteries about Kiev, but nowhere did he find that strict life, which had drawn him to Athos. 	Through the Providence of God, on one of the hills of Kiev at a steep bank of the River Dneipr, reminiscent for him of the beloved Athos, in a forested area near the village of Berestovo, he espied a cave, dug out by the Priest Ilarion (who afterwards became Metropolitan of Kiev, Comm. 21 October). He began to asceticise there in prayer, fasting, vigil and work, eating over the course of a day but a bit of food, and sometimes he did not eat throughout the week. People began to come to the ascetic for blessing and counsel, and some decided to remain thereafter with the saint. Among the first disciples of the Monk Antonii was Saint Nikon, who in the year 1032 tonsured at the monastery the similarly arrived Monk Theodosii (Feodosii) of Pechersk (+ 1074, Comm. 3 May). 	The holy life of the Monk Antonii brightened all the Russian Land with the beauty of monastic striving. Saint Antonii received with love those yearning for monasticism. After instructions on how one ought to follow Christ, he bid Blessed Nikon to tonsure those willing. When 12 men had gathered about the Monk Antonii, the brethren together dug out a large cave and within it was built a church and cells for the monks. Saint Antonii, having appointed Blessed Varlaam as hegumen over the brethren, himself withdrew from the monastery, and having dug out for himself a new cave, he secluded himself within it. But there also, around the place of his seclusion, monks soon began to settle. Thus were formed the Nearer and Farther Cave monasteries. Afterwards over the Farther Caves was built by the monk a small wooden church in honour of the Uspenie-Dormition of the Mother of God.  	At the insistence of prince Izyaslav, the hegumen Varlaam withdrew to the Dimitriev monastery. With the blessing of the Monk Antonii and with the general agreement of the brethren , there was chosen as hegumen the meek and humble Theodosii. During this time the number of brethren had already reached an hundred men. The Kiev Great-prince Izyaslav (+ 1078) gifted to the monks the hill, on which was built the large church and cells, and around it was built a palisade wall. Thus was established the reknown monastery, which was called the Pechersk, foundationed over the caves. Giving the account of this, the chronicler remarks, that many a monastery exists built by rich emperors and nobility, they however cannot compare with those, which are built up by the prayers of saints, and by their tears, fasting and vigil. And thus though the Monk Antonii possessed not gold, he raised up by his efforts a monastery, incomparable with others, which became the first spiritual centre of Rus&apos;. 	For his holiness of life, God glorified the Monk Antonii with the gift of foresight and wonderworking. In an especial instance this occurred during their construction of the Great Pechersk church. The MostHoly Mother of God Herself stood before him and the Monk Theodosii in the Blakhernae church (in Byzantium), whither they had been miraculously transported and enraptured, without having left their Pechersk monastery (Vide account of this under 3 May, regarding the Kievo-Pechersk Icon of the MostHoly Mother of God). Having received gold from the Mother of God, the saints commissioned master-architects, who on the command of the Queen of Heaven set off (from Byzantium) to the Russian Land for building the church at the Pechersk monastery. During this appearance the Mother of God foretold the impending death of the Monk Antonii, which occurred at age 90 on 7 May 1073. The relics of the Monk Antonii, through Divine Providence, remain concealed. 	The Monk Siluan, Kievo-Pechersk SchemaMonk, was a zealous preserver of purity both of soul and body, he beset his flesh with fasting and vigil, and he cleansed his soul with prayer and meditation on God. He was granted by the Lord an abundance of spiritual gifts: an especial prayerful boldness towards God, constant joy in the Lord, perspicacity and wonderworking. The monk lived at the end-XIII to beginning-XIV Centuries. His relics rest in the Theodosiev Caves.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Needs English translation
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Needs English translation
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>