<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой мученик Феодор Тирон"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святой мученик Феодор Тирон был воином в г. Аласии Понтий- ской области (северо-восточная область Малой Азии, тянувшаяся вдоль берега Понта Эвксинского, т. е. Черного моря), под началь-  твом некоего Вринка. Его принуждали принести жертву идолам. Святой Феодор твердо, во всеуслышание исповедал свою веру во- Христа Спасителя. Начальник дал ему несколько дней на размыш- ление, во время которых святой Феодор усиленно молился. Его об- винили в поджоге языческого храма и бросили в темницу на голод- ную смерть. Там ему явился Господь Иисус Христос, утешил и под- крепил его. Приведенный вновь к правителю, святой Феодор еще раз смело и безбоязненно исповедал свою веру, за что был предан новым истязаниям и осужден на сожжение. Мученик Феодор без трепета взошел на костер и с молитвой и славословием предал свою святую душу Богу.     Это произошло около 306 года при римском императоре Гале- рии (305—311).Неповрежденное огнем тело святогоФеодора было погребено в городе Евхаитах, недалеко от Амасии. Впоследствии мощи его были перенесены в Царьград, в храм, освященный во имя его. Глава же его находится в Италии, в городе Гаэте.     Спустя 50 лет после мученической кончины святого Феодора, император Юлиан Отступник (361—363), желая надругаться над христианами, приказал градоначальнику Константинополя окроп- лять в первую седмицу Великого поста все съестные припасы на рынках идоложертвенной кровью. Святой Феодор, явившись во сне  архиепископу Евдоксию, повелел ему объявить всем христианам,  чтобы никто не покупал ничего на рынках, а ели вареную пшеницу  с медом — коливо (кутью или сочиво). В память этого события  Православная Церковь ежегодно совершает празднование свя-  тому великомученику Феодору Тирону в субботу первой недели  Великого поста. В навечерие субботы, в пятницу, на Божествен-  ной литургии Преждеосвященных Даров после заамвонной молит-  вы читается канон молебный святому великомученику Феодору,  составленный преподобным Иоанном Дамаскиным. После этого  коливо благословляется и раздается верующим. Празднование ве-  ликомученику Феодору в субботу первой седмицы Великого поста  описывал Патриарх Константинопольский Нектарий (381—397). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
Ве́лїѧ вѣ́ры и҆справлє́нїѧ, во и҆сто́чницѣ пла́мене, ꙗ҆́кѡ на водѣ̀ ѹ҆покое́нїѧ, ст҃ы́й мч҃нкъ ѳео́дѡръ ра́довашесѧ: ѻ҆гне́мъ бо всесожже́гсѧ, ꙗ҆́кѡ хлѣ́бъ сла́дкїй трⷪцѣ принесе́сѧ. тогѡ̀ мл҃твами хрⷭтѐ бж҃е сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Вѣ́рꙋ хрⷭто́вꙋ ꙗ҆́кѡ щи́тъ внꙋ́трь прїи́мъ въ се́рдцѣ твое́мъ, проти҄вныѧ си҄лы попра́лъ є҆сѝ многострада́льче, и҆ вѣнце́мъ нбⷭнымъ вѣнча́лсѧ є҆сѝ вѣ́чнѡ ѳео́дѡре, ꙗ҆́кѡ непобѣди́мый. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyr Theodore of Tyre"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyr Theodore of Tyre was a soldier in the city of Alasium of the Pontine district (northeast province of Asia Minor, stretching alongside the coast of the Pontus Euxine, i.e. the Black Sea), under the command of a certain Brincus. They commanded him to offer sacrifice to idols. Saint Theodore firmly and in a loud voice confessed his faith in Christ the Saviour. The commander gave him several days to think it over, during which time Saint Theodore prayed intensely. They charged him with setting afire a pagan temple and threw him into prison for death by starvation. The Lord Jesus Christ appeared to him there, comforting and encouraging him. Brought again to the governor, Saint Theodore yet once more boldly and fearlessly confessed his faith, for which he was subjected to new torments and condemned to burning. The martyr Theodore without hesitation climbed onto the bon-fire and with prayer and laudation gave up his holy soul to God. 	This occurred in about the year 306 under the Roman emperor Gallerius (305-311). Unharmed by the fire, the body of Saint Theodore was buried in the city of Eukhaitakheia, not far from Amasium. His relics were afterwards transferred to Tsar&apos;grad, to a church dedicated to his name. His head is situated in Italy, in the city of Gaeto. 	Later on, 50 years after the martyr&apos;s death of Saint Theodore, the emperor Julian the Apostate (361-363), wanting to commit an outrage upon the christians, commanded the city-commander of Constantinople during the first week of Great Lent to sprinkle all the food provisions in the market-places with the blood of idol-sacrifices. Saint Theodore, having appeared in a dream to archbishop Eudoxios, ordered him to inform all the christians, -- that no one should buy anything at the market-places, but rather to eat cooked wheat with honey -- kolivo ( kut&apos;ya or sochivo). In memory of this occurrence the Orthodox Church annually makes celebration of the holy GreatMartyr Theodore of Tyre on Saturday of the first week of Great Lent. On the eve of Saturday, on Friday, in the Divine Liturgy of the Pre-Sanctified Gifts after the amvon prayer there is read the molieben-kanon to the holy GreatMartyr Theodore, compiled by the monk John Damascene. After this, kolivo is blessed and distributed to the faithful. The celebration to the GreatMartyr Theodore on Saturday of the first week of Great Lent was set by the Patriarch of Constantinople Nektarios (381-397). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
Great are the accomplishments of faith!/ In the fountain of flame, as in refreshing water, the holy martyr Theodore rejoiced;/ for, wholly consumed by the fire he was offered as sweet bread unto the Trinity.// By his prayers, O Christ God, save Thou our souls!
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Having received the faith of Christ within thy heart as a shield,/ thou didst trample down hosts of the adversary, O longsuffering one;// and with a heavenly crown hast thou been crowned everlastingly, O Theodore, as thou art invincible.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>