<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святая великомученица Марина"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святая великомученица Марина родилась в Малой Азии, в городе Антиохии в семье языческого жреца. В младенчестве она лишилась матери, и отец отдал ее на попечение кормилице, кото- рая воспитала Марину в православной вере. Узнав о том, что дочь его стала христианкой, отец в негодовании отказался от нее. Во время гонения на христиан императора Диоклитиана (284—305) святая Марина в пятнадцатилетнем возрасте была схвачена и заключена в темницу. С твердым упованием на волю Божию и Его помощь готовилась юная узница к предстоящему подвигу. Правитель Олимврий, очарованный красотой девушки, пытался уговорить её отречься от Христовой веры и стать его женой. Но святая, не колеблясь, отвергла льстивые предложения. Тогда разгневанный правитель предал святую мученицу истязаниям. Жестоко избитую, святую прибили гвоздями к доске и трезубцами рвали тело. Сам правитель, не выдержав ужаса этой пытки, за- крыл лицо руками. Но святая мученица оставалась непоколебимой. Брошенная на ночь в темницу, она сподобилась Небесного посе- щения и была исцелена от ран. Привязав к дереву, мученицу опаляли огнем. Едва живая, святая молилась: «Господи, Ты спо- добил меня за Имя Твое пройти через огонь, сподоби меня пройти и через воду святого Крещения». Услышав слово «вода», правитель повелел утопить святую в огромной бочке. Мученица просила Господа, чтобы эта казнь стала для нее святым Крещением. Когда ее погружали в воду, внезапно засиял свет и белоснежная голубка опустилась с Неба, неся в клюве золотой венец. Узы, наложенные на святую Марину, сами собой развязались. Мученица стояла в купели Крещения славя Святую Троицу —Отца, Сына и Святого Духа. Святая Ма- рина вышла из купели совершенно здоровой, без единого следа ожогов. Пораженный чудом народ стал славить Истинного Бога, и многие уверовали. Это привело в ярость правителя, и он прика- зал уничтожать всех, кто исповедует Имя Христа. Тогда погибло 15000 христиан, а святая мученица Марина была обезглавлена. Страдания великомученицы описал очевидец событий, по имени Феотим. До взятия Константинополя крестоносцами в 1204 году мощи великомученицы Марины находились в монастыре Пантепонта. По другим сведениям, они находились в Антиохии до 908 года и оттуда были перенесены в Италию. Честная ее рука была пере- несена на Афон, в Ватопедский монастырь. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
А҆́гница твоѧ̀, ї҆и҃се, марї́на, зове́тъ ве́лїимъ гла́сомъ: тебѐ женишѐ мо́й люблю̀, и҆ тебѐ и҆́щꙋщи страда́льчествꙋю, и҆ сраспина́юсѧ, и҆ спогреба́юсѧ кр҃ще́нїю твоемꙋ̀, и҆ страждꙋ̀ тебѐ ра́ди, ꙗ҆́кѡ да ца́рствꙋю въ тебѣ̀, и҆ ѹ҆мира́ю за тѧ̀, да и҆ живꙋ̀ съ тобо́ю: но ꙗ҆́кѡ же́ртвꙋ непоро́чнꙋю прїими́ мѧ, съ любо́вїю поже́ршꙋюсѧ тебѣ̀. тоѧ̀ мл҃твами, ꙗ҆́кѡ ми́лостивъ сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Дѣ́вства добро́тами преиспещре́на дв҃о, нетлѣ́нными вѣнцы̀ вѣнча́ласѧ є҆сѝ марї́но. кровьми́ же мꙋ́ченичества ѡ҆багре́на, чꙋдесы̀ просвѣти́вшисѧ и҆сцѣле́нїй, бл҃гоче́стнѡ мꙋ́ченице прїѧ́ла є҆сѝ по́честь побѣ́ды твоегѡ̀ страда́нїѧ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy GreatMartyress Marina"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy GreatMartyress Marina was born in Asia Minor, in the city of Antioch, into the family of a pagan priest. In infancy she lost her mother, and her father gave her over into the care of a nursemaid, who raised Marina in the Orthodox faith. Upon learning that his daughter had become a Christian, the father angrily disowned her. During the time of the persecution against Christians under the emperor Diocletian (284-305), Saint Marina at fifteen years of age was arrested and locked up in prison. With firm trust in the will of God and His help, the young prisoner prepared for her impending fate. The governor Olymbrios, charmed with the beautiful girl, tried to persuade her to renounce the Christian faith and become his wife. But the saint, unswayed, refused his false offers. The vexed governor gave the holy martyress over to torture. Having beaten her fiercely, they fastened the saint with nails to a board and tore at her body with tridents. The governor himself, unable to bear the horror of these tortures, hid his face in his hands. But the holy martyress remained unyielding. Thrown for the night into prison, she was granted Heavenly aid and healed of her wounds. Tied to a tree, they scorched the martyress with fire. Barely alive, the martyress prayed: &quot;Lord, Thou hast granted me to go through fire for Thine Name, grant me also to go through the water of holy Baptism&quot;. 	Hearing the word &quot;water&quot;, the governor gave orders to drown the saint in a large barrel. The martyress besought the Lord, that this manner of execution should become for her holy Baptism. When they plunged her into the water, there suddenly shone a light, and a snow-white dove came down from Heaven, bearing in its beak a golden crown. The fetters put upon Saint Marina of themselves came apart. The martyress stood up in the fount of Baptism glorifying the Holy Trinity -- Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. Saint Marina emerged from the fount completely healed, without any trace of burns. Amazed at this miracle, the people glorified the True God, and many came to believe. This brought the governor into a rage, and he gave orders to kill anyone, who might confess the Name of Christ. There then perished 15,000 Christians, and the holy Martyress Marina was beheaded. The sufferings of the GreatMartyress Marina were described by an eye-witness of the event, named Theotimos. 	Up until the taking of Constantinople by Western crusaders in the year 1204, the relics of the GreatMartyress Marina were situated in the Panteponteia monastery. According to other sources, they were located in Antioch until the year 908 and from there transferred to Italy. Her venerable hand was transferred to Athos, to the Batopedeia monastery.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Thy ewe-lamb Marina crieth out to Thee with a loud voice, O Jesus:/ "I love Thee, O my Bridegroom,/ and, seeking Thee, I pass through many struggles:/ I am crucified and buried with Thee in Thy baptism,/ and suffer for Thy sake, that I may reign with Thee;/ I die for Thee that I might live with Thee./ As an unblemished sacrifice accept me,/ who sacrifice myself with love for Thee// By her supplications save Thou our souls, in that Thou art merciful.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Arrayed in the beauties of virginity, O Virgin Marina,/ thou wast crowned with imperishable crowns;/ and stained with the blood of thy martyrdom, O martyr,/ thou hast received the trophy of victory for thy suffering,// piously shining forth miracles of healing.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>