<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобная Параскева-Петка Сербская, Болгарская"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov">
Родилась в благочестивой болгарской семье, жившей в XI веке в селении Епиват, между Силистрией и Константинополем. Однажды, как стрела, пронзили ее сердце услышанные за богослужением слова Господа: Иже хочет по Мне идти, да отвержется себе (Мф. 16, 24). По смерти родителей святая постриглась в монашество и удалилась в Иорданскую долину, где славно подвизалась до глубокой старости. За два года до кончины преподобной Параскеве явился Ангел и повелел ей вернуться на родину, что она исполнила.

Святая скончалась мирно. Мощи ее, покоящиеся в соборном храме в Яссах, ознаменовались нетлением и многими исцелениями.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Пꙋсты́нное и҆ безмо́лвное житїѐ возлюби́вши, и҆ во слѣ́дъ хрⷭта̀ жениха̀ твоегѡ̀ ѹ҆се́рднѡ поте́кши, и҆ тогѡ̀ бл҃го́е и҆́го во ю҆́ности твое́й взе́мши, крⷭтнымъ зна́менїемъ къ мы́слєннымъ врагѡ́мъ мꙋ́жески воѡрꙋжи́вшисѧ, по́стническими по́двиги, посто́мъ и҆ мл҃твами, и҆ сле́зными ка́плѧми ѹ҆́глїе страсте́й ѹ҆гаси́ла є҆сѝ, достосла́внаѧ параске́ѵо: и҆ ны́нѣ въ нбⷭнѣмъ черто́зѣ съ мꙋ́дрыми дѣ́вами предстоѧ́щи хрⷭтꙋ̀, молѝ ѡ҆ на́съ почита́ющихъ честнꙋ́ю па́мѧть твою̀. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2">
Ст҃ꙋ́ю всѝ застꙋ́пницꙋ сꙋ́щымъ въ бѣда́хъ, бл҃гоче́стнѡ воспои́мъ параске́ѵꙋ всечестнꙋ́ю: та́ бо житїѐ ѡ҆ста́вльши тлѣ́нное, и҆ нетлѣ́емое прїѧ́тъ во вѣ́ки. сегѡ̀ ра́ди сла́вꙋ ѡ҆брѣ́те, чꙋде́съ бл҃года́ть, бж҃їимъ велѣ́нїемъ. 
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Venerable Parasceva (Petka)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Fr. Eugene Tarris">
       Born in the Serbian village of Epibata (between Silinaurius and Constantinople)
she was brought up in a pious family. After the death of her parents and hating “the vain
seductive way of life” she, “as a faithful faster” and “an adornment of virgins”, entered
monasticism and left for the Jordan valley, where she practiced asceticism up to old age.
Here “by works of fasting”, “by true affection and perfect humility” she overcame the
“demon’s hosts” and “bodily passions” and lived a “bodiless life in a material body”.
Within two years of her death obeying a call from heaven, she returned to her home
country and settled in the temple of the Holy Apostles, where she died peacefully (in
first half of the 11th century). In the year 1238 by the order of Tsar John Asen, the relics
of Venerable Parasceva were transferred to Trnovo, the capital of Bulgaria; upon the
capture of this city by the Sultan Bayazid the relics were transferred to Jassy, the capital
of Wallachia. After Wallachia fell to the Turks in 1396 the pious Serbian Prince Militsa
begged for the relics of the Venerable Parasceva and they were transferred to Belgrade.
In 1521 they were bought by the Turks, who took them from Belgrade and transferred
them to Constantinople, and in 1641 to Jassy, where they repose to this day in the
cathedral.

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
Having loved the hermetic and silent life, and having longingly run in the footsteps of thy bridegroom Christ, thou didst accept His good yoke in thy tender years. By the sign of the Cross thou courageously fought against the noetic enemies; through asceticism, fasting, prayer and the shedding of tears, thou didst quench the burning coals of the passions. O Parasceva, worthy of glory: standing now before Christ in the heavenly bridal chamber, together with the wise virgins,
pray for us, who honour thy memory.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">
Holy intercessor of all who are in trouble, let us piously hymn the All-honorable Parasceva:
for she rejected the corruptible and accepted the incorruptible way of life forever: therefore she obtained glory, the grace of wonders, by the command of God.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>
