<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Максим Исповедник"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобный Максим Исповедник родился в Константинополе около 580 года и вырос в благочестивой христианской семье. В юности он получил разностороннее образование: изучил филосо- фию, грамматику, риторику, был начитан в древних авторах и в совершенстве владел Богословской диалектикой. Когда преподоб- ный Максим поступил на государственную службу, знания и доб- росовестность позволили ему стать первым секретарем императора Ираклия (611—641). Но придворная жизнь тяготила его, и он уда- лился в Хрисопольскую обитель (на противоположном берегу Босфора — ныне Скутари), где принял иноческий постриг. Своим смиренномудрием он вскоре приобрел любовь братии и был из- бран игуменом монастыря, но и в этом сане, по своей необыкно- венной скромности, он, по собственным его словам, «оставался простым монахом». В 633 году по просьбе одного Богослова, буду- щего святителя Иерусалимского Патриарха Софрония (память И марта), преподобный Максим оставил обитель и уехал в Алек- сандрию.    Святой Софроний стал известен к тому времени как не- примиримый противник монофелитской ереси. После того, как IV Вселенский Собор (451 г.) осудил монофизитов, исповедовав- ших одну (Божественную) природу в Господе Иисусе Христе, ере- тиками-монофелитами было введено понятие единой Божествен- ной воли (&amp;бХт)|ха) и единого (Божественного) действования (еуер^екх), что приводило к признанию отвергнутого монофизитско- го лжеучения. Монофелитство нашло многочисленных сторонников в Армении, Сирии, Египте. Ересь, усиливаемая национальной враж- дой, стала серьезной угрозой церковному единству Востока. Борь- ба Православия с ересями особенно осложнилась тем, что к 630 го- ду три патриарших престола на Православном Востоке оказались занятыми монофизитами: Константинопольский — Сергием, Антио- хийский — Афанасием, Александрийский — Киром.     Путь преподобного Максима из Константинополя в Александ- рию лежал через Крит, где и началась его проповедническая дея- тельность. Там он столкнулся с епископатом, придерживавшимся еретических взглядов Севера и Нестория. В Александрии и ее окрестностях преподобный провел около 6 лет. В 638 году импе- ратор Ираклий вместе с патриархом Сергием, стремясь уменьшить вероисповедные разногласия, издал указ, так называемый «Экфе- сис» ( &quot;Ехвеск; щс, чиотеох; —«Изложение веры»), который окончатель- но повелевал исповедовать учение об одной воле при двух приро- дах Спасителя. Защищая Православие, преподобный Максим обращался к людям различных званий и сословий, и беседы эти  имели успех. «Не только клир и все епископы, но и народ, и все мирские начальники ощущали в себе какое-то неодолимое влечение к нему», •— свидетельствует его житие.     В конце 638 года умер патриарх Сергий, а в 641 году — импера- тор Ираклий. Императорский престол занял жестокий и грубый  Констанс II (642—668), откровенный сторонник монофелитов. Уси- лились нападки еретиков на Православие. Преподобный Максим ушел в Карфаген и проповедовал в нем и окрестностях еще 5 лет.  Когда туда прибыл преемник патриарха Сергия патриарх Пирр,  покинувший Константинополь из-за придворных интриг, по убеж- дениям монофелит, между ним и преподобным Максимом в июне 645 года произошел открытый диспут, на котором Пирр всенарод-  но признал свои заблуждения и пожелал даже вручить папе Фео- дору письменное отречение от них. Преподобный Максим вместе с Пирром отправились в Рим, где папа Феодор принял покаяние  бывшего патриарха и восстановил его в сане.     В 647 году преподобный Максим вернулся в Африку. Там на соборах епископов монофелитство осуждалось как ересь. В 648 г. вместо «Экфесиса» вышел новый указ, составленный, по поручению  Константина, константинопольским патриархом Павлом—«Типос» (Тоттос хт)с к&apos;кзх&amp;ос—«Образец веры»), который запрещал всякие  рассуждения равно как об одной воле, так и о двух волях при при- знании двух природ Господа Иисуса Христа. Тогда преподобный Максим обратился к сменившему папу Феодора Римскому папе Мартину I (649—654) с просьбой вынести вопрос о монофелитстве  на соборное обсуждение всей Церкви. В октябре 649 года был со-  бран Латеранский Собор, на котором присутствовало 150 западных епископов и 37 представителей Православного Востока, среди кото- рых находился и преподобный Максим Исповедник. Собор осудил монофелитство, а его защитники, Константинопольские патриархи Сергий, Павел и Пирр, были преданы анафеме.      Когда Констанс II получил определение Собора, он приказал схватить и папу Мартина, и преподобного Максима. Этот приказ был выполнен через пять лет, в 654 году. Преподобного Максима обвинили в измене отечеству и заключили в тюрьму. В 656 году он был сослан во Фракию, а затем снова привезен в Константинополь- скую тюрьму. Преподобного вместе с двумя его учениками под- вергли жесточайшим пыткам: каждому отрезали язык и усекли правую руку. Затем их сослали в Колхиду. Но тут Господь явил неизреченное чудо: все они обрели способность говорить и писать. Преподобный Максим предсказал свою кончину ( { 13 августа                                                    •• 662 года). В греческих прологах 13 августа указывается перенесе- ние его мощей в Константинополь; оно могло быть приурочено к кончине преподобного. Возможно, что установление памяти на 21 января связано с тем, что 13 августа празднуется отдание празд- ника Преображения Господня. Над могилой преподобного Максима ночами возжигались три чудесно явленных светильника и совер- шалось множество исцелений. Преподобный Максим Исповедник  оставил Церкви большое Богословское наследие. Его экзегетиче-  ские труды содержат объяснения трудных мест из Священного Пи-  сания, толкования молитвы Господней и 59-го псалма, схолии к  сочинениям священномученика Дионисия Ареопагита (1* 96; память  3 октября) и святителя Григория Богослова ( } 389, память 25 ян-                                              ••  варя). К экзегетике относится также объяснение Богослужения,  озаглавленное «Мистагогия» («Введение о таинстве»).      К догматическим трудам преподобного относятся: изложение  его диспута с Пирром, несколько трактатов и письма к разным ли-  цам. В них содержится изложение Православного учения о Боже-  ственной сущности и ипостаси, о Боговоплощении и об обожении  человеческой природы.      «Ничто в обожении не есть произведение природы,—-писал пре-  подобный Максим в письме к своему другу Фалассию,— ибо при-  рода не может понять Бога. Единственно лишь милость Божья об-  ладает способностью давать обожение существам... Человек (образ   Божий) в обожении уподобляется Богу, он радуется изобилию все-   го, что принадлежит ему по природе, потому что благодать Духа   торжествует в нем и потому что Бог действует в нем» (письмо   22). Преподобному Максиму принадлежат и антропологические   труды. Он рассматривает природу души и ее сознательно-личное   существование после смерти человека. Среди нравственных сочи-   нений особенно важны «Главы о любви». Преподобный Максим   написал также три гимна в лучших традициях церковной гимно-   графии, ведущих начало от святителя Григория Богослова.       Богословие преподобного Максима Исповедника,основанное на   духовном опытном знании великих отцов-пустынников, использую-   щее искусство диалектики, выработанное дохристианской филосо- фией, было продолжено и развито в трудах преподобного Симеона Нового Богослова (+ 1021; память 12 марта) и святителя Григория Паламы (+ ок. 1360; память 14 ноября).     На русский язык переведены: «Вопросы и ответы Фалассию» (частично — «Богословский вестник», 1916—1917 гг.), «Мистаго- гия» («Введение о таинстве» — «Писания святых отцов, относящие- ся к истолкованию Православного Богослужения». Вып. 1. СПб., 1855); отрывки из «Глав о любви» и работы догматического и нрав- ственного содержания — в III томе «Добротолюбия»; историко-эк- зегетический трактат «О цели установления царской власти» («Ра- дость христианина» 1895, ноябрь). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Правосла́вїѧ наста́вниче, бл҃гоче́стїѧ ѹ҆чи́телю и҆ чистоты̀, вселе́нныѧ свѣти́льниче, а҆рхїере́євъ бг҃одꙋхнове́нное ѹ҆добре́нїе. маѯсї́ме премꙋ́дре, ѹ҆че́ньми твои́ми всѧ҄ просвѣти́лъ є҆сѝ, цѣвни́це дх҃о́внаѧ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Трⷪцы рачи́телѧ и҆ вели́каго маѯсї́ма, наꙋча́юща ꙗ҆́снѡ вѣ́рѣ бж҃е́ственнѣй, є҆́же сла́вити хрⷭта̀ во двꙋ̀ є҆стества́хъ, во́лѧхъ же и҆ дѣ́йствахъ сꙋ́ща, въ пѣ́снехъ досто́йныхъ вѣ́рнїи почти́мъ взыва́юще: ра́дꙋйсѧ проповѣ́дниче вѣ́ры. 
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
Свѣ́тъ трисїѧ́нный все́льшїйсѧ въ дꙋ́шꙋ твою̀, сосꙋ́дъ и҆збра́нъ показа́ тѧ всебл҃же́нне: ꙗ҆влѧ́юща бж҃е́ствєннаѧ концє́мъ, неꙋдобопости́жныхъ разꙋмѣ́нїй ты̀ сказꙋ́ѧй бл҃же́нне, и҆ трⷪцꙋ всѣ҄мъ маѯсї́ме воспроповѣ́дꙋѧй ꙗ҆́снѡ, пресꙋ́щнꙋю, безнача́льнꙋю. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Maximos the Confessor"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Maximos the Confessor was born in Constantinople in about the year 580 and raised in a pious Christian family. In his youth he received a very diverse education: he studied philosophy, grammatics, rhetoric, he was well-read in the authors of antiquity and he mastered to perfection theological dialectics. When Saint Maximos entered into government service, the scope of his learning and his conscientiousness enabled him to become first secretary to the emperor Heraclius (611-641). But court life vexed him, and he withdrew to the Chrysopoleia monastery (on the opposite shore of the Bosphorus -- now Skutari), where he accepted monastic tonsure. By the humility of his wisdom he soon won the love of the brethren and was chosen hegumen of the monastery, but even in this dignity, in his own words, he &quot;remained a simple monk&quot;. But in 633 at the request of a theologian, the future Jerusalem Patriarch Saint Sophronios (Comm. 11 March), the Monk Maximos left the monastery and set off to Alexandria.  	Saint Sophronios was known in these times as an implacable antagonist against the Monothelite heresy. The Fourth OEcumenical Council (year 451) had condemned the Monophysite heresy, which confessed in the Lord Jesus Christ only one nature (the Divine, but not the Human nature, of Christ). Influenced by this erroneous tendency of thought, the Monothelite heretics introduced the concept that in Christ there was only &quot;one Divine will&quot; (&quot;thelema&quot;) and only &quot;one Divine effectuation or energy&quot; (&quot;energia&quot;), -- which sought to lead back by another path to the repudiated Monophysite heresy. Monotheletism found numerous adherents in Armenia, Syria, Egypt. The heresy, fanned also by nationalist animosities, became a serious threat to church unity in the East. The struggle of Orthodoxy with the heresies was particularly complicated by the fact, that in the year 630 three of the Patriarchal thrones in the Orthodox East were occupied by Monothelites: at Constantinople -- by Sergios, at Antioch -- by Athanasias, and at Alexandria -- by Cyrus. 	The path of the Monk Maximos from Constantinople to Alexandria led through Crete, where indeed he began his preaching activity. He clashed there with a bishop, who adhered to the heretical opinions of Severus and Nestorius. At Alexandria and its surroundings the monk spent about 6 years. In 638 the emperor Heraclius, together with the patriarch Sergios, attempted to downplay the discrepancies in the confession of faith, and the issued an edict: the so-called &quot;Ecthesis&quot; (&quot;Ekthesis tes pisteos&quot; -- &quot;Exposition of Faith), -- which ultimately decreed that there be confessed the teaching about &quot;one will&quot; (&quot;mono-thelema&quot;) operative under the two natures of the Saviour. In defending Orthodoxy against this &quot;Ecthesis&quot;, the Monk Maximos recoursed to people of various vocations and positions, and these conversations had success. &quot;Not only the clergy and all the bishops, but also the people, and all the secular officials felt within themselves some sort of invisible attraction to him, -- testifies his Vita. 	Towards the end of 638 the patriarch Sergios died, and in 641 -- the emperor Heraclius also died. The imperial throne came to be occupied by the cruel and coarse Constans II (642-668), an open adherent of the Monothelites. The assaults of the heretics against Orthodoxy intensified. The Monk Maximos went off to Carthage and he preached there and in its surroundings for about 5 years. When the successor of patriarch Sergios,  patriarch Pyrrhos, arrived there in forsaking Constantinople because of court intrigues, and being by persuasion a Monothelite, -- there occurred between him and the Monk Maximos an open disputation in June 645. The result of this was that Pyrrhos publicly acknowledged his error and even wanted to put into writing to Pope Theodore the repudiation of his error. The Monk Maximos together with Pyrrhos set off to Rome, where Pope Theodore accepted the repentance of the former patriarch and restored him to his dignity. 	In the year 647 the Monk Maximos returned to Africa. And there, at a council of bishops Monotheletism was condemned as an heresy. In the year 648, in place of the &quot;Ecthesis&quot;, there was issued a new edict, commissioned by Constans and compiled by the Constantinople patriarch Paul,  the &quot;Typus&quot; (&quot;Tupos tes pisteos&quot; -- &quot;Pattern of the Faith&quot;), which overall forbade any further deliberations, whether if be about &quot;one will&quot; or about &quot;two wills&quot;, as regarding the acknowledged &quot;two natures&quot; of the Lord Jesus Christ. The Monk Maximos thereupon turned to the successor of the Roman Pope Theodore, PopeMartin I (649-654), with a request to examine the question of Monotheletism at a conciliar consideration by all the Church. In October of 649 there was convened the Lateran Council, at which were present 150 Western bishops and 37 representatives of the Orthodox East, amongst which was also the Monk Maximos the Confessor. The Council condemned Monotheletism, and its defenders -- the Constantinople patriarchs Sergios, Paul and Pyrrhos, were consigned to anathema.  	When Constans II received the determinations of the Council, he gave orders to arrest both Pope Martin and the Monk Maximos. This summons took 5 years to fulfill, in the year 654. They accused the Monk Maximos of treason to the realm and locked him up in prison. In 656 he was sent off to Thrace, and again later brought back to a Constantinople prison. The monk, together with two of his students, was subjected to the cruellest torments: for each they cut out the tongue and cut off the right hand. Then they were sent off to Colchis. But here the Lord worked an inexplicable miracle: all three of them found the ability to speak and to write. The Monk Maximos indeed foretold his own end (+ 13 August 662). On the Greek Saints-Prologue (Calendar), 13 August indicates the Transfer of the Relics of Saint Maximos to Constantinople, but possibly it might apply to the death of the saint. Or otherwise, the establishing of his memory under 21 January may be connected with this -- that 13 August celebrates the Leavetaking of the Feast of the Transfiguration of the Lord. Over the grave of the Monk Maximos shone three miraculously-appearing lights, and there occurred many an healing.  	The Monk Maximos has left to the Church a large theological legacy. His exegetical works contain explanations of difficult places within the Holy Scripture, also Commentary on the Prayer of the Lord and on the 59th Psalm, various &quot;scholia&quot; (&quot;marginalia&quot; or text-margin commentaries) on treatises of the PriestMartyr Dionysios the Areopagite (+ 96, Comm. 3 October) and Sainted Gregory the Theologian (+ 389, Comm. 25 January). To the exegetical works of Saint Maximos belongs likewise his explication of Divine-services, entitled &quot;Mystagogia&quot; (&quot;Introduction concerning the Mystery&quot;). 	To the dogmatic works of the Monk Maximos belong: the Exposition on his dispute with Pyrrhos, and several tracts and letters to various people. In them are contained expositions of the Orthodox teaching of the Divine Essence and about Hypostatic-Persons of the Holy Trinity, about the Incarnation of God, and about the &quot;theosis&quot; (&quot;deification&quot;, &quot;obozhenie&quot;) of human nature. 	&quot;Nothing in theosis is the product of human nature, -- the Monk Maximos writes in a letter to his friend Thalassios, -- since nature cannot comprehend God. It is only but the mercy of God that has the capacity to endow theosis unto the existing... In theosis man (the image of God) becomes likened to God, he rejoices in all the plenitude that does belong to him by nature, since the grace of the Spirit doth triumph within him and because God doth act within him&quot; (Letter 22).  	To the Monk Maximos belong also works concerning the anthropologic (i.e. concerning man). He deliberates on the nature of the soul and its consciously-personal existence after the death of a man. Among his moral compositions, especially important is his &quot;Chapters on Love&quot;. The Monk Maximos the Confessor wrote likewise three hymns in the finest traditions of church hymnography, following the lead of Saint Gregory the Theologian. 	The theology of the Monk Maximos the Confessor, based on the spiritual experience of the knowledge of the great Desert-Fathers, and utilising the skilled art of dialectics worked out by pre-Christian philosophy, was continued and developed upon in the works of the Monk Simeon the New Theologian (+ 1021, Comm. 12 March), and Sainted Gregory Palamas (+ c. 1360, Comm. 14 November).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
O instructor of Orthodoxy, teacher of piety and purity,/ beacon for the whole world, divinely inspired adornment of monastics./ O most wise Maximus by thy doctrines thou hast illumined all.// O harp of the Spirit, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
With fitting hymns, O ye faithful, let us honor the great Maximus,/ the lover of the Trinity, who manifestly teacheth us the divine Faith,/ to worship Christ in two natures, volitions and activities;// and let us cry aloud: Rejoice, O preacher of the faith!
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="6" Podoben="1">
The thrice-radiant light which abode in thy soul showed thee forth as a chosen vessel, O most blessed one,/ revealing things divine to the ends of the earth./ O blessed Maximus, recount understandings of things hard to comprehend// and manifestly preach to all the transcendent and unoriginate Trinity!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>