<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святая мученица Татиана"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Святая мученица Татиана родилась в знатной римской семье — ее отец трижды избирался консулом. Он был тайным христиани- ном и воспитал дочь преданной Богу и Церкви. Достигнув совер- шеннолетия, Татиана не стала выходить замуж и все свои силы отдала Церкви. Она была поставлена диаконисой в одном из рим- ских храмов и служила Богу, в посте и молитве ухаживая за больными и помогая нуждающимся. Праведность свою Татиане предстояло увенчать венцом мученичества.     Когда Римом начал править шестнадцатилетний Александр Север (222—235), вся власть сосредоточилась в руках злейшего врага и гонителя христиан Ульпиана. Кровь христианская поли- лась рекой. Схвачена была и диакониса Татиана. Когда ее при- вели в храм Аполлона, чтобы заставить принести жертву идолу, святая помолилась — и внезапно произошло землетрясение, идола разнесло на куски, а часть храма обрушилась и придавила жре- цов и многих язычников. Бес, обитавший в идоле, с воплем бежал от того места, при этом все видели пронесшуюся по воздуху тень. Тогда стали бить святую деву, выкололи ей глаза, но она терпела всё мужественно, молясь за своих мучителей, чтобы Господь от-  крыл им духовные очи. И Господь внял молитве Своей рабы.  Палачам открылось, что четыре Ангела окружили святую и от-  водили от нее удары, и им слышан был Глас с небес, обращенный  к святой мученице. Все они, восемь человек, уверовали во Христа  и пали к ногам святой Татианы, прося отпустить им их грех про-  тив нее. За исповедание себя христианами они были подвергнуты  пыткам и казнены, приняв Крещение кровью. На другой день свя-  тую Татиану вновь предали мучениям: ее обнажили, били, стали  резать бритвами ее тело, и тогда из ран вместо крови истекло  молоко и в воздухе разлилось благоухание. Мучители изнемогли  и заявили, что кто-то невидимый бьет их самих железными пал-  ками, девять из них тут же умерли. Святую бросили в темницу,  где она молилась всю ночь и с Ангелами воспевала хвалы Гос- поду. Настало новое утро, и святую Татиану вновь привели на суд. Пораженные мучители увидели, что после стольких страш- ных мучений она явилась совершенно здоровой и еще более сияю- щей и прекрасной, чем прежде. Ее стали уговаривать принести жертву богине Диане. Святая сделала вид, что согласна, и ее привели к капищу. Святая Татиана перекрестилась и стала мо- литься,— и вдруг раздался оглушительный удар грома, и молния испепелила идола, жертвы и жрецов. Мученицу снова жестоко истязали, а на ночь опять бросили в темницу, и снова к ней яви- лись Ангелы Божий и исцелили ее раны. На следующий день святую Татиану привели в цирк и выпустили на нее голодного льва; зверь не коснулся святой и стал кротко лизать ее ноги. Льва хотели загнать обратно в клетку, и тут он растерзал одного из мучителей. Татиану бросили в огонь, но и огонь не повредил муче- нице. Язычники, думая, что она чародейка, остригли ей волосы, чтобы лишить ее волшебной силы, и заперли в храме Зевса. Но силы Божией нельзя отнять. На третий день пришли жрецы в окру- жении толпы, готовясь принести жертвы. Отворив храм, они увидели поверженного в прах идола и святую мученицу Татиану, радост- но призывающую Имя Господа Иисуса Христа. Все пытки были истощены, ей вынесли смертный приговор, и мужественная стра- далица была усечена мечом. Вместе с ней, как христианин, был казнен и отец святой Татианы, открывший ей истины веры Хрис- товой. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Свѣ́тлѡ во страда́нїи твое́мъ возсїѧ́ла є҆сѝ стрⷭтоте́рпице, ѡ҆ крове́й твои́хъ преиспещре́на, и҆ ꙗ҆́кѡ кра́снаѧ голꙋби́ца, къ нб҃сѝ возлетѣ́ла є҆сѝ татїа́но: тѣ́мже молѝ при́снѡ за чтꙋ́щыѧ тѧ̀. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyress Tatiana"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyress Tatiana was born into an illustrious Roman family -- her father was thrice elected consul. He was secretly a christian and raised his daughter devoted to God and the Church. Having reached the age of maturity, Tatiana did not enter into marriage but with all her strength devoted herself to the Church. She was made deaconess in one of the Roman churches and served God, in fasting and prayer tending the sick and helping the needy. By her righteousness Tatiana gained in future to be crowned with the crown of martyrdom. 	When Rome came to be ruled by the sixteen year old Alexander Severus (222235), all power was concentrated in the hands of the evil enemy and persecutor of christians Ulpian. Christian blood flowed like streams. Deaconess Tatiana was also arrested. When they brought her into the temple of Apollo so as to force her to offer sacrifice to the idol, the saint began praying -- and suddenly there occurred an earthquake -- the idol was smashed into pieces, and part of the temple collapsed and fell down on the pagan priests and many pagans. The demon inhabiting the idol ran out with an howl from that place, in front of which all saw it flying through the air like a ghost. They then began to beat the holy virgin about the eyes, but she bravely endured everything, praying for her tormentors that the Lord would open for them their spiritual eyes. And the Lord heard the prayer of His servant. The executioners came to see, that four Angels encircled the saint and fended off from the blows; they heard a Voice from the heavens addressed to the holy martyress. All of them, eight men, believed in Christ and fell on their knees to Saint Tatiana, begging them to forgive them their wrongs against her. For confessing themselves christians they were subjected to tortures and execution, receiving Baptism by blood. Saint Tatiana was again given over to tortures on another day: they uncovered her and beat her, they cut at her body with razors, and from her wounds then there permeated a fragrance in the air. The torturers became exhausted and said, that someone invisible was beating at them with iron staffs, and nine of them fell dead. They then threw the saint in prison, where she prayed all night and with the Angels sang praise to the Lord. A new morning began, and they again took Saint Tatiana to the court. The torturers beheld with astonishment that after such terrible torments she appeared completely healthy and even more radiant and beautiful than before. They began to urge her to offer sacrifice to the goddess Diana. The saint seemed to appear agreeable, and they took her to the heathen temple. Saint Tatiana made the sign of the cross and began to pray -- and suddenly there sounded a crash of deafening thunder, and lightning struck the idol, the sacrificial offerings and the pagan priests. They again fiercely tortured the martyress, and at night they again threw her in prison, and again there appeared Angels and healed her wounds. On the following day they took Saint Tatiana to the circus and let loose at her an hungry lion; the beast did not touch the saint but only lay meekly at her feet. They wanted to pen up the lion back in its cage, and here instead it clawed up one of the torturers. They threw Tatiana into a fire, but the fire did not harm the martyress. The pagans, thinking that she was a sorceress, cut her hair to deprive her of magical powers, and locked her up in the temple of Zeus. But it was impossible to take away the power of God. On the third day pagan priests came with an encircling throng, preparing to offer sacrifice. Opening the temple, they beheld the idol thrown down into the dust and the holy martyress Tatiana joyously invoking the Name of the Lord Jesus Christ. All the instruments of torture were worn out, and they carried out a sentence of death: the valiant sufferer was beheaded with a sword. Also executed as a christian together with her was her father, for having shewn her the true faith of Christ. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Thou didst shine forth radiantly in thy suffering,/ O passion-bearer, adorned with thy blood,/ and like a beautiful turtle-dove thou hast soared aloft/ to the heavens, O Tatiana.// Wherefore, pray thou ever for those who honor thee.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>