<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой мученик Неофит"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Святой мученик Неофит, родом из города Никеи, был воспитан своими родителями в строгом христианском благочестии. За добро- ту, воздержание и постоянную молитву Богу угодно было еще в отрочестве прославить святого Неофита даром чудотворений. По- добно Моисею, святой отрок извлекал воду из камней городской стены ударом руки и поил этой водой страдавших жаждой. По молитве матери святого Неофита, просившей открыть ей Промы- сел Божий о сыне, произошло чудесное явление белого голубя, возвестившего об ожидающем его спасительном пути. Явлением того же голубя святой выведен был из родительского дома и при- веден в горную пещеру, служившую убежищем льву. Там прожил отрок до пятнадцати лет, выйдя из нее лишь раз для того, чтобы похоронить родителей и раздать имущество нищим.    Во время гонений Диоклитиана (284—305) он добровольно явился в Никею и смело начал обличать нечестие языческой веры. Пришедшие в ярость гонители повесили святого на дереве, били его воловьими жилами и строгали тело железом. Затем бросили его в раскаленную печь, но святой мученик остался невредимым, пробыв в ней 3 дня и 3 ночи. Мучители, не зная, что сделать еще с Неофитом, решили убить его. Один из язычников вонзил копье в грудь святого, и страдалец отошел ко Господу на 16-м году своей жизни, около 303—305 года, в Никее. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нкъ тво́й гдⷭи, неофѵ́тъ, во страда́нїи свое́мъ вѣне́цъ прїѧ́тъ нетлѣ́нный ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мѣ́ѧй бо крѣ́пость твою̀, мꙋчи́телей низложѝ, сокрꙋшѝ и҆ де́монѡвъ немощны́ѧ де́рзѡсти: тогѡ̀ мл҃твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyr Neophytes"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyr Neophytes, a native of the city of Nicea, was raised by his parents in strict Christian piety. For his virtue, temperance and unceasing prayer, it pleased God to glorify Saint Neophytes with the gift of wonderworking, while the saint was yet but a lad! Like unto Moses, the holy lad brought forth water from a stone of the city wall and gave this water to those suffering thirst. In answer to the prayer of the mother of Saint Neophytes, seeking that the Will of God concerning her son might be revealed to her, a white dove miraculously appeared, and announced about the salvific path awaiting him. The saint was led forth from his parental home by this dove and brought to a mountain cave, which served as a sheltering den for a lion. The lad dwelt there until his fifteenth year, leaving it but once to bury his parents and distribute their substance to the poor.  	During the time of the persecution by Diocletian (284-305), he voluntarily appeared in Nicea and boldly began to denounce the impiety of the pagan faith. The enraged persecutors suspended the saint on a tree, they whipped him with ox thongs and cut at his body with iron. Then they threw him into a red-hot oven, but the holy martyr remained unharmed, spending 3 days and 3 nights in it. The torturers, not knowing what more to do with him, decided to kill him. One of the pagans thrust a spear into his chest, and the saint expired to the Lord in his 16th year of life, somewhere in the years 303-305, at Nicea.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In his suffering, O Lord,/ Thy martyr Neophytus received an imperishable crown from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ he set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By his supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>