<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Празднество Владимирской иконе Божией Матери"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Празднество Владимирской иконе Божией Матери установлено в память спасения Москвы в 1521 году от нашествия татар под предводительством хана Махмет-Гирея. Татарские полчища при- ближались к Москве, предавая огню и разрушению русские города и селения, истребляя их жителей. Великий князь Василий собирал войско против татар, а Московский митрополит Варлаам вместе с жителями Москвы усердно молился об избавлении от гибели. В это грозное время одна благочестивая слепая инокиня имела видение: из Спасских ворот Кремля выходили московские святи- тели, покидая город и унося с собой Владимирскую икону Божи- ей Матери — главную святыю Москвы, — в наказание Божие за грехи ее жителей. У Спасских ворот святителей встретили препо- добные Сергий Радонежский и Варлаам Хутынский, слезно умоляя их не оставлять Москвы. Все они вместе принесли Господу пла- менную молитву о прощении согрешивших и избавлении Москвы от врагов. После этой молитвы святители возвратились в Кремль и внесли обратно Владимирскую святую икону. Подобное же ви- дение было и московскому святому, блаженному Василию, кото- рому было открыто, что заступлением Божией Матери и молитва- ми святых Москва будет спасена. Татарскому хану было видение Божией Матери, окруженной грозным войском, устремившимся на их полки. Татары в страхе бежали, столица Русского государства была спасена.     Празднование иконе Божией Матери Владимирской совершает- ся также 23 июня и 26 августа. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Дне́сь свѣ́тлѡ красꙋ́етсѧ сла́внѣйшїй гра́дъ москва̀, ꙗ҆́кѡ зарю̀ со́лнечнꙋю воспрїе́мши влⷣчце, чꙋдотво́рнꙋю твою̀ ї҆кѡ́нꙋ, къ не́йже ны́нѣ мы̀ притека́юще, и҆ молѧ́щесѧ тебѣ̀, взыва́емъ си́це: пречꙋ́днаѧ влⷣчце бцⷣе, моли́сѧ и҆з꙽ тебѐ воплоще́нномꙋ хрⷭтꙋ̀ бг҃ꙋ на́шемꙋ, да и҆зба́витъ гра́дъ се́й, и҆ всѧ҄ гра́ды и҆ страны҄ хрїстїа҄нскїѧ невреди́мы ѿ всѣ́хъ навѣ҄тъ вра́жїихъ, и҆ сп҃се́тъ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ ꙗ҆́кѡ милосе́рдъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Взбра́нной воево́дѣ побѣди́тєльнаѧ, ꙗ҆́кѡ и҆зба́вльшесѧ ѿ ѕлы́хъ прише́ствїемъ твоегѡ̀ честна́гѡ ѡ҆́браза, влⷣчце бцⷣе, свѣ́тлѡ сотворѧ́емъ празднество̀ срѣ́тенїѧ твоегѡ̀, и҆ ѻ҆бы́чнѡ зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ невѣ́сто неневѣ́стнаѧ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Celebration of the Vladimir Icon of the Mother of God"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Celebration of the Vladimir Icon of the Mother of God was established in memory of the saving of Moscow in the year 1521 from an invasion of Tatars led by khan Makhmet-Girei. The Tatar hosts approached towards Moscow, burning and destroying Russian cities and villages, and exterminating their inhabitants. Greatprince Vasilii gathered an army against the Tatars, and the Moscow metropolitan Varlaam together with the people of Moscow prayed fervently for deliverance from destruction. During this grim time a certain pious blind nun had a vision: from the Saviour gates of the Kremlin the Moscow sainted-hierarchs were exiting, forsaking the city and bearing with them the Vladimir Icon of the Mother of God -- the chief holy thing of the city of Moscow, -- in the chastisement of God for the sins of its inhabitants. At the Saviour-gates the sainted-hierarchs were met by the Monks Sergei of Radonezh and Varlaam of Khutynsk, tearfully imploring them not to quit Moscow. All of them together offered up intense prayer to the Lord about the forgiving of transgressions and the deliverance of Moscow from its enemies. After this prayer the sainted-hierarchs returned to the Kremlin and they carried back the holy Vladimir Icon. There was a similar vision also to a Moscow saint, Blessed Vasilii, to whom it was revealed, that through the intercession of the Mother of God and the prayers of the saints, Moscow would be saved. The Tatar khan likewise had a vision of the Mother of God amidst a fearsome host, contending against his forces. The Tatars fled in fear, and the capital of the Russian realm was saved. 	The celebration of the Vladimir Icon of the Mother of God is made likewise on 23June and 26 August.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Today the most glorious city of Moscow is adorned, having received thy wonder-working icon like the radiance of the sun; and we, hastening to it and entreating thee, O Mistress, do thus cry out: O all-wondrous Mistress Theotokos, entreat Christ our God, Who became incarnate through thee, that He deliver this city, and all cities and lands where Christians dwell, unharmed by all the assaults of the enemy, and save thou our souls, in that thou art compassionate.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
As ones delivered from evils by the arrival of thy precious image, O Mistress Theotokos, do we splendidly chant hymns of victory to thee, the chosen leader, on the feast of thy meeting, and we cry to thee as is our wont: Rejoice, O Bride unwedded!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>