<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Священномученик Климент"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Священномученик Климент родился в Галатийском городе Ан- кире в 258 году от отца язычника и матери христианки В младен- честве лишился отца, а на двенадцатом году—и матери, которая предсказала ему мученическую кончину за веру во Христа. Усыно- вившая его женщина, София, воспитывала его в страхе Божием. Во время страшного голода в Галатии некоторые язычники броса- ли своих детей, не имея возможности их прокормить, и София соби- рала несчастных к себе, питала и одевала их, а святой Климент помогал ей в этом. Он учил детей и готовил их к принятию святого Крещения. Многие из них впоследствии скончались мученически за веру во Христа.     За добродетельную жизнь святой Климент был поставлен в чте- ца, а затем в диакона, в восемнадцать лет получил сан пресвите- ра, а в двадцатилетнем возрасте был рукоположен во епископа Анкирского. Вскоре вспыхнуло гонение Диоклитиана (284—305)  на христиан. По доносу привлечен был к ответу и епископ Кли-  мент. Правитель Галатии Дометиан пытался склонить святого к  поклонению языческим богам, но епископ Климент твердо испове-  довал веру Христову и мужественно претерпел все мучения, кото-  рым подверг его лютый наместник. Его вешали на дереве, резали  тело острым железом так, что видны были кости, жестоко били  палками и камнями, вертели на колесе и жгли на медленном огне.  Господь хранил Своего страдальца и чудесно исцелял его истер-  занное тело. Тогда Дометиан послал святого в Рим к самому им-  ператору Диоклитиану с донесением о том, что епископ Климент  был жестоко мучим, но оказался непреодолим. Диоклитиан, увидев  мученика совершенно здоровым, не поверил донесению и подверг  его еще более жестоким пыткам, а затем заключил в темницу.     Многие из язычников, видя мужество святого и чудесное исце-  ление его от ран, уверовали во Христа. К святому Клименту в тем- лицу стекались люди для наставлений, исцелений и Крещения, так что темница превратилась в храм. Многие из них по доносу были  казнены императором. Диоклитиан, пораженный удивительным терпением святого Климента, отослал его в Никомидию к своему соправителю Максимиану.     По дороге, на корабле, к святому присоединился ученик его Агафангел, избежавший казни с другими исповедниками и желав- ший пострадать и умереть за Христа вместе с епископом Кли- ментом.     Император Максимиан отдал святых Климента и Агафангела правителю Агриппину, который подверг их таким нечеловечес- ким истязаниям, что даже в зрителях-язычниках вспыхнуло чувство сострадания к мученикам и они побили камнями му- чителей.     Получив свободу, святые исцеляли жителей города возложением рук, крестили и наставляли людей, стекавшихся к ним во множе- стве. Снова схваченные по распоряжению Максимиана, они были отправлены на родину в город Анкир, где князь Анкирский Куриний вновь подверг их мучениям, а затем отослал в город Амисию к наместнику Дометию, отличавшемуся особой жесто- костью.     В Амисии святые мученики были брошены в кипящую известь,  пробыли в ней сутки и остались невредимы. С них сдирали кожу, •били железными палками, клали на раскаленные железные кро- вати и поливали серой. Святым всё это не вредило, и они были •отправлены в Таре для новых мучений. По дороге в пустыне свя- тому Клименту, по его молитве, было дано откровение, что он еще 28 лет будет страдать за Имя Христово. Претерпев множество му- чений, овятые были заключены в темницу.     После смерти Максимиана святой Агафангел был усечен мечом. Святого Климента освободили анкирские христиане из темницы и отвезли в пещерный храм. Там, после совершения Литургии, святой возвестил верующим скорое окончание гонений и свое близкое от- шествие. Святой мученик действительно вскоре был }бит воинами города, ворвавшимися в храм. Святому отсекли мечом голову во время принесения им Бескровной Жертвы (+ ок. 312). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Лоза̀ преподо́бства, и҆ сте́бль страда́льчества, цвѣ́тъ сщ҃е́ннѣйшїй, и҆ пло́дъ бг҃ода́нный вѣ҄рнымъ всесщ҃е́нне присноцвѣтꙋ́щъ дарова́лсѧ є҆сѝ: но ꙗ҆́кѡ мч҃нкѡвъ сострада́лецъ, и҆ сщ҃еннонача́льникѡвъ сопресто́льникъ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Лозы̀ бы́лъ є҆сѝ честна́ѧ розга̀ хрⷭто́ва, многострада́льне кли́менте всехва́льне, ꙗ҆́вльсѧ: со стра́ждꙋщими же взыва́лъ є҆сѝ: ты̀ мч҃нкѡвъ хрⷭтѐ, свѣ́тлое ра́дованїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="PriestMartyr Clement"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The PriestMartyr Clement was born in the Galatian city of Ancyra in the year 258, from a pagan father and a Christian mother. In infancy he lost his father, and at twelve years of age also his mother, who predicted for him a martyr&apos;s death for belief in Christ. A woman adopting him named Sophia raised him in the fear of God. During the time of a terrible famine in Galatia several pagans cast out their own children, not having the wherewithal to feed them, and Sophia gathered up also these hapless ones, she fed and clothed them, and Saint Clement assisted her in this. He taught the children and prepared them for Holy Baptism. Many of them died as martyrs for the faith in Christ. 	For his virtuous life Saint Clement was made a reader, and later a deacon, and at age eighteen he received the dignity of presbyter, and at age twenty he was ordained bishop of Ancyra. Soon afterwards there flared up the persecution against Christians under Diocletian (284-305). Bishop Clement was arrested under denunciation and had also to answer for himself. The governor of Galatia, Dometian, tried to sway the saint to the worship of the pagan gods, but Saint Clement firmly confessed his faith and valiantly endured all the tortures, which the cruel official subjected him to. They suspended him on a tree, and tore at his body such that the bare bones could be seen, they struck him fiercely with clubs and stones, and they turned him about on a wheel and burned at him with a low fire. The Lord preserved His sufferer and healed his lacerated body. Then Dometian dispatched the saint to Rome to the emperor Diocletian himself, with a report that Bishop Clement had been fiercely tortured, but had proven unyielding. Diocletian, seeing the martyr completely healthy, did not believe the report and subjected him to still yet crueler tortures, and then had him locked up in prison. 	Many of the pagans, seeing the bravery of the saint and the miraculous healing of his wounds, believed in Christ. People flocked to Saint Clement in prison for guidance, healing and Baptism, such that the prison was literally transformed into a church.Many of these people, when reported about, were executed by the emperor. Diocletian, struck by the amazing endurance of Saint Clement, sent him off to Nicomedia to his co-emperor Maximian.  	On the ship along the way, the saint was joined by his disciple Agathangelos, who had avoided being executed with the other confessors, and who now wanted to suffer and die for Christ together with Bishop Clement. 	The emperor Maximian in turn sent off Saint Clement and Agathangelos to the governor Agrippina, who subjected them to such inhuman torments, that even among the pagan on-lookers there was felt a sense of pity for the martyrs and they began to pelt the torturers with stones.  	Having been set free, the saints healed an inhabitant of the city with a laying on of hands and they baptised and instructed people, thronging to them in multitudes. Arrested again on orders of Maximian, they were sent off home to the city of Ancyra, where the Ancyra prince Cyrenius had them put to torture, and then dispatched them off to the city of Amasia to the official Dometius, known for his especial cruelty.  	In Amasia the martyrs were thrown into molten lime, they spent a whole day in it and remained unharmed. They flayed their skin, beat them with iron rods, they set them on red-hot beds and poured sulfur. All this failed to harm the saints, and they were sent off to Tarsis for new tortures. In the wilderness along the way Saint Clement in prayer had a revelation, that he would suffer another 28 years for the Name of Christ. And then having endured a multitude of tortures, the saints were locked up in prison.  	After the death of Maximian, Saint Agathangelos was beheaded with the sword. Ancyra Christians set free Saint Clement from prison and they took him to a cave church. There, after celebrating Liturgy, the saint announced to the faithful the soon impending end of the persecution and his own approaching demise. The holy martyr soon actually was killed by soldiers from the city, who stormed the church. They beheaded the saint during the time of his offering the Bloodless Sacrifice (+ c. 312).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Thou hast been given to the faithful, O most sacred one, as a branch of holiness and a stem of struggle, a most sacred flower and divinely bestowed and everblossoming fruit. As a fellow sufferer of the martyrs and a fellow-prelate of hierarchs, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Thou wast a precious scion of Christ the branch, O much-suffering and most lauded Clement, and thou didst cry out with those who suffered: "Thou art the radiant joy of the martyrs, O Christ!"
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>