<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобная Ксения"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобная Ксения (V), в миру Евсевия, была единственной дочерью знатного римского сенатора. С юности она стремилась к Богу. Чтобы избежать предстоящего ей брака, она тайно ушла из родительского дома с двумя преданными ей служанками и от- плыла на корабле. Встретившись, по промыслу Божию, с настояте- лем обители святого апостола Андрея, которая находилась в городе Милассе, в Кесарии, она упросила его взять ее, вместе со спутни- цами, в Миласс; изменив свое имя, она назвалась Ксенией. В Ми- лассе она купила землю, построила храм во имя святого Стефана и основала женский монастырь. Вскоре после этого епископ Ми- ласса, Павел, посвятил Ксению в диаконисы, как вполне достой- ную этого звания по добродетельной жизни. Святая всем оказы- вала помощь: для бедных была благотворительницей, для скорбя- щих— утешительницей, для грешных — наставницей. Имела глубо- кое смирение, считая себя хуже и грешнее всех. В подвигах своих руководствовалась советами палестинского подвижника преподоб- ного Евфимия. Высокой жизнью святая Ксения привлекла многие души ко спасению. Кончина святой девы, во время молитвы, была отмечена Господом явлением в небе над монастырем знамения в виде светлого венца с блистающим посреди него крестом, который сопровождал тело святой, вынесенное в город к народу, и сохра- нялся до самого момента погребения. Множество больных, прика- саясь к мощам святой, получило исцеления. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Въ тебѣ̀ ма́ти и҆звѣ́стнѡ сп҃се́сѧ є҆́же по ѡ҆́бразꙋ: прїи́мши бо крⷭтъ, послѣ́довала є҆сѝ хрⷭтꙋ̀, и҆ дѣ́ющи ѹ҆чи́ла є҆сѝ презира́ти ѹ҆́бѡ пло́ть, прехо́дитъ бо, прилѣжа́ти же ѡ҆ дꙋшѝ ве́щи безсме́ртнѣй: тѣ́мже и҆ со а҆́гг҃лы сра́дꙋетсѧ, прпⷣбнаѧ ѯсе́нїе, дꙋ́хъ тво́й. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="6">
Твою̀ страннонра́внꙋю ѯсе́нїе, па́мѧть соверша́юще, любо́вїю почита́ющїи тѧ̀, пое́мъ хрⷭта̀ во всѣ́хъ тебѣ̀ подаю́щаго крѣ́пость и҆сцѣле́нїй: є҆мꙋ́же всегда̀ моли́сѧ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Nun Xenia"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Nun Xenia (V), in the world Eusebia, was the only daughter of an eminent Roman senator. From her youth she yearned for God. In order to evade the marriage set up for her, she secretly left from her parental home together with two servants devoted to her and they set sail upon a ship. Through the Providence of God meeting up with the head of the monastery of the holy Apostle Andrew, which was situated in the city of Milassa, in Caesarea, she besought him to take her with her companions to Milassa. Having changed her name, she called herself Xenia [which in Greek means &quot;stranger&quot; or foreigner&quot;]. At Milassa she bought land, built a church in the name of Saint Stephen and founded a woman&apos;s monastery. Soon after this the bishop of Milassa, Paul, consecrated Xenia a deaconess, as fully worthy of that calling through virtuous life. The saint rendered aid to all: for the destitute she was a benefactress, for the grief-stricken -- a comforter, for sinners -- a guide. She possessed deep humility, accounting herself worst and most sinful of all. In her ascetic deeds she was guided by the counsels of the Palestinian ascetic, the Monk Euthymios. By her lofty life Saint Xenia attracted many a soul to salvation. The death of the holy virgin, during a time of prayer, was marked by the Lord with the appearance over the monastery in the heavens of an apparition in the form of a luminous crown with a radiant cross amidst it, which accompanied the body of the saint when it was carried into the city to the people, and it stayed until the moment of burial. Many of the sick, having touched to the remains of the saint, received healing.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
In thee, O mother, that which was created according to the image of God was manifestly saved./ For accepting thy cross thou didst follow after Christ,/ and praying thou didst learn to disdain the flesh,/ for thou didst transcend it to take care of thine immortal soul.// Wherefore, with the angels doth thy soul rejoice, O venerable Xenia.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="6">
Celebrating thy strange memorial, O Xenia,/ we who honor thee with love hymn Christ,/ Who giveth thee the power of healing in all things./ To Him do thou ever pray in our behalf.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>