<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые мученики Вавила Сицилийский и два ученика его Тимофей и Агапий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святые мученики Вавила Сицилийский и два ученика его Тимо- фей и Агапий жили в III веке в окрестностях Рима. Святой Ва- вила родился в городе Реупол в богатой семье и был воспитан ро- дителями в христианской вере. Еще в юности он оставил земное, тайно ушел из дома родителей и поселился на горе, где проводил все время в посте, молитве и безмолвии. Вместе с ним подвиза- лись два его ученика: Агапий и Тимофей. Избегая преследования язычников, он вместе с ними удалился на остров Сицилию, где обратил ко Христу многих неверных. Начальник острова, раздра- женный просветительской деятельностью святого Вавилы, велел схватить его вместе с учениками и предал жестоким мучениям. Святые терпеливо переносили страдания, и все трое скончались от меча. Тела их были брошены в огонь, но пламя не коснулось вои- нов Христовых. Они были погребены на острове Сицилии местными христианами. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyrs Babyla of Sicily and his two Disciples Timothy and Agapius"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyrs Babyla of Sicily and his two Disciples Timothy and Agapius lived during the III Century on the outskirts of Rome. Saint Babyla was born in the city of Reupolium into a rich family, and he was raised by his parents in the Christian faith. While still in his youth he abandoned the world, secretly going from the house of his parents to a mountain, where he spent all his time in fasting, prayer and silence. Together with him asceticised his two disciples: Timothy and Agapius. Fleeing a persecution by the pagans, he set off with his disciples to the island of Sicily, where they converted many of the unbelieving to Christ. The governor of the island, angered by the enlightening activity of Saint Babyla, gave orders to arrest him together with his disciples, and he then gave them over to fierce tortures. The saints patiently endured the sufferings, and all three died from the sword. Their bodies were thrown into a fire, but the flames did not harm the warriors of Christ. They were buried on the island of Sicily by local Christians.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>