<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Афанасий Сяндемский, Вологодский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобный Афанасий Сяндемский, Вологодский, был учени- ком преподобного Александра Свирского (\ 1533; память 30 авгу- ста). После кончины своего наставника он основал в лесах Каре- лии, недалеко от города Олонца, Успенскую пустынь, между озе- рами Сяндема и Рощинское. Клевета и нападки местных жителей вынудили преподобного Афанасия переселиться в Свирский мона- стырь, где его избрали игуменом. Вернувшись в Успенскую пус- тынь, преподобный скончался около 1550 года глубоким старцем и был погребен на одном из мысов Рощинского озера. Впослед- ствии над его могилой был построен храм во имя святителей Афа- насия и Кирилла Александрийских, в который в 1720 году были положены нетленные мощи святого. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Athanasii (Afanasii) of Syadem and Vologda"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Athanasii (Afanasii) of Syadem and Vologda was a disciple of the Monk Alexander of Svir (+ 1533, Comm. 30 August). After the death of his mentor, he established in the forests of Karelia the Dormition (Uspenie) hermitage, not far from the city of Olonets, amidst the islands of Syadem and Roschinsk. The slander and pettiness of the local inhabitants compelled the Monk Athanasii to move back to the Svir monastery, where they chose him as hegumen. Later returning to the Uspenie hermitage, the monk died in about the year 1550 in extreme old age and was buried on one of the promontories of Roschinsk island. Afterwards there was built over his grave a church in the name of Saints Athanasias and Cyril of Alexandria, into which in 1720 were placed the unperished relics of the saint. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>