<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Мученики Евстратий, Авксентий, Евгений, Мардарий и Орест Севастийские"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
Святые мученики Евстратий, Авксентий, Евгений, Мардарий и Орест пострадали за Христа при императоре Диоклитиане (284 - 305) в Севастии, в Армении. В числе первых христиан, принявших тогда мучения, был пресвитер Аравийской церкви мученик Авксентий, заключенный в темницу. Видя непоколебимость христиан, градоправитель Саталиона, благородный военачальник святой Евстратий, бывший тайным христианином, решился на открытое исповедание веры, за что был подвергнут пыткам: его избивали, надевали на ноги железные сапоги, жгли огнем. После этих жестоких мучений его сожгли, а мученика Авксентия обезглавили. Увидев их мученическую смерть, святой Мардарий, который был из простого народа, также исповедал свою веру и был повешен вниз головой. Перед кончиной он произнес молитву: &quot;Владыко Господи Боже, Отче Вседержителю...&quot;, которая читается в конце 3-го часа и на полунощнице. Мученику Евгению вырвали язык, отрубили руки и ноги и отсекли голову мечом. Молодой воин святой Орест исповедал себя христианином и за это предстал перед судом. Он был приговорен к сожжению на раскаленном железном ложе, куда взошел укрепляемый молитвой святого Евстратия. Предсмертная молитва святого Евстратия (&quot;Величая, величаю Тя, Господи...&quot;) читается на субботней полунощнице. Мученик Евстратий скончался 13 декабря.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нцы твоѝ гдⷭи, во страда́нїихъ свои́хъ вѣнцы̀ прїѧ́ша нетлѣ҄нныѧ ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мꙋ́ще бо крѣ́пость твою̀ мꙋчи́телей низложи́ша, сокрꙋши́ша и҆ де́мѡнѡвъ немощны҄ѧ де́рзѡсти. тѣ́хъ моли́твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="4">
Свѣти́льникъ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ свѣтлѣ́йшїй, во тьмѣ̀ невѣ́дѣнїѧ сѣдѧ́щымъ, стрⷭтоте́рпче. вѣ́рою бо ꙗ҆́кѡ копїе́мъ ѡ҆бложи́всѧ, врагѡ́въ шата́нїѧ не ѹ҆боѧ́лсѧ є҆сѝ, є҆ѵстра́тїе, ри́торѡвъ сы́й бл҃гоѧзы́чнѣйшїй. 
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Витї́йствꙋѧ пред꙽ беззако́ннꙋющими бж҃е́ствєннаѧ, бїє́нїѧ претерпѣ́лъ є҆сѝ мꙋ́жественнѣйшимъ се́рдцемъ, ѡ҆блиста́лъ є҆сѝ бг҃озна́меньми пречꙋ́днѣ, ѹ҆гаси́лъ є҆сѝ возвы́шенный пре́лести пла́мень сегѡ̀ ра́ди тѧ̀ чествꙋ́емъ, всебл҃же́нне, мч҃нче хрⷭто́въ є҆ѵстра́тїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The Holy Martyrs Eustratius, Auxentius, Eugene, Mardarius and Orestes"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
These holy martyrs suffered deeply for Christ during the reign of theEmperor Diocletian in Sebaste, Armenia. St. Eustratius, &quot;the accuser ofHellenic thinkers of fables and preacher of Christian divine wisdom&quot;, wasthe magistrate of Satalios. For his belief in Christ, being &quot;relentlesslybeaten, and burned in fire, and nailed in his boots with iron, and driven on the way,and enclosed in prison&quot;, he was burned to death after these severe tortures. Auxentius,&quot;who with wise words and patience became a martyr exposing godlessness&quot;, waspresbyter of the Arabian church and, after being &quot;tested by various torments,confessing Christ God&quot;, died, being beheaded by the sword. Eugene, &quot;needed by Godfor good and not needed for torture was saved by his confession&quot;, and Mardarius, &quot;themeek dove&quot;, were voluntarily led into martyrdom for the sake of Christ and died whilebeing tortured. St. Orestes, &quot;a true and wonderful warrior for every Caesar&quot;, whofound his faith in Christ by the cross on his chest, after being tortured &quot;was burned onan iron griddle&quot;, received &quot;a blessed end to his life and an incorruptible crown&quot;. Therelics of these holy martyrs repose in Rome.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In their sufferings, O Lord,/ Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By their supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="4">
Thou hast been shown to be a most splendid luminary,/ for those who sit in the darkness of ignorance, O passion-bearer;/ for, armed with faith as with a spear,/ thou wast undaunted by the arrogance of the enemy, O Eustratius,// who art far more eloquent than any orator.
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Speaking of divine things eloquently before the iniquitous, O all-wondrous one,/ thou didst endure beatings with most courageous heart,/ didst shine forth with godly signs,/ and didst extinguish the towering flame of falsehood.// Wherefore, we honor thee, O most blessed Eustratius, martyr of Christ.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>