<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Десять святых мучеников Критских: Феодул, Саторнин, Евпор, Геласий, Евникиан, Зотик, Помпий, Агафопус, Василид и Еварест"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
Десять святых мучеников Критских: Феодул, Саторнин, Евпор, Геласий, Евникиан, Зотик, Помпий, Агафопус, Василид и Еварест пострадали за Христа в III веке при императоре Декии (249 - 251). Правитель Крита, соименный императору Декию, жестоко преследовал Критскую Церковь. Однажды перед ним предстали 10 христиан из разных городов Крита, которые твердо исповедали на суде свою веру во Христа и обличили поклонение идолам. В течение 30 дней их подвергали жестоким истязаниям, но с помощью Божией они всё перенесли, славя Господа. Перед смертью они молились, чтобы Господь просветил их мучителей светом истинной веры. Все святые были обезглавлены.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нцы твоѝ гдⷭи, во страда́нїихъ свои́хъ вѣнцы̀ прїѧ́ша нетлѣ҄нныѧ ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мꙋ́ще бо крѣ́пость твою̀ мꙋчи́телей низложи́ша, сокрꙋши́ша и҆ де́мѡнѡвъ немощны҄ѧ де́рзѡсти. тѣ́хъ моли́твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Денни́ца возсїѧ̀ мч҃нкѡвъ, честно́е страда́льчество пред꙽ѡзарѧ́ющее на́мъ въ верте́пѣ ражда́емаго, є҆го́же дв҃а безсѣ́меннѡ родѝ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Ten Holy Martyrs of Crete"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
Ten Holy Martyrs of Crete: Theodulus, Saturninus, Euporus, Gelasius,   Eunician, Zoticus, Pompeius, Agathopus, Basilides, and Evaristus        They suffered for Christ during the persecution of Decius. These Holy martyrs came from different cities on the island of Crete, but with a single determination they confessed themselves Christians and have endured terrible tortures for their faith, after which they were beheaded by the sword. In the church hymns all these holy martyrs are called out by name and are hymned as &quot;the ten called by God, and the ten-rayed lamp&quot; and &quot;unshakeable pillars&quot;. Their relics subsequently were transferred to Rome. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In their sufferings, O Lord,/ Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By their supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
A morning-star hath shone forth,/ the honorable contest of the martyrs,/ illumining for us beforehand Him Who is born in the cave,// to Whom the Virgin gave birth without seed.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>