<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые апостолы Варфоломей и Варнава"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святой апостол Варфоломей родом из Каны Галилейской,, из числа 12-ти апостолов Христовых. После Сошествия Святого Духа в день Пятидесятницы ему и апостолу Филиппу (память 14 но- ября) выпал жребий проповеди Евангелия в Сирии и Малой Азии. Благовествуя, они то расходились по разным городам, то сходи- лись вновь. Святому апостолу Филиппу сопутствовала сестра, дева Мариамна. Проходя города Сирии и Мизии, они перенесли много скорбей и напастей, их побивали камнями, заключали в темницы. В одном из селений они встретились с апостолом Иоанном Бого- словом и вместе отправились во Фригию. В городе Иераполе силой своих молитв они уничтожили громадную ехидну, которой язычники покланялись как божеству. Святые апостолы Варфоло- мей и Филипп с сестрой свою проповедь подтверждали многими знамениями.    В Иераполе жил человек, по имени Стахий, бывший 40 лет слепым. Когда он получил исцеление, то уверовал во Христа и крестился. Молва об этом разнеслась по городу, и к дому, где жили апостолы, стеклось множество народа. Больные и беснова- тые освобождались от своих недугов, многие крестились. Началь- ник города приказал схватить проповедников и бросить в темни- цу, а дом Стахия сжечь. На суде языческие жрецы выступили с жалобой, что чужестранцы отвращают народ от поклонения отечественным богам. Считая, что волшебная сила заключается в одежде апостолов, правитель приказал сорвать её. Дева Ма- риамна предстала в их глазах, как огненный факел, и никто не смел коснуться ее. Святых приговорили к распятию. Апостол Филипп был вознесен на крест вниз головой. Началось земле- трясение, разверзшаяся земля поглотила правителя города, жре- цов и множество народа. Прочие испугались и бросились снимать Апостолов с креста. Так как апостол Варфоломей был подвешен невысоко, то его сняли скоро. Апостол же Филипп умер. Поста- вив Стахия епископом Иераполя, апостол Варфоломей и блажен- ная Мариамна оставили этот город.    Благовествуя Слово Божие, Мариамна пошла в Ликаонию, где мирно скончалась (память ее 17 февраля). Апостол Варфо- ломей отправился в Индию, там перевел с еврейского на мест- ный язык Евангелие от Матфея и обратил ко Христу много языч- ников. Он посетил также Великую Армению (страна между рекой Курой и верховьями рек Тигра и Евфрата), где сотворил многие чудеса и исцелил одержимую бесом дочь царя Полимия. В бла- годарность царь послал апостолу дары, но тот отказался принять их, сказав, что ищет только спасения душ человеческих. Тогда Полимий с царицей, исцеленной царевной и многими приближен- ными приняли Крещение. Их примеру последовали жители деся- ти городов Великой Армении. По проискам языческих жрецов, брат царя Астиаг схватил Апостола в городе Альбане (ныне го- род Баку) и распял вниз головой. Но он и с креста не переставал возвещать людям благую весть о Христе Спасителе. Тогда, по приказу Астиага, содрали с Апостола кожу и отсекли главу. Ве- рующие положили его останки в оловянную раку и погребли. Около 508 года святые мощи апостола Варфоломея перенесли в Месопотамию, в город Дары. Когда в 574 году городом завладе- ли персы, христиане взяли мощи Апостола и удалились к берегам Черного моря. Но так как их настигли враги, они были вынуж- дены опустить раку в море. Силою Божией рака чудесно при- плыла к острову Липару. В IX веке, после взятия острова араба- ми, святые мощи были перенесены в Неаполитанский город Бене- вент, а в X веке часть их перенесена в Рим.    О святом апостоле Варфоломее упоминается в житии Иосифа песнописца (+ 883, память 4 апреля). Получив от одного человека часть мощей апостола Варфоломея, преподобный Иосиф принес их в свою обитель близ Константинополя и построил во имя Апостола церковь, в которой положил часть его мощей. Препо- добный Иосиф горел желанием составить в честь святого хвалеб- ные песнопения и усердно молил Бога даровать ему способность к составлению их. В день памяти апостола Варфоломея преподоб- ный Иосиф увидел его в алтаре. Тот подозвал Иосифа, взял с престола святое Евангелие и возложил ему на грудь со слова- ми: «Да благословит тебя Господь, песнопения твои да усладят вселенную». С того времени преподобный Иосиф начал писать гимны и каноны и украсил ими не только праздник Апостола, но и дни памяти многих других святых, составив около 300 канонов. Святители Иоанн Златоуст, Кирилл Александрийский, Епифаний Кипрский и некоторые другие учители Церкви считают апостола Варфоломея за одно лицо с Нафанаилом (Ин. 1, 45—51; 21, 2).     Святой апостол Варнава родился на острове Кипре в семье богатых евреев и был назван Иосифом. Образование он получил в Иерусалиме, воспитываясь вместе со своим другом и сверстни- ком Савлом (будущим апостолом Павлом) у знаменитого в то время законоучителя Гамалиила. Иосиф был благочестив, часто посещал храм, строго соблюдал посты, хранил себя от юноше- ских увлечений. В то время Господь наш Иисус Христос начал общественную проповедь. Увидев Господа и услышав Его Боже- ственные слова, Иосиф уверовал в Него как в Мессию, возгорел- ся к Нему любовию и последовал за Ним. Господь избрал его в числе 70-ти учеников. Среди последователей Господа Иосиф по- лучил второе имя — Варнава, что по-еврейски значит «сын уте- шения». После Вознесения Господа на Небо, он продал принад- лежавшую ему близ Иерусалима землю и принес деньги к ногам апостолов, ничего не оставив себе (Деян. 4, 36, 37).    Когда Савл после своего обращения пришел в Иерусалим и старался присоединиться к ученикам Христовым, то все опаса- лись его как недавнего гонителя. Варнава же пришел с ним к апостолам и рассказал, как Господь явился Савлу на пути в Да- маск (Деян. 9, 26—28).    По поручению Апостолов святой Варнава ходил в Антиохию Для утверждения уверовавших: «Прибыв и увидев благодать Божию, возрадовался и убеждал всех держаться Господа искрен- ним сердцем» (Деян. 11, 23). Затем апостол Варнава пошел в Таре, а потом привел апостола Павла в Антиохию, где около года учили в храме народ. Здесь ученики впервые стали называть- ся христианами. По случаю наступившего голода, взяв щедрую милостыню, апостолы возвратились в Иерусалим. Когда царь Ирод умертвил апостола Иакова Зеведеева и в угоду иудеям взял под стражу апостола Петра, святые апостолы Варнава и Павел, выведенные из темницы Ангелом Господним, скрылись в доме тетки Варнавы, Марии. И как только гонение утихло, они возвратились в Антиохию, взяв с собой сына Марии Иоанна, про- званного Марком. По внушению Духа Святого, бывшие там про- роки и учители рукоположили Варнаву и Савла и отпустили на дело, к которому призывал их Господь (Деян. 13, 2—3). Побыв в Селевкии, они отплыли на Кипр и в городе Саламине в иудей- ских синагогах проповедовали Слово Божие. В Пафе они нашли волхва, лжепророка по имени Вариисус, который находился при проконсуле Сергии. Желая услышать Слово Божве, проконсул пригласил святых апостолов к себе. Волхв старался • отвратить проконсула от веры, но апостол Павел обличил волхва и, по его слову, тот внезапно ослеп. Проконсул уверовал во Христа (Деян. 13, 6—12). Из Пафа Апостолы прибыли в Пергию Памфилий- скую, а затем проповедовали иудеям и язычникам в Антиохии Писидийской и по всей стране той. Иудеи произвели возмущение и изгнали Павла и Варнаву. Апостолы пришли в Иконию, но, узнав о том, что иудеи хотят побить их камнями, удалились в Листру и Дервию. Там апостол Павел исцелил человека, от рож- дения не владевшего ногами. Народ принял их за богов Зевса и Гермеса и хотел принести им жертву, Апостолы едва убедили не делать этого (Деян. 14, 8—18).     Когда возник вопрос, следует ли обращенным язычникам при- нимать обрезание, апостолы Варнава и Павел отправились в Иерусалим. Там их с любовью приняли апостолы и пресвитеры. Проповедники рассказали, «что Бог сотворил с ними и как Он отверз дверь веры язычникам» (Деян. 14, 27). По долгом рас- суждении Апостолы соборно постановили не возлагать на языч- ников никакого бремени, кроме необходимого — воздерживаться от идоложертвенного и крови, удавленины и блуда и не делать другим того, чего не желают себе (Деян. 15, 19—20). Послание было отправлено с апостолами Варнавой и Павлом, и они вновь благовествовали в Антиохии, а спустя некоторое время решили посетить города, где ранее проповедовали. Апостол Варнава же- лал взять с собой Марка, но апостол Павел не хотел, так как он ранее отстал от них. Произошло разногласие, и Апостолы разлучились. Павел взял с собой Силу и отправился в Сирию и Киликию, а Варнава с Марком — на Кипр (Деян. 15, 36—41).     Умножив число верующих на Кипре, апостол Варнава отпра- вился в Рим, где, возможно, первый проповедовал Христа.     Апостол Варнава основал епископский престол в Медиолане  (Милане), а по возвращении на Кипр продолжил проповедь о Христе Спасителе. Тогда ожесточенные иудеи возбудили язычни- ков против Апостола, вывели его из города, побили камнями, и разложили костер, чтобы сжечь тело. Позднее, придя на это место, Марк взял оставшееся невредимым тело Апостола и похо- ронил в пещере, положив на грудь, согласно завещанию Апосто- ла, переписанное его собственной рукой Евангелие от Матфея.     Скончался апостол Варнава около 62 года, на 76 году жиз- ни. С течением времени место погребения Апостола в пещере было забыто. Но многочисленные знамения были явлены на этом месте. В 448 году при императоре Зеноне апостол Варнава триж- ды являлся в сновидении архиепископу Кипра Анфиму и показал место погребения своих мощей. Начав копать в указанном мес- те, христиане нашли нетленное тело Апостола и лежавшее на его груди святое Евангелие. С этих пор Кипрская Церковь стала именоваться апостольской и получила право самостоятельного избрания предстоятеля. Так апостол Варнава защитил Кипр от притязаний противника IV Вселенского Собора, еретика Петра, по прозванию Кнафея, захватившего патриарший престол в Ан- тиохии и домогавшегося власти над Кипрской Церковью. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Гдⷭень бы́лъ є҆сѝ всеи́стинный слꙋжи́тель, а҆пⷭлѡвъ же ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ седми́десѧтихъ пе́рвый, ѡ҆зари́лъ є҆сѝ и҆ съ па́ѵломъ про́повѣдь твою̀, всѣ҄мъ возвѣща́ѧй хрⷭта̀ сп҃са: сегѡ̀ ра́ди пѣснопѣ́нїи бж҃е́ственнꙋю па́мѧть твою̀ варна́во соверша́емъ. 
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ вели́кое со́лнце вселе́ннѣй, ѹ҆че́нїй сїѧ́ньми и҆ чꙋде́съ стра́шныхъ, свѣтоводѧ̀, почита́ющыѧ тѧ̀, варѳоломе́е, гдⷭень а҆пⷭле. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Apostles Bartholomew and Barnabas"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Apostle Bartholomew was born at Cana of Galilee and was one of the Twelve Apostles of Christ. After the Descent of the Holy Spirit on the Day of Pentecost, it fell by lot to the holy Apostles Bartholomew and Philip (Comm. 14 November) to preach the Gospel in Syria and Asia Minor. In their preaching they dispersed through various cities, and then met up together again. Accompanying the holy Apostle Philip was his sister, the holy virgin Saint Mariam. Traversing the cities of Syria and Myzia, they underwent much hardship and tribulations, they were stoned and they were locked up in prison. In one of the villages they met up with the Apostle John the Theologian, and together they set off to Phrygia. In the city of Hieropolis by the power of their prayers they destroyed an enormous viper, which the pagans worshipped as a god. The holy Apostles Bartholomew and Philip with his sister proved their preaching with many a miraculous sign. 	At Hieropolis there lived a man by the name of Stakhios, who had been blind for 40 years. When he received healing, he then believed in Christ and was baptised. News of this spread throughout the city, and a multitude of the people thronged to the house where the apostles were staying. The sick and those beset by demons were released from their infirmities, and many were baptised. The city governor gave orders to arrest the preachers and throw them in prison, and to burn down the house of Stakhios. At the trial pagan priests came forth with the complaint, that the strangers were turning people away from the worship of the ancestral gods. Thinking that perhaps some sort of magic power was hidden away in the clothes of the apostles, the governor gave orders to strip them. But Saint Mariam began to seem like a fiery torch before their eyes, and none dared touch her. They sentenced the saints to crucifixion. The Apostle Philip was raised up on the cross upside down. But there then began an earthquake, and a fissure in the earth swallowed up the governor of the city, together with the pagan priests and many of the people. Others took fright and rushed to take down the apostles from the crosses. Since the Apostle Bartholomew had not been put up high, they managed to take him down quickly. The Apostle Philip however had died. Making Stakhios the bishop of Hieropolis, the Apostle Bartholomew and Blessed Mariam left the city and moved on. 	Preaching the Word of God, Mariam arrived in Likaoneia, where she peacefully died (Comm. 17 February). The Apostle Bartholomew set off to India, and there he translated from Hebrew the Gospel of Matthew, and he converted many pagans to Christ. He visited likewise Great Armenia (the country between the River Kura and the upper stretches of the Tigrus and Euphrates Rivers), where he worked many a miracle and healed the daughter of the emperor Polimios from the demons afflicting her. The emperor in gratitude sent gifts to the apostle, who however refused to accept them, saying that he sought only for the salvation of the souls of mankind. Then Polimios together with the empress, their healed daughter and many of those close to them accepted Baptism. And people from the ten cities of Great Armenia followed their example. But through the intrigues of the pagan priests, the Apostle Bartholomew was seized by the emperor brother Astiag in the city of Al&apos;ban (now the city of Baku), and crucified upside down. But even from the cross he did not cease to proclaim the good news about Christ the Saviour. Finally, on orders from Astiag, they flayed the skin from the Apostle Bartholomew and cut off his head. Believers placed his remains in a pewter coffin  and buried him. 	In about the year 508 the holy relics of the Apostle Bartholomew were transferred to Mesopotamia, to the city of Dara. When the Persians seized the city in 574, Christians took the relics of the Apostle Bartholomew with them when they fled to the shores of the Black Sea. But since the enemy overtook them there, they were compelled to leave the coffin at the sea. By the power of God the coffin miraculously arrived on the island of Lipara. In the IX Century, after the taking of the island by the Arabs, the holy relics were transferred to the Neapolitan city of Beneventum in Italy, and in the X Century part of the relics were transferred to Rome.  	There is mention about the holy Apostle Bartholomew in the Vita of Joseph the Melodist (+ 883, Comm. 4 April). Having received from a certain man part of the relics of the Apostle Bartholomew, the Monk Joseph conveyed them to his own monastery near Constantinople, and he built a church in the name of the Apostle Bartholomew, placing therein part of the relics. The Monk Joseph ardently desired to compile a laudation in song in honour of the saint, and he fervently besought God to grant him the ability to do so. On the feastday in memory of the Apostle Bartholomew, the Monk Joseph caught sight of him at the altar. He beckoned to Joseph and took the holy Gospel from the altar-table and pressed it to his bosom with the words: &quot;Bless thou the Lord, and let thine song delight the world&quot;. And from that time the Monk Joseph began to write hymns and canons and with them adorn not only the feastday of the Apostle Bartholomew, but also the feastdays of many other saints, -- compiling altogether about 300 canons. Saints John Chrysostom, Cyril of Alexandria, Epiphanios of Cyprus and certain other teachers of the Church regard the Apostle Bartholomew as being one and the same person as Nathanael (Jn. 1: 45-51, 21: 2).  	The Holy Disciple Barnabas was born on the island of Cyprus into the family of rich Hebrews, and he was named Joseph. He received his education at Jerusalem, being raised with his friend and co-student Saul (the future Apostle Paul) under the then reknown teacher of the law, Gamaliel. Joseph was pious, he frequented the Temple, he strictly observed the fasts and avoided youthful distractions. And during this time period our Lord Jesus Christ began His public ministry. Seeing the Lord and hearing His Divine Words, Joseph believed on Him as the Messiah, he was ardent with love for Him and followed Him. The Lord chose him to be among His Seventy Disciples. And it was amongst the followers of the Lord that Joseph received a second name -- Barnabas, which in Hebrew means &quot;son of consolation&quot;. After the Ascension of the Lord to Heaven, Barnabas sold land belonging to him near Jerusalem and he brought the money to the feet of the Apostles, leaving nothing for himself (Acts 4: 36-37). 	When Saul after his conversion arrived in Jerusalem and sought to join with the followers of Christ, everyone there was afraid of him as having been a persecutor but a short while before. Barnabas however came with him to the Apostles and reported, how the Lord had appeared to Saul on the road to Damascus (Acts 9: 26-28). 	As entrusted him by the Apostles, Saint Barnabas went to Antioch to encourage the believers: &quot;Having come and having seen the grace of God, he rejoiced and he urged all to cleave to the Lord with sincerity of heart&quot; (Acts 11: 23). Then the Disciple Barnabas went to Tarsis, and thereafter he brought the Apostle Paul to Antioch, where for about a year they taught the people in the Church. It was here that the disciples first began to be called Christians (Acts 11: 26). With the onset of famine, and taking along generous alms, Paul and Barnabas returned to Jerusalem. When king Herod killed the Apostle James Zebedaeus, and to please the Jews had the Apostle Peter put under guard in prison, Saints Barnabas and Paul and Peter were led out of the prison by an Angel of the Lord, and they hid out at the house of Barnabas&apos; aunt Maria. Later, when the persecution had quieted down, they returned to Antioch, taking with them Maria&apos;s son John, surnamed Mark. Under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit, the prophets and teachers there imposed hands upon Barnabas and Paul, and sent them off on matters to which the Lord had summoned them (Acts 13: 2-3). Arriving in Seleucia, they sailed off to Cyprus and in the city of Salamis they preached the Word of God in the Jewish synagogues. On Paphos they came across a sorcerer and false-prophet named Barjesus, who was close with the proconsul Sergios. Wanting to hear the Word of God, the proconsul invited the saints to come to him. The sorcerer attempted to sway the proconsul from the faith, but the Apostle Paul denounced the sorcerer, who through his words suddenly fell blind. The proconsul believed in Christ (Acts 13: 6-12). From Paphos Barnabas and Paul set sail for Pergamum Pamphylia, and then they preached to the Jews and the Gentiles at Pisidian Antioch and throughout all that region. The Jews made a riot and expelled Paul and Barnabas. The saints arrived in Iconium, but learning that the Jews wanted to stone them, they withdrew to Lystra and Derben. There the Apostle Paul healed a man, crippled in the legs from birth. The people assumed them to be the gods Zeus and Hermes and wanted to offer them sacrifice. The saints just barely persuaded them not to do this (Acts 14: 8-18). 	When the question arose, whether those converted from the Gentiles should accept circumcision, Barnabas and Paul set off to Jerusalem. There they were warmly received by the Apostles and elders. The preachers related, &quot;what God had wrought with them and how He had opened the door of faith to the Gentiles &quot;Acts 14: 27). After long deliberations the Apostles collectively resolved not to impose upon Gentile-Christians any sort of burden beyond that necessary -- to refrain from idol-sacrifice and its blood, and from things strangled, and from fornication, and not to do to others that which they themselves not do (Acts 15: 19-20). Letters were dispatched with Barnabas and Paul, and they again evangelised at Antioch, and after a certain while they decided to visit the other cities, where earlier they had preached. The Disciple Barnabas wanted to take Mark along with him, but the Apostle Paul did not want to, since earlier he had gone off from them. A quarrel arose, and they separated. Paul took with him Silas and set off to Syria and Cilicia, and Barnabas took with him Mark -- to Cyprus (Acts 15: 36-41). 	Having multiplied the number of believers, the Disciple Barnabas set off to Rome, where he was perhaps the first to preach Christ. 	The Disciple Barnabas founded the episcopal seat at Mediolanum (now Milan in Italy), and upon his return to Cyprus he continued to preach about Christ the Saviour. Thereupon the enraged Jews incited the pagans against Saint Barnabas, and they led him out beyond the city and stoned him, and then built a bon-fire so as to burn the body. Later on, having come upon this spot, Mark took up the unharmed body of the Disciple Barnabas and buried it in a cave, placing upon the bosom of Saint Barnabas, in accord with his final wishes, the Gospel of Matthew copied out in his own hand. 	The Disciple Barnabas died in about the year 62, at age 76. Over the course of time the place of burial of the Disciple Barnabas was forgotten. But numerous signs appeared at this place. In the year 448, during the time of the emperor Zeno, the Disciple Barnabas thrice appeared in a dram-vision to the Cyprus archbishop Anthymos and indicated the place of burial of his relics. Starting to dig at the indicated spot, Christians found the incorrupt body of the saint, and upon his chest was the Holy Gospel. It was from these times that the Cyprus Church began to be termed Apostolic in origin and received the right of autonomously choosing its head. And thus the Disciple Barnabas defended Cyprus against the pretensions of the opponent of the Fourth OEcumenical Council, the heretic surnamed Knapheios, who had usurped the patriarchal throne at Antioch and sought to gain dominion over the Cyprus Church. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
O holy apostles/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Thou wast a most true servant of the Lord,/ and, as the foremost of the seventy apostles,/ didst shine forth in thy preaching with Paul,/ proclaiming Christ the Savior unto all;// wherefore, with songs we hymn thy divine memory, O Barnabas.
</KONTAKION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Thou hast been shown to be a great sun for the whole world,/ shining with the radiance of doctrines and awesome miracles,// and illuminating those who honor thee, O Bartholemew, apostle of the Lord.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>