<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Вукол, епископ Смирнский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобный Вукол, епископ Смирнский, ученик святого апос- тола и евангелиста Иоанна Богослова, был им поставлен первым епископом Смирнской Церкви (Малая Азия).    Благодатию Божией, святитель Вукол обратил ко Христу и крестил множество язычников и как опытный и мудрый наставник защищал свою паству от тьмы ересей. Скончался в мире около 100—105 года. Свою паству он передал святому Поликарпу, зна- менитому мужу апостольскому, который также был учеником свя- того апостола Иоанна Богослова (память его 23 февраля). У гро- ба святителя Вукола выросло миртовое дерево, которое исцеляло больных. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Пра́вило вѣ́ры и҆ ѡ҆́бразъ кро́тости, воздержа́нїѧ ѹ҆чи́телѧ ꙗ҆ви́ тѧ ста́дꙋ твоемꙋ̀, ꙗ҆́же веще́й и҆́стина: сегѡ̀ ра́ди стѧжа́лъ є҆сѝ смире́нїемъ высѡ́каѧ, нището́ю бога҄таѧ, ѻ҆́тче вꙋко́ле, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Bukolos, Bishop of Smyrna"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Bukolos, Bishop of Smyrna, was a disciple of the holy Apostle and Evangelist John the Theologian, and was established by him as the first bishop of the Smyrna Church (Asia Minor). 	By the grace of God, Saint Bukolos converted to Christ and baptised many of the pagans, and as an experienced and wise guide he defended his flock from the darkness of heresy. He died at peace in about the years 100-105. He passed his flock on to SaintPolycarp (Comm. 23 February), one of the apostolic fathers, who likewise was a disciple of the holy Apostle John the Theologian. At the grave of Saint Bukolos grew a myrtle tree, which healed the sick.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
The truth of things revealed thee to thy flock as a rule of faith,/ a model of meekness and a teacher of abstinence/ wherefore thou hast attained the heights through humility/ and riches through poverty.// O hierarch Bucolus our father, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>