<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Парфений, епископ Лампсакийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святитель Парфений, епископ Лампсакийский, был родом из города Мелитополя (Малая Азия), где его отец Христофор служил диаконом. Юноша не был научен грамоте, но хорошо усвоил Божественное Писание, присутствуя в храме при богослужениях. У него было доброе сердце и, занимаясь рыболовством,, он выру- ченные деньги раздавал нищим. Исполненный благодати Божией, святой Парфений с 18-ти лет именем Христовым врачевал болез- ни, изгонял бесов и творил другие чудеса. Узнав о добродетельной жизни юноши, Мелитопольский епископ Филипп дал ему образо- вание и посвятил во пресвитера. В 325 году, в царствование Константина Великого, архиепископ Кизический Ахиллий поставил его епископом города Лампсака (Малая Азия). В городе было множество язычников, и святитель стал усердно распространять веру во Христа, утверждая ее по воле Божией многими чудесами и исцелениями больных. Люди стали отходить от языческих веро- ваний, и тогда святитель Парфений отправился к царю Констан- тину Великому с просьбой дать ему власть разрушать идольские капища и строить на их месте христианские храмы. Царь принял святителя с честью, дал ему грамоту на разорение капищ и снаб- дил средствами для постройки храма. Возвратившись в Лампсак, святитель Парфений приказал разрушить идольские капища и посреди города воздвигнуть прекрасный Божий храм.    Найдя на одном из разоренных капищ большой камень, удоб- ный для устроения святого престола в храме, святитель приказал обработать его и отвезти на строительство церкви. По злобе диа- вола, который возъярился за взятый из капища камень, повозка опрокинулась и камнем убило возничего Евтихиана. Святой Пар- фений воскресил его своей молитвой, и посрамил диавола, который хотел воспрепятствовать Божьему делу.    Милосердие святителя было так велико, что он не отказывал в исцелении никому из множества приходящих к нему или встре- чаемых им на дорогах людей,, страждущих телесными недугами и одержимых нечистыми духами. Народ перестал обращаться к вра- чам, так как все болезни, во Имя Господа Иисуса Христа, без- мездно исцелял святой Парфений. Великой силой Имени Христова изгнал святитель множество бесов из людей, домов, морских вод. Когда святитель изгонял беса из одного человека, одержимого им с детства, нечистый дух стал просить святого дать ему другое место обитания. Святой пообещал указать такое место и, открыв уста свои, сказал бесу: «Войди и обитай во мне». Диавол, как бы опаленный огнем, возопил: «Как я войду в дом Божий?», и скрыл- ся в местах пустынных и непроходимых. Нечистый дух, изгнанный святителем из дома, где изготовлялись царские порфиры, кричал во всеуслышание, что Божественный огонь гонит его в геенну ог- ненную.    Так, являя людям великую силу веры во Христа, святитель обратил множество идолопоклонников к истинному Богу.    Святитель Парфений скончался мирно и был торжественно погребен рядом с соборной церковью Лампсака, в построенной им самим часовне. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е ѻ҆тє́цъ на́шихъ, творѧ́й при́снѡ съ на́ми по твое́й кро́тости, не ѡ҆ста́ви млⷭть твою̀ ѿ на́съ, но мл҃твами и҆́хъ въ ми́рѣ ѹ҆пра́ви живо́тъ на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Чꙋде́съ прїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ бж҃е́ственнꙋю бл҃года́ть, бг҃омꙋ́дре сщ҃е́нне парѳе́нїе, чꙋдотво́рче бг҃оно́се, всѧ҄ вѣ́рныхъ стра҄сти ѡ҆чища́ѧ, дꙋ́хи лꙋка́вства ѻ҆́тче и҆згонѧ́ѧ: сегѡ̀ ра́ди тѧ̀ воспѣва́емъ, ꙗ҆́кѡ ве́лїѧ таи́нника бж҃їѧ бл҃года́ти. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Parthenias, Bishop of Lampsaka"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Parthenias, Bishop of Lampsaka, was a native of the city of Melitopolis (Asia Minor), where his father Christopher served as deacon. The youth was not learned at grammar, but he well assimilated the Holy Scripture by being present in church for Divine-services. He possessed a good heart, and the money he earned working as a fisherman he distributed to the poor. Filled with the grace of God, Saint Parthenias from age 18 in the Name of Christ healed the sick, cast out demons and worked other miracles. Learning about the virtuous life of the youth, the Melitopolis bishop Philip gave him an education and ordained him presbyter. In the year 325 during the reign of Constantine the Great, the Kysikhos archbishop Achilles made him bishop of the city of Lampsaka (Asia Minor). In the city were many pagans, and the saint fervently began to spread the faith in Christ, affirming it by the will of God through many miracles and healings of the sick. The people began to forsake their pagan manners of belief, and the saint then went to the emperor Constantine the Great with a petition to tear down the idolous pagan-temple and build in its place a Christian church. The emperor received the saint with honour, gave him the edict for the destruction of the pagan-temple, and furnished him means for the building of a church. Returning to Lampsaka, Saint Parthenias gave orders to tear down the idolous pagan-temple and to erect amidst the city a beautiful church of God. 	Having found in one of the torn-down temples a large stone suitable to be made the holy altar-table in the church, the saint gave orders to set to work about it and move it for the construction of the church. Through the malice of the devil, which became enraged at the removal of the stone from the pagan-temple, the cart overturned and killed the driver Eutykhion. Saint Parthenias restored him to life by his prayer and shamed the devil, who wanted to frustrate the work of God.  	The kindly saint was so great, that he refused healing to no one of the multitude coming to him or who chanced to meet him by the wayside, whether suffering bodily illnesses or afflicted with unclean spirits. People even stopped going to physicians, since Saint Parthenias healed all the sick for free, in the Name of the Lord Jesus Christ. With the great power of the Name of Christ the saint banished an host of demons from people, from their homes, and from the waters of the sea. When the saint cast out a devil from a certain man, who had been afflicted by it since childhood, the unclean spirit began to implore the saint to give him another place of habitation. The saint promised to indicate such a place and, having opened his mouth, said to the demon: &quot;Come and dwell in me&quot;. The demon, as though stung by fire, cried out: &quot;How canst I go into the house of God?&quot;, and vanished off into places desolate and untrodden. An unclean spirit, cast out from the house where the imperial porphyry-dye was prepared, cried out for everyone to hear, that a Divine fire was pursuing him with the fire of Gehenna. 	Thus, have shown people the great power of faith in Christ, the saint converted a multitude of idol-worshippers to the true God. 	Saint Parthenias died peacefully and was solemnly buried alongside the cathedral church of Lampsaka, in a chapel built by him.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O God of our fathers,/ deal with us ever according to Thy meekness./ Deprive us not of Thy mercy,/ but through their supplications// direct our life in peace.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Thou didst receive the divine grace of miracles,/ O sacred Parthenius of godly wisdom, God-bearing wonder,/ cleansing the faithful of all the passions and dispelling spirits of wickedness, O father./ Wherefore, we hymn thee as a great initiate// of the mysteries of the grace of God.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>