<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Сисой Великий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Преподобный Сисой Великий (\ 429) был монахом-отшельни- ком, подвизался в Египетской пустыне в пещере, освященной мо- литвенными трудами его предшественника — преподобного Анто- ния Великого (память 17 января). За шестьдесят лет пустынного подвига преподобный Сисой достиг высокой духовной чистоты и воспринял дар чудотворения, так что однажды даже своей молит- вой вернул к жизни умершего отрока. Чрезвычайно строгий к себе, преподобный Сисой был очень милостив и сострадателен к ближним и всех принимал с любовью. Тех, кто посещал его, преподобный всегда прежде всего учил сми- рению. На вопрос одного пустынника, как он мог достичь непре- станного памятования о Боге, преподобный заметил: «Это еще не- много, сын мой, важнее того — считать себя ниже всех, потому что такое уничижение способствует приобретению смирения». Спрошенный монахами, достаточно ли одного года для покаяния впадшему в грех брату, — преподобный Сисой сказал: «Я верую в милосердие Человеколюбца Бога, и если человек покается всей душой, то Бог примет его покаяние в течение трех дней». Когда преподобный Сисой лежал на смертном одре, окружав- шие старца ученики увидели, что лицо его просияло. Они спроси- ли умирающего, что он видит. Авва Сисой ответил, что он зрит святых пророков и апостолов. Ученики спросили, с кем Препо- добный беседует? Он сказал, что пришли Ангелы за его душой, а он просит их дать ему еще хоть краткое время на покаяние. «Тебе, отче, нет нужды в покаянии», — возразили ученики. Но пре- подобный Сисой, по своему великому смирению, ответил: «Поис- тине я не знаю, сотворил ли я хоть начало покаяния моего». После этих слов лицо святого аввы просияло так, что братия не дерзали на него смотреть. Преподобный успел сказать им, что видит Само- го Господа, и святая душа его отошла в Царство Небесное. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Пꙋсты́нный жи́тель и҆ въ тѣлесѝ а҆́гг҃лъ. и҆ чꙋдотво́рецъ показа́лсѧ є҆сѝ, бг҃оно́се ѻ҆́тче на́шъ сїсѡ́е, посто́мъ, бдѣ́нїемъ, моли́твою, нбⷭнаѧ дарова́нїѧ прїи́мъ, и҆сцѣлѧ́еши недꙋ҄жныѧ, и҆ дꙋ́шы вѣ́рою притека́ющихъ къ тебѣ̀. сла́ва да́вшемꙋ тебѣ̀ крѣ́пость: сла́ва вѣнча́вшемꙋ тѧ̀: сла́ва дѣ́йствꙋющемꙋ тобо́ю всѣ҄мъ и҆сцѣлє́нїѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Подвиза́всѧ, а҆́гг҃лъ на землѝ ви́дѣнъ бы́лъ є҆сѝ, ѡ҆зарѧ́ѧ прпⷣбне помышлє́нїѧ вѣ́рныхъ бг҃озна́меньми всегда̀: тѣ́мже тѧ̀ вѣ́рою сїсѡ́е почита́емъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Sisoes the Great"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Monk Sisoi the Great (+ 429) was an hermit-monk, pursuing asceticism in the Egyptian wilderness in a cave sanctified by the prayerful labours of his predecessor -- the Monk Anthony the Great (Comm. 17 January). For his sixty years of wilderness deeds the Monk Sisoi attained to sublime spiritual purity and he was vouchsafed a gift of wonderworking, such that by his prayer he even once returned a dead lad back to life. 	Extremely strict with himself, the Monk Sisoi was very merciful and compassionate to those nearby and he received everyone with love. Those, who visited him, the monk first of all always taught humility. To the question of one of the monks as to how might he attain to a constant mindfulness of God, the monk remarked: &quot;That is still not of much consequence, my son, but more important is this -- to account oneself below everyone else, because such disparagement assists in the acquisition of humility&quot;. Asked by the monks, whether one year is sufficient for repentance in having fallen into sin against a brother, -- the Monk Sisoi said: &quot;I believe in the mercy of God the Lover-of-Mankind, and if a man repent with all his soul, then God wilt accept his repentance in the course of three days&quot;. 	When the Monk Sisoi lay upon his death-bed, the disciples surrounding the elder saw that his face did shine. They asked the dying man what he saw. Abba Sisoi answered, that he looked upon the prophets and apostles. The disciples asked, with whom did the monk converse? He said that Angels had come for his soul, and he had entreated them to give him a short bit of time yet for repentance. &quot;Thou, father, hast not need for repentance,&quot; -- replied the students. But the Monk Sisoi, with his great humility, answered: &quot;I do not know for sure whether I have even begun to make my repentance&quot;. After these words the face of the holy abba shone so, that the brethren were not able to look upon him. The monk had time to tell them that he saw the Lord Himself, and his holy soul expired to the Heavenly Kingdom.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
A desert dweller, an angel in the flesh,/ and a wonderworker wast thou shown to be,/ O our God-bearing father Sisoes,/ for having acquired heavenly gifts through fasting, vigilance, and prayer,/ thou dost heal the infirm,/ and the souls of those who have recourse to thee with faith./ Glory to Him Who hath given thee strength!/ Glory to Him Who hath crowned thee!// Glory to Him Who worketh healings for all through thee!
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Having struggled, thou wast seen to be an angel on the earth, O venerable one,/ ever illumining the thoughts of the faithful with divine signs.// Wherefore, we honor thee with faith, O Sisoes.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>