<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой великомученик Прокопий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святой великомученик Прокопий, в миру Неаний, родом из Иерусалима, жил и пострадал в царствование императора Диок- литиана (284—305). Отец его, знатный римлянин, по имени Хрис- тофор, был христианином, но мать святого, Феодосия, оставалась язычницей. Рано лишившись отца, юный отрок был воспитан ма- терью. Получив прекрасное светское образование, он был пред- ставлен Диоклитиану в первый год его вступления на престол и быстро продвинулся по службе. К 303 году, когда было воздвиг- нуто открытое гонение на христиан, Неаний был послан прокон- сулом в Александрию с повелением беспощадно преследовать Церковь Божию. Но на пути в Египет, близ сирийского города Апамен, Неанию было явление Господа Иисуса Христа, как не- когда Савлу на пути в Дамаск. Божественный голос возвестил: «Неаний, и ты идешь на Меня?» Неаний спросил: «Кто Ты, Гос- поди?»— «Я^— распятый Иисус, Сын Божий». В то же время в воздухе появился сияющий крест. После видения Неаний ощутил в своем сердце неизреченную радость и духовное веселие и пре- вратился из гонителя в ревностного последователя Христа. С тех пор Неаний возлюбил христиан и победоносно сражался только против варваров-язычников. Но на святом угоднике сбылось слово Спасителя, что «враги человеку — домашние его» (Мф. 10, 36). Мать, язычница, сама пришла к императору с жалобой на сына, непочитающего отече- ственных богов. Неаний был вызван к прокуратору Иудеи Иусту, где ему торжественно было вручено послание Диоклитиана. Про- читав полное богохульств послание, Неаний молча на глазах у всех изорвал его. Это было уже преступление, которое римляне обозначили как «оскорбление величества». Неаний был взят под стражу и в узах отправлен в Кесарию Палестинскую, где томился когда-то апостол Павел. После страшных мучений Святого бро- сили в сырую темницу. Ночью в тюремной комнате воссиял свет, и Сам Господь Иисус Христос, придя со светлыми Ангелами, со- вершил Крещение страдальца-исповедника, дав ему имя Про- копий. Многократно святого Прокопия водили в судилище, принужда- ли отречься от Христа и вновь подвергали пыткам. Стойкость мученика и его пламенная вера низводили обильную благодать Божию на людей, видевших казнь. Вдохновленные подвигом Про- копия пошли под меч палача многие из прежних стражей святого узника и римские солдаты вместе со своими трибунами Никост- ратом и Антиохом. Мученическими венцами запечатлели свою веру двенадцать женщин-христианок, сами пришедшие к воротам Кесарийской претории. Пораженная великой верой христиан и их мужеством, видя непреклонность сына, переносившего тяжкие страдания, Феодосия раскаялась, встала в ряды исповедниц и была казнена. Наконец, уже новый прокуратор, Флавиан, убе- дившись в бесполезности пыток, приговорил святого великомуче- ника Прокопия к усекновению мечом. Ночью христиане взяли многострадальное тело и, обвив гробными пеленами, со слезами и молитвами предали земле (\ 303). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нкъ тво́й гдⷭи, проко́пїй, во страда́нїи свое́мъ вѣне́цъ прїѧ́тъ нетлѣ́нный ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мѣ́ѧй бо крѣ́пость твою̀, мꙋчи́телей низложѝ, сокрꙋшѝ и҆ де́монѡвъ немощны́ѧ де́рзѡсти: тогѡ̀ мл҃твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Ре́вностїю ко хрⷭтꙋ̀ бж҃е́ственною распала́емь, и҆ крⷭта̀ крѣ́постїю ѡ҆гражда́емь, врагѡ́въ шата́нїе и҆ де́рзость низложи́лъ є҆сѝ проко́пїе, и҆ честнꙋ́ю цр҃ковь возвы́силъ є҆сѝ, вѣ́рою преꙋспѣва́ѧ, и҆ просвѣща́ѧ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy GreatMartyr Procopius"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy GreatMartyr Procopius, in the world Neanius, a native of Jerusalem, lived and suffered during the reign of the emperor Diocletian (284-305). His father, an eminent Roman by the name of Christopher, was a Christian, but the mother of the saint, Theodosia, remained a pagan. He was early deprived of his father, and the young lad was raised by his mother. Having received an excellent secular education, he was introduced to Diocletian in the very first year of the emperor&apos;s accession to the throne, and he quickly advanced in government service. Towards the year 303, when open persecution against Christians was enacted, Neanius was dispatched as a proconsul to Alexandria with orders to mercilessly persecute the Church of God. But on the way to Egypt, near the Syrian city of Apameia, Neanius had a vision of the Lord Jesus, just as once formerly had happened with Saul on the road to Damascus. A Divine voice exclaimed: &quot;Neanius, why persecutest thou Me?&quot; Neanius asked: &quot;Who art Thou, Lord?&quot; -- &quot;I am the crucified Jesus, the Son of God&quot;. And at this moment in the air appeared a radiant cross. Neanius sensed in his heart an inexpressible joy and spiritual happiness and he was transformed from being a persecutor into instead a zealous follower of Christ. From this point in time Neanius became fondly disposed towards Christians and struggled victoriously only against the barbarian pagans. 	But for the saint there transpired the words of the Saviour, that &quot;the enemies for a man -- are of his own household&quot; (Mt. 10: 36). His mother, a pagan herself went to the emperor with a complaint against her son, of not reverencing the ancestral gods. Neanius was summoned to the procurator Judaeus Justus, where he was solemnly handed the missive of Diocletian. Having read through the missive filled with its blasphemies, Neanius quietly before the eyes of everyone tore it up. This itself was already a crime, which the Romans regarded as an &quot;insult to authority&quot;. Neanius was held under guard and in chains sent off to Caesarea Palestine, where the Apostle Paul once languished. After terrible torments they threw the saint into a dank prison. By night in the prison room there shone a light, and the Lord Jesus Christ Himself, having come with luminous Angels, made Baptism for the suffering confessor, and gave him the name Procopius. 	Repeatedly they led Saint Procopius to the courtroom, demanding him to renounce Christ and anew they subjected him to tortures. The stolidity of the martyr and his fiery faith brought down God&apos;s abundant grace viewing the execution. Inspired by the deed of Procopius, beneathe the sword of the executioner went many of the holy prisoner&apos;s former guards and Roman soldiers together with their tribunes Nicostrates and Antiochus. And with martyr&apos;s crowns was sealed the faith of 12 Christian Women, having themselves come to the gates of the Caesarea Praetorium. Struck by the great faith of the Christians and their courage, and having seen the firmness of her son in bearing terrible sufferings, Theodosia became repentant and stood amidst the line of confessors and was executed. Finally the new procurator, Flavian, convinced of the uselessness of the tortures, sentenced the holy GreatMartyr Procopius to beheading by the sword. By night Christians took up the much-tortured body, and having wrapped it in grave-clothes, with tears and prayers they committed it to earth (+ 303).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In his suffering, O Lord,/ Thy martyr Procopius received an imperishable crown from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ he set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By his supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Set afire by divine zeal for Christ,/ and protected by the might of the Cross, O Procopius,/ thou didst cast down the audacity and boldness of the foe,/ and didst raise up an honorable church,// excelling in faith and enlightening us.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>