<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые мученики Прокл и Иларий"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святые мученики Прокл и Иларий, уроженцы селения Калип- та близ Анкиры, пострадали во время гонения при императоре Траяне (98—117). Первым был взят под стражу святой Прокл. Представ перед правителем Максимом, он бесстрашно исповедал свою веру во Христа. Правитель решил силой заставить святого подчиниться императору и принести жертву языческим богам. Во время пыток мученик предрек Максиму, что скоро тот сам будет принужден исповедать Христа Истинным Богом. Мученика заста- вили бежать за колесницей правителя, направлявшегося в селение Калипт. Изнемогая в пути, святой Прокл молился, чтобы Господь остановил колесницу. Силой Божией колесница остановилась, и никакие усилия не могли сдвинуть ее с места. Сидевший в ней сановник словно окаменел и оставался недвижим до тех пор, пока, по требованию мученика, не написал своей рукой хартию с испо- веданием Христа; только после этого колесница с правителем смогла продолжить путь. Посрамленный язычник жестоко отомстил святому Проклу: после многих истязаний он приказал вывести его за город и, при- вязав к столбу, расстрелять из луков. Воины, ведшие святого Прок- ла на казнь, уговаривали его покориться и тем сохранить свою жизнь, но святой сказал, чтобы они исполнили то, что им при- казано. По дороге к месту убийства, их встретил племянник святого Прокла Иларий, который со слезами обнял дядю-мученика и тоже исповедал себя христианином. Воины задержали его, и он был брошен в тюрьму. Святой мученик Прокл под градом стрел молился за своих мучителей и с молитвой предал свою душу Богу. Святой Иларий, представ пред судьей, с таким же бесстрашием, как святой Прокл, исповедал себя христианином и после истяза- ний был приговорен к смерти. Мученику связали руки и за ноги волокли по городу, израненного и окровавленного, а потом обез- главили, через 3 дня после смерти его дяди, святого мученика Прокла. Христиане похоронили их вместе в одной могиле. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Въ тебѣ̀, ѻ҆́тче, и҆звѣ́стнѡ сп҃се́сѧ є҆́же по ѡ҆́бразꙋ: прїи́мъ бо крⷭтъ послѣ́довалъ є҆сѝ хрⷭтꙋ̀, и҆ дѣ́ѧ ѹ҆чи́лъ є҆сѝ презира́ти ѹ҆́бѡ пло́ть, прехо́дитъ бо: прилѣжа́ти же ѡ҆ дꙋшѝ, ве́щи безсме́ртнѣй: тѣ́мже и҆ со а҆́гг҃лы сра́дꙋетсѧ, прпⷣбне мїхаи́ле дх҃ъ тво́й. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ денни́ца ѕвѣзда̀ возсїѧ̀ мч҃нкѡвъ про́кла и҆ ї҆ла́рїа честно́е страда́нїе, пред꙽ѡзарѧ́ющи на́съ чꙋде́съ свѣтлостьмѝ: тѣ́мже пра́зднꙋемъ па́мѧть ва́шꙋ, хрⷭта̀ бг҃а моли́те, да сп҃се́тъ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyrs Proklos and Ilarion"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyrs Proklos and Ilarion were natives of the village of Kalipta, near Ancyra, and they suffered during the time of a persecution under the emperor Trajan (98-117). Saint Proklos was put under arrest first. Brought before the governor Maximus, he fearlessly confessed his faith in Christ. The governor decided to compel the saint by force to submit himself to the emperor to offer sacrifice to the pagan gods. During the time of tortures, the martyr predicted to Maximus, that soon he himself would be compelled to confess Christ as the True God. They forced the martyr to run after the chariot of the governor, heading towards the village Kalipta. Exhausted along the way, Saint Proklos prayed, that the Lord would halt the chariot. By the power of God the chariot halted, and no sort of force could move it from the spot. The dignitary sitting in it was as it were petrified and remained unmoving until such time, at the demand of the martyr, that he would sign a statement with a confession of Christ; only after this was the chariot with the governor able to continue on its way. 	The humiliated pagan took fierce revenge on Saint Proklos: after many tortures he commanded that he be led out beyond the city, tied to a pillar and executed with arrows. The soldiers, leading saint Proklos to execution, told him to give in and save his life, but the saint said that they should do what they had been ordered. 	Along the way to the place of killing, there met them the nephew of Saint Proklos, Ilarion, who with tears hugged his martyr-uncle and also confessed himself a Christian. The soldiers seized him, and he was thrown into prison. The holy Martyr Proklos beneathe the hail of arrows prayed for his tormentors and with prayer gave up his soul to God. 	Saint Ilarion, having been brought to trial, with the same fearlessness as Saint Proklos confessed himself a Christian, and after tortures he was sentenced to death. They tied the martyr&apos;s hands and dragged him by his feet through the city, wounded and bloody, and then they beheaded him 3 days after the death of his uncle, the holy Martyr Proklos. Christians buried them together in a single grave.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Needs English translation
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
The honorable suffering of Proclus and Hilarius/ hath shone forth like the morning-star,/ illumining us with the splendors of miracles./ Wherefore, we celebrate your memory, crying:// Entreat Christ God, that He save our souls!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>