<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые мученики Кирик и Иулитта"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святые мученики Кирик и Иулитта жили в Малой Азии в го- роде Иконии Ликаонской области. Святая Иулитта происходила из знатного рода и была христианкой. Рано овдовев, она воспи- тывала своего трехлетнего сына Кирика. Во время гонения, возд- вигнутого на христиан императором Диоклитианом (284—305), святая Иулитта с сыном и двумя верными рабынями ушла из города, оставив свой дом, имущество и рабов. Под видом нищей она сначала скрывалась в Селевкии, а затем в Тарсе. Там около 305 года она была узнана, задержана и пред- ставлена на суд правителя Александра. Укрепленная Господом, святая бесстрашно отвечала на вопросы судьи и твердо испове- дала свою веру во Христа. Правитель приказал бить святую пал- ками. Во время пыток святая Иулитта повторяла: «Я христианка и не принесу жертвы бесам». Младенец Кирик плакал, глядя на мучения своей матери, и рвался к ней. Правитель Александр пробовал ласкать его, но мальчик вырывался и кричал: «Пустите меня к матери, я христиа- нин». Правитель швырнул ребенка с высоты помоста на каменные ступени, мальчик покатился вниз, ударяясь об острые углы, и умер. Мать, увидев своего истерзанного сына, возблагодарила Бога за то, что Он удостоил младенца мученического венца. Пос- ле многих жестоких пыток святую Иулитту усекли мечом. Мощи святых Кирика и Иулитты были обретены в царствова- ние святого равноапостольного царя Константина (\ 337, память 21 мая). В честь святых мучеников близ Константинополя был устроен монастырь, а недалеко от Иерусалима воздвигнут храм. По народному верованию, святым Кирику и Иулитте молятся о семейном счастье и выздоровлении больных детей. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нцы твоѝ гдⷭи, во страда́нїихъ свои́хъ вѣнцы̀ прїѧ́ша нетлѣ҄нныѧ ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мꙋ́ще бо крѣ́пость твою̀ мꙋчи́телей низложи́ша, сокрꙋши́ша и҆ де́мѡнѡвъ немощны҄ѧ де́рзѡсти. тѣ́хъ моли́твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Во ѡ҆б꙽ѧ́тїихъ носѧ́щи хрⷭтомч҃нца ї҆ꙋлї́тта ки́рѷка, на по́двизѣ мꙋ́жески веселѧ́щисѧ взыва́ше: хрⷭто́съ є҆́сть мч҃нкѡвъ похвала̀. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyrs Kyrikos and Julitta"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyrs Kyrikos and Julitta lived in Asia Minor in the city of Iconium in the Likaoneia region. Saint Julitta was descended from an illustrious family and was a Christian. Widowed early on, she raised her three year old son Kyrikos. During the time of the persecution made against Christians by the emperor Diocletian (284-305), Saint Julitta with her son and two trustworthy servants departed the city, leaving behind her home and property and servants. 	Under the guise of being impoverished she his out first at Seleucia, and then at Tarsis. And it was there in about the year 305 that she was recognised, arrested and brought to trial before the governor named Alexander. Strengthened by the Lord, she fearlessly gave answer to the questions of the judge and she firmly confessed her faith in Christ. The governor gave orders to beat the saint with canes. During the time of torment Saint Julitta kept repeating: &quot;I am a Christian and will not offer sacrifice to demons&quot;. 	The little boy Kyrikos cried, seeing his mother being tortured, and wanted to go to her. The governor Alexander tried to hug him, but the boy broke free and shouted: &quot;Let me go to my mother, I am a Christian&quot;. The governor flung the boy from the high rostrum onto the stone steps, and the boy tumbled downwards striking the sharp edges, and died. The mother, seeing her lacerated son, gave thanks to God that He had vouchsafed the boy a martyr&apos;s end. After many cruel tortures they beheaded Saint Julitta with the sword.  	The relics of Saints Kyrikos and Julitta were discovered during the reign of holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Constantine (+ 337, Comm. 21 May). In honour of these holy martyrs there was built near Constantinople a monastery, and not far off from Jerusalem was built a church. In popular custom, Saints Kyrikos and Julitta are prayed to for family happiness, and the restoring to health of sick children.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In their sufferings, O Lord,/ Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By their supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
Holding Cyricus in her embrace, Julitta, the martyr of Christ,/ cried out, exulting manfully in the contest:// "Christ is the boast of the martyrs!"
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>