<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобные Симеон, Христа ради юродивый"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Преподобные Симеон, Христа ради юродивый, и спостник его Иоанн были сирийцами, жили в VI в. в городе Едессе. С детства их связывала тесная дружба. Старший из них, Симеон, был хо- лост и жил с престарелой матерью. Иоанн же, только что вступив в брак, жил с отцом (мать его умерла) и с молодой супругой. Оба друга принадлежали к богатым семьям. Когда Симеону исполни- лось 30 лет, а Иоанну 24, они совершили путешествие в Иеруса- лим на праздник Воздвижения Честного и Животворящего Креста Господня. На обратном пути друзья беседовали о путях спасения души. Сойдя с коней, они отправили слуг с конями вперед, а сами пошли пешком. Дойдя до Иордана, они увидели на берегу реки монастыри, расположенные на границе пустыни. У обоих вспыхну- ло неудержимое желание оставить мир и провести остальную жизнь в иноческих подвигах. Они свернули с дороги, по которой шли их слуги в Сирию, и, усердно помолившись Богу, направились в про- тивоположную сторону — к монастырям. Они просили Господа ука- зать, какой монастырь им избрать и решили пойти в ту обитель, ворота которой будут открыты. В это время Господь известил во сне игумена обители Никона открыть монастырские ворота и впу- стить в обитель овец Христовых. В великой радости друзья подо- шли к открытым воротам монастыря, были ласково приняты игу- меном и остались в обители. В скором времени они приняли пост- риг. Пробыв некоторое время в обители, Симеон возгорелся жела- нием усилить свой подвиг, уйти в глубь пустыни и там подвизаться в полном уединении. Иоанн не захотел отстать от своего друга и решил разделить с ним труды пустынножительства. Игумену Ни- кону Господь открыл намерение друзей, и в ту ночь, когда иноки Симеон и Иоанн хотели покинуть обитель, он сам открыл им во- рота, помолился с ними, дал свое благословение и отпустил в пу- стыню. Начав пустынническую жизнь, духовные братья вначале претерпели сильную брань от диавола, внушавшего им печаль об оставленных родных, устрашавшего подвижников, наводившего на них расслабление, уныние и леность. Братья Симеон и Иоанн, твердо помня о данных ими при пострижении обетах, уповая на молитвы своего старца, игумена Никона, продолжали неуклонно следовать по избранному пути, проводили время в непрестанных молитвах в строгом посте, поддерживая друг друга в борьбе против искушений. Через некоторое время, с помощью Божией, искуше- ния прекратились. Иноки получили от Бога извещение, что мать Симеона и супруга Иоанна скончались и Господь удостоил их рай- ского блаженства. После этого Симеон и Иоанн прожили в пусты- не 29 лет, достигли полного бесстрастия и высокой степени духов- ности. Преподобный Симеон, по внушению Божию, помыслил о том, что им следует теперь послужить людям, а для этого необхо- димо оставить пустынное уединение и идти в мир. Но святой Иоанн, считая, что не достиг еще такой степени бесстрастия, как его сподвижник, решил не оставлять пустыни. Братья расстались со слезами. И Симеон направился в Иерусалим, там поклонился Гробу Господню и всем святыням. По своему великому смирению святой подвижник усердно молился Господу сподобить его послу- жить ближним таким образом, чтобы они не прославляли его. Свя- той Симеон избрал для себя трудный подвиг юродства Христа ра- ди. Придя в город Емессу, он остался в нем и вел себя, как без- умный, совершая странные поступки, за что подвергался насмеш- кам, брани и побоям, и между тем совершал много добрых дел. Он изгонял бесов, исцелял болезни, избавлял от скоропостижной смерти, неверующих приводил к вере, а грешников — к покаянию. Все эти добрые дела он совершал под видом юродства, и никакой похвалы или благодарности от людей не получал. Но высоко чтил своего духовного брата преподобный Иоанн: когда в пустыне его навещал кто-либо из жителей города Емессы, прося совета и мо- литв, он неизменно направлял их к «юродивому Симеону», кото- рый мог лучше преподать совет духовный. За три дня до своей смерти святой Симеон перестал появляться на улицах, затворился в своей хижине, в которой, кроме вязанки хвороста, ничего не было. Пробыв в непрестанной молитве три дня, святой Симеон пре- ставился ко Господу. Некоторые из городских нищих, друживших с ним, не встречая юродивого, пришли к его хижине и там нашли его мертвым. Взяв тело усопшего, они отнесли его без обычного Церковного пения на место, где погребали бездомных и странни- ков. Когда несли тело святого Симеона, некоторые из жителей слы- шали дивное церковное пение, не понимая откуда оно исходит. Вслед за святым Симеоном в пустыне мирно отошел к Господу преподобный Иоанн. Незадолго до кончины святому Симеону было Дано увидеть венец над головой своего духовного брата с над- писью: «За пустынническое терпение». 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е ѻ҆тє́цъ на́шихъ, творѧ́й при́снѡ съ на́ми по твое́й кро́тости, не ѡ҆ста́ви млⷭть твою̀ ѿ на́съ, но мл҃твами и҆́хъ въ ми́рѣ ѹ҆пра́ви живо́тъ на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Во пло́ти ꙗ҆́вльшасѧ безпло́тнаго, и҆ добродѣ́тельми премї́рнѡ просїѧ́вшаго, сѷмеѡ́на равноа́гг҃льнаго и҆ бг҃оно́снаго восхва́лимъ, съ ни́мже ї҆ѡа́нна приснопа́мѧтнаго, вѣ́рою и҆ любо́вїю, ꙗ҆́кѡ молѧ́щыѧсѧ гдⷭꙋ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monks Simeon, Fool-for-Christ, and his Fellow-Ascetic John"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
	The Monks Simeon, Fool-for-Christ, and his Fellow-Ascetic John were Syrians, and they lived in the VI Century at the city of Edessa. From childhood a close friendship held them together. The older of them, Simeon, was unmarried and lived with his aged mother. John, however, although he entered into marriage, lived with his father (his mother was dead) and with his young spouse. Both friends belonged to wealthy families. When Simeon became 30 years old, and John 24, they made a pilgrimage to Jerusalem on the feast of the Exaltation of the Venerable and Life-Creating Cross of the Lord. On the return journey home the friends conversed about the ways of salvation for the soul. Journeying with horses, they sent the servants with the horses on ahead, and they themselves went on foot. Going through Jordan, they saw monasteries, situated at the edge of the wilderness. Both of them were filled with an irrepressible desire to leave the world and spend their remaining life in monastic deeds. They turned off from the road, along which their servants went into Syria, and they prayed zealously to God, to guide them towards the monasteries on the opposite side. They besought the Lord to indicate which monastery for them to choose and they resolved to enter whichever monastery the gates of which would be open. At this time in a dream the Lord informed the hegumen Nikon of a monastery to open the monastery gates, and that the sheep of Christ would enter in. In great joy the comrades came through the open gates of the monastery, where they were warmly welcomed by the hegumen, and they remained at the monastery. In a short while they took monastic vows. Having dwelt for a certain while at the monastery, Simeon became keen with the desire to intensify his effort, to go into the deep wilderness and there to pursue asceticism in complete solitude. John did not wish to be left behind by his companion and he decided to share with him the work of wilderness-dweller. The Lord revealed to the hegumen Nikon the intentions of the companions, and on that night when the Monks Simeon and John intended to depart the monastery, he himself opened for them the gates, he prayed with them, gave them his blessing and sent them into the wilderness. Having begun wilderness life, the spiritual brothers at first underwent the strong assault of the devil, suggesting to them grief over abandoning their families, frightening the ascetics, directing upon them weakness, despondency and idleness. The brothers Simeon and John, firmly mindful of the monastic vows given by them, and trusting on the prayers of their starets the hegumen Nikon, continued straight upon their chosen path, and they passed the time in unceasing prayer and strict fasting, encouraging each the other in their struggle against temptation. After a certain while, with the help of God, the temptations stopped. The monks received from God the report, that the mother of Simeon and the spouse of John had died and that the Lord had vouchsafed them the blessing of paradise. After this Simeon and John dwelt in the wilderness for 29 years, and they attained complete dispassion (apatheia) and an high degree of spirituality. The Monk Simeon, through the inspiration of God, pondered about that it now was proper that he should serve people, and for this it was necessary to leave the wilderness solitude and go into the world. But Saint John, reckoning that he had not attained to such a degree of dispassion as his companion, decided not to quit the wilderness. The brethren parted with tears. Simeon journeyed to Jerusalem, and there he worshipped at the Tomb of the Lord and all the holy places. By his great humility the holy ascetic zealously besought the Lord to permit him to serve his neighbour in suchlike manner, that they should not acknowledge him. Saint Simeon chose for himself the difficult task of fool-for-Christ. Having come to the city of Emessus, he stayed in it and passed himself off as a simpleton, doing strange acts, for which he was subjected to insults, abuse and beatings, and amidst which he accomplished many good deeds. He cast out devils, healed the sick, delivered from immanent death, brought the unbelieving to faith, and sinners -- to repentance. All these good deeds he did under the guise of foolishness, and in no wise did he receive praise or thanks from people. But the Monk John highly esteemed his spiritual brother: when someone of the inhabitants of the city of Emessus visited him in the wilderness, asking advice and prayer, he would invariably direct them to &quot;the fool Simeon&quot;, who could better offer them spiritual counsel. For three days before his death Saint Simeon ceased to appear on the streets, and he enclosed himself in his hut, in which, except for bundles of fire-wood, there was nothing. Having remained at unceasing prayer for three days, Saint Simeon reposed to the Lord. Some of the city poor, companions with him, and not coming across the fool, went to his hut and there found him dead. Taking up the dead body, they carried him without church singing to a place, where the homeless and strangers were buried. While they carried the body of Saint Simeon, several of the inhabitants heard a wondrous church singing, but could not comprehend from whence it came. After Saint Simeon, the Monk John peacefully expired to the Lord in the wilderness. Shortly before death, Saint Simeon was given to behold the crown upon the head of his spiritual brother with the inscription: &quot;For endurance in the wilderness&quot;.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O God of our fathers,/ deal with us ever according to Thy meekness./ Deprive us not of Thy mercy,/ but through their supplications// direct our life in peace.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="5">
Let us praise the God-bearing Symeon,/ the peer of the angels,/ who appeared in the flesh as one incorporeal,/ and with him the ever-memorable John:// for with faith and love they entreat the Lord unceasingly in behalf of us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>