<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Мученица Христина"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Мученица Христина жила в III веке. Она родилась в богатой семье. Отец ее Урван был правителем города Тира. В возрасте 11 лет девочка отличалась необыкновенной красотой, и многие хотели жениться на ней. Однако отец Христины мечтал о том, чтобы дочь стала жрицей. Для этого он поместил ее в особое по- мещение, где поставил множество золотых и серебряных идолов, и велел дочери воскуривать пред ними фимиам. Две рабыни прислуживали Христине. В своем уединении Христина стала задумываться над тем, кто же сотворил этот прекрасный мир? Из своей комнаты она любо- валась звездным небом и постепенно пришла к мысли о Едином Творце всего мира. Она убедилась, что безгласные и бездушные идолы, стоявшие в ее покоях, ничего не могли сотворить, так как сами были сотворены руками человека. Она стала молиться Еди- ному Богу со слезами, прося Его открыть Себя. Душа ее разгора- лась любовью к Неведомому Богу, она все более усиливала молит- ву, соединяя ее с лощением. Однажды Христина удостоилась посещения Ангела, который наставил ее в истинной вере во Христа, Спасителя мира. Ангел назвал ее невестой Христовой и предвозвестил ей будущий стра- дальческий подвиг. Святая дева разбила всех стоявших у нее идо- лов и выбросила их за окно. Отец Христины Урван, посещая свою дочь, спросил ее, куда исчезли идолы? Христина молчала. Тогда, призвав рабынь, Урван узнал от них правду. В гневе отец начал бить дочь по щекам. Святая дева сначала безмолвствовала, а по- том открыла отцу свою веру в Единого Истинного Бога и что сво- ими руками она уничтожила идолов. Тогда Урван приказал убить всех прислуживавших дочери рабынь, а Христину предал жесто- кому бичеванию и бросил в темницу. Узнав о случившемся, мать святой Христины с плачем пришла к дочери, прося ее отречься от Христа и вернуться к отеческим верованиям. Однако Христина осталась непреклонной. На другой день Урван призвал дочь на суд и начал ее уговаривать воздать поклонение богам, просить прощения за свой грех, но увидел твердое и непреклонное ее ис- поведание. Мучители -привязали ее к железному колесу, под которым раз- вели огонь. Тело мученицы, поворачиваясь на колесе, обжигалось со всех сторон. Затем ее бросили в темницу. Ангел Божий явился ночью, исцелил ее от ран и подкрепил пи- щей. Отец, увидев ее наутро невредимой, приказал утопить в море. Но Ангел поддержал святую, камень погрузился,, а Христина чу- десно вышла из воды и явилась к своему отцу. В ужасе мучитель отнес это к действию волшебства и решил наутро казнить ее. Ночью же сам неожиданно умер. Присланный на его место другой правитель, Дион, призвал святую мученицу и также пытался склонить к отречению от Христа, по, видя ее непреклонную твер- дость, вновь предал жестоким мучениям. Святая мученица Хри- стина долго была в темнице. К ней стали проникать люди, и она обращала их к истинной вере во Христа. Так обратилось около 3000 человек. На место Диона прибыл новый правитель Юлиан и приступил к истязаниям святой. После различных мучений Юлиан велел бро- сить ее в раскаленную печь и затворить в ней. Через пять дней печь открыли и нашли мученицу живой и невредимой. Видя проис- ходящие чудеса, многие уверовали во Христа Спасителя, а мучи- тели святую Христину зарубили мечом. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
А҆́гница твоѧ̀, ї҆и҃се, є҆ѵфи́мїа, зове́тъ ве́лїимъ гла́сомъ: тебѐ женишѐ мо́й люблю̀, и҆ тебѐ и҆́щꙋщи страда́льчествꙋю, и҆ сраспина́юсѧ, и҆ спогреба́юсѧ кр҃ще́нїю твоемꙋ̀, и҆ страждꙋ̀ тебѐ ра́ди, ꙗ҆́кѡ да ца́рствꙋю въ тебѣ̀, и҆ ѹ҆мира́ю за тѧ̀, да и҆ живꙋ̀ съ тобо́ю: но ꙗ҆́кѡ же́ртвꙋ непоро́чнꙋю прїими́ мѧ, съ любо́вїю поже́ршꙋюсѧ тебѣ̀. тоѧ̀ мл҃твами, ꙗ҆́кѡ ми́лостивъ сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Свѣтови́днаѧ голꙋби́ца позна́лсѧ є҆сѝ, крилѣ̀ и҆мꙋ́щи зла҄тѣ и҆ къ высотѣ̀ нбⷭнѣй возлетѣ́ла є҆сѝ хрїстї́но чⷭтна́ѧ: тѣ́мже тво́й сла́вный пра́здникъ соверша́емъ, вѣ́рою покланѧ́ющесѧ твои́хъ моще́й ра́цѣ, и҆з꙽ неѧ́же и҆стека́етъ всѣ҄мъ ѻ҆би́льнѡ и҆сцѣле́нїе бж҃е́ственное, дꙋша́мъ же и҆ тѣ́лѡмъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Martyress Christina"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Martyress Christina lived during the III Century. She was born into a rich family, and her father was governor of Tyre. By the age of 11 the girl was exceptionally beautiful, and many wanted to be married to her. Christina&apos;s father, however, envisioned that his daughter should become a pagan-priestess. To this end he situated her in a special dwelling, where he had set up many gold and silver idols, and he commanded his daughter to burn incense before them. Two servants attended to Christina. 	In her solitude Christina began to ponder over the thought, -- who had created this beautiful world? From her room she was delighted by the stars of the heavens and she constantly came back to the thought about the One Maker of all the world. She was convinced, that the voiceless and soul-less idols standing in her room could not create anything, since they themselves were created by human hands. She began to pray to the One God with tears, beseeching Him to reveal Himself. Her soul blazed with love for the Unknown God, and she intensified her prayer all the more, and combining with it fasting. 	One time Christina had the visitation of an Angel, which instructed her in the true faith in Christ, the Saviour of the world. The Angel called her a bride of Christ and announced to her about her future act of suffering. The holy virgin smashed all the idols standing in her room and cast them out the window. In visiting his daughter Christina&apos;s father, Urban, asked her where all the idols had disappeared. Christina was silent. Then, having summoned the servants, Urban learned the truth from them. In a rage the father began to slap his daughter on the face. The holy virgin at first remained quiet, but then she revealed to her father about her faith in the One True God, and that by her own hands she had destroyed the idols. Urban then gave orders to kill all the servants in attendance upon his daughter, and he gave Christina a fierce beating and threw her in prison. Having learned about what had happened, the mother of Saint Christina came in tears, imploring her to renounce Christ and to return to her ancestral beliefs. But Christina remained unyielding. On another day Urban brought his daughter to trial and urged her to offer worship to the gods, to ask forgiveness for her misdeeds, but he saw instead her firm and steadfast confession of faith in Christ. 	The torturers tied her to an iron wheel, beneathe which they set a fire. The body of the martyress, turning round on the wheel, was scorched from all sides. They then threw her in prison.  	An Angel of God appeared at night, healing her from her wounds and strengthening her with food. Her father, in the morning seeing her unharmed, gave orders to drown her in the sea. But an Angel sustained the saint while the stone sank down, and Christina miraculously came out from the water and re-appeared before her father. In terror, the torturer imputed this to the doings of sorcery and he decided to execute her in the morning. But by night he himself suddenly died. Another governor, Dion, was sent in his place. He summoned the holy martyress and likewise tried to persuade her to renounce Christ, but seeing her unyielding firmness, he again subjected her to cruel tortures. The holy martyress was for a long while in prison. People began to throng to her, and she converted them to the true faith in Christ. Thus about 300 were converted. 	In place of Dion, a new governor Julian arrived and anew set about the torture of the saint. After various tortures, Julian gave orders to throw her into a red-hot furnace and lock her in it. After five days they opened the furnace and found the martyress alive and unharmed. Seeing this miracle take place, many believed in Christ the Saviour, and the torturers executed Saint Christina with a sword.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Thy ewe-lamb Christina crieth out to Thee with a loud voice, O Jesus:/ "I love Thee, O my Bridegroom,/ and, seeking Thee, I pass through many struggles:/ I am crucified and buried with Thee in Thy baptism,/ and suffer for Thy sake, that I may reign with Thee;/ I die for Thee that I might live with Thee./ As an unblemished sacrifice accept me,/ who sacrifice myself with love for Thee// By her supplications save Thou our souls, in that Thou art merciful.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Thou wast known to be a radiant dove with wings of gold,/ and didst soar aloft to the heights of heaven, O honored Christina./ Wherefore, we celebrate thy glorious festival,/ bowing down before the shrine of thy relics with faith,// from whence divine healing for souls and bodies poureth forth upon all in abundance.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>