<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой равноапостольный великий князь Владимир"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Немногие имена на скрижалях истории могут сравниться по значению с именем святого равноапостольного Владимира, кре- стителя Руси, на века вперед предопределившего духовные судь- бы Русской Церкви и русского православного народа. Владимир был внук святой равноапостольной Ольги, сын Святослава ( { 972). Мать его, Малуша ( } 1001) — дочь Малка Любечанина, • • • • которого историки отождествляют с Малом, князем Древлянским. Приводя к покорности восставших древлян и овладев их города- ми, княгиня Ольга повелела казнить князя Мала, за которого пытались ее сватать после убийства Игоря, а детей его, Добрыню и Малушу, взяла с собой. Добрыня вырос храбрым умелым вои- ном, обладал государственным умом, был впоследствии хорошим помощником своему племяннику Владимиру в делах военного и государственного управления. «Вещая дева» Малуша стала христианкой (вместе с великой княгиней Ольгой в Царьграде), но сохранила в себе таинственный сумрак языческих древлянских лесов. Тем и полюбилась она суро- вому воину Святославу, который, против воли матери, сделал ее своей женой. Разгневанная Ольга, считая невозможным брак своей «ключницы», пленницы, рабыни с сыном Святославом, наследни- ком великого Киевского княжения, отправила Малушу на свою родину в весь неподалеку от Выбут. Там и родился, около 960 го- да, мальчик, названный русским языческим именем Володимир — владеющий миром, владеющий особым даром мира. В 970 году Святослав, отправляясь в поход, из которого ему не суждено уже было вернуться, поделил Русскую Землю меж тремя сыновьями. В Киеве княжил Ярополк, в Овруче, центре Древлянской земли, Олег, в Новгороде — Владимир. Первые годы княжения мы видим Владимира яростным язычником. Он возглав- ляет поход, в котором ему сочувствует вся языческая Русь, про- тив Ярополка-христианина, или, во всяком случае, по свидетель- ству летописи, «давшего &apos;великую волю христианам», и вступает 11 июня 978 года в Киев, став «единодержцем» Киевского госу- дарства, «покорив окрестные страны, одни — миром, а непокор- ных — мечем». Молодой Владимир предавался бурной чувственной жизни, хотя далеко не был таким сластолюбцем, каким его иногда изоб- ражают. Он «пас свою землю правдою, мужеством и разумом», как добрый и рачительный хозяин, при необходимости расширял и оборонял ее пределы силой оружия, а возвращаясь из похода, устраивал для дружины и для всего Киева щедрые и веселые пиры. Но Господь готовил ему иное поприще. Где умножается грех, там, — по слову Апостола, — преизобилует благодать. «И прииде на него посещение Вышнего, призре на него Всемилостиве око Благого Бога, и воссияла мысль в сердце его, да разумеет суету идольского прельщения, да взыщет Единого Бога, сотворившего все видимое и невидимое». Дело принятия Крещения облегчалось для него внешними обстоятельствами. Византийскую империю сотрясали удары мятежных полководцев Варды Склира и Варды Фоки, каждый из которых уже примеривал царскую корону. В трудных условиях императоры, братья-соправители Василий Болгаробойца и Константин, обратились за помощью к Вла- димиру. События развивались быстро. В августе 987 года Варда Фока провозгласил себя императором и двинулся на Константинополь, осенью того же года послы императора Василия были в Киеве. «И истощились богатства его (Василия), и побудила его нужда вступить в переписку с царем Руссов. Они были его врагами, но он просил у них помощи, — пишет о событиях 980-х годов один из арабских хронистов. — И царь Руссов согласился на это, и просил свойства с ним». В награду за военную помощь Владимир просил руки сестры императоров Анны, что было для византийцев неслыханной дер- зостью. Принцессы крови никогда не выходили замуж за «варвар- ских» государей, даже христиан. В свое время руки той же Анны домогался для своего сына император Оттон Великий, и ему было отказано, но сейчас Константинополь вынужден был согласиться. Был заключен договор, согласно которому Владимир должен был послать в помощь императорам шесть тысяч варягов, принять святое Крещение и при этом условии получить руку царевны Анны. Так в борьбе человеческих устремлений воля Божия опре- делила вхождение Руси в благодатное лоно Церкви Вселенской. Великий князь Владимир принимает Крещение и направляет в Византию военную подмогу. С помощью русских мятеж был раз- громлен, а Варда Фока убит. Но греки, обрадованные неожидан- ным избавлением, не торопятся выполнить свою часть уговора. Возмущенный греческим лукавством, князь Владимир «вборзе собра вся своя» и двинул «на Корсунь, _ град греческий», древний Херсонес. Пал «неприступный» оплот византийского господства на Черном море, один из жизненно важных узлов экономических и торговых связей империи. Удар был настолько чувствителен, что эхо его отозвалось по всем Византийским пределам. Решающий довод снова был за Владимиром. Его послы, воево- да Олег и Ждьберн, прибыли вскоре в Царьград за царевной. Восемь дней ушло на сборы Анны, которую братья утешали, под- черкивая значительность предстоящего ей подвига: способствовать просвещению Русского государства и земли их, сделать их навсег- да друзьями Ромейской державы. В Тавриде ее ждет святой Владимир, к титулам которого прибавился новый, еще более бле- стящий— цесарь (царь, император). Надменным владыкам Кон- стантинополя пришлось уступить и в этом — поделиться с зятем цесарскими (императорскими) инсигниями. В некоторых греческих источниках святой Владимир именуется с того времени «могущест- венным басилевсом», он чеканит монеты по византийским образ- цам и изображается на них со знаками императорской власти: в царской одежде, на голове — императорская корона, в правой руке — скипетр с крестом. С царевной прибыл посвященный святым Патриархом Нико- лаем II Хризовергом на Русскую кафедру митрополит Михаил со свитой, клиром, многими святыми мощами и другими святынями. В древнем Херсонесе, где каждый камень помнил святого Андрея Первозванного, свершилось венчание святого равноапостоль- ного Владимира и блаженной Анны, напомнив и подтвердив исконное единство благовестия Христова на Руси и в Византии. Корсунь, «вено царицы», был возвращен Византии. Великий князь весной 988 года отправляется с супругой через Крым, Тамань, Азовские земли, входившие в состав его обширных владений, в обратный путь к Киеву. Впереди великокняжеского поезда с ча- стыми молебнами и несмолкающими священными песнопениями несли кресты, иконы, святые мощи. Казалось, сама Святая Все- ленская Церковь двинулась в просторы Русской земли, и обнов- ленная в купели Крещения Святая Русь открывалась навстречу Христу и Его Церкви. Наступило незабываемое и единственное в русской истории утро Крещения киевлян в водах Днепра. Накануне святой Влади- мир объявил по городу: «Если кто не придет завтра на реку — богатый или бедный, нищий или раб — будет мне враг». Священ- ное желание святого князя было исполнено беспрекословно: «в одно время вся земля наша восславила Христа со Отцем и Свя- тым Духом». Трудно переоценить глубину духовного переворота, совершив- шегося молитвами святого равноапостольного Владимира в рус- ском пароде, во всей его жизни, во всем мировоззрении. В чистых киевских водах, как в «бане пакибытия», осуществилось таинст- венное преображение русской духовной стихии, духовное рожде- ние народа, призванного Богом к невиданным еще в истории под- вигам христианского служения человечеству. — «Тогда начал мрак идольский от нас отходить, и заря Православия явилась, и Солнце Евангельское землю нашу осияло». В память священного события, обновления Руси водою и Духом, установился в Русской Церкви обычай ежегодного крестного хода «на воду» 1 августа, соединив- шийся впоследствии с празднеством Происхождения Честных Древ Животворящего Креста Господня, общим с Греческой Церковью, и русским церковным празднеством Всемилостивому Спасу и Пре- святой Богородице (установленным святым Андреем Боголюбским в 1164 году). В этом соединении праздников нашло точное выра- жение русское Богословское сознание, для которого неразрывны Крещение и Крест. Всюду по Святой Руси, от древних городов до дальних пого- стов, повелел святой Владимир ниспровергнуть языческие треби- ща, иссечь истуканов, а на месте их рубить по холмам церкви, освящать престолы для Бескровной Жертвы. Храмы Божий выра- стали по лицу земли, на возвышенных местах, у излучин рек, на старинном пути «из варяг в греки» — словно путеводные знаки, светочи народной святости. Прославляя храмоздательные труды равноапостольного Владимира, автор «Слова о законе и благода- ти», святитель Иларион, митрополит Киевский, восклицал: «Капи- ща разрушаются, и церкви поставляются, идолы сокрушаются и иконы святых являются, бесы убегают, Крест грады освящает». С первых веков христианства ведет начало обычай воздвигать храмы на развалинах языческих святилищ или на крови святых мучеников. Следуя этому правилу, святой Владимир построил храм святого Василия Великого на холме, где находился жертвен- ник Перуна, и заложил каменный храм Успения Пресвятой Бого- родицы (Десятинный) на месте мученической кончины святых варягов-мучеников (память 12 июля). Великолепный храм, при- званный стать местом служения митрополита Киевского и всея Руси, первопрестольным храмом Русской Церкви, строился пять лет, был богато украшен настенной фресковой живописью, креста- ми, иконами и священными сосудами, привезенными из Корсуня. День освящения храма Пресвятой Богородицы, 12 мая (в некото- рых рукописях—11 мая), святой Владимир повелел внести в месяцесловы для ежегодного празднования. Событие было соот- несено с существовавшим уже праздником 11 мая, связывавшим новый храм двойной преемственностью. Под этим числом отме- чается в святцах церковное «обновление Царьграда» — посвяще- ние святым императором Константином новой столицы Римской империи, Константинополя, Пресвятой Богородице (в 330 году). В тот же день при святой равноапостольной Ольге освящен в Киеве храм Софии — Премудрости Божией (в 960 году). Святой равноапостольный Владимир, освятив кафедральный собор Пре- святой Богородицы, посвящал тем самым, вслед за равноапостоль- ным Константином, стольный град Земли Русской, Киев, Влады- чице Небесной. Тогда же святым Владимиром была пожалована Церкви деся- тина, почему и храм, ставший центром общерусского сбора церков- ной десятины, нарекли Десятинным. Древнейший текст уставной грамоты, или церковного Устава, святого князя Владимира гла- сил: «Се даю церкви сей Святыя Богородицы десятину из всего своего княжения, и тако же и по всей земле Русской от всего княжья суда десятую векшу, из торгу — десятую неделю, а из до- мов на всяко лето — десятое всякого стада и всякого жита, чудной Матери Божией и чудному Спасу». Устав перечислял также «цер- ковных людей», освобождавшихся от судебной власти князя и его тиунов, подлежавших суду митрополита. Летопись сохранила молитву святого Владимира, с которой он обратился к Вседержителю при освящении Успенского Десятин- ного храма: «Господи Боже, призри с Небесе и виждь, и посети винограда Своего, яже насади десница Твоя. И сверши новые люди сии, им же обратил еси сердце и разум — познати Тебя, Бога Истинного. И призри на церковь Твою сию, юже создал недостойный раб Твой во имя Рождшей Тя Матери, Приснодевы Богородицы. Аще кто помолится в церкви сей, то услыши молитву его, молитв ради Пречистой Богородицы». С Десятинной церковью и епископом Анастасом некоторые историки связывали начало русского летописания. При ней были составлены Житие святой Ольги и сказание о варягах-мучениках в их первоначальном виде, а также «Слово о том, како крестися Владимир возмя Корсунь». Там же возникла ранняя, греческая редакция Жития святых мучеников Бориса и Глеба. Киевскую митрополичью кафедру при святом Владимире зани- мали последовательно митрополиты святой Михаил ( | 15 июня 991), митрополит Феофилакт, переведенный в Киев с кафедры Севастии Армянской (991—997), митрополит Леонтий (997— 1008), митрополит Иоанн I (1008—1037). Их трудами были откры- ты первые епархии Русской Церкви: Новгородская (первым ее предстоятелем был святитель Иоаким Корсунянин (+ 1030, соста- витель Иоакимовской летописи), Владимиро-Волынская (откры- та 11 мая 992 года), Черниговская, Переяславская, Белгородская, Ростовская. «Сице же и по всем грады и по селам воздвизахуся церкви и монастыри, и умножахуся священницы, и вера право- славная цветяше и сияше яко солнце». Для утверждения веры в новопросвещенном народе нужны были ученые люди и школы для их подготовки. Поэтому святой Владимир со святым митрополи- том Михаилом «начата от отцов и матерей взимати младые дети и давати в училище учитися грамоте». Такое же училище устроил святитель Иоаким Корсунянин (\ 1030) в Новгороде, были они и в других городах. «И бысть множество училищ книжных, и бысть от сих множество любомудрых философев». Святой Владимир твердой рукой сдерживал на рубежах вра- гов, строил города, крепости. Им построена первая в русской ис- тории «засечная черта» — линия оборонительных пунктов про- тив кочевников. «Нача ставити Володимер грады по Десне, по Выстри, по Трубежу, по Суде, по Стугне. И населил их новго- родцами, смольнянами, чудью и вятичами. И воевал с печенега- ми и одолевал их». Действенным оружием часто была мирная христианская проповедь среди степных язычников. В Никонов- ской летописи под 990 годом записано: «Того же лета приидоша из болгар к Володимеру в Киев четыре князя и просветишася Божественным Крещением». В следующем году «прииде печенег- ский князь Кучуг и прият греческую веру, и крестися во Отца и Сына и Святого Духа, и служаше Владимиру чистым сердцем». Под влиянием святого князя крестились и некоторые видные ино- земцы, например, живший несколько лет в Киеве норвежский ко- нунг (король) Олаф Трюггвасон ( | 1000), знаменитый Торвальд Путешественник, основатель монастыря святого Иоанна Предтечи на Днепре под Полоцком, и другие. В далекой Исландии поэты- скальды назвали Бога «хранителем греков и русских». Средством христианской проповеди были и знаменитые пиры святого Владимира: по воскресеньям и большим церковным празд- никам после литургии выставлялись для киевлян обильные празд- ничные столы, звонили колокола, славословили хоры, «калики перехожие» пели былины и духовные стихи. Например, 12 мая 996 года по поводу освящения Десятинной церкви князь «сотвори пирование светло», «раздавая имения много убогим, и нищим, и странникам, и по церквам и по монастырям. Больным же и нищим доставлял по улицам великие кады и бочки меду, и хлеб, и мясо, и рыбу, и сыр, желая, чтобы все приходили и ели, славя Бога». Пиры устраивались также в честь побед киевских богатырей, пол- ководцев Владимировых дружин — Добрыни, Александра Попо- вича, Рогдая Удалого. В 1007 году святой Владимир перенес в Десятинную церковь мощи святой равноапостольной Ольги. А четыре года спустя, в 1011 году, там же была погребена его супруга, сподвижница мно- гих его начинаний, блаженная царица Анна. После ее кончины князь вступил в новый брак — с младшей дочерью немецкого гра- фа Куно фон Эннингена, внучкой императора Оттона Великого. Эпоха святого Владимира была ключевым периодом для госу- дарственного становления православной Руси. Объединение сла- вянских земель и оформление государственных границ державы Рюриковичей происходили в напряженной духовной и политиче- ской борьбе с соседними племенами и государствами. Крещение Руси от православной Византии было важнейшим шагом ее государственного самоопределения. Главным врагом святого Вла- димира стал Болеслав Храбрый, в планы которого входило широ- кое объединение западнославянских и восточнославянских племен под эгидой католической Польши. Это соперничество восходит еще ко времени, когда Владимир был язычник: «В лето 6489 (981). Иде Володимер на ляхи и взя грады их, Перемышль, Червень и иные грады, иже есть под Русью». Последние годы X сто- летия также наполнены войнами святого Владимира и Боле- слава. После кратковременного затишья (первое десятилетие XI века) «великое противостояние» вступает в новую фазу: в 1013 году в Киеве был раскрыт заговор против святого Владимира: Святополк Окаянный, женившийся на дочери Болеслава, рвался к власти. Вдохновителем заговора был духовник Болеславны, католический епископ Колобжегский Рейберн. Заговор Святополка и Рейберна был прямым покушением на историческое существование Русского государства и Русской Церкви. Святой Владимир принял решительные меры. Все трое были арестованы, и Рейберн вскоре скончался в заточении. Святой &apos;Владимир не мстил «гонящим и ненавидевшим» его. Принесший притворное покаяние Святополк был оставлен па сво- боде. Новая беда назревала на Севере, в Новгороде. Ярослав, еще не столь «мудрый», каким он вошел позже в русскую историю, ставший в 1010 году держателем Новгородских земель, задумал отложиться от своего отца, великого князя Киевского, завел от- дельное войско, перестал платить в Киев обычную дань и деся- тину. Единству Русской земли, за которое всю жизнь боролся святой Владимир, угрожала опасность. В гневе и скорби князь повелел «мосты мостить, гати гатить», готовиться к походу на Нов- город. Силы его были на исходе. В приготовлениях к последнему своему, к счастью несостоявшемуся, походу креститель Руси тяже- ло заболел и предал дух Господу в селе Спас-Берестове 15 июля 1015 года. Он правил Русским государством тридцать семь лет (978—1015). из них двадцать восемь лет прожил во святом Кре- щении. Готовясь к новой борьбе за власть и надеясь в ней на помощь поляков, Святополк, чтобы выиграть время, пытался скрыть смерть отца. Но патриотически настроенные киевские бояре тайно, ночью, вывезли тело почившего государя из Берестовского дворца, где сторожили его люди Святополка, и привезли в Киев. В Деся- тинной церкви гроб с мощами святого Владимира встретило киев- ское духовенство во главе с митрополитом Иоанном. Святые мощи были положены в мраморной раке, поставленной в Климентовском приделе Десятинного Успенского храма рядом с такой же мрамор- ной ракой царицы Анны... Имя и дело святого равноапостольного Владимира, которого народ назвал Красным Солнышком, связано со всей последующей историей Русской Церкви. «Им мы обожились и Христа, Истинную Жизнь, познали», — засвидетельствовал святитель Иларион. Под- виг его продолжили его сыновья, внуки, правнуки, владевшие Рус- ской землей в течение почти шести столетий: от Ярослава Мудро- го, сделавшего первый шаг к независимому существованию Рус- ской Церкви — до последнего Рюриковича, царя Феодора Иоанно- вича, при котором (в 1589 году) Русская Православная Церковь стала пятым самостоятельным Патриархатом в диптихе Право- славных Автокефальных Церквей. Празднование святому равноапостольному Владимиру было установлено святым Александром Невским после того, как 15 мая 1240 года, помощью и заступлением святого Владимира, была им одержана знаменитая Невская победа над шведскими крестонос- цами. Но церковное почитание святого князя началось на Руси значительно ранее. Митрополит Иларион, святитель Киевский ( } 1053), в «Слове о законе и благодати», сказанном в день памяти святого Владимира у раки его в Десятинном храме, называет его «во владыках апостолом», «подобником» святого Константина, и сравнивает его апостольское благовестие Русской Земле с бла- говестием святых апостолов. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Ѹ҆подо́билсѧ є҆сѝ кꙋпцꙋ̀ и҆́щꙋщемꙋ до́брагѡ би́сера, славнодержа́вный влади́мїре, на высотѣ̀ стола̀ сѣдѧ̀ ма́тере градѡ́въ, бг҃оспаса́емагѡ кї́ева: и҆спытꙋ́ѧ же и҆ посыла́ѧ къ ца́рскомꙋ гра́дꙋ, ѹ҆вѣ́дѣти правосла́внꙋю вѣ́рꙋ, ѡ҆брѣ́лъ є҆сѝ безцѣ́нный би́серъ хрⷭта̀, и҆збра́вшаго тѧ̀ ꙗ҆́кѡ втора́го па́ѵла, и҆ ѿтрѧ́сшаго слѣпотꙋ̀ во ст҃ѣ́й кꙋпѣ́ли дꙋше́внꙋю вкꙋ́пѣ и҆ тѣле́снꙋю. тѣ́мже пра́зднꙋемъ твоѐ ѹ҆спе́нїе лю́дїе твоѝ сꙋ́ще: молѝ сп҃сти́сѧ держа́вы твоеѧ̀ рѡссї́йскїѧ нача́льникѡмъ, хрⷭтолюби́вомꙋ ї҆мпера́торꙋ, и҆ мно́жествꙋ владо́мыхъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Подо́бствовавъ вели́комꙋ а҆пⷭлꙋ па́ѵлꙋ, въ сѣди́нахъ всесла́вне влади́мїре, всѧ҄ ꙗ҆́кѡ младе́нчєскаѧ мꙋдрова҄нїѧ, ꙗ҆̀же ѡ҆ ї҆́дѡлѣхъ тща́нїѧ ѡ҆ста́вль, ꙗ҆́кѡ мꙋ́жъ соверше́нный ѹ҆краси́лсѧ є҆сѝ бж҃е́ственнагѡ креще́нїѧ багрѧни́цею. и҆ ны́нѣ сп҃сꙋ хрⷭтꙋ̀ въ весе́лїи предстоѧ̀, молѝ сп҃сти́сѧ держа́вы рѡссї́йскїѧ нача́льникѡмъ, и҆ мно́жествꙋ владо́мыхъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Great Prince Vladimir"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Few names in the annals of history can compare in significance with the name of holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Vladimir, the Baptiser of Rus&apos;, who stands forever at the onset of the foreordained spiritual destiny of the Russian Church and the Russian Orthodox people. Vladimir was the grandson of holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Olga, and he was the son of Svyatoslav (+ 972). His mother, Malusha (+ 1001) -- was the daughter of Malk Liubechanin, whom historians identify with Mal, prince of the Drevlyani. Having subdued an uprising of the Drevlyani and conquered their cities, Princess Olga gave orders to execute prince Mal, for his attempt to marry her after his murder of her husband Igor, and she took to herself the children of Mal, Dobrynya and Malusha. Dobrynya grew up to be a valiant brave warrior, endowed with a mind for state affairs, and he was later on an excellent help to his nephew Vladimir in matters of military and state administration. 	The &quot;capable girl&quot; Malusha became a Christian (together with GreatPrincess Olga at Tsar&apos;grad), but she preserved in herself a bit of the mysterious darkness of the pagan Drevlyani forests. And thus she fell in love with the austere warrior Svyatoslav, who against the will of his mother Olga made her his wife. The enraged Olga, reckoning as unseemly the marriage of her &quot;housekeeper&quot; and captive servant with her son Svyatoslav, heir to the Great Kiev principality, sent Malusha away to her own native region not far off from Vybut&apos;. And there in about the year 960 was born the boy, called with the Russian pagan name -- Volodimir, meaning peaceful ruler, ruling with a special talent for peace. 	In the year 970 Svyatoslav set out on a campaign from which he was fated not to return. He had divided the Russian Land amongst his three sons. At Kiev Yaropolk was prince; at Ovrucha, the centre of the Drevlyani lands, there was Oleg; at Novgorod there was Vladimir. His first years as prince we see Vladimir as a fierce pagan. He heads a campaign, in which the whole of pagan Rus&apos; is sympathetic to him, against Yaropolk the Christian, or in any case, according to the chronicles, &quot;having given great freedom to the Christians&quot;, on 11 July 978 he enters into Kiev, having become the &quot;sole ruler&quot; of the Kiev realm, &quot;having subdued the surrounding lands, some -- by peaceful means, and the unsubmissive ones -- by the sword&quot;. 	Young Vladimir indulged himself in a wild sensuous life, though far from being the libertine that they sometimes portray him. He &quot;shepherded his land with truth, valour and reason&quot;, as a good and diligent master, of necessity he extended and defended its boundaries by force of arms, and in returning from military campaign, he made for his companions and for all Kiev liberal and merry feastings. 	But the Lord prepared him for another task. Where sin increases, there -- in the words of the Apostle, -- grace abounds. &quot;And upon him did come visitation of the MostHigh, and the All-Merciful eye of the Good God didst gaze upon him, and shine forth the thought in his heart, of understanding the vanity of idolous delusion, and of appealing to the One God, Creator of all things both visible and invisible&quot;. The matter of the acceptance of Baptism was facilitated through external circumstances. The Byzantine empire was in upheaval under the blows of the mutinous regiments of Bardas Skliros and Bardas Phokas, each of which sought to gain the imperial throne. In these difficult circumstances the emperors -- the co-regent brothers Basil the Bulgar-Slayer and Constantine, turned for help to Vladimir. 	Events unfolded quickly. In August 987 Bardas Phokas proclaimed himself emperor and moved against Constantinople, and in Autumn of that same year the emissaries of emperor Basil were at Kiev. &quot;And having exhausted his (Basil&apos;s) wealth, it compelled him to enter into an alliance with the emperor of the Russes. They were his enemies, but he besought their help, -- writes one of the Arab chronicles of events in the 980&apos;s. -- And the emperor of the Russes did consent to this, and did make common cause with him&quot;. 	In reward for his military help, Vladimir besought the hand of the emperors&apos; sister Anna, which for the Byzantines was an unheard of audacity. Princesses of the imperial lineage did not go off to marry &quot;barbarian&quot; rulers, even though they be Christian. At this same time the emperor Otto the Great was seeking the hand of this Anna for his son, and he was refused, but herein regarding Vladimir Constantinople was obliged to consent. 	An agreement was concluded, according to which Vladimir had to send in aid to the emperors six thousand Varangians, to accept holy Baptism, and under these conditions he would receive the hand of the imperial daughter Anna. Thus in the strife of human events the will of God directed the entering of Rus&apos; into the graced bosom of the OEcumenical Church. GreatPrince Vladimir accepted Baptism and dispatched the military assistance to Byzantium. With the aid of the Russians, the mutineers were destroyed and Bardas Phokas killed. But the Greeks, gladdened by their unexpected deliverance, were in no hurry to fulfill their part of the agreement. 	Vexed at the Greek duplicity, Prince Vladimir &quot;hastened to collect his forces&quot; and he moved &quot;against Korsun, the Greek city&quot;, the ancient Chersonessus. The &quot;impenetrable&quot; rampart of the Byzantine realm on the Black Sea fell, and it was one of the vitally important hubs of the economic and mercantile links of the empire. This blow was so much felt, that its echo resounded throughout all the regions of Byzantium. 	Vladimir again had the upper hand. His emissaries, the voevoda-commanders Oleg and Sjbern soon arrived in Tsar&apos;grad for the imperial daughter. Eight days passed in Anna&apos;s preparation, during which time her brothers consoled her, stressing the significance of the opportunity before her: to enable the enlightening of the Russian realm and its lands, and to make them forever friends of the Romanoi-Byzantine realm. At Taurida Saint Vladimir awaited her, and to his titles there was added a new one -- Caesar (tsar&apos;, emperor). It required the haughty rulers of Constantinople to accede also in this -- to bestow upon their new brother-in-law the Caesar (i.e. imperial) insignia. In certain of the Greek historians, Saint Vladimir is termed from these times as a &quot;mighty basileios-king&quot;, he coins money in the Byzantine style and is depicted on it with the symbols of imperial might: in imperial attire, and on his head -- the imperial crown, and in his right hand -- the sceptre with cross. 	Together with the empress Anna, there arrived for the Russian cathedra-seat metropolitan Michael -- ordained by holy Patriarch Nicholas II Chrysobergos, and he came with his retinue and clergy, and many holy relics and other holy things. In ancient Chersonessus, where each stone brings to mind Saint Andrew the First-Called, there took place the marriage-crowning of Saint Vladimir and Blessed Anna, both reminiscent and likewise affirming the oneness of the Gospel good-news of Christ in Rus&apos; and in Byzantium. Korsun, the &quot;empress dowry&quot;, was returned to Byzantium. In the Spring of 988 the greatprince with his spouse set out through the Crimea, Taman&apos; and the Azov lands, which had come into the complexion of his vast realm, on the trip of return to Kiev. Leading the greatprincely cortege with frequent moliebens and incessant priestly singing they carried crosses, icons and holy relics. It seemed, that the OEcumenical Holy Church was moving into the spacious Russian land, and renewed in the font of Baptism, Holy Rus&apos; came forth to meet Christ and His Church. 	There ensued the unforgettable and quite singular event in Russian history: the morning of the Baptism of the Kievans in the waters of the River Dneipr. On the evening beforehand, Saint Vladimir declared throughout the city: &quot;If anyone on the morrow goeth not into the river -- be they rich or poor, beggar or slave -- that one be mine enemy&quot;. The sacred wish of the holy prince was fulfilled without a murmur: &quot;all our land all at the same time did glorify Christ with the Father and the Holy Spirit&quot;. 	It is difficult to overestimate the deep spiritual transformation -- effected by the prayers of Saint Vladimir, effected within the Russian people, in all the entirety of its life and world-outlook. In the pure Kievan waters, as in a &quot;bath of regeneration&quot;, there was realised a mysteried transfiguration of the Russian spiritual element, the spiritual birth of the nation, called by God to yet unforeseen deeds of Christian service to mankind. -- &quot;Then did the darkness of the idols begin to lift from us, and the dawn of Orthodoxy appear, and the Sun of the Gospel didst illumine our land&quot;. In memory of this sacred event, the renewal of Rus&apos; by water and the Spirit, there was established within the Russian Church the custom of an annual church procession &quot;to the water&quot; on 1 August, combined afterwards with the feastday of the Bring-Forth of the Venerable Wood of the Life-Creating Cross of the Lord, in common with the Greek Church, and likewise the Russian Church feastday of the All-Merciful Saviour and the MostHoly Mother of God (established by Saint Andrei Bogoliubsky in the year 1164). In this combination of feasts there is found a precise expression of the Russian theological consciousness, for which both Baptism and the Cross are inseparable. 	Everywhere throughout Holy Rus&apos;, from the ancient cities to the far outposts, Saint Vladimir gave orders to tumble down the pagan sanctuaries, to flog the idols, and in their place to chop along the hilly woods for churches, in which to consecrate altars for the Bloodless Sacrifice. Churches of God grew up along the face of the earth, at high elevated places, and at the bends of the rivers, along the ancient trail &quot;from the Variangians to the Greeks&quot; -- figuratively as road signs, and lamps of national holiness. As regards the famed church-building activity of holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Vladimir, the Kiev Metropolitan Saint Ilarion (author of the &quot;Word about the Law and Grace&quot;) exclaimed: &quot;They demolished the pagan temples, and built up churches, they destroyed the idols and produced holy icons, the demons are fled, and the Cross hath sanctified the cities&quot;. From the early centuries of Christianity it was the custom to raise up churches upon the ruins of pagan sanctuaries or upon the blood of the holy martyrs. Following this practise, Saint Vladimir built the church of Saint Basil the Great upon an hill, where a sanctuary of Perun had been located, and he situated the stone church of the Uspenie-Dormition of the MostHoly Mother of God (Desyatinnaya) on the place of the martyrdom of the holy Varangian-Martyrs (Comm. 12 July). The magnificent temple intended to become the place of serving for the Metropolitan of Kiev and All Rus&apos; -- and hence the primal-altar of the Russian Church, was built in five years: it was richly adorned with wall-fresco painting, crosses, icons and sacred vessels, brought from Korsun. The day of the consecration of the church of the MostHoly Mother of God, 12 May (in some manuscripts 11 May), was ordered by Saint Vladimir to be inserted as an annual celebration in the Church-kalendar lists. This event was tied in with other previous happenings for the celebration of 11 May, and it provided the new Church a twofold sense of succession. Under this day in the Saints is noted the churchly &quot;renewal of Tsar&apos;grad&quot; -- dedicated by the holy emperor Saint Constantine as the new capital of the Roman Empire, the Constantine-city Constantinople, dedicated to the MostHoly Mother of God (330). And on this same day of 11 May, under holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Olga, there had been consecrated at Kiev the church of Sophia -- the Wisdom of God (in the year 960). Saint Vladimir, having had the cathedral church consecrated to the MostHoly Mother of God, followed the example of Saint Constantine in dedicating the capital city of the Russian Land, Kiev, to the Queen of Heaven. 	And then there was bestown on the Church a tithe or tenth; and since this church had become the centre of the All-Russian gathering of churchly tithes, they called it the Desyatinnaya (Tithe) church. The most ancient text of the deed-grant document, or churchly ustav-rule by holy Prince Vladimir spoke thusly: &quot;For I do bestow this church of the Holy Mother of God a tenth of all mine principality, and likewise throughout all the Russian Land from all the princely jurisdiction a tithe of squirrel-pelts, and from the merchant -- a tithe of the week, and from households each year -- a tenth of every herd and every livelihood, to the wondrous Mother of God and the wondrous Saviour&quot;. The ustav likewise specified &quot;church people&quot; as being free from the jurisdictional power of the prince and his &quot;tiuni&quot;-officials, and placed them under the jurisdiction of the metropolitan. 	The chronicle has preserved a prayer of Saint Vladimir, with which he turned to the Almighty at the consecration of the Uspensky Desyatin-Tithe church: &quot;O Lord God, look Thou down from Heaven and behold, and visit Thine vineyard, which Thy right-hand hath planted. And make this new people, whom Thou hast converted in heart and mind -- to know Thee, the True God. And look down upon this Thine church, which Thy unworthy servant hath built in the name of the Mother Who hath given birth to Thee, She the Ever-Virgin Mother of God. And whosoever doth pray in this church, let his prayer then be heard, on account of the prayers to the All-Pure Mother of God&quot;.  	With the Desyatin-Tithe church and bishop Anastasii, certain historians have made a connection with the beginnings of Russian chronicle writing. At it were compiled the Vita-Life of Saint Ol&apos;ga and the account of the Varangian-Martyrs  in their original form, and likewise the &quot;Account, How in the Taking of Korsun, Vladimir came to be Baptised&quot;. Here also there originated the early Greek redaction of the Vitae-Lives of the holy Martyrs Boris and Gleb. 	The Kiev Metropolitan cathedra-seat during the time of Saint Vladimir was occupied successively by the Metropolitan Saint Michael (+ 15 June 991, Comm. 30September), Metropolitan Theophylakt -- transferred to Kiev from the see of Armenian Sebasteia (991-997), Metropolitan Leontii (997-1008), and Metropolitan John I (1008-1037). Through their efforts the first dioceses of the Russian Church were opened: at Novgorod (its first representative was Sainted Joakim the Korsunite -- + 1030, compiler of the Joakimov Chronicle), Vladimir-Volyn (opened 11 May 992), Chernigov, Pereslavl&apos;, Belgorod, and Rostov. &quot;And thus throughout all the cities and villages there were set up churches and monasteries, and the clergy did increase, and the Orthodox Faith did blossom forth and shine like the sun&quot;. To advance the faith amongst the newly enlightened people, learned people and schools were needed for their preparation. Saint Vladimir therefore with holy Metropolitan Michael &quot;did command fathers and mothers to take their young children and send them to schools to learn reading and writing&quot;. Saint Joakim the Korsunite (+1030) set up such a school at Novgorod, and they did likewise in other cities. &quot;And there were a multitude of schools of scholars, and of these were there a multitude of wisdom-loving philosophers&quot;. 	With a firm hand Saint Vladimir held in check enemies at the frontiers, and he built cities with fortifications. He was the first in Russian history to set up a &quot;notched boundary&quot; -- a line of defensive points against nomadic peoples. &quot;Volodimir did begin to set up cities along the Desna, along the Vystra, along the Trubezha, along the Sula and along the Stugna. And he did settle them with the Novgorodians, the Smol&apos;yani, the Chuds and the Vyatichi. And he did war against the Pechenegs and defeated them&quot;. But the actual means was often the peaceful Christian preaching amongst the steppe pagans. In the Nikol&apos;sk Chronicles under the year 990 was written: &quot;And in that same year there came to Volodimir at Kiev four princes from the Bulgars and they were illumined with Divine Baptism&quot;. In the following year &quot; there came the Pecheneg prince Kuchug and accepted the Greek faith, and he was baptised in the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, and did service to Vladimir with a pure heart&quot;. Under the influence of the holy prince there were baptised also several apparent foreigners, as for example, the Norwegian &quot;koenig&quot; (king&quot;) Olaf Trueggvason (+ 1000) who lived several years at Kiev, and also the reknown Torval&apos;d the Wanderer -- founder of a monastery of Saint John the Precursor  along the Dneipr near Polotsk, among others. In faraway Iceland the poet-skalds called God the &quot;Protector of the Greeks and Russians&quot;. 	Amidst the Christian preaching was also the reknown feastings of Saint Vladimir: after Liturgy on Sundays and Church Great-Feasts there were put out abundant feasting tables for the Kievans, they rang the bells, choirs sang praise, the &quot;transported infirm&quot; sang bylini-ballads and spiritual verses. On 12 May 996, for example, on the occasion of the consecration of the Desyatin-Tithe church, the prince &quot;made a bright feast&quot;, &quot;distributing goods to many of the poor, and destitute and wanderers, and through the churches and the monasteries. To the sick and the needy he delivered through the streets casks and barrels of mead, and bread, and meat, and fish, and cheese, desiring that all might come and eat, glorifying God&quot;. Feasts were likewise arrayed in honour of the victories of Kievan bogatyr-warriors, and the regiments of Vladimir&apos;s retinue -- of Dobrynya, Aleksandr Popovich, Rogda the Bold. 	In the year 1007 Saint Vladimir transferred the relics of holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Ol&apos;ga to the Desyatin-Tithe church. And four years later, in 1011, there was also buried there his spouse and companion in many of his undertakings, the Blessed Empress Anna. After her death the prince entered into a new marriage -- with the young daughter of the German Graf Kuno von Enningen, grand-daughter of the emperor Otto the Great. 	The era of Saint Vladimir was a crucial initial period for the state formation of Orthodox Rus&apos;. The unification of the Slavic lands and the formation of state boundaries under the domain of the Riurikovichi resulted from a strenuous spiritual and political struggle with neighbouring tribes and states. The Baptism of Rus&apos; by Orthodox Byzantium was a most important step in its state self-definition. The chief enemy of Vladimir became Boleslav the Brave, whose plans included the extensive unification of the West-Slavic and East-Slavic  tribes under the aegis of Catholic Poland. This rivalry arose still back in the times, when Vladimir was still a pagan: &quot;In the year 6489 (981). Volodimir went against the Lakhs and took their cities, Peremyshl&apos;, Cherven&apos;, and other cities, which be under Rus&apos;&quot;. The final years of the X Century are likewise filled with the wars of Vladimir and Boleslav. 	After a short lull (the first decade of the XI Century), the &quot;great stand-off&quot; enters into a new phase: in the year 1013 at Kiev a conspiracy against Saint Vladimir is discovered: Svyatopolk the Accursed, who is married to a daughter of Boleslav, yearns for power. The instigator of the conspiracy is the clergyman of Boleslav -- the Kolobzheg Catholic bishop Reibern. 	The conspiracy of Svyatopolk and Reibern was an all-out threat to the historical existence of the Russian state and the Russian Church. Saint Vladimir took decisive measures. All the three involved were arrested, and Reibern soon died in prison. 	Saint Vladimir did not take revenge on those that &quot;opposed and hated&quot; him. Under the pretense of feigned repentance, Svyatopolk was set free. 	A new misfortune erupted in the North, at Novgorod. Yaroslav, still not so very much &quot;the Wise&quot; -- as he was later to go down in Russian history, in the year 1010 having become ruler of Novgorod, decided to defect from his father the greatprince of Kiev, and he formed his own separate army, moving on Kiev to demand the customary tribute and tithe. The unity of the Russian land, for which Saint Vladimir had struggled all his life, was threatened with ruin. In both anger and in sorrow Saint Vladimir gave orders to &quot;secure the dams and set the bridges&quot;, and to prepare for a campaign against Novgorod. His powers were on the decline. In the preparations for his final campaign, happily not undertaken, the Baptiser of Rus&apos; fell grievously ill and gave up his spirit to the Lord in the village of Spas-Berestov, on 15 July 1015. He had ruled the Russian realm for thirty-seven years (978-1015), and twenty-eight of these years had been spent since holy Baptism.  	Preparing for a new struggle for power and hoping for Polish help in it, and to play for time, Svyatopolk attempted to conceal the death of his father. But patriotically inclined Kievan boyar-nobles, secretly by night, removed the body of the deceased sovereign from the Berestov court, where Svyatopolk&apos;s people were guarding it, and they conveyed the body to Kiev. At the Desyatin-Tithe church the coffin with the relics of Saint Vladimir was met by Kievan clergy with Metropolitan John at the head. The holy relics were placed in a marble crypt, set within the Clement chapel of the Desyatin Uspenie church alongside the marble crypt of Empress Anna... 	The name and deeds of holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Vladimir, whom the people called the Splendid Sun, is interwoven with all the successive history of the Russian Church. &quot;Through him we too have come to worship and to know Christ, the True Life, -- testified Saint Ilarion. His deeds were continued by his sons, and grandsons and descendants -- rulers of the Russian land over the course of almost six centuries: from Yaroslav the Wise with the taking of the first steps towards the independent existence of the Russian Church -- down to the last of the Riurikovichi, tsar Feodor Ioannovich, under whom (in 1589) the Russian Orthodox Church became the fifth independent Patriarchate in the dyptich-lists of Orthodox Autocephalous Churches. 	The feastday celebration to holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Vladimir was established under Saint Alexander Nevsky, in memory of the intercession of Saint Vladimir on 15 May 1240, for his help in gaining the reknown victory by Nevsky over Swedish crusaders. 	But the first reverencing of the holy prince began in Rus&apos; rather earlier. The Metropolitan of Kiev Saint Ilarion (+ 1053), in his &quot;Word on Law and Grace&quot;, spoken on the day of memory of Saint Vladimir at the saint&apos;s crypt in the Desyatin-Tithe church, calls him &quot;an apostolic sovereign&quot;, &quot;like&quot; Saint Constantine, and he compares his apostolic evangelisation of the Russian Land to that of the evangelisation by the holy Apostles.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Seated on the high throne of Kiev, the mother of cities saved by God,/ thou didst emulate the merchant who sought the goodly pearl,/ O Vladimir glorious in might,/ and examining and sending emissaries to the Imperial City to learn about the Orthodox Faith,/ thou didst find Christ the priceless Pearl, Who chose thee as a second Paul/ and in the holy font removed thy blindness, spiritual and bodily./ Wherefore, we, thy people, celebrate thy repose./ Pray thou, that Russia, thy land, be saved,// and that peace and great mercy be granted to the Orthodox people.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8">
Emulating the great Apostle Paul in thy maturity, O most glorious Vladimir,/ and putting aside all thy zeal for idols as childish thoughts,/ thou hast adorned thyself with the purple robe of divine baptism./ And standing now in gladness before Christ the Savior,/ pray thou that Russia, thy land, be saved,// and that peace and great mercy be granted to the Orthodox people.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>