<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые апостолы от 70: Прохор, Никанор, Тимон и Пармен"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святые апостолы от 70: Прохор, Никанор, Тимон и Пармен были первыми диаконами Церкви Христовой. В книге Деяний Апостолов (6, 1—6) рассказывается, что в Иерусалиме двенадцать апостолов избрали семь мужей: Стефана, Филиппа, Прохора, Никанора, Тимона, Пармена и Николая, испол- ненных Святого Духа и премудрости, и поставили их на диакон- ское служение. Святая Церковь совершает их общую память 28 июля, хотя они скончались в разное время и в разных местах. Святой Прохор вначале сопровождал первоверховного апосто- ла Петра и от него поставлен епископом в город Никомидию. После Успения Божией Матери Прохор был спутником и сотруд- ником святого апостола Иоанна Богослова и вместе с ним сослан на остров Патмос. Там он записал Откровение Божие, бывшее святому апостолу Иоанну, о конечных судьбах мира (Апокалип- сис). По возвращении в Никомидию святой Прохор обращал языч- ников ко Христу в городе Антиохии и там принял мученическую кончину. Святой Никанор пострадал в тот день, когда был побит кам- нями святой первомученик архидиакон Стефан и множество дру- гих христиан. Святой Тимон был поставлен Апостолами во епископа города Бастории в Аравии и пострадал от иудеев и язычников за пропо- ведь Евангелия. Он был брошен в печь, но силой Божией вышел из нее невредимым. Предание Римской Церкви говорит, что святой Тимон скончался распятым на кресте. Святой Пармен усердно проповедовал Христа в Македонии. Умер он от посетившей его болезни. Существует также мнение, что святой Пармен пострадал при Траяне (98—117), в последний год его царствования, приняв мученическую кончину. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
А҆пⷭли ст҃ї́и, моли́те млⷭтиваго бг҃а да прегрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе пода́стъ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1" Podoben="3">
Дїа́кони честнї́и и҆ самови́дцы сло́ва, и҆ сосꙋ́ди и҆збра́ннїи ꙗ҆ви́стесѧ вѣ́ры, нїкано́ръ, про́хѡръ, парме́нъ и҆ тї́мѡнъ, сла́внїи: тѣ́мже де́нь сщ҃е́ннꙋю па́мѧть ва́шꙋ пра́зднꙋемъ, въ весе́лїи се́рдца ва́съ ѹ҆бл҃жа́юще. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Disciples from the 70: Prochorus, Nikanor, Timon and Parmenas"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Disciples from the 70: Prochorus, Nikanor, Timon and Parmenas were of the first deacons in the Church of Christ. 	In the book of the Acts of the Apostles (6: 1-6) it relates, that at Jerusalem the twelve apostles chose seven men: Stephen, Philip, Prochorus, Nikanor, Timon, Parmenas and Nicholas, full of the Holy Spirit and wisdom, and established them to serve as deacons. 	Holy Church makes their memory in common on 28 July, although they died at various times and in various places.  	Saint Prochorus at first accompanied the first-ranked Apostle Peter and was made by him bishop in the city of Nikomedia. After the Falling-Asleep (Dormition or Uspenie) of the MostHoly Mother of God, Prochorus was a companion and co-worker of the holy Apostle John the Theologian and together with him was banished to the island of Patmos. There he wrote down the Revelation of God, -- revealed to the holy Apostle John, about the final fate of the world (Apocalypse). Upon returning to Nikomedia, Saint Prochorus converted pagans to Christ in the city of Antioch and there accepted a martyr&apos;s end. 	Saint Nikanor suffered on that day when the holy First-Martyr Stephen and many other Christians were killed by stoning. 	Saint Timon was established by the Apostles as bishop of the city of Bastoria in Arabia and suffered from the Jews and pagans for preaching the Gospel. He was thrown into a furnace, but by the power of God he came out of it unharmed. The tradition of the Roman Church says, that Saint Timon died by crucifixion on a cross. 	Saint Parmenas zealously preached Christ in Macedonia. He died from sickness befalling him. There exists also the opinion, that Saint Parmenas suffered under Trajan (98-117) in the final year of his reign, having accepted a martyr&apos;s end.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
O holy apostles/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1" Podoben="3">
The glorious Nicanor, Prochorus, Parmenus and Timon,/ the honored deacons and eye-witnesses to the Word,/ have been shown to be chosen vessels of the Faith./ Wherefore, we celebrate your sacred memory today,// blessing you in gladness of heart.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>