<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой благоверный князь Всеволод, в Крещении Гавриил"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святой благоверный князь Всеволод, в Крещении Гавриил, Псковский, внук Владимира Мономаха, родился и почти всю жизнь прожил в Новгороде, где в 1088—1093 и 1095—1117 годах княжил его отец, святой благоверный князь Мстислав-Феодор Великий {\ 15 апреля 1132). В 1117 году, когда великий князь Владимир Мономах дал в удел Мстиславу Белгород Киевский, фактически сделав его своим соправителем, молодой Всеволод остался на- местником отца на Новгородском княжении.    Много доброго сделал святой князь Всеволод для Новгорода. Со святителем Нифонтом, архиепископом Новгородским (память 8 апреля), он воздвиг множество храмов, среди которых — собор великомученика Георгия в Юрьевском монастыре и храм свято- го Иоанна Предтечи на Опоках, построенный в честь Ангела его сына-первенца Иоанна, умершего в младенчестве (\ 1128). В Уставе князь даровал льготные грамоты собору Святой Софии и другим церквам. В страшный голод, спасая людей от гибели, он истратил всю казну. Князь Всеволод был доблестным воином,. победоносно ходил на ямь (в 1123) и на чудь, но никогда не брался за меч ради корысти и власти.    В 1132 году, по смерти святого великого князя Мстислава, Киевский князь Ярополк Владимирович,, дядя Всеволода, следуя завещанию брата, перевел Всеволода в Переяслав Южный, счи-  тавшийся старшим после Киева городом. Но младшие сыновья Мономаха — Юрий Долгорукий и Андрей Добрый, опасаясь, что Ярополк сделает Всеволода своим наследником, выступили против  племянника. Не желая междоусобиц, святой князь вернулся в Новгород, но его приняли с неудовольствием. Новгородцы считали, что князь был «вскормлен» ими и не должен был уходить от них. «Ходил Всеволод в Русь, в Переяслав, — отметил новгородский летописец, — а целовал крест новгородцам, сказав, «хочу у вас умереть»».     Стремясь восстановить добрые отношения с новгородцами, князь в 1133 году предпринял новый победоносный поход на Чудь и присоединил к новгородским владениям Юрьев. Но тяжелый зимний поход 1135—1136 годов на Суздаль окончился неудачей. Своевольные новгородцы не вразумились Божиим наказанием и не могли простить поражения своему князю. Вече решило при- звать князя из враждебного Мономаховичам рода Ольговичей, а святого Всеволода осудило на изгнание: «изгнание претерпел еси от своих», — поется в тропаре святому. Полтора месяца князя с семь- ей, как преступника, держали под стражей на архиерейском дворе, а когда прибыл князь Святослав Ольгович, «пустиша из города».     Всеволод вновь ушел в Киев, и дядя Ярополк дал ему в держа- ние Вышгородскую волость под Киевом, где в X веке, в годы прав- ления своего сына Святослава, жила святая равноапостольная великая княгиня Российская Ольга (память 11 июля). Ольга, «градов Киева и Пскова изрядная доброто», защитила своего не- праведно обиженного потомка: в следующем, 1137 году жители Пскова, помнившие походы новгородско-псковского войска под во- дительством князя, призвали его на псковское княжение, на роди- ну равноапостольной Ольги. Это был первый Псковский князь, из- бранный по воле самих псковичей.     Славным деянием святого благоверного князя Всеволода-Гав- риила во Пскове была постройка первого каменного храма во Имя Живоначальной Троицы, на месте деревянного, времен равноапо- стольной Ольги. На иконах святого часто пишут держащим в руке храм «об одном верху — Святая Троица».     Только год прокняжил во Пскове святой Всеволод — 11 фев- раля 1138 года он скончался, прожив 46 лет. Весь Псков собрался на погребение любимого князя, не было слышно церковного пения от народного плача. Новгородцы, опомнившись, прислали протопо-  па из Софийского собора, чтобы взять в Новгород его святое тело,  но князь отвратился от Новгорода,, и рака не двинулась с места.  Горько плакали новгородцы, раскаиваясь в неблагодарности, и  молили даровать им хоть малую частицу святого праха «на утвер-  ждение граду». По их молитвам отпал ноготь от руки святого.  Псковичи положили святого Всеволода в храме святого великому-  ченика Димитрия. Рядом с гробом поставили боевое оружие кня-  зя щит и меч, имевший форму креста, с надписью по-латыни  «Чести моей никому не отдам».    27 ноября 1192 года были обретены мощи святого князя Все- волода и перенесены в Троицкий собор, в котором был освящен в честь его придел.    22 апреля 1834 года, в первый день Пасхи, святые мощи были торжественно перенесены в главный храм собора.    Никогда не нарушалась глубокая духовная связь города свя- той равноапостольной Ольги со святым князем: он навсегда остал- ся Псковским чудотворцем. При осаде Пскова Стефаном Баторием в 1581 году, когда уже была разрушена крепостная стена и поля- ки были готовы ворваться в город, из Троицкого собора с крест- ным ходом принесли на место сражения святые мощи князя Всеволода, и враг отступил. При явлении чудотворной Псково- Покровской иконы (память 1 октября) святой благоверный князь Всеволод-Гавриил был среди Небесных защитников Пскова. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
И҆з꙽ мла́да ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ бг҃омꙋ́дре кнѧ́же гаврїи́ле бж҃е́ственный сосꙋ́дъ, и҆збра́нъ бг҃ови, бл҃гоче́стїемъ воспита́нъ, вѣ́рꙋ непоро́чнꙋ соблю́дъ, и҆ мнѡ́ги ст҃ы҄ѧ цр҃кви ѹ҆стро́ивъ, и҆згна́нїе претерпѣ́лъ є҆сѝ ѿ свои́хъ, ꙗ҆́коже и҆ цѣломꙋ́дрїи прароди́тели твоѝ ѿ бра́та ѹ҆бїе́нїе. съ ни́миже предстоѧ̀ ст҃ѣ́й трⷪцѣ моли́сѧ, держа́вы рѡ́сскїѧ нача́льникѡмъ сохранє́ннымъ бы́ти, и҆ всѣ҄мъ на́мъ сп҃сти́сѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Многомꙋ́дреннѡ пресели́всѧ во гра́дъ пско́въ, бл҃же́нне кнѧ́же гаврїи́ле, пло́дъ бл҃гї́й бг҃ови въ жи́зни се́й бы́лъ є҆сѝ, присноцвѣтꙋ́щь добродѣ́тельми, и҆ ꙗ҆́коже дв҃дъ неѕло́бїемъ: тогѡ̀ ра́ди полꙋчи́лъ є҆сѝ жи́знь вѣ́чнꙋю на нб҃сѣ́хъ, всегда̀ зрѧ̀ ст҃ꙋ́ю трⷪцꙋ, молѝ и҆зба́витисѧ на́мъ ѿ всѧ́кихъ бѣ́дъ, да зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ ѹ҆твержде́нїе гра́дꙋ на́шемꙋ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Nobleborn Prince Vsevolod of Pskov, in Baptism Gabriel"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Holy Nobleborn Prince Vsevolod of Pskov, in Baptism Gabriel (Gavriil), a grandson of Vladimir Monomakh, was born at and spent almost all his life in Novgorod, where in the years 1088-1093 and 1095-1117 his father ruled as prince. His father was the holy prince Saint Mstislav-Theodore (Feodor) the Great (+ 15 April 1132). In the year 1117, when Greatprince Vladimir Monomakh gave Mstislav Kievan Belgorod as his &quot;udel&quot; (land-holding), practically making him co-ruler, young Vsevolod remained as vicar of his father in the Novgorod principality. 	Holy Prince Vsevolod did much good for Novgorod. Together with the Archbishop of Novgorod, Saint Nyphontii (Comm. 8 April), he raised up many a church, among which were -- the cathedral of the GreatMartyr George at the Yur&apos;ev monastery, and the church of Saint John the Forerunner at Opokakh, built in honour of the &quot;Angel&quot; (i.e. &quot;patron saint&quot;) of his first-born son John, who had died in infancy (+ 1128). In his Ustav (Law-code) the prince bestowed a grammota-deed of privileges to the cathedral of Saint Sophia and other churches. During the time of a terrible famine, to save people from perishing, he exhausted his entire treasury. Prince Vsevolod was a valiant warrior, he marched victoriously against the Yam (in 1123) and Chud peoples, but never did he brandish the sword for lucre or power. 	In 1132, upon the death of holy Greatprince Mstislav, Vsevolod&apos;s uncle the Kiev prince Yaropolk Vladimirovich followed up the last-wishes of his brother and transferred Vsevolod Pereyaslavl&apos;-South, then reckoned the eldest city after Kiev itself. But the younger sons of Monomakh -- Yurii Dolgoruky and Andrei Dobry, were apprehensive lest Yaropolk make Vsevolod his successor, and so they marched out against their nephew. Not wanting internecine strife, Saint Vsevolod returned to Novgorod, but was received there with disaffection. The Novgorodians reckoned, that the prince had been &quot;raised&quot; by them and should not earlier have left them. &quot;Vsevolod did go to Rus&apos;, to Pereslavl&apos;, -- noted the Novgorod chronicler, -- and did kiss the cross against the Novgorodians, saying, &quot;Ye I would kill&quot;&quot;. 	Striving to restore good relations with the Novgorodians, the prince in 1133 undertook a new victorious campaign against the Chud people, and he annexed Yur&apos;ev to the Novgorod domain. But an harsh Winter campaign in 1135-1136 against Suzdal&apos; ended unsuccessfully. The stubborn minded Novgorodians would not heed their chastisement by God, and they could not forgive the prince their defeat. The veche-assembly decided to summon a prince from the hostile Monomakh line of the Ol&apos;govichei, and Saint Vsevolod they condemned to banishment: &quot;Thou didst suffer banishment from thine own&quot;, -- is sung in the tropar to the saint. For a month and an half they held the prince with his family under guard at the archbishop&apos;s palace, and when prince Svyatoslav Ol&apos;govich arrived, &quot;he was expelled from the city&quot;. 	Vsevolod went again to Kiev, and his uncle Yaropolk gave him as holding the Vyshgorod district near Kiev, -- the place where in the X Century during the rule of her son Svyatoslav had lived holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Greatprincess Olga (Comm. 11 July). Saint Olga, &quot;well preferring the cities of Kiev and Pskov&quot;, came to the defense of her unrighteously wronged descendant: in the following year of 1137 the people of Pskov, mindful of the campaigns of the Novgorod-Pskov army under the lead of the prince, invited him to the Pskov principality, the native region of Saint Olga. This was the first Pskov prince, chosen through the will of the Pskov people itself.  	Among the glorious works of holy prince Saint Vsevolod-Gabriel at Pskov was the construction of the first stone church in the Name of the Life-Originating Trinity, replacing a wooden one from the times of Saint Olga. On the icons of the saint they often depict him holding a temple &quot;of That Above -- the Holy Trinity&quot;.  	Saint Vsevolod ruled as prince at Pskov for only a year -- on 11 February 1138 he died, at age 46. All Pskov gathered at the funeral of the beloved prince, and the church singing could barely be heard over the people&apos;s wailing. The Novgorodians, in retrospect, sent off an archpriest from the Sophia cathedral to take his holy body back to Novgorod, but the prince had become loatheful of Novgorod, and the coffin would not move from the spot. Bitterly then did the Novgorod people bewail and repent in their misfortune, and they then besought to be given but a small bit of the holy dust &quot;for upholding their city&quot;. Through their prayers fell out a fingernail from the hand of the saint. The Pskov people put Saint Vsevolod into the temple of the holy GreatMartyr Demetrios. Alongside the grave they placed the military armament of the prince -- shield and sword, in cruciform shape, with the Latin inscription to wit, -- &quot;I give away mine honour to no one&quot;. 	On 27 November 1192, the relics of holy Prince Vsevolod were uncovered and transferred into the Trinity cathedral, in which a chapel was consecrated in his honour.  	On 22 April 1834, on the first day of Pascha, the holy relics were solemnly transferred into the main church-area of the cathedral.  	The deep spiritual bond of the city of holy Equal-to-the-Apostles Olga with holy Prince Vsevolod was never broken: he always remained a Pskov wonderworker. At the siege of Pskov by Stefan Bathory in 1581, when the fortress walls were already breached and the Poles were ready to rush into the city, from the Trinity cathedral with a church procession they brought to the place of battle the holy relics of Prince Vsevolod, and the enemy withdrew. And with the appearance of the wonderworking Pskovo-Pechersk Icon (Comm. 1 October), holy Nobleborn Prince Vsevolod-Gabriel has stood amidst the Heavenly defenders of Pskov.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>