<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые 12 мучеников -- Памфил пресвитер, Валент (Уалент) диакон, Павел, Порфирий, Селевкий, Феодул, Иулиан, Самуил, Илия, Даниил, Иеремия, Исайя"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святые 12 мучеников — Памфил пресвитер, Валент (Уалент) диакон, Павел, Порфирий, Селевкий, Феодул, Иулиан, Самуил, Илия, Даниил, Иеремия, Исайя пострадали во время гонения на христиан, воздвигнутого императором Диоклитианом в 308—309 го- дах в Кесарии Палестинской. Святой мученик Памфил, уроженец города Берита (Бейрут), получил образование в Александрии, пос- ле чего был поставлен пресвитером в Кесарии. Он много потрудил- ся над сличением и исправлением текстов Нового Завета, повреж- денных переписчиками. Исправленные копии святой Памфил пере- писывал и рассылал желающим их иметь. Таким образом им были обращены ко Христу многие язычники. Его трудами и заботами в Кесарии была собрана обширная библиотека духовных книг, слу- жившая христианскому просвещению. Блаженный Иероним (IV— начало V в.) очень чтил святого Памфила и считал себя счастли- вым, ибо обрел и хранил у себя некоторые его рукописи. Святому Памфилу в благовестии веры Христовой деятельно помогали свя- той Валент, диакон Елийской церкви, человек преклонного возра- ста, прекрасно знавший Священное Писание, и святой Павел, го- ревший верой и любовью ко Христу Спасителю. Все трое были заключены на 2 года в темницу правителем Кесарии Палестинской Урбаном. В правление его преемника Фирмилиана в Египте были осуждены и отправлены в Киликию (Малая Азия) на золотонос- ные рудники 130 христиан. Их провожали до места изгнания пять юношей-братьев. На обратном пути в Египет они были задер- жаны в Кесарии и брошены в темницу за исповедание Христа. Юношей привели на суд к Фирмилиану вместе с заключенными ранее святыми Памфилом, Валентом и Павлом. Назвавшись име- нами ветхозаветных пророков — Илии, Иеремии, Исайи, Самуила и Даниила, на вопрос об их отечестве юноши отвечали, что они граждане Иерусалима, разумея под этим небесный Иерусалим. Фирмилиан ничего не знал о городе с таким названием, так как на месте Иерусалима, разрушенного императором Титом в 70 году, был построен императором Адрианом (117—138) город, именуемый в то время Елий-Адриан. Фирмилиан долго мучил юношей, пытаясь узнать месторасположение неведомого города и склонить юношей  к вероотступничеству; ничего не добившись, правитель предал их  усечению мечом вместе с Памфилом, Валентом и Павлом.      Прежде этого пришлось пострадать слуге пресвитера Памфила,  18-летнему юноше Порфирию, кроткому и смиренному. Услышав о вынесенном смертном приговоре мученикам, он просил разреше-  ния у правителя похоронить тела приговоренных после их казни,  за что был умерщвлен и предан сожжению на костре.      Свидетель этого мученичества, благочестивый христианин Се-  левкий, бывший воин, приветствуя подвиг страдальцев, подошел  к Памфилу перед казнью и рассказал ему о мученической кончине  святого Порфирия. Он тут же был схвачен воинами и, по повеле-  нию Фирмилиана, усечен мечом вместе с приговоренными.      Один из слуг правителя, Феодул, человек преклонного возра-  ста и тайный христианин, приветствуя мучеников, ведомых на  казнь, поцеловал их и просил помолиться за него. Он был приве-  ден воинами на допрос к Фирмилиану и по приказу последнего  распят на кресте.      Юноша Иулиан, родом каппадокиец, подходя к Кесарии, уви-  дел тела святых, брошенные без погребения на съедение зверям.   Подойдя к ним, Иулиан преклонил колена и облобызал тела стра-   дальцев. Стоявшие в стороне воины схватили его, повели к прави-   телю, который осудил святого Иулиана на сожжение. Тела всех   12-ти мучеников пребывали без погребения в течение 4-х дней. Ни   звери, ни птицы не коснулись их. Смущенные этим обстоятель-   ством, язычники позволили христианам взять тела мучеников и   похоронить их. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нцы твоѝ гдⷭи, во страда́нїихъ свои́хъ вѣнцы̀ прїѧ́ша нетлѣ҄нныѧ ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мꙋ́ще бо крѣ́пость твою̀ мꙋчи́телей низложи́ша, сокрꙋши́ша и҆ де́мѡнѡвъ немощны҄ѧ де́рзѡсти. тѣ́хъ моли́твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Мꙋче́нїємъ стра҄шнымъ предлежа́щымъ, гдⷭни страда́льцы до́блїи въ небоѧ́зненномъ ра́дꙋющесѧ мꙋдрова́нїи, си́мъ собесѣ́доваша ѡ҆ пло́ти неради́вше. тѣ́мже наслѣ́дствоваша вѣ́чнꙋющꙋю сла́вꙋ, ѡ҆ на́съ молѧ́щесѧ при́снѡ восхвалѧ́ющихъ и҆́хъ по́двиги. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="12 Martyred Saints -- Pamphilos the Presbyter, Valentus (Ualentos) the Deacon, Paul, Porphyrios, Seleucios, Theodoulos, Julian, Samuel, Ilias, Daniel, Jeremiah and Isaiah"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The 12 Martyred Saints -- Pamphilos the Presbyter, Valentus (Ualentos) the Deacon, Paul, Porphyrios, Seleucios, Theodoulos, Julian, Samuel, Ilias, Daniel, Jeremiah and Isaiah suffered during the time of a persecution against christians, initiated by the emperor Diocletian in the years 308-309 at Caesarea in Palestine. The holy martyr Pamphilos, a native of the city of Berit (Beirut), received his education at Alexandria, after which he was made presbyter at Caesarea. He laboured much over the collation and correction of copyist errors in texts of the New Testament. The corrected texts of Saint Pamphilos were copied out and distributed to those wanting them. In such form many pagans were converted to Christ through them. His works and concerned matters at Caesarea were gathered up into the extensive library of spiritual books available for the enlightening of christians. Blessed Jerome (IV -- beginning V Century) deeply respected Saint Pamphilos and considered himself fortuneate to have located and come into possession of several of his manuscripts. Actively assisting Saint Pamphilos in proclaiming the faith in Christ were Saint Valentus, deacon of the church at Eleia -- a man bent over with age and well-versed in the Holy Scriptures, and Saint Paul, ardent in faith and love for Christ the Saviour. All three were imprisoned for 2 years by the governor of Palestinian Caesarea, Urban. During the rule of his successor Firmilian, 130 christians were sentenced in Egypt and sent off to Cilicia (Asia Minor) to work in the gold mines. Five young brothers accompanied them there to the place of exile. On the return journey to Egypt they were detained at Caesarea and thrown into prison for confessing Christ. They brought the youths for judgement to Firmilian, together with those imprisoned earlier -- Saints Pamphilos, Valentus and Paul. Having been named with names of Old Testament prophets -- Ilias, Jeremiah, Isaiah, Samuel and Daniel -- the youths answered the question of their fatherland by saying, that they were citizens of Jerusalem, meaning by this the heavenly Jerusalem. Firmilian knew nothing about a such-named city, since on the site of Jerusalem -- razed to the ground by the emperor Titus in the year 70 -- had been constructed a new city by the emperor Adrian (117-138), which at the time was named Eleia-Adrian. Firmilian tortured the youths for a long time. He sought to learn the location of the unknown city, and he sought to persuade the youths to apostacise. But nothing was accomplished, and the governor gave them over for beheading by the sword together with Pamphilos, Valentus and Paul. 	Before this occurred, a servant of presbyter Pamphilos was given to suffer -- this was the 18 year old youth Porphyrios, meek and humble. He had heard the sentence of death for the condemned martyrs, and asked the governor&apos;s permission to bury the bodies after execution. For this he was sentenced to death and given over to burning on a bon-fire. 	A witness of this execution -- the pious christian Seleucios, a former soldier -- in saluting the deeds of the sufferers, went up to Pamphilos before execution and told him about the martyr&apos;s end of Saint Porphyrios. He was seized upon by soldiers and, on orders from Firmilian, was beheaded by the sword together with the condemned. 	One of the governor&apos;s servants, Thoedoulos, a man of venerable age and secretly a christian, greeted the martyrs being led to execution, gave them a kiss and asked them to pray for him. He was taken by soldiers for questioning to Firmilian, on whose orders he was crucified on a cross. 	The youth Julian, a native of Cappadocia who had come to Caesarea, caught view of the bodies of the saints which had been thrown to wild beasts without burial. Julian went down on his knees and venerated the bodies of the sufferers. Soldiers standing by at the wall seized hold of him and took him to the governor, who condemned him to burning. The bodies of all 12 martyrs stayed without burial for 4 days. Neither beasts nor birds would touch them. Embarrassed by this situation, the pagans permitted christians to take the bodies of the martyrs and bury them.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
In their sufferings, O Lord, Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee, our God; for, possessed of Thy might, they set at nought the tyrants and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons. By their supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Rejoicing in wisdom made manifest by heaven,/ when dreadful torments lay before them,/ the valiant athletes conversed amongst themselves, sparing not their flesh./ Wherefore, they have inherited everlasting glory,// ever praying for us who praise their contest.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>