<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой Лев"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святой Лев был епископом в городе Катане, в Сицилии. Он сла- вился добротой и милосердием, христианской любовью к нищим и странникам. Господь удостоил его дара врачевания от различ- ных болезней и чудотворений. Во времена епископства святого Льва в Катанах жил чародей Илиодор, который поражал народ ложными чудесами. Он прежде был христианином, но потом тайно отвергся Спасителя и сделался служителем диавола. Святитель Лев часто убеждал Илиодора отстать от злых дел и обратиться к Богу, но напрасно. Однажды Илиодор дошел до такой дерзости, что, войдя в храм, где епископ совершал Богослужение, своим вол- хвованием произвел там смятение и соблазн, пытаясь устроить бес- чинства. Видя народ, беснующийся по колдовскому внушению, свя- той Лев понял, что время кротких увещеваний прошло. Он спокой- но вышел из алтаря и, обвязав шею чародея-своим омофором, вывел его из храма на площадь. Там он заставил Илиодора признаться во всех злодеяниях, приказал развести костер и без колебаний вступил вместе с чародеем в огонь, удерживая его омофором. Так они стояли в огне, пока Илиодор не сгорел, а святитель Лев, силой Божией, остался невредим. Это чудо еще при жизни прославило пре- подобного Льва. Когда преподобный скончался, при его гробе по- лучила исцеление кровоточивая женщина. Тело святого было поло- жено в храме святой мученицы Лукии, созданном им самим, а впо- следствии мощи его были перенесены в церковь святителя Мартина Милостивого, епископа Турского (память 12 октября). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Пра́вило вѣ́ры и҆ ѡ҆́бразъ кро́тости, воздержа́нїѧ ѹ҆чи́телѧ ꙗ҆ви́ тѧ ста́дꙋ твоемꙋ̀, ꙗ҆́же веще́й и҆́стина: сегѡ̀ ра́ди стѧжа́лъ є҆сѝ смире́нїемъ высѡ́каѧ, нището́ю бога҄таѧ, ѻ҆́тче львѐ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="3">
Ꙗ҆́коже свѣти́льника превели́ка цр҃ковь и҆́мать всебл҃же́нне, тебѐ па́че со́лнца сїѧ́юща, ю҆́же твои́ми мл҃твами сохранѝ бл҃же́нне, непобѣди́мꙋ и҆ непоколеби́мꙋ ѿ є҆́реси всѧ́кїѧ, и҆ нескве́рнꙋ, ꙗ҆́кѡ приснопа́мѧтный. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Leo"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Leo was bishop of the city of Catania, in Sicily. He was famed for his benevolence and charity, and his Christian love for the poor and the vagrant. The Lord granted him the gifts of healing of various illnesses, and also wonderworking. During the time when Saint Leo was bishop in Catania, there lived a certain sorcerer magician named Heliodorus, who impressed people with his fake miracles. This fellow was originally a Christian, but then he secretly rejected Christ and became a servant of the devil. Saint Leo often urged Heliodorus to be done with his wicked deeds and return to God, but in vain. One time Heliodorus got so impudent that, having entered into the church where the bishop was celebrating Divine-services, he by his sorcery sowed confusion and temptation there, trying to create a disturbance. Seeing the people beset by devils under the sorcerous spell, Saint Leo realised, that the time of gentle persuasions had passed. He calmly emerged from the altar and, grabbing the magician by the neck with his omophorion, he led him out of the church into the city-square. There he forced Heliodorus to own up to all his wicked deeds; he commanded a bon-fire be built, and without flinching he jumped together with the sorcerer into the fire, while having on his omophorion. Thus they stood in the fire, until Heliodorus got burnt, while by the power of God Saint Leo remained unharmed. This miracle while still during his lifetime brought Saint Leo reknown. When he died, at his grave a woman with issue of blood received healing. The body of the saint was placed in a church of the holy Martyress Lucy, which he himself had built, and later on his relics were transferred into a church of Sainted Martin the Merciful, Bishop of Tours (Comm. 12 October). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
The truth of things revealed thee to thy flock as a rule of faith,/ a model of meekness and a teacher of abstinence/ wherefore thou hast attained the heights through humility/ and riches through poverty.// O hierarch Leo our father, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="3">
The Church hath thee, O most blessed one, as a great beacon shining more brightly than the sun./ By thy supplications preserve it invincible, unshaken and unharmed by any heresy,// in that thou art ever-memorable.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>