<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Герасим"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
    Преподобный Герасим был родом из Ликии (Малая Азия). С юности он отличался благочестием. Приняв монашество, препо- добный удалился в глубь Фиваидской пустыни (Египет). Около 450 года преподобный пришел в Палестину и поселился у Иордана, где основал монастырь.     Одно время святой был соблазнен ересью Евтихия и Диоскора, признававших в Иисусе Христе только Божественное естество. Однако преподобный Евфимий Великий (память 20 января) помог ему вернуться к правой вере.     В обители святой установил строгие правила. Пять дней в не- делю инок проводил в уединении, занимаясь рукоделием и молит- вой. В эти дни пустынники не ели вареной пищи и даже не разво- дили огня, а питались сухим хлебом, корнями и водой. В субботу и воскресенье все собирались в монастырь к Божественной литур- гии и причащались Святых Христовых Тайн. После полудня, взяв с собой запас хлеба, кореньев, воды и охапку ветвей финиковой пальмы для плетения корзин, пустынники возвращались в свои уединенные келлии. Каждый имел только ветхую одежду и рогожу,  на которой спал. Уходя из келлии, дверь не запирали, чтобы вся-  кий пришедший мог войти, отдохнуть или взять необходимое.     Сам преподобный являл высокий образец подвижничества.  В Великий пост он не ел ничего до самого светлого дня Воскресе-  ния Христова, когда причащался Святых Тайн. Уходя на весь  Великий пост в пустыню, преподобный брал с собой блаженного  Кириака, своего любимого ученика (память 29 сентября), которого  направил к нему преподобный Евфимий Великий.     Во время кончины святого Евфимия Великого преподобному  Герасиму было открыто, как душу усопшего Ангелы возносили на  небо. Взяв с собой Кириака, преподобный немедленно пошел в  обитель святого Евфимия и предал земле его тело.    Преподобный Герасим скончался мирно, оплаканный братией и  учениками. До самой кончины преподобному Герасиму помогал в  трудах лев, который по смерти старца умер на его могиле и был  зарыт близ гроба святого. Посему льва изображают на иконах,  у ног преподобного. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Возгорѣ́всѧ раче́нїемъ го́рнимъ, же́стость пꙋсты́ни ї҆ѻрда́новы па́че всѣ́хъ мї́ра сла́дкихъ предпоче́лъ є҆сѝ: ѿѻнꙋ́дꙋже повинꙋ́всѧ тебѣ̀ ѕвѣ́рь да́же до сме́рти ѻ҆́тче, послꙋ́шнѣ, и҆ жа́лостнѣ на гро́бѣ твое́мъ сконча́сѧ, просла́вльшꙋ тѧ̀ та́кѡ бг҃ꙋ: къ немꙋ́же молѧ́сѧ и҆ ѡ҆ на́съ, ѻ҆́тче гера́сїме, помина́й. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Gerasimos"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Gerasimos was a native of Lycia (Asia Minor). From his early years he was distinguished for his piety. Having then accepted monasticism, the monk withdrew into the depths of the Thebaid wilderness (in Egypt). Thereafter, in about the year 450, the monk arrived in Palestine and settled at the Jordan, where he founded a monastery. 	For a certain while Saint Gerasimos was tempted by the heresy of Eutykhios and Dioskoros, which acknowledged in Jesus Christ only the Divine nature, but not His human nature (i.e. the Monophysite heresy). The Monk Euthymios the Great (Comm. 20 January) helped him to return to the true faith.  	At the monastery the Monk Gerasimos established a strict monastic rule. He spent five days of the week in solitude, occupying himself with handicrafts and prayer. On these days the wilderness dwellers did not eat cooked food, nor even kindle a fire, but rather ate only dry bread, roots and water. On Saturday and Sunday all gathered at the monastery for Divine Liturgy and to commune the Holy Mysteries of Christ. In the afternoon, taking with them a supply of bread, tubers, water and an armload of date-palm branches for weaving into baskets, the wilderness dwellers returned to their own cells. Each had only old clothes and a mat, upon which he slept. In exiting their cells, the door was never secured, so that anyone coming by could enter, and rest, or take along necessities. 	The Monk Gerasimos himself attained an high level of asceticism. During Great Lent he ate nothing until the very day of the All-Radiant Resurrection of Christ, when he communed the Holy Mysteries. Going out into the wilderness for the whole of Great Lent, the Monk Gerasimos took along with him his beloved disciple Blessed Kyriakos (Comm. 29 September), whom the Monk Euthymios had sent off to him. 	At the time of the death of Saint Euthymios the Great, the Monk Gerasimos saw how Angels carried up the soul of the departed off to Heaven. Taking Kyriakos with him, the monk immediately set off to the monastery of Saint Euthymios and consigned his body to earth.  	The Monk Gerasimos himself died peacefully, wept over by brethren and disciples. Before his death, a lion had aided the Monk Gerasimos in his tasks, and upon the death of the elder it too died at his grave and was buried nearby. And therefore the lion is depicted on icons of the saint, at his feet.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Burning with heavenly love, thou didst prefer the harshness of the desert of Jordan/ more than all the delights of the world;/ hence, a wild beast submitted unto thee even unto thy death, O father,/ dying in obedience and grief on thy grave./ Thus did God glorify thee./ And when thou dost pray to Him, O father Gerasimus,// be thou mindful of us.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>