<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Софроний, Патриарх Иерусалимский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святитель Софроний, Патриарх Иерусалимский, родился в Да- маске. С юных лет он отличался благочестием и любовью к нау- кам. Особенно он преуспел в философии, за что его стали назы- вать Премудрым. Но будущий святитель искал высшей мудрости в монастырях, в беседах с пустынножителями. Он прибыл в Иеру- салим, в обитель святого Феодосия, и там сблизился с иеромона- хом Иоанном Мосхом. Он стал его духовным сыном и отдался ему в послушание. Праведники вместе путешествовали по монастырям, записывали жития и поучения подвизавшихся в них. Из этих за- писей позже составилась их знаменитая книга «Лимонарь» или «Луг духовный», которую высоко оценил Седьмой Вселенский Со-  бор. (Иоанн Мосх, иером. Луг духовный. Слав. пер. Киев, 1628. То же. Пер. архиеп. Филарета (Гумилевского). М., 1848, 1850,  1853. То же. 2-й пер. М., 1859. То же. 3-й пер. Свящ. М. Хитрова. Сергиев Посад (СТСЛ), 1896.)     Спасаясь от опустошительных набегов персов, святые Иоанн и Софроний оставили Палестину и удалились в Антиохию, а оттуда в Египет. В Египте святой Софроний тяжко занемог. В то время он и решил стать монахом и принял постриг от преподобного Иоанна Мосха. После выздоровления святого Софрония они оба решили остаться в Александрии. Там их с любовью принял святой Патри- арх Иоанн Милостивый (память 12 ноября), которому они оказа- ли большую помощь в борьбе против монофелитов. В Александрии у святого Софрония заболели глаза, и он прибегнул с молитвой и верой к святым бессребреникам Киру и Иоанну (память 31 янва- ря) и в церкви, посвященной им, получил исцеление. В благодар- ность святой Софроний написал житие святых целителей-бессреб- реников.     Когда варвары стали угрожать Александрии, святой Патриарх Иоанн в сопровождении святых Софрония и Иоанна направился в Константинополь, но по дороге умер. Святые Иоанн и Софроний с одиннадцатью другими монахами отправились в Рим. В Риме преподобный Иоанн скончался (\ 622). Тело его было перевезено святым Софронием в Иерусалим и похоронено в обители святого Феодосия.     В 628 году из персидского плена вернулся Иерусалимский Пат- риарх Захария (609—633). После его смерти в течение двух лет патриарший престол занимал святой Модест (633—634; память  18 декабря), а по кончине святителя Модеста Патриархом был избран святой Софроний. Святитель Софроний много потрудился на благо Иерусалимской Церкви как ее Предстоятель (634—644).     В конце жизни святитель Софроний со своей паствой пережил двухлетнюю осаду Иерусалима магометанами. Изнуренные голо- дом христиане согласились наконец открыть городские ворота с условием, что противник пощадит святыни. Однако это условие не было выполнено, и святой Патриарх Софроний умер в глубо- кой скорби об осквернении христианских святынь.     До нас дошли сочинения патриарха Софрония по догматике, а также «Объяснение на Литургию», Житие преподобной Марии Египетской (память 1 апреля), около х 950 тропарей, стихиры от Пасхи до Вознесения. Еще будучи иеромонахом, святой Софроний пересмотрел и исправил «Устав» монастыря преподобного Саввы Освященного (память 5 декабря). «Трипеснцы» святителя на Свя- тую Четыредесятницу входят и в состав современной Триоди. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
И҆́же бж҃е́ственною ре́вностїю подви́гсѧ, и҆ и҆́стинныхъ повелѣ́нїй ѹ҆стнѣ̀ распросте́ръ, церкѡ́внаѧ ѡ҆снова҄нїѧ бл҃гоꙋзако́нивъ, и҆ та́мѡ сꙋ́щымъ мона́шєскимъ соста́вѡмъ преда́въ, премꙋ́дрый въ патрїа́рсѣхъ ї҆ерⷭли́мскїй сѡфро́нїе, всемꙋ҄драѧ словеса̀ во свѣ́тъ и҆зве́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆́миже наставлѧ́еми зове́мъ тѝ: ра́дꙋйсѧ, свѣ́тлаѧ правосла́вныхъ похвало̀. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Sophronios, Patriarch of Jerusalem"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Sophronios, Patriarch of Jerusalem, was born in Damascus. From his youthful years he distinguished himself by his piety and his love for the classical sciences. He advanced especially in philosophy, for which they were wont to call him the Wise. But the future hierarch sought out an higher wisdom in the monasteries, and in conversations with the wilderness-dwellers. He arrived in Jerusalem at the monastery of Saint Theodosios, and there he became close with the PriestMonk John Moskhos, becoming his spiritual son and devoting himself to him in obedience. They journeyed together through the monasteries, and they wrote down descriptions of the lives and precepts of the ascetics found there. From these jottings was afterwards compiled their reknown book, the &quot;Leimonarion&quot; or &quot;Spiritual Meadow&quot;, which was highly esteemed at the Seventh OEcumenical Council. 	To save themselves from the devastating incursions of the Persians, Saints John and Sophronios quit Palestine and withdrew to Antioch, and from there they went to Egypt. In Egypt Saint Sophronios became seriously ill. During this time he also decided to become a monk and so he accepted tonsure from the Monk John Moskhos. After the return to health of Saint Sophronios, they both decided to remain in Alexandria. There they were fondly received by the holy Patriarch John the Merciful (Comm. 12 November), to whom they rendered great aid in the struggle against the Monophysite heresy. At Alexandria Saint Sophronios&apos; eyesight was afflicted, and he recoursed with prayer and faith to the holy UnMercenaries Cyrus and John (Comm. 31 January), and he received healing in a church named for them. In gratitude, Saint Sophronios then wrote the Vita of these holy unmercenaries. 	When the barbarians began to threaten Alexandria, the holy Patriarch John, accompanied by Saints Sophronios and John Moskhos, set out for Constantinople, but along the way he died. Saints John Moskhos and Sophronios with eighteen other monks then set out for Rome. At Rome the Monk John Moskhos also died (+ 622). His body was conveyed by Saint Sophronios to Jerusalem and buried at the monastery of Saint Theodosios.  	In the year 628 the Jerusalem patriarch Zacharias (609-633) returned from the Persian Captivity. After his death, the patriarchal throne was occupied for a space of two years by Saint Modestos (633-634, Comm. 18 December). After the death of Saint Modestos, Saint Sophronios was chosen patriarch. Sainted Sophronios toiled much for the welfare of the Jerusalem Church as its primate (634-644). 	Towards the end of his life, Saint Sophronios with his flock lived through a two year siege of Jerusalem by the Mahometans. Worn down by hunger, the Christians finally consented to open the city gates, on the condition that the enemy spare the holy places. But this condition was not fulfilled, and holy Patriarch Sophronios died in deep grief over the desecration of the Christian holy places. 	Written works by Patriarch Sophronios have come down to us in the area of dogmatics, and likewise his &quot;Excursus on the Liturgy&quot;, the Vita of the Nun Mary of Egypt (Comm. 1 April), and also about 950 tropars and stikhi-verses from Pascha to the Ascension. While still a priestmonk, Saint Sophronios made review and corrections to the &quot;ustav-rule&quot; of the monastery of the Monk Sava the Sanctified (Comm. 5 December). And the &quot;tri-odic song&quot; of the saint for the Holy Forty Day Great Lent is included in the composition of the contemporary Lenten Triodion.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
O Sophronius of Jerusalem, most wise among patriarchs, who struggled with divine zeal,/ spread the commandments of truth with thy lips, set the foundations of the Church in good order,/ and there transmitted them to those in the monastic ranks:/ thou didst bring most wise discourses to light; and, instructed thereby, we cry out to thee:// Rejoice, O splendid boast of the Orthodox!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>