<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой пророк Елисей"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Святой пророк Елисей жил в IX веке до Рождества Христова, был родом из селения Авелмаум, близ Иордана. По повелению Господню был призван к пророческому служению святым проро- ком Божиим Илией (память 20 июля). Когда настало время взятия святого пророка Илии на Небо,, он сказал Елисею: «Проси, что сделать тебе, прежде нежели я буду взят от тебя». Елисей дерзновенно испросил для дела Божия су- губую благодать: «Дух, который в тебе, пусть будет на мне вдвойне». Пророк Илия сказал: «Трудного ты просишь; если уви- дишь как я буду взят от тебя, то будет тебе так, а если не уви- дишь, не будет» (4 Цар. 2, 9—10). Когда они шли по дороге и беседовали, явились огненная колесница и кони и разлучили их обоих. Елисей воскликнул: «Отец мой, отец мой, колесница Из- раилева и конница его!» (4 Цар. 2, 12). Подняв упавшую с неба милоть (плащ) своего учителя, Елисей получил силу и пророче- ский дар Илии. Пророческое служение он проходил более 65 лет, при шести израильских царях (от Ахаза до Иоаса). «И во дни свои не трепетал перед князем, и никто не превозмог его» (Сир. 48, 13). Святой пророк творил многочисленные чудеса. Разделил воды Иордана, ударив по ним милотию пророка Илии; сделал пригодной для питья воду Иерихонского источника; обильным изведением воды молитвой спас от гибели стоявшие в безводной пустыне войска Израильского и Иудейского царей; избавил бед- ную вдову от голодной смерти чудесным умножением масла в со- суде. Оказавшая пророку гостеприимство женщина-соманитянка была обрадована рождением сына по его молитве, когда же ребе- нок умер, то был воскрешен пророком. Сирийский военачальник Нееман был исцелен от проказы, а слуга пророка Гиезий пора- жен ею за то, что ослушался пророка и тайно от него взял деньги от Неемана. Елисей предсказал израильскому царю Иоасу победу над врагами и силой своей молитвы совершил много других чудес. Скончался святой пророк Елисей в глубокой старости в Самарии. «И при жизни своей совершал он чудеса, и по смерти были дивны дела его» (Сир. 48, 15). Через год после его смерти мертвец, бро- шенный в пещеру, где лежали его останки, воскрес от прикосно- вения к его костям. Пророк Елисей, так же как и его учитель, святой пророк Илия, не оставил после себя книг, их проповедь была только устной. Иисус, сын Сирахов, написал похвалу обоим великим пророкам (Сир. 48, 1—15). Святой Иоанн Дамаскин написал канон в честь пророка Ели- сея, а в Константинополе был воздвигнут храм его имени. Юлиан Отступник (361—363) приказал сжечь мощи пророков Елисея, Авдия и Иоанна Предтечи, но останки святых мощей были сохранены верующими и часть их перенесена в Алек- сандрию. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Во пло́ти а҆́гг҃лъ, прⷪро́кѡвъ ѡ҆снова́нїе, вторы́й прⷣте́ча прише́ствїѧ хрⷭто́ва, и҆лїа̀ сла́вный, свы́ше посла́вый є҆лїссе́еви бл҃года́ть, недꙋ́ги ѿгонѧ́ти, и҆ прокажє́нныѧ ѡ҆чища́ти: тѣ́мже и҆ почита́ющымъ є҆го̀ то́читъ и҆сцѣлє́нїѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Прⷪро́къ бж҃їй ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆сѝ, сꙋгꙋ́бꙋю бл҃года́ть прїе́мъ, вои́стиннꙋ досто́йнꙋю тебѐ, є҆лїссе́е бл҃же́нне: и҆лїи́ бо бы́лъ є҆сѝ совсе́льникъ, съ ни́мже хрⷭтꙋ̀ бг҃ꙋ моли́сѧ непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Prophet Elisha (Elisei)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Prophet Elisha (Elisei) lived in the IX Century before the Birth of Christ, and was a native of the village of Abelmaum, near Jordan. By the command of the Lord he was called to prophetic service by the holy Prophet of God Eliah (Ilias, Elijah) (Comm. 20 July). 	When it became time for the holy Prophet Eliah to be taken up to Heaven, he said to Elisha: &quot;Ask, what shalt I do for thee, before that I be taken from thee&quot;. Elisha boldly asked for a double portion of the grace of God: &quot;The Spirit, which be in thee, let it be upon me twofold&quot;. The Prophet Eliah said: &quot;Thou dost ask the difficult; if thou seest as I be taken from thee, then so shalt it be for thee, but if thou seest not, it wilt not be&quot; (4[2]Kings 2: 12). And when they went along the way and conversed, there appeared a fiery chariot and horses and parted them both. Elisha cried out: &quot;My father, my father, the chariot of Israel and its horse!&quot; (4 [2] Kings 2: 12). Picking up the cloak (mantle) of his teacher which fell from the sky, Elisha received the power and prophetic gift of Eliah. He spent more than 65 years in prophetic service, under six Israelite kings (from Ahab to Joash). &quot;And in those days he trembled not before the prince, and no one could overcome him&quot; (Sirach 48: 13 [&quot;Sirach&quot; in the canon of Old Testament books is found in Catholic but not Protestant English translations of the Bible, rendered as &quot;Ecclesiasticus&quot;]). The holy prophet worked numerous miracles. He divided the waters of the Jordan, having smitten it with the mantle of the Prophet Eliah; he made fit for drinking the waters of a Jericho spring; by an abundant bringing forth of water by his prayer he saved the armies of the kings of Israel and Judah that stood in an arid wilderness; he delivered a poor widow from death by starvation through a miraculous increase of oil in a vessel. The Shunamite woman showing hospitality to the prophet was gladdened by the birth of a son through his prayer, and when the child died, he was raised back to life by the prophet. The Syrian military-commander Namaan was healed from leprosy but the servant of the prophet, Gehazi, was afflicted since he disobeyed the prophet and on the sly took money from Namaan. Elisha predicted to the Israelite king Joash the victory over his enemies and by the power of his prayer worked many other miracles (4 [2] Kings 3-13). The holy Prophet Elisha died in old age at Samaria. &quot;And in life he worked miracles, and at death astounding was his deed&quot; (Sir. 48: 15). A year after his death, a corpse was thrown into the cave wherein lay his remains, and came alive by a mere touch to his bones. The Prophet Elisha, just like his teacher the Prophet Eliah, left behind them no books, since their prophetic preaching was but oral. Jesus, son of Sirach, inscribed eulogistic praise to both the great prophets (Sir. 48: 1-15). 	Saint John Damascene compiled a canon in honour of the Prophet Elisha, and at Constantinople a church was built in his name. 	Julian the Apostate (361-363) gave orders to burn the relics of the Prophet Elisha, Abdia (Obadiah) and John the Forerunner, but the remains of the holy relics were preserved by believers, and part of them were transferred to Alexandria. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
The angel in the flesh, the foundation of the prophets,/ the second forerunner of the coming of Christ,/ the glorious Elijah from on high sent down grace upon Elisha/ to dispel infirmities and to cleanse lepers.// Wherefore, he poureth forth healings upon those who honor him.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Thou wast shown to be a prophet of God,/ receiving a twofold measure of grace,/ which truly befitted thee, O blessed Elisha;/ for thou wast the companion of Elijah,// and with him dost unceasingly entreat Christ God in behalf of us all.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>