<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые мученики Ермил и Стратоник"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святые мученики Ермил и Стратоник, по происхождению сла- вяне, жили в начале IV века, при гонителе христиан императоре Ликинии (307—324), и были друзьями. Святой Ермил служил диа- коном в городе Сингидоне (Белград). Осужденный Ликинием на тюремное заключение, он был долго и жестоко мучим за Имя Христово, но остался непреклонным. Святой Стратоник был тю- ремным надзирателем и тайным христианином. Видя страшные мучения своего друга, он не мог удержаться от слез и обнаружил себя христианином. Его также подвергли мучениям. После истяза- ний мучеников зашили в сети и бросили в Дунай. Тела святых на третий день были найдены христианами на берегу реки и по- гребены близ Сингидона. Честные главы их находились в храме святой Софии в Константинополе, где в 1200 году их видел рус- ский паломник Антоний. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Мч҃нцы твоѝ гдⷭи, во страда́нїихъ свои́хъ вѣнцы̀ прїѧ́ша нетлѣ҄нныѧ ѿ тебѐ бг҃а на́шегѡ: и҆мꙋ́ще бо крѣ́пость твою̀ мꙋчи́телей низложи́ша, сокрꙋши́ша и҆ де́мѡнѡвъ немощны҄ѧ де́рзѡсти. тѣ́хъ моли́твами сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Martyrs Ermil and Stratonik"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Martyrs Ermil and Stratonik, by origin Slavs, lived at the beginning of the IV Century during the time of persecution against Christians by the emperor Licinius (307-324). They were friends. Saint Ermil served as deacon in the city of Singedonum (Belgrade). Condemned by Licinius to imprisonment, he was long and cruelly tortured for the Name of Christ, but he remained unyielding. Saint Stratonik was a superintendent of the prison and a secret christian. Seeing the agonising torments of his friend, he was not able to keep from weeping, and he revealed that he was a christian. They subjected him also to torture. After the torturing, they put the martyrs into a net and threw them into the Danube/Dunai. On the third day, the bodies of the saints were discovered on the bank of the river by christians and buried near Singedonum. Their venerable heads are located in the Church of Saint Sophia, where the Russian pilgrim Antonii saw them in the year 1200. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
n their sufferings, O Lord,/ Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God;/ for, possessed of Thy might,/ they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons.// By their supplications save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>