<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Василий исповедник, епископ Парийский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобный Василий исповедник, епископ Парийский, жил в VIII веке. Он был избран на епископскую кафедру жителями го- рода Парии, почитавшими святителя как истинного пастыря стада Христова.    Когда возникла иконоборческая ересь, святитель Василий ре- шительно выступил за почитание святых икон и отказался подпи- сать постановление об их уничтожении («Неправедный свиток» Собора 754 года, созванного при Константине Копрониме (741— 775)). Святитель избегал всякого общения с еретиками и не допу- скал их в свою епархию. За свою ревность он претерпел многие гонения, голод и нищету.    До конца своей жизни святитель Василий был верен право- славному исповеданию. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Вы́шнѧгѡ свѣ́томъ ѡ҆зари́всѧ бл҃же́нне, просвѣща́еши всѧ҄, и҆̀же любо́вїю чествꙋ́ющыѧ твоѐ ѻ҆́тче честно́е страда́нїе васї́лїе сщ҃еннострада́льне: молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а непреста́ннѡ ѡ҆ всѣ́хъ на́съ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Basil the Confessor, Bishop of Para"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Basil the Confessor, Bishop of Para, lived during the VIII Century. He was chosen to the bishop&apos;s chair by the inhabitants of Para, who venerated the saint as a true pastor of the flock of Christ. 	When the Iconoclast heresy broke out, Saint Basil resolutely came out on the side of icon veneration and refused to sign the directives for their abolition (the &quot;IniquitousScroll&quot; of the Council of 754 which had convened under the emperor Constantine V Copronymos (741-775). The saint shunned any contact with the heretics and did not permit them into his diocese. For his zeal he suffered much persecution, hunger and deprivation. 	To the very end of his life Saint Basil was faithful to the Orthodox confession. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Illumined by the light of the Most High, O blessed father, thou dost enlighten all who with love venerate thine honored suffering. O sacred athlete Basil, entreat Christ God unceasingly in behalf of us all!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>