<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Акакий, епископ Мелитинский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
    Преподобный Акакий, епископ Мелитинский, родился в благо- честивой семье в армянском городе Мелитина. Родители его дол- го были бездетными и, молясь о ребенке, обещали посвятить его Богу. Поэтому отрока Акакия отдали Мелитинскому епископу Отрию на служение Церкви. Святитель Отрий был твердым по- борником Православия. Когда возникла ересь Македония, святи- тель Отрий па II Вселенском Соборе (381) отстаивал Православ- ное учение о Святом Духе как Третьем Лице Святой Единосущ- ной и Нераздельной Троицы.    Святитель с любовью воспитывал Акакия, поставил его в чте- ца, а затем посвятил в сан диакона и во священника. Святой Ака- кий преданно служил Церкви. Он обучал взрослых и детей Свя- щенному Писанию, Православному исповеданию христианской веры.    Среди его учеников был такой светильник Церкви, как пре- подобный Евфимий Великий (+ 473; память 20 января).     После кончины святителя Отрия по всеобщему согласию на епископский престол Мелитины был возведен святой Акакий. Он мудро управлял своей епархией. Твердой верой, смирением и под- вигами святитель стяжал дар чудотворения. Однажды, когда в засушливое лето святитель совершал Божественную литургию в открытом поле, вино в Святой Чаше было растворено внезапно прошедшим дождем, напоившим всю землю. По его молитве раз- лившаяся во время наводнения горная река не пошла дальше камня, положенного им на берегу. На одном из островов реки Азар святитель, несмотря на сопротивление язычников, устроил храм в честь Пресвятой Богородицы. Строители храма по нера- дению или по злому умыслу непрочно построили свод. Во время литургии свод прогнулся и готов был упасть. Народ в страхе уст- ремился из храма. Но святитель остановил бегущих возгласом: «Господь Защититель живота моего, кого устрашуся?» (Пс. 26, 1). Свод остановился и как бы повис в воздухе. Лишь когда кончи- лось Богослужение и святитель последним вышел из храма, свод рухнул, не причинив никому вреда. После этого храм был отстро- ен вновь.    Святитель Акакий был участником III Вселенского Собора (431) и отстаивал Православное исповедание двух естеств (Бо- жественного и человеческого) Спасителя и Его бессеменного Рож- дества от Пресвятой Девы Богородицы. Святитель Акакий с миром отошел ко Господу около 435 года. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Akakios, Bishop of Melitinea"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Akakios, Bishop of Melitinea, was born into a pious family in the Armenian city of Melitinea. His parents for a long time were childless, and in praying for a son, they vowed to dedicate him to God. Therefore the lad Akakios was given over to the Melitinea bishop Ostrios for the service of the Church. Sainted Ostrios was a firm supporter of Orthodoxy. When the heresy of Macedonias arose, it was Saint Ostrios at the Second OEcumenical Council (381) that set forth the Orthodox teaching about the HolySpirit as the Third Person of the Holy Trinity One-in-Essence and Undivided. 	The sainted-hierarch with love raised Akakios, made him a reader, and then ordained him to the dignity of deacon and then to priest. Saint Akakios devoutly served the Church. He instructed both adults and children in the Holy Scripture, and in the Orthodox Confession of faith.  	Among his students was such a luminary of the Church as the Monk Euthymios the Great (Comm. 20 January). 	After the death of Saint Ostrios, by general acclamation Saint Akakios was elevated to the bishop&apos;s throne of Melitinea. He wisely governed his diocese. By his firm faith, humility and deeds, the saint acquired the gift of wonderworking. One time, when during a dry Summer the saint made Liturgy in an open field, the wine in the Holy Chalice was mixed suddenly by the falling rain, which fell throughout all the land. Through his prayer during a time of flooding an advancing river flowed off and did not come higher than the stone which he had placed at the riverbank. On one of the islands of the River Azar, despite the opposition of the pagans, the saint built a temple in honour of the MostHoly Mother of God. The builders of the church either through carelessness or through malice defectively built the dome. During the time of Liturgy the dome gave way and was ready to collapse. The people in terror rushed out of the church. But the saint halted the fleeing with the exclamation: &quot;The Lord is Defender of my life, of what shalt I be afraid?&quot; (Ps. 26 [27]: 1). The dome remained as though suspended in the air. Only when the Divine-services were ended, and the saint was the last one to emerge from the church, did the dome collapse, causing harm to no one. After this the church was rebuilt again.  	Sainted Akakios was a participant in the Third OEcumenical Council (431) and he defended the Orthodox Confession of the Two Natures (Divine and Human) of the Saviour, and of His Birth without seed from the MostHoly Virgin Mother of God. Saint Akakios peacefully expired to the Lord in about the year 435.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>