<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Иоанн"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Преподобный Иоанн родился в конце VIII века. В юношеском возрасте он стал учеником преподобного Григория Декаполита (I ок. 820, память 20 ноября) и принял от него иноческий постриг в Солунском монастыре. Под руководством опытного учителя пре- подобный Иоанн достиг высокого духовного совершенства.    Когда император Лев Армянин (813—820) возобновил гонение на православных христиан за почитание святых икон, преподобный Григорий Декаполит вместе с преподобным Иосифом Песнописцем (\ ок. 820, память 4 апреля) и своим учеником преподобным Иоанном отправился из Солуни в Константинополь, чтобы проти- водействовать иконоборческой ереси. Несколько лет, невзирая на гонения, святые Григорий и Иоанн безбоязненно защищали Пра- вославие, проповедуя почитание святых икон. После многих тру- дов преподобный Григорий скончался (около 820 года), а вскоре за ним отошел ко Господу и его верный ученик Иоанн. Преподоб- ный Иосиф Песнописец перенес мощи святых Григория и Иоанна в построенную им церковь во имя святителя Николая Чудотворца. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Воздержа́нїемъ ѻ҆́тче, житїѐ ѹ҆краси́въ, и҆ пло́ть ѹ҆мертви́лъ є҆сѝ: тѣ́мже и҆ побѣди́лъ є҆сѝ вра҄жїѧ прило́ги пребл҃же́нне, и҆ преше́лъ є҆сѝ къ бг҃ꙋ въ безско́рбный и҆ вѣ́чный живо́тъ, ꙗ҆́кѡ досто́инъ наслѣ́дникъ ї҆ѡа́нне: є҆мꙋ́же моли́сѧ сп҃сти́сѧ на́мъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk John"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk John was born at the end of the VIII Century. At a young age he became a disciple of the Monk Gregory Dekapolites (+ c. 820, Comm. 20 November) and accepted monastic tonsure from him at the Soluneia (Thessalonika) monastery. Under the guidance of this experienced teacher, the Monk John attained to high spiritual accomplishment. 	When the emperor Leo the Armenian (813-820) renewed the persecution against Orthodox Christians because of their veneration of holy icons, the Monk Gregory Dekapolites together with the Monk Joseph the Writer of Church-Song (+ c. 863, Comm.4 April) and his student the Monk John set off from Soluneia to Constantinople, to muster opposition to the Iconoclast heresy. In spite of persecution, for several years Saints Gregory and John fearlessly defended Orthodoxy, and preached veneration of holy icons. After many hardships the Monk Gregory died (in about the year 820), and soon after him his faithful student John also expired to the Lord. The Monk Joseph the Song-Writer transferred the relics of Saints Gregory and John and placed them in a church of Saint Nicholas the Wonderworker.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="2">
Adorning thy life with abstinence, O father,/ thou didst mortify thy flesh;/ wherefore , thou didst vanquish the attacks of the enemy, O all-blessed John,/ and hast passed over to God,/ to life everlasting free from sorrow, as a worthy heir.// Pray thou to Him, that we be saved.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>