<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Иоанн Златоуст"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Святитель Иоанн Златоуст — великий вселенский учитель и иерарх, скончался в 407 году в городе Команы на пути к месту ссылки, осужденный по проискам императрицы Евдоксии за сме- лое обличение пороков, царивших в Константинополе. Перенесение его честных мощей из Коман в Константинополь совершилось в 438 году, через 30 лет после смерти святителя, при сыне Евдок- сии императоре Феодосии II (408—450).     Святитель Иоанн Златоуст пользовался горячей любовью и глубоким уважением народа, и скорбь о его безвременной кон- чине жила в сердцах христиан. Ученик святителя Иоанна, святой Прокл, Патриарх Константинопольский (434—447), совершая Бо- гослужение в храме Святой Софии, произнес проповедь, в которой, прославляя святителя Иоанна, говорил: «О Иоанн! Жизнь твоя многотрудна, но смерть славна, гроб твой блажен и воздаяние обильно по благодати и милосердию Господа нашего Иисуса Христа. О благЪдать, препобеждающая пределы, место и время! Место препобедила любовь, предел уничтожила незабвенная па- мять, и местом не ограничились чудеса святителя». Присутство- вавшие в храме, глубоко тронутые словом святителя Прокла, не дали даже ему окончить проповедь и стали единодушно умолять Патриарха ходатайствовать перед императором, чтобы мощи свя- тителя Иоанна были перенесены в Константинополь. Император, убежденный святителем Проклом, дал согласие и повелел пере- нести мощи святителя Иоанна, но посланные им люди никак не могли поднять святые мощи до тех пор, пока император, поняв свою ошибку, не прислал послание к святителю Иоанну, смирен- но прося у него прощения за себя и за свою мать Евдоксию. По- слание зачитали у гроба святителя Иоанна и после этого легко подняли мощи, внесли их на корабль и доставили в Константи- нополь. Рака с мощами была поставлена в церкви святой муче- ницы Ирины. Патриарх открыл гроб: тело святителя Иоанна ока- залось нетленным. Царь, припав к гробу со слезами, просил про- щения. Народ весь день и ночь не отходил от раки. Наутро рака с мощами святителя была перенесена в церковь святых Апостолов. Народ воскликнул: «Приими престол твой, отче!» Тогда Патриарх Прокл и клирики, стоявшие у раки, увидели, что святитель Иоанн открыл уста и произнес: «Мир всем».    В IX веке на праздник в честь перенесения мощей святителя Иоанна Златоуста написаны церковные песнопения. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Ѹ҆́стъ твои́хъ ꙗ҆́коже свѣ́тлость ѻ҆гнѧ̀ возсїѧ́вши бл҃года́ть, вселе́ннꙋю просвѣтѝ. не сребролю́бїѧ мї́рови сокрѡ́вища сниска̀, высотꙋ̀ на́мъ смиреномꙋ́дрїѧ показа̀: но твои́ми словесы̀ наказꙋ́ѧ, ѻ҆́тче ї҆ѡа́нне златоꙋ́сте, молѝ сло́ва хрⷭта̀ бг҃а, сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1" Podoben="2">
Возвесели́сѧ та́инственнѡ чⷭтна́ѧ цр҃ковь, возвраще́нїемъ чⷭтны́хъ твои́хъ моще́й, и҆ сїѧ҄ сокры́вши ꙗ҆́кѡ зла́то многоцѣ́нное, пою́щымъ тѧ̀ неѡскꙋ́днѡ подава́етъ мл҃твами твои́ми и҆сцѣле́нїй бл҃года́ть, ї҆ѡа́нне златоꙋ́сте. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted John Chrysostom"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted John Chrysostom -- a great ecumenical teacher and hierarch, died in the city of Comene in the year 407 on his way to a place of exile, having been condemned by the intrigues of the empress Eudoxia because of his daring denunciation of the vices ruling over Constantinople. The transfer of his venerable relics was made in the year 438: after 30 years following the death of the saint during the reign of Eudoxia&apos;s son emperor Theodosius II (408-450).  	Saint John Chrysostom had the warm love and deep respect of the people, and grief over his untimely death lived on in the hearts of christians. Saint John&apos;s student Saint Proclus, Patriarch of Constantinople (434-447), making Divine-services in the Church of Saint Sophia, preached a sermon which in glorifying Saint John he said: &quot;O John! Thy life was filled with difficulties, but thy death was glorious, thy grave is blessed and reward abundant through the grace and mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ. O graced one, having conquered the bounds of time and place! Love hath conquered space, unforgetting memory hath annihilated the limits, and place doth not hinder the miracles of the saint&quot;. Those who were present in church, deeply touched by the words of Saint Proclus, did not allow him even to finish his sermon. With one accord they began to entreat the Patriarch to intercede with the emperor, so that the relics of Saint John might be transferred to Constantinople. The emperor, overwhelmed by Saint Proclus, gave his consent and made the order to transfer the relics of Saint John. But the people dispatched by him were by no means able to lift up the holy relics -- not until that moment when the emperor realising his oversight that he had not sent the message to Saint John, humbly beseeching of him forgiveness for himself and for his mother Eudoxia. The message was read at the grave of Saint John and after this they easily lifted up the relics, carried them onto a ship and arrived at Constantinople. The reliquary coffin with the relics was placed in the Church of the holy Martyr Irene. The Patriarch opened the coffin: the body of Saint John had remained without decay. The emperor, having approached the coffin with tears, asked forgiveness. All day and night people did not leave the coffin. In the morning the reliquary coffin with its relics was brought to the Church of the Holy Apostles. The people cried out: &quot;Receive back thy throne, father!&quot; Then Patriarch Proclus and the clergy standing at the relics -- saw Saint John open his mouth and pronounce: &quot;Peace be to all&quot;. 	In the IX Century the feastday in honour of the transfer of the relics of Sainted John Chrysostom was written into church singing.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Grace shining forth from thy mouth like a beacon hath illumined the universe,/ and disclosed to the world treasures of uncovetousness, and shown us the heights of humility;/ but while instructing by thy words, O father John Chrysostom,// intercede with the Word, Christ our God, to save our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1" Podoben="2">
The honored Church was mystically gladdened by the return of thy precious relics;/ and having hidden them like most precious gold,/ by thy supplication she bountifully imparteth the grace of healings unto them that hymn thee,// O John Chrysostom.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>