<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Первое (IV) и второе (452) обретение главы Иоанна Предтечи"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   После усекновения главы Пророка, Предтечи и Крестителя Господня Иоанна (память29 августа), тело его было погребено уче- никами в самарийском городе Севастии, а честная глава сокрыта Иродиадой в бесчестном месте. Благочестивая Иоанна, жена цар- ского домоправителя Хузы (о ней упоминает святой евангелист Лука — Лк. 8, 3), тайно взяла святую главу, положила ее в сосуд и погребла на горе Елеонской — в одном из поместий Ирода. Через много лет поместье это перешло во владение благочести- вому вельможе Иннокентию, который стал строить там церковь. Когда копали ров для фундамента, был обретен сосуд с честной главой Иоанна Крестителя. Иннокентий узнал о величии святыни по бывшим от нее благодатным знамениям. Так произошло Первое обретение главы. Иннокентий хранил ее с величайшим благого- вением, но перед своей смертью, боясь, как бы святыня не была поругана неверными, он снова скрыл ее в том самом месте, где обрел... По кончине его церковь пришла в запустение и раз- рушилась.    В дни равноапостольного царя Константина Великого (1 337, память 21 мая), когда христианская вера стала процветать, двум инокам, пришедшим в Иерусалим на поклонение святым местам, дважды явился сам святой Предтеча и открыл место нахождения своей честной главы. Иноки отрыли святыню и, положив ее в ме- шок из верблюжьей шерсти, пошли к себе домой. По дороге они встретили незнакомого горшечника и дали ему нести драгоценную ношу. Не зная, что он несет, горшечник спокойно продолжал путь. Но ему явился сам святой Предтеча и велел- бежать от нерадивых и ленивых иноков вместе с тем, что было у него в руках. Горшеч- ник скрылся от иноков и дома с почестью хранил честную главу. Перед смертью он запечатал ее в водоносный сосуд и передал сестре. С тех пор честная глава была преемственно хранима бла- гоговейными христианами, пока ее обладателем не стал священ- ник Евстафий, зараженный арианской ересью. Он совратил множество недужных, исцелившихся от святой главы, приписывая благодать еретичеству. Когда его кощунство открылось, он был вынужден бежать. Закопав святыню в пещере, близ Емессы, ере- тик рассчитывал впоследствии вернуться и снова овладеть ею для распространения лжеучения. Но Бог не допустил этого. В пещере  поселились благочестивые иноки, а потом на этом месте возник  монастырь. В 452 г. архимандриту этой обители Маркеллу святой  Иоанн Креститель в видении указал место сокрытия своей главы. Это обретение стало праздноваться как второе. Святыня была  перенесена в Емессу, а затем в Константинополь. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
Ѿ землѝ возсїѧ́вши прⷣте́чева глава̀, лꙋчы̀ и҆спꙋща́етъ нетлѣ́нїѧ, вѣ҄рнымъ и҆сцѣле́нїй, свы́ше собира́етъ мно́жество а҆́гг҃лъ, до́лѣ же созыва́етъ человѣ́ческїй ро́дъ, є҆диногла́снꙋю возсыла́ти сла́вꙋ хрⷭтꙋ̀ бг҃ꙋ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Прⷪро́че бж҃їй и҆ прⷣте́че бл҃года́ти, главꙋ̀ твою̀ ꙗ҆́кѡ ши́покъ сщ҃е́ннѣйшїй ѿ землѝ ѡ҆брѣ́тше, и҆сцѣлє́нїѧ всегда̀ прїе́млемъ: и҆́бо па́ки ꙗ҆́коже пре́жде въ мї́рѣ проповѣ́дꙋеши покаѧ́нїе. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="The First (IV) and the Second Discovery of the Head of John the ForeRunner"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
After the cutting off of the Head of the Prophet, ForeRunner and Baptist John (Comm. 29 August), his body was buried by disciples in the Samarian city of Sebasteia, and the venerable head was hidden by Herodias in an unclean place. Pious Joanna, wife of king Herod&apos;s steward Chuza (there is made mention about him by the holy evangelist Luke -- Lk 8: 3), secretly took the holy head and placed it into a vessel and buried it on the Mount of Olives -- in one of the properties of Herod. After many years this property passed into the possession of the dignitary Innocentius, who began to build a church there. When they dug a trench for the foundation, the vessel with the venerable head of John the Baptist was uncovered. Innocentius recognised the great holiness of it from the signs of grace occurring from it. Thus occurred the First Discovery of the Head. Innocentius preserved it with great piety, but before his own death, fearful so that the holy relic should not be abused by unbelievers, he again hid it in that same place, where it was found...Upon his death the church fell into ruin and was destroyed. 	During the days of Equal-to-the-Apostles Constantine the Great (+ 337, Comm. 21 May), when the Christian faith began to flourish, the holy ForeRunner himself appeared twice unto two monks journeying to Jerusalem on pilgrimage to the holy places, and he revealed the location of his venerable head. The monks uncovered the holy relic and, placing it into a sack of camel-hair, they proceeded homewards. Along the way they encountered an un-named potter and gave him to carry the precious burden. Not knowing what he was carrying, the potter continued on his way. But the holy ForeRunner himself appeared to him and ordered him to flee from the careless and lazy monks, together with that which was in his hands. The potter concealed himself from the monks and at home he preserved the venerable head with reverence. Before his death he sealed it into a water-carrying vessel and gave it over to his sister. From that time the venerable head was successively preserved by pious christians, until the priest Eustathios infected with the Arian heresy -- came into possession of it. He seduced a multitude of the infirm, healed by the holy head, adding abundance to the heresy. When his blasphemy was uncovered, he was compelled to flee. Having buried the holy relic in a cave, near Emessus, the heretic intended to afterwards return and again take possession of it for disseminating falsehood. But God did not permit this. Pious monks settled into the cave, and then at this place arose a monastery. In the year 452 Saint John the Baptist in a vision to the archimandrite of this monastery Marcellus indicated the place of concealment of his head. This became celebrated as the Second Discovery. The holy relic was transferred to Emessus, and later to Constantinople.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">
The head of the Forerunner,/ which hath shone forth from the earth,/ doth shed rays of incorruption/ and healing upon the faithful./ On High it assembleth a multitude of angels,/ and below it calleth upon the human race// with one voice to send up glory to Christ God.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
O prophet of God and Forerunner of grace,/ having obtained thy head from the earth like a most sacred rose,/ we ever receive healings,// for again, as of old, thou dost preach repentance in the world.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>