<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Петр Афонский"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Преподобный Петр Афонский, родом грек, служил воеводой в императорских войсках и жил в Константинополе. В 667 году во время войны с сирийцами святой Петр был взят в плен и за- ключен в крепости города Самары на реке Евфрате. Долгое время он томился в темнице и размышлял о том, за какие грехи подвергся наказанию Божию. Святой Петр вспомнил, что однажды имел намерение оставить мир и уйти в монастырь, но так и не исполнил его. Он стал соблюдать в темнице строгий пост, усердно молиться и просил у святителя Николая Чудотвор- ца заступничества перед Богом. Святитель Николай явился свя- тому Петру во сне и дал совет призывать на помощь святого Симеона Богоприимца. Укрепляя узника в терпении и надежде, святитель еще раз являлся ему во сне. В третий раз он явился вместе со святым Симеоном Богоприимцем наяву. Святой Симеон коснулся жезлом цепей святого Петра, и железо при этом растая- ло, словно воск. Двери темницы раскрылись, и святой Петр вышел на свободу. Святой Симеон Богоприимец стал невидим, а свя- титель Николай проводил святого Петра до границы греческой земли. Напомнив об обете, святитель Николай также стал неви- дим. Для принятия иноческого образа при гробнице апостола Пет- ра святой Петр ушел в Рим. Святитель Николай не оставил его без своей помощи: он явился во сне Римскому Папе и рассказал об обстоятельствах освобождения святого Петра из плена, нака- зав Папе постричь бывшего узника в монашество. На следующий день, при многолюдном стечении народа во время Богослужения, Папа громко сказал: «Петр, пришедший из греческой земли, которого святитель Николай освободил в Сама- ре из темницы, приди ко мне». Святой Петр предстал перед Па- пой, который постриг его в монашество при гробнице апостола Петра. Папа учил святого Петра правилам иноческой жизни и держал инока при себе. Потом он с благословением отпустил свя- того Петра туда, куда Бог соблаговолит его направить. Святой Петр сел на корабль, плывший на восток. Корабель- щики, во время остановки сходившие на берег, просили святого Петра придти помолиться в один дом, где хозяин и все домаш- ние лежали больные. Святой Петр исцелил их своей молитвой. Во сне святому Петру явилась Пресвятая Богородица и указа- ла место, где он должен был жить до конца своих дней — Свя- тую Гору Афон. Когда корабль проплывал мимо Афона, то оста- новился сам по себе. Святой Петр понял, что в этом месте ему надлежит сойти, и сошел на берег. Это было в 681 году. Препо- добный Петр провел в пустынных местах Святой Горы, не видя никого из людей, 53 года. Одежда его истлела,, а волосы и борода отросли и покрыли тело вместо одежды. В первое время преподобный Петр многократно подвергался бесовским нападениям. Стараясь принудить святого покинуть пе- щеру, бесы принимали вид то вооруженных воинов, то свирепых зверей и гадов, готовых растерзать отшельника. Но горячей мо- литвой к Богу и Матери Божией преподобный Петр побеждал бесовские нападения. Тогда враг стал действовать хитростью. Явившись под видом отрока, посланного к нему из родного дома, он со слезами умолял преподобного оставить пустыню и вер- нуться в свой дом. Преподобный прослезился, но без колебаний ответил: «Сюда меня привел Господь и Пресвятая Богородица, без Ее позволения я отсюда не пойду». Услышав имя Матери Божией, бес исчез. Через семь лет бес предстал перед преподобным в виде свет- лого Ангела и сказал, что Бог повелевает ему идти в мир для просвещения и спасения нуждавшихся в его руководстве людей. Опытный подвижник снова ответил, что без повеления Божией Матери не покинет пустыни. Бес исчез и больше не смел присту- пать к преподобному. Матерь Божия явилась преподобному Пет- ру во сне вместе со святителем Николаем и сказала мужествен- ному отшельнику, что каждые 40 дней Ангел будет приносить ему Небесную манну. С того времени преподобный Петр 40 дней постился, а на сороковой день подкреплялся Небесной ман- ной, получая крепость на дальнейшее сорокадневное воздер- жание. Однажды охотник, гнавшийся за оленем, увидел нагого чело- века, обросшего волосами и препоясанного по чреслам листвой. Он испугался и бросился бежать. Преподобный Петр остановил его и рассказал о своей жизни. Охотник просил позволения ос- таться с ним, но святой отослал его домой. Преподобный Петр дал охотнику год для самоиспытания и запретил рассказывать о встрече с ним. Через год охотник возвратился с братом, одержимым бесом, и другими спутниками. Когда они вошли в пещеру преподобного Петра, то увидели, что он уже преставился к Богу. Охотник с горьким плачем рассказал своим спутникам о жизни преподобно- го Петра, а его брат, как только прикоснулся к телу святого, получил исцеление. Преподобный Петр скончался в 734 году. Его святые мощи находились на Афоне в обители святого Климента. Во время иконоборчества они были сокрыты, а в 969 году пере- несены во Фракийское селение Фотоками. С именем преподобного Петра Афонского связан священный завет Матери Божией о сво- ем земном уделе — Святой Горе Афон, который и поныне оста- ется в силе: «Во Афонстей Горе будет покой его, то бо есть жре- бий Мой от Сына Моего и Бога, данный Мне, да отлучающийся мирских молв и емлющиися духовных по силе своей подвигов, верою же и любовию от души призывающий имя Мое, тамо вре- менное свое житие проводят без печали, и Богоугодных ради дел своих жизнь вечную получат: зело бо люблю то место и хощу на том умножити чин иноческий, и милость Моего Сына и Бога имущим тамо иночествовати не разорится во веки, аще и они соблюдут спасительныя заповеди; и распространю их в Горе на юг и север, и возобладают ею от мира до мира, и имя их во всей подсолнечной хвально сотворю и защищу тех, иже тамо терпе- ливно в постничестве подвизатися будут» (О Святой Горе Афон — «Журнал Московской Патриархии», 1974, NoNo 3—5, 8). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е ѻ҆тє́цъ на́шихъ, творѧ́й при́снѡ съ на́ми по твое́й кро́тости, не ѡ҆ста́ви млⷭть твою̀ ѿ на́съ, но мл҃твами и҆́хъ въ ми́рѣ ѹ҆пра́ви живо́тъ на́шъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Ѹ҆дали́въ себѐ человѣ́ческагѡ сожи́тельства, въ пеще́рахъ ка́менныхъ и҆ разсѣ́линахъ пожи́лъ є҆сѝ жела́нїемъ бж҃е́ственнымъ: и҆ любо́вїю, пе́тре, гдⷭа твоегѡ̀, ѿ негѡ́же вѣне́цъ прїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ, молѝ непреста́ннѡ сп҃сти́сѧ на́мъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk Peter of Athos"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk Peter of Athos, a Greek by birth, served as a soldier in the imperial armies and he lived at Constantinople. In the year 667 during the time of a war with the Syrians, Saint Peter was taken captive and locked up in a fortress in the city of Samara on the River Euphrates. 	For a long time he languished in prison and he pondered over what sins of his had incurred the chastisement of God. Saint Peter remembered, that once upon a time he had the intention to leave the world and go off to a monastery, but he had not done so. He began to observe strict fast in the prison and to pray fervently, and he besought of Saint Nicholas the Wonderworker to intercede before God for him. Saint Nicholas appeared in a dream to Saint Peter and advised him to call for help on Saint Simeon the God-Receiver. And encouraging the prisoner in patience and hope, Saint Nicholas once more appeared to him in a dream. The third time it was not in a dream that he appeared with Saint Simeon the God-Receiver. Saint Simeon touched his staff to the chains of Saint Peter, and the chains melted away, literally like wax. The doors of the prison opened up, and Saint Peter emerged to freedom. Saint Simeon the God-Receiver became invisible, but Saint Nicholas conveyed Saint Peter to the borders of the Greek lands. And reminding him of his vow, Saint Nicholas likewise became invisible. Saint Peter then journeyed to Rome to assume the monastic form at the tomb of the Apostle Peter. And even here Saint Nicholas did not leave without his help: he appeared in a dream to the Pope of Rome and informed him about the circumstances of Saint Peter&apos;s liberation from captivity, and he commanded the Pope to tonsure the former prisoner into monasticism. 	On the following day, amidst a numerous throng of the people during Divine-services, the Pope loudly exclaimed: &quot;Peter, thou who art come from the Greek lands, and whom Saint Nicholas hath freed from prison in Samara, come thou forth unto me&quot;. Saint Peter stood forth in front of the Pope, who tonsured him into monasticism at the tomb of the Apostle Peter. The Pope taught Saint Peter the rules of monastic life and kept the monk by him. And then with a blessing he sent off Saint Peter thither, whence God had blessed him to journey. 	Saint Peter boarded a ship, sailing to the East. The ship-owners, during a time of having come ashore, besought Saint Peter to come and pray at a certain house, wherein the owner and all the household lay sick. Saint Peter healed them through his prayer.  	The MostHoly Mother of God then appeared in a dream to Saint Peter and indicated the place, where he should live til the very end of his days -- Holy Mount Athos. When the ship sailed alongside Athos, it then halted of its own accord. Saint Peter realised, that this was the place he had to go, and so he went ashore. This was in the year 681. The Monk Peter then dwelt in the desolate places of the Holy Mountain, not seeing another person for 53 years. His clothing had tattered, but his hair and beard had grown out and covered his body in place of clothes.  	At first the Monk Peter was repeatedly subjected to demonic assaults. Trying to force the saint to abandon his cave, the devils took on the form at times of armed soldiers, and at other times of fierce beasts and vipers that seemed ready to tear apart the hermit. But through fervent prayer to God and the Mother of God, the Monk Peter conquered the demonic assaults. Then the enemy began to resort to trickery. Appearing under the guise of a lad, sent to him from his native home, he with tears besought the monk to leave the wilderness and return to his own home. The monk was in tears, but without hesitation answered: &quot;Hither have the Lord and the MostHoly Mother of God led me, and without Her leave I go not from hence&quot;. Hearing the Name of the Mother of God, the demon vanished. 	After seven years the devil came before the monk in the guise of a luminous angel and said, that God was commanding him to go into the world for the enlightening and salvation of people needful of his guidance. The experienced ascetic again replied, that without the permission of the Mother of God he would not forsake the wilderness. The devil disappeared and did not bother more to approach the saint. The Mother of God appeared to the Monk Peter in a dream together with Saint Nicholas and said to the brave hermit, that each 40 days an Angel would bring him Heavenly manna. From that time the Monk Peter fasted for 40 days, and on the fortieth day he fortified himself with the Heavenly manna, receiving the strength for further forty-day abstinence. 	One time an hunter, chasing after a stag, caught sight of the naked man, covered about with hair and girded about the loins with leaves. He took fright and was about to flee. The Monk Peter stopped him and told him about his life. The hunter asked leave to remain with him, but the saint sent him off home. The Monk Peter gave the hunter a year for self-examination and forbade him to tell about the meeting with him. 	A year later the hunter returned with his brother, afflicted with a demon, and together with several other companions. When they entered the cave of the Monk Peter, they then saw, that he had already reposed to God. The hunter amidst bitter sobs told his companions about the life of the Monk Peter, and his brother, with but a touch to the body of the saint, received healing. The Monk Peter died in the year 734. His holy relics were situated on Athos at the monastery of Saint Clement. During the Iconoclast period the relics were hidden away, and in the year 969 they were transferred to the Thracian village of Photokami. With the name of the Monk Peter of Athos is connected the sacred testimonial of the Mother of God about Her earthly appenage -- Holy Mount Athos, which even now presently remains in force: &quot;To Mount Athos let there be its peace, for this is allotted Me by My Son and God, given unto Me, wherein let them be separated from worldly whisperings and gathered together those spiritual in the power of their exploits, with faith and love in soul calling out My Name, thereupon to pass their earthly lifetime without travail, and for their God-pleasing deeds to receive life eternal: for exceedingly do I love this place and I do wish upon it the increase of monks, and they possessing the mercy of My Son and God thereupon as monks shalt never be undone, if they observe the saving commandments: and I shalt spread them forth upon the Mountain to the south and to the north, and they shalt possess it from the world til the end of the world, and their name throughout all under the sun I shalt make praiseworthy and so defend those, which there with patience would asceticise in fasting&quot;.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
O God of our fathers, who dealest always with us according to Thy meekness, take not away Thy mercy from us but through their prayers guide our lives in peace.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
Having withdrawn thyself from human companionship,/ out of divine desire and love for thy Lord, O Peter,/ thou didst dwell in caves of stone and deep ravines;/ and thou didst receive a crown from Him.// Pray thou unceasingly, that we be saved.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>