<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святитель Стефан"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святитель Стефан, просветитель Перми, апостол зырян, родил- ся около 1340 года в семье устюжского причетника Симеона. Под влиянием своей благочестивой матери Марии, обладая большими способностями, он с юных лет проявлял необыкновенное усердие к служению Церкви: в один год выучился читать Священные Кни- ги и помогал отцу в церкви при Богослужении, исполняя долж- ность канонарха и чтеца.    В молодости святой принял иночество в монастыре в честь святителя Григория Богослова в Ростове. Монастырь славился богатым книжным собранием. Святой Стефан хотел читать святых отцов в подлиннике и для этого изучал греческий язык. В юнос- ти, помогая отцу в церкви, он часто беседовал с зырянами. Те-  перь, овладев богатой церковной культурой, святой Стефан горел  желанием обратить зырян ко Христу.     Для просвещения зырян он составил азбуку их языка и пере- вел на него несколько церковных книг. За подвиги благочестия  Ростовский епископ Арсений (1374—1380) посвятил его в сан  иеродиакона. Приготовив себя к миссионерской деятельности, свя- титель Стефан явился в Москву (1379 г.) к Коломенскому еписко- пу Герасиму, который управлял тогда делами митрополии, и про- сил его: «Благослови меня, Владыко, идти в страну языческую — Пермь. Хочу учить святой вере неверных людей. Я решился или привести их ко Христу, или сложить у них за Христа голову». Епископ с радостью благословил его и посвятил в сан иеромона- ха. Он снабдил его антиминсами, святым миром и Богослужеб- ными книгами, а великий князь Димитрий Иоаннович дал ему охранные грамоты.     Из Устюга святой Стефан спустился по Северной Двине до впадения в нее Вычегды, откуда начинались поселения зырян. Много трудов, борьбы, лишений и скорбей вытерпел проповедник веры Христовой, живя среди язычников, поклонявшихся идолам, «огню, воде, деревьям, камню и золотой бабе, и кудесником, и волхвом, и древью».     Особо благоговели зыряне перед так называемой «прокудли- вой березой». Громадная по толщине и вышине береза росла на возвышенном месте. Зыряне собирались к ней и приносили в жертву добытых зверей. Святой Стефан поставил свою келлию невдалеке от березы и использовал собрания суеверных язычни- ков у дерева, чтобы учить их святой истине. Затем святой Стефан срубил и сжег березу для искоренения суеверия. Зыряне собира- лись убить его. Святой обратился к ним с проповедью: «Судите сами, сильны ли боги ваши, когда они не могут защитить себя от огня? Боги ли они, когда так немощны, да и не имеют не только смысла, но и слуха и зрения? И от меня,, слабого, не сумело защи- тить себя ваше божество. Не таковы же ли и все другие боги ваши? Не таков Бог Христианский. Он видит все, все знает и Всемогущ, ибо создал весь мир и о всем промышляет. И как Он благ, особенно к знающим Его! Я желаю вам добра, проповедуя вам Истинного Бога. Он будет любить вас, будет благотворить вам, когда станете чтить Его искренне». На месте «прокудливой березы» святой Стефан построил храм в честь Архангела Михаила, низложителя духов тьмы.     Крестившиеся зыряне сами стали истреблять то, чему раньше поклонялись: рубили священные деревья, сокрушали идолов; бо- гатые дары, предназначенные для языческих жертвенников, они приносили святому Стефану. Он велел служившему при нем зыря- нину Матфею все предавать огню и лишь дозволял употреблять полотно на обвертывание ног.     Но окончательный перелом в зырянах произошел после того, как святой Стефан посрамил их главного жреца Паму, который восстал против распространения святой веры. Жрец вступил в спор со святым Стефаном. «У вас„ христиан, — говорил Пама,— один Бог, а у нас много помощников и на суше, и на воде, подаю- щих нам счастливую ловлю в лесах и ее избытками снабжающих Москву, орду и дальние страны; они сообщают нам в волхвовании тайны, недоступные вам». Святой Стефан отвечал, что Истинный Бог — один; Всемогущество — одно, а бессилие богов-идолов оче- видно по опыту. После долгих споров жрец Пама в оправдание своей веры вызвался пройти сквозь огонь и воду и того же потребо- вал от святого Стефана. «Я не повелеваю стихиями, — смиренно отвечал святой Стефан,—но Христианский Бог велик: иду с тобой». Пама затрепетал и молил избавить его от верной смерти. «Вы сви- детели,— сказал святой Стефан собравшемуся народу, — сам он потребовал решить спор о вере огнем и водой и однако не хочет креститься. За кого считать теперь Паму? Что с ним делать?» «Обманщика предать смерти, — ответил народ, — если отпустить Паму, он наделает тебе пакостей». «Нет, — ответил святой, — Хри- стос меня послал не предавать кого-либо смерти, а учить. Пама не хочет принять спасительной веры, пусть его упорство накажет его, но не я». Пама был выгнан. В благодарность Господу за по- беду над главой язычников, святой Стефан построил на Вишере храм в честь святителя Николая. После этого проповедь святого о Христе стала идти все успешнее.     В 1383 году святой Стефан был поставлен епископом Малой Перми. Как любвеобильный отец он неустанно заботился о своей пастве. Для утверждения в вере новообращенных святитель Сте- фан при храмах открывал училища, где Священные Книги изуча- лись на пермском языке. Святитель присматривался к учащимся, учитывал их способности с тем, чтобы из них ставить священников и диаконов. Некоторых учеников святитель Стефан научил писать по-пермски. Святитель строил церкви, в которых ставил священ- ников из зырян, ввел Богослужение на зырянском языке.     Святитель Стефан перевел на зырянский язык Часослов, Псал- тирь, избранные чтения из Евангелия и Апостола, Паремийник, Стихирарь, Октоих, несколько праздничных служб и Божественную литургию.     Во время неурожая Святитель снабжал зырян хлебом, много раз избавлял их от насилия и взяток тиунов, облегчал им подати, защищал от нападений других племен, ходатайствуя за них в Мо- скве. Плодом его подвигов и добродетелей стало обращение всей обширной Пермской земли к христианству. Это великое дело было совершено силой веры и христианской любви. Жизнь святителя — это победа веры над неверием, любви и кротости — над злобой и нечестием.     Умилительно «заочное свидание» святителя Стефана Пермско- го с преподобным Сергием Радонежским, бывшее в 1390 году во время путешествия святителя в Москву по церковным делам. Свя- титель Стефан горячо любил Радонежского подвижника и очень желал повидаться с ним на пути из Пермской земли, но не мог исполнить этого из-за недостатка времени. Находясь в 10 верстах от монастыря преподобного Сергия, святитель Стефан, помолив- шись, обратился в сторону обители и с поклоном произнес: «Мир тебе, духовный брате!». Преподобный Сергий, который сидел вме- сте с братией за трапезой, встал, помолился и, поклонившись в ту сторону, где проезжал святитель, ответил: «Радуйся и ты, пасты- рю стада Христова, и мир Божий да пребывает с тобой!»     О глубокой духовной связи святителя Стефана Пермского и Преподобного Сергия Радонежского свидетельствует и ныне осо- бая повседневная молитва к ним на братской трапезе.     Кроме устройства церквей, святитель Стефан основал для зы- рян и несколько монастырей: Спасскую Ульяновскую пустынь в  165 верстах от Усть-Сысольска, Стефановскую — в 60 верстах от Усть-Сысольска, Усть-Вымскую Архангельскую, Яренгскую Ар-  хангельскую.     В 1395 году святитель Стефан снова отправился в Москву по делам паствы и здесь скончался. Тело его было положено в мо-  настыре «Спаса за стеною» (в храме на Бору в честь Спасителя)  в Московском Кремле. Горько оплакивали зыряне кончину своего  апостола. Они усиленно упрашивали Московского князя и Мит-  рополита отпустить в Пермь тело их наставника, но Москва не хо-  тела расстаться с останками великого святителя.     Прославление святителя Стефана началось еще в начале XV века. Житие было написано вскоре после смерти святителя в  1472 году. Службу ему составил иеромонах Пахомий Серб с  иеромонахом Епифанием Премудрым, учеником преподобного  Сергия Радонежского, который хорошо знал святителя и любил  с ним беседовать. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Бж҃е́ственнымъ жела́нїемъ ѿ ю҆́нагѡ во́зраста, стефа́не премꙋ́дре разже́гсѧ, ꙗ҆ре́мъ хрⷭто́въ взѧ́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ люде́й ѡ҆лѧденѣ҄вшаѧ дре́вле невѣ́рїемъ сердца̀, бж҃е́ственное сѣ́мѧ въ ни́хъ сѣ́ѧвъ, є҆ѵⷢльски дх҃о́внѣ породи́лъ є҆сѝ. тѣ́мже пресла́внꙋю твою̀ па́мѧть почита́юще мо́лимъ тѧ̀: молѝ є҆го́же проповѣ́далъ є҆сѝ, да сп҃се́тъ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Самозва́ненъ не и҆́щꙋщымъ тебѐ ст҃и́телю ѡ҆брѣ́лсѧ є҆сѝ, лю́ди ѿ ї҆́дѡльскїѧ ле́сти свободи́въ, ко хрⷭто́вѣй вѣ́рѣ приве́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ волхва̀ пансо́тника посрами́лъ є҆сѝ: тѣ́мже и҆ пе́рвый є҆пⷭкпъ и҆ ѹ҆чи́тель пе́рми бы́лъ є҆сѝ. сегѡ̀ ра́ди дꙋхѡ́внаѧ твоѧ҄ ча҄да, ꙗ҆́кѡ тобо́ю и҆зба́вльшесѧ ѿ ї҆́дѡлъ, бл҃года҄рнаѧ тебѣ̀ возопїе́мъ: ра́дꙋйсѧ стефа́не ѹ҆чи́телю премꙋ́дрый. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Sainted Stephen the Enlightener of Perm', and Apostle to the Zyryani People"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Sainted Stephen the Enlightener of Perm&apos;, and Apostle to the Zyryani People, was born in about the year 1340 into the family of the Ustiug church-assistant Simeon. Under the influence of his pious mother Maria, endowed with great abilities, he displayed already in his young years an unusual zeal for the service of the Church: in a single year he learned to read the Holy Books and he assisted his father in church during Divine-services, fulfilling the duty of kanonarch, arranging church music, and also that of reader. 	In youth the saint took monastic vows at a monastery in honour of Sainted Gregory the Theologian at Rostov. The monastery was famed for its fine collection of books. Saint Stephen wanted to read the holy fathers in the original and for this he studied the Greek language. In his youth when he had assisted his father in church, he frequently spoke with the Zyryani people. And now, having been immersed in the rich culture of the Church, Saint Stephen burned with a desire to convert the Zyryani to Christ.  	For the enlightening of the Zyryani, he compiled an alphabet of their language and translated into it some of the Church books. For his pious deed the Rostov bishop, Arsenii (1374-1380), ordained him to the dignity of monk-deacon. Having prepared himself for missionary activity, Saint Stephen journeyed to Moscow (1379) to the Kolomensk bishop, Gerasim, who then oversaw the affairs of the metropolitanate, and the saint petitioned him: &quot;Bless me, Vladyka, to go into a pagan land -- Perm&apos;. I want to teach the holy faith to the unbelieving people. I am resolved either to lead them to Christ, or for Christ to lay down my head for them&quot;. The bishop with joy blessed him and ordained him to the dignity of priest-monk. He provided him with an antimins (&quot;antimension&quot; or &quot;corporal&quot; for the altar-table), holy chrism and Divine-service books, and GreatPrince Dimitrii Ioannovich gave him a grammota (document) of safe-passage. 	From Ustiug Saint Stephen made his way along the North Dvina River up to the confluence of the Vychegda into it, where settlements of the Zyryani began. The proponent of faith in Christ suffered many a toil, and struggle, deprivation and sorrow, living amidst the pagans who worshipped idols &quot;with fire, water, trees, a stone and golden woman-figure, and shaman, and wizard, and wood&quot;. 	The Zyryani were wont to make their devotions particularly in front of a so-called &quot;magic-mischief birch tree&quot;. Immense in its thickness and height, the birch tree grew on an elevated spot. The Zyryani gathered at it and brought wild animals they caught as sacrifice. Saint Stephen made his cell not far from the birch tree and made use of the gathering of the superstitious pagans at the tree, to teach the holy truth. Then Saint Stephen cut down and burnt the birch tree for the dispelling of the superstition. The Zyryani gathered to kill him. The saint turned to them preaching: &quot;Judge for yourselves, whether or not your gods have any power, when they are not able to defend themselves from the fire? Are they gods, when they are so powerless, and indeed possess not only not a mind, but neither also ears nor sight? And your divinity could not defend itself against me, a weak man. Are all your other gods such as this? Not so is the Christian God. He sees everything, knows everything and is Almighty, since He created the whole world and fore-thinks everything. And how blessedly good He is, particularly for those knowing Him! I desire what is good for you, bringing the True God to you. He wilt love you and bless you, when ye begin to honour Him genuinely&quot;. On the place of &quot;the magic-mischief birch tree&quot;, Saint Stephen built a church in honour of the Archangel Michael, the dispeller of the spirits of darkness. 	The baptised Zyryani themselves began to do away with that, which earlier they had worshipped: they cut down sacred trees, they destroyed idols; the rich gifts, set aside for the pagan sacrifices, they brought to Saint Stephen. He bid his Zyryan helper Matthew to throw it all into the fire and permitted only the use of the linen cloth for foot wrappings. 	But things came to a final culmination among the Zyryani after Saint Stephen got the better of their chief-priest Pam, who rose up against the dissemination of the holy faith. The pagan priest entered into a debate with Saint Stephen. &quot;Christian, you have only but the one God, -- said Pam, -- but we have many an helper on the dry land, and in the water, granting us a lucky hunt in the forests and with its abundance providing Moscow, the Horde and faraway lands; they impart to us the magic mysteries, inaccessible to you&quot;. Saint Stephen answered, that the True God -- is one; the Almighty -- is one, but that the idol-gods evidently through the test of experience are powerless. After lengthy dispute the pagan-priest Pam in a proof of his faith made a challenge to go through fire and water, and demanded that Saint Stephen do this. &quot;I have no command of poetic verse, -- humbly answered Saint Stephen, -- but great is the Christian God: thus I shall go it with thee&quot;. Pam however lost his nerve and besought the saint to save him from certain death. &quot;Ye art witnesses, -- said Saint Stephen to the gathered people, -- how he demanded to resolve the dispute about faith by means of fire and water, but now doth not wish to be baptised. Who now hath regard for Pam? What is to be done with him?&quot; &quot;Let the deceiver be put to death, -- answered the people, -- for if Pam be set free, he wilt make mischief for thee&quot;. &quot;No, -- answered the saint, -- Christ hath sent me not to hand someone over to death, but to teach. Pam desireth not to accept the saving faith, , wherefore let his stubbornness punish him, but not I&quot;. Pam was banished. In thanksgiving to the Lord for victory over the chief pagans, Saint Stephen built at Vishero a church in honour of Saint Nicholas. After this, the preaching of the saint about Christ began to go all the more successfully.  	In 1383 Saint Stephen was ordained bishop of Malaya Perm&apos; (Lesser Perm&apos;). Like a doting father he incessantly concerned himself about his flock. For the encouraging in the faith of the newly-converted, Saint Stephen opened schools alongside the churches, where they studied the Holy Books in the Permian language. The saint supervised the instructions, and taught them the necessities for them to become priests and deacons. Saint Stephen taught several of his students how to write in the Permian language. The saint constructed churches, in which he put priests from among the Zyryani, and led Divine-services in the Zyryani tongue. 	Saint Stephen transposed into the Zyryani language the Chasoslov (Book of Hours), the Psalter, selected readings from the Gospel and the Epistles, the Paroemnik (Church-service Old testament readings), the Stikhirar (Church-service &quot;stikhi&quot; verses), Oktoikhon (Eight Tones), several feastday services and the Divine liturgy. 	During a time of crop failure the saint provided the Zyryani with bread, many a time he delivered them from being taken advantage of and from the trickery of corrupt officials, he bestowed alms upon them, and defended them from the incursion of other tribes, interceding for them at Moscow. The fruition of his efforts and good deeds came in the conversion of all the extent of the Perm&apos; land to Christianity. This great deed was accomplished by his strength of faith and Christian love. The life of the saint -- was a victory of faith over unbelief, of love and meekness -- over malice and impiety. 	There was a touching &quot;meeting in absence&quot; of Sainted Stephen of Perm&apos; with the Monk Sergei of Radonezh, occurring in the year 1390 during the time of a journey of the saint to Moscow on church business. Saint Stephen fervently loved the Radonezh ascetic and very much wanted to pay him a visit on the way from the Perm&apos; land, but was not able to do so because of insufficient time. Being 10 versts from the monastery of the MonkSergei, Saint Stephen in praying turned towards the direction of the monastery and with a bow he uttered: &quot;Peace unto thee, spiritual brother!&quot; The Monk Sergei, who sat together with the brethren at the refectory meal, stood up, made a prayer and, bowing towards the direction where the saint rode, answered: &quot;Hail also to thee, thou pastor of the flock of Christ, and the peace of God dwell with thee!&quot; 	The deep spiritual connection of Sainted Stephen of Perm&apos; and the Monk Sergei of Radonezh is testified to even at present by a particular daily prayer to them at the refectory-dining of the brethren. 	Besides building churches, Saint Stephen founded for the Zyryani also several monasteries: the Saviour Ul&apos;yanovsk wilderness-monastery 165 versts from Ust&apos;-Sysol&apos;sk, the Stephanovsk -- 60 versts from Ust&apos;-Sysol&apos;sk, the Ust&apos;-Vymsk Arkhangel&apos;sk, and the Yarengsk Arkhangel&apos;sk. 	In the year 1395 Saint Stephen again set out to Moscow on affairs of his flock, and here died. His body was placed in the monastery &quot;Saviour at the Wall&quot; (in a church to the north in honour of the Saviour) in the Moscow Kremlin. The Zyryani bitterly bewailed the death of their apostle. They earnestly entreated the Moscow prince and the Metropolitan to send back to Perm&apos; the body of their patron, but Moscow did not wish to part with the remains of the great saint. 	The glorification of Sainted Stephen began already at the beginning of the XVCentury. The Life of the saint was written soon after his death. The service to him was compiled by the priestmonk Pakhomii the Serb, together with the priestmonk Epiphanii the Wise, who was a student of the Monk Sergei of Radonezh and also well knew Saint Stephen and loved to converse with him.   
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Afire with divine desire from the years of thy youth, O all-wise Stephen, thou didst take up the burden of Christ, and, sowing the divine seed in the hearts of the people, which had from of old been hardened by unbelief, thou didst spiritual beget them evangelically; wherefore, honoring thine all-glorious memory, we beseech thee: Entreat Him Whom thou didst preach, that He save our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="8" Podoben="2">
Thou wast found to be called not for those who sought thee, O holy hierarch, but, freeing men from the falsehood of idolatry, thou didst lead them to the Christian Faith and didst put to shame the sorcerer Pamoi; wherefore, thou becamest the first bishop and teacher of Perm. For this cause, we, thy spiritual children, as ones delivered by thee from idols, cry out to thee in hymns of thanksgiving: Rejoice, O Stephen, all-wise teacher!
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>