<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святые мученики Дада, Максим и Квинтилиан"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святые мученики Дада, Максим и Квинтилиан пострадали при императоре Диоклитиане (284—305), когда вышло повеление при- носить на торжественных празднествах жертвы языческим богам, а христиан предавать смерти.    Наместники императора Тарквиний и Гавиний в городе Доро- столе устроили пышное торжество,, на котором присутствовали жители не только города, но и окрестных сёл.    Когда празднество закончилось, кто-то донес императору, что три брата — Дада, Максим и Квинтилиан не подчинились приказу императора и ушли к себе в деревню Озовию. За ними были по- сланы воины, которые застали святых братьев за молитвой и от- вели их на суд.    Правители допросили братьев, которые исповедали себя хри- стианами. Тогда Тарквиний предложил святому Максиму стать жрецом бога Зевса. Но тот назвал Зевса скверным прелюбодеем и снова исповедал Истинного Бога.    Тарквиний пытался уговорить святых Даду и Квинтиллиана. Они сказали, что их брат Максим хорошо знает Священное Писа- ние и они во всем следуют ему. Мучеников отправили в темницу, но и там они помышляли только о спасении своих душ. В полночь, когда святые уснули, им явился диавол, ополчившийся на них с оружием. Но когда мученики проснулись, они увидели Ангела, который сказал: «Не бойтесь, Бог, ваша надежда, примет вас к Себе. Он недалеко от вас и поможет вам». Наутро Тарквиний сказал братьям, что боги объявили ему во. сне свою волю: предать их смерти, если они не принесут жертвы. Мученики от- ветили, что им Господь приказал претерпеть мучения за Его Святое Имя.    Несколько дней пытки и допросы продолжались непрерывно с утра до вечера. Наконец мученикам вынесли смертный приговор, отвели под стражей в их деревню и там усекли мечом (+ 286). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Martyrs Dadus, Maximus and Quintilian"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Martyrs Dadus, Maximus and Quintilian suffered under the emperor Diocletian (284-305), when there came out a decree to offer sacrifice to the pagan gods on the solemn feastdays, and to put Christians to death. 	The representatives of the emperor in the city of Dorostolum, -- Tarquinius and Gabinius, made a sumptuous festivity, to which came not only the inhabitants of the city, but also from the surrounding villages.  	When the festivity finished, someone reported to the emperor, that three brothers  Dadus, Maximus and Quintilian, did not obey the decree of the emperor and withdrew themselves into the Ozovia forest. Soldiers were sent after them, who caught the holy brothers at prayer and led them forth for trial. 	The governors interrogated the brothers, who confessed themselves Christians. But Tarquinius offered to Saint Maximus to become a pagan-priest of the god Zeus. But that one called Zeus a foul adulterer and again confessed the True God. 	Tarquinius attempted to reason with Saints Dadus and Quintilian. They said, that their brother well knew the Holy Scripture and they would follow him in everything. They dispatched the martyrs to prison, but there also they pondered only about the salvation of their souls. At midnight when the saints were asleep, the devil appeared to them, up in arms against them. But when the martyrs woke, they beheld an Angel, which said: &quot;Fear not, for God your hope bringeth you to Himself. He is not far from you and wilt sustain you&quot;. In the morning Tarquinius said to the brothers that the gods had declared their will to him in a dream: give them death if they would not offer sacrifice. The martyrs answered, that the Lord had commanded them to endure torments for His Holy Name. 	The tortures and interrogations continued constantly from morning to evening for several days. Finally, they brought out a death sentence against the martyrs, led them out under guard to their forest and there beheaded them with a sword (+ 286).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="1">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="1">

</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>