<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой Акила, апостол от 70-ти"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
Возможно, что он ученик апо- стола Павла, уроженец Понта, иудей, живший в городе Риме со своей женой Прискиллой (память 13 февраля). В правление импе- ратора Клавдия (41—54) все евреи были изгнаны из столицы. Святой Акила с женой вынуждены были уехать. Поселились они в Коринфе. В скором времени туда пришел из Афин с проповедью Евангелия святой апостол Павел. Познакомившись с Акилой, он стал жить у него в доме и вместе с ними трудился над изготовле- нием палаток. Приняв Крещение от апостола Павла, Акила и Прискилла сделались его преданными и ревностными учениками. Они сопро- вождали апостола в Ефес. Апостол Павел поручил им продолжать проповедь Евангелия в Ефесе, а сам направился в Иерусалим, чтобы провести там праздник Пятидесятницы. В Ефесе Акила и Прискилла услышали смелую проповедь пришельца из Александ- рии, еврея Аполлоса, наставленного в начатках веры, но знавшего только крещение Иоанна Предтечи. Они позвали его к себе и бо- лее точно объяснили путь Господень. После смерти императора Клавдия евреям было разрешено возвратиться в Италию, и тогда Акила и Прискилла вернулись в Рим. Апостол Павел в своем Послании к Римлянам вспоминал о своих верных учениках: «Приветствуйте Прискиллу и Акилу, сотрудников моих во Христе Иисусе, которые голову свою полага- ли за мою душу, которых не я один благодарю, но и все Церкви из язычников и домашнюю их церковь» (Рим. 16, 3—4). В Риме святой Акила пробыл недолго: апостол Павел поставил его епи- скопом в Асию. Святой Акила ревностно трудился в Евангельской проповеди в Асии, Ахаии и Ираклии: обращал язычников ко Хри- сту, утверждал в вере новообращенных христиан, поставлял пре- свитеров, сокрушал идолов. В апостольских трудах ему неустанно помогала святая Прискилла. Святой Акила окончил жизнь муче- нически: его убили язычники. По преданию Церкви, вместе с ним была убита святая Прискилла. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
А҆пⷭле ст҃ы́й а҆кѵ́ло, молѝ млⷭтиваго бг҃а, да прегрѣше́нїй ѡ҆ставле́нїе пода́стъ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Ꙗ҆́кѡ ве́лїе со́лнце, цр҃ковь тѧ̀ стѧжа́вши сла́вне а҆кѵ́ло свѣтлостьмѝ ѹ҆че́нїѧ твоегѡ̀, просвѣща́етъ вѣ́рнѡ чтꙋ́щыѧ тѧ́ гдⷭень а҆пⷭле. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Saint Aquila, Disciple from the 70"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
Saint Aquila, Disciple from the 70: It is possible, that he was a disciple of the Apostle Paul, a native of Pontus and a Jew, living in the city of Rome with his wife Priscilla (Comm. 13 February). During the reign of the emperor Claudius (41-54) all the Jews were banished from Rome. Saint Aquilla and his wife were compelled to leave. They settled in Corinth. A short while afterwards the holy Apostle Paul arrived there from Athens preaching the Gospel. Having made the acquaintance of Aquila, he began to live at his house and laboured together with him over the making of tents.  	Having accepted Baptism from the Apostle Paul, Aquila and Priscilla bacame his devoted and zealous disciples. They accompanied the apostle to Ephesus. The Apostle Paul instructed them to continue the preaching of the Gospel at Ephesus, and he himself set off to Jerusalem, in order to be present there for the feast of Pentecost. At Ephesus Aquila and Priscilla heard the bold preaching of a new-comer from Alexandria, the Jew Apollos, who had been instructed in the fundamentals of the faith, but knew only the baptism of John the ForeRunner [i.e. John the Baptist]. They called him over to themselves and explained more precisely about the way of the Lord. 	After the death of the emperor Claudius, Jews were permitted to return to Italy, and Aquila and Priscilla then returned to Rome. The Apostle Paul in his Epistle to the Romans recollects about his faithful disciples: &quot;Greet Priscilla and Aquila, my co-workers in Christ Jesus, who put forth their heads for my soul, whom I do not alone thank, but also all the Church of the Gentiles and the church of their household&quot; (Rom. 16: 3-4). Saint Aquila did not long dwell in Rome: the Apostle Paul made him a bishop in Asia. Saint Aquila zealously laboured at preaching the Gospel in Asia, Achaeia and Herakleia: he converted pagans to Christ, he confirmed in the faith newly-converted Christians, he established presbyters and destroyed idols. Saint Priscilla constantly assisted him in the apostolic work. Saint Aquila finished his life a martyr: pagans murdered him. According to the tradition of the Church, Saint Priscilla was killed together with him.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="3">
O holy apostle Aquila/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4">
Having acquired thee like a great sun,/ O glorious Aquila, apostle of the Lord,// the Church enlighteneth with the splendors of thy teaching those who honor thee.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>