<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой апостол и Евангелист Иоанн Богослов"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святой апостол и Евангелист Иоанн Богослов занимает особое место в ряду избранных учеников Христа Спасителя. Нередко в иконографии апостол Иоанн изображается кротким, величествен- ным и духоносным старцем, с чертами девственной нежно- сти, с печатью полного спокойствия на челе и глубоким взором созерцателя неизреченных откровений. Другая главная особен- ность духовного облика апостола открывается через его учение о любви, за которое ему по преимуществу усвоено наименование Апостола любви. Действительно, любовью пронизаны все его писа- ния, основная мысль которых сводится к понятию, что Бог в Сво- ем существе есть Любовь (I Ин. 4, 8). В них он останавливается преимущественно на проявлениях неизреченной любви Бога к миру и человеку, на любви своего Божественного Учителя. Он постоян- но увещевает учеников к взаимной любви.    Служение Любви — весь жизненный путь апостола Иоанна Бо- гослова.     Ему были свойственны спокойствие и глубина созерцания в сочетании с горячей верностью, нежная и безграничная любовь с пылкостью и даже некоторой резкостью. Из кратких указаний Евангелистов видно, что он обладал в высшей степени пылкой натурой, сердечные порывы его иногда доходили до такой бурной ревности, что Иисус Христос вынужден был умерять их, как не- согласные с духом нового учения (Мк. 9, 38—40; Лк. 9; 49—50; 54— 56) и назвал апостола Иоанна и его родного брата Иакова «сына- ми грома» (Воанергес). В то же время он обнаруживает редкую скромность и, несмотря на свое особенное положение среди апо- столов как ученика, которого любил Иисус, он не выделялся из ряда других учеников Спасителя. Отличительными чертами его характера были наблюдательность и восприимчивость к событиям, проникнутые тонким чувством послушания воле Божией. Полу- ченные извне впечатления редко обнаруживались в его слове или действии, но сильно и глубоко проникали во внутреннюю жизнь святого Апостола. Всегда чуткий к другим, он болезновал сердцем о погибающих. Апостол Иоанн с благоговейным трепетом внимал Богодухновенному учению своего Учителя, исполненному благода- ти и истины, в чистой и возвышенной любви созерцая Славу Сына Божия. Ни одна черта из земной жизни Христа Спасителя не ускользнула от проницательного взора апостола Иоанна, ни одно событие не прошло, не оставив глубокого следа в его памяти, по- этому в нем сосредоточились вся полнота и целостность человече- ской личности. Такой же целостностью обладали и мысли апостола Иоанна Богослова. Для него не существовало раздвоенности. По его убеждению, где нет полной преданности, там нет ничего. Из- брав путь служения Христу, он до конца жизни совершал его с полнотой и безраздельной последовательностью. Апостол Иоанн говорит о всецелой преданности Христу, о полноте жизни в Нем, поэтому и грех рассматривается им не как слабость и поврежден- ность человеческой природы, а как зло, как отрицательное начало, совершенно противоположное добру (Ин. 8, 34; I Ин. 3, 4; 8—9). По его воззрению, можно принадлежать или Христу или дьяволу, среднего, неопределенного состояния быть не может (I Ин. 2, 22; 4, 3). Поэтому он служил Господу с безраздельной любовью и самоотверженностью, отвергая все, что принадлежит исконному врагу человека, врагу истины и родоначальнику лжи (I Ин. 2, 21—22). Чем сильнее он любит Христа, тем сильнее ненавидит антихриста; чем больше он любит истину, тем больше ненавидит ложь, — свет исключает тьму (Ин. 8, 12; 12, 35—36). Этим прояв- лением внутреннего огня любви он свидетельствовал с особой силой духа о Божестве Иисуса Христа (Ин. I, 1 —18; I Ин. 5, 1 — 12).     Апостолу Иоанну было определено выразить последнее слово Божественного Откровения, вводящего в сокровеннейшие тайны внутренней Божественной жизни, ведомые только вечному Слову Божию, Единородному Сыну.     Истина отображена в его уме и слове, потому что он чувствует и сердцем постигает ее. Он созерцает вечную Истину и как видит, так и передает своим возлюбленным чадам. Апостол Иоанн просто утверждает или отрицает и всегда говорит с абсолютной точно- стью (I Ин. 1, 1). Он слышит голос Господа, открывающего ему то, что Сам Он слышит от Отца.     Богословие апостола Иоанна уничтожает границу между на- стоящим и будущим. Наблюдая настоящее, временное, он не оста- навливается на нем, а переносит свой взор к вечному в прошедшем и к вечному в будущем. И поэтому он, призывая к святости жиз- ни, торжественно провозглашает, что «всякий, рожденный от Бога не согрешит» (I Ин. 5, 18, 3, 9). В общении с Богом истинный христианин причастен жизни Божественной, поэтому будущее че- ловечества совершается уже на земле. В изложении и раскрытии учения о Домостроительстве спасения Апостол Иоанн Богослов переходит в область вечно настоящего, в котором Небо сошло на землю и обновленная земля освещается Светом Небесной Славы.      1ак галилейский рыбак, сын Зеведея, стал Богословом, воз-   гстившим через Откровение тайну миробытия и судьбы челове- чества.     Празднование 8 мая святому апостолу Иоанну Богослову уставлено Церковью в воспоминание ежегодного исхождения в этот день на месте его погребения тончайшего розового праха, который собирали верующие для исцелений от различ-ных болезней. Све- дения о жизни святого Евангелиста Иоанна Богослова помещены 26 сентября, в день преставления.  
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
А҆пⷭле хрⷭтꙋ̀ бг҃ꙋ возлю́бленне, ѹ҆скорѝ и҆зба́вити лю́ди без꙽ѿвѣ́тны, прїе́млетъ тѧ̀ припа́дающа, и҆́же па́дша на пє́рси прїе́мый: є҆го́же молѝ бг҃осло́ве, и҆ належа́щїй ѻ҆́блакъ ꙗ҆зы́кѡвъ разгна́ти, просѧ̀ на́мъ ми́ра и҆ ве́лїѧ млⷭти. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2">
Вели҄чїѧ твоѧ҄ дѣ́вственниче, кто̀ повѣ́сть; то́чиши бо чꙋдеса̀, и҆ и҆злива́еши и҆сцѣлє́нїѧ, и҆ мо́лишисѧ ѡ҆ дꙋша́хъ на́шихъ, ꙗ҆́кѡ бг҃осло́въ и҆ дрꙋ́гъ хрⷭто́въ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Apostle and Evangelist John the Theologian"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Apostle and Evangelist John the Theologian occupies an unique place in the ranks of the chosen disciples of Christ the Saviour. Often in iconography the Apostle John is depicted as a gentle, majestic and spiritual elder, with features of innocent tenderness, with the imprint of complete calm upon his forehead and the deep look of a contemplator of unuttered revelations. Another main trait of the spiritual countenance of the Apostle John is revealed through his teaching about love, for which the title &quot;Apostle of Love&quot; is preeminently designated to him. Actually, all his writings are permeated by love, the basic concept of which leads to the comprehension, that God in His Being is Love (1 Jn. 4: 8). In his writings, Saint John dwells especially upon the manifestations of the inexpressible love of God for the world and for mankind, the love of his Divine Teacher. He constantly exhorts his disciples to mutual love one for another. 	The service of Love -- was the entire pathway of life of the Apostle John the Theologian. 	The qualities of calmness and profound contemplation were in him combined with an ardent fidelity, tender and boundless love with intensity and even a certain abruptness. From the brief indications of the Evangelists it is apparent, that he was endowed in the highest degree with an ardent nature, and his hearty passionateness sometimes reached such a stormy zealousness, that Jesus Christ was compelled to give the admonishment, that it was discordant with the spirit of the new teaching (Mk. 9: 38-40; Lk. 9: 49-50, 5456) and He called the Apostle John and his brother by birth the Apostle James &quot;Sons of Thunder&quot; (&quot;Boanerges&quot;). During this while Saint John shows scant modesty, and besides his particular position among the Apostles as &quot;the disciple whom Jesus loved&quot;, he did not stand out among the other disciples of the Saviour. The distinguishing features of his character were the observance and sensitivity to events, permeated by a keen sense of obedience to the Will of God. Impressions received from without rarely showed up in his word or actions, but they penetrated deeply and powerfully into the inner life of the holy Apostle John. Always sensitive to others, his heart ached for the perishing. The Apostle John with pious tremulation was attentive to the Divinely-inspired teaching of his Master, to the fulness of grace and truth, in pure and sublime comprehending the Glory of the Son of God. No feature of the earthly life of Christ the Saviour slipped past the penetrating gaze of the Apostle John, nor did any event occur, that did not leave a deep impression on his memory, since in him was concentrated all the fulness and wholeness of the human person. The thoughts also of the Apostle John the Theologian are imbued with suchlike an integral wholeness. The dichotomy of person did not exist for him. In accord with his precepts, where there is not full devotion, there is nothing. Having chosen the path to service to Christ, to the end of his life he fulfilled it with complete and undivided devotion. The Apostle John speaks about wholistic a devotion to Christ, about the fulness of life in Him, wherefore also sin is considered by him not as a weakness and injury of human nature, but as evil, as a negative principle, which is completely set in opposition to the good (Jn. 8: 34; 1 Jn. 3: 4, 8-9). In his perspective, it is necessary to belong either to Christ or to the devil, it is not possible to be of a mediocre lukewarm, undecided condition (1 Jn. 2: 22, 4: 3; Rev. 3: 15-16). Therefore he served the Lord with undivided love and self-denial, having repudiated everything that appertains to the ancient enemy of mankind, the enemy of truth and the father of lies (1 Jn. 2: 21-22). Just as strongly as he loves Christ, just as strongly he contemns the Anti-Christ; just as intensely he loves truth, with an equal intensity does he contemn falsehood, -- for light doth expel darkness (Jn. 8: 12; 12: 35-36). By the manifestation of the inner fire of love he witnesses with the unique power of spirit about the Divinity of Jesus Christ (Jn. 1: 1-18; 1 Jn. 5: 1-12). 	To the Apostle John was given to express the last word of the Divine Revelation (i.e. the final book of the Holy Scripture), ushering in the most treasured mysteries of the Divine inner life, known only to the eternal Word of God, the Only-Begotten Son. 	Truth is reflected in his mind and in his words, wherein he senses and grasps it in his heart. He has comprehension of eternal Truth, and as he sees it, he transmits it to his beloved spiritual children. The Apostle John with simplicity affirms or denies and speaks always with absolute precision (1 Jn. 1: 1). He hears the voice of the Lord, revealing to him what He Himself hears from the Father. 	The theology of the Apostle John abolishes the borderline between the present and the future. Looking at the present time, he does not halt at it, but transports his gaze to the eternal in the past time and to the eternal in the future time. And therefore he, exhorting for holiness in life, solemnly proclaims, that &quot;all, born of God, sin not&quot; (1 Jn. 5: 18; 3: 9). In communion with God the true Christian partakes of life Divine, whereby the future of mankind is accomplished already on earth. In his explanation and disclosing of the teaching about the Economia of salvation, the Apostle John crosses over into the area of the eternal present, in which Heaven would co-incide with earth and the earth would be enlightened with the Light of Heavenly Glory.  	Thus did the Galilean fisherman, this son of Zebedee, become Theologian proclaiming through Revelation the mystery of world-existence and the fate of mankind. 	The celebration on 8 May of the holy Apostle John the Theologian was established by the Church in remembrance of the annual drawing forth on this day at the place of his burial of fine rose ashes, which believers gathered for healing from various maladies. The account about the life of the holy Evangelist John the Theologian is situated under 26September, the day of his repose.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
O beloved apostle of Christ God,/ haste thou to deliver a defenseless people./ He Who permitted thee to recline against His breast/ receiveth thee, prostrate in supplication./ Him do thou beseech, O theologian,/ that He dispel the gloom of the nations which doth beset us,// asking for us peace and great mercy.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2">
Who can recount thy mighty works, O virgin apostle?/ For thou pourest out miracles/ and dost cause healings to flow forth;/ and thou prayest for our souls,// in that thou art a theologian and the friend of Christ.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>