<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Святой пророк Иеремия"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Настольная книга свщеннослужителя. Москва. 1978.">
   Святой пророк Иеремия, один из четырех великих ветхозавет- ных пророков, сын священника Хелкии из города Анафофа, близ Иерусалима, жил за 600 лет до Рождества Христова при израиль- ском царе Иосии и четырех его преемниках. К пророческому слу- жению был призван на 15 году своей жизни, когда Господь от- крыл ему, что прежде рождения Он определит его быть пророком. Иеремия отказывался, указывая на свою молодость и неумение говорить, но Господь обещал всегда быть с ним и охранять его. Он коснулся уст избранника и сказал: «Вот Я влагаю слова Мои в уста твои, поручаю тебе с сего дня судьбу народов и царств. По твоему пророческому слову они будут падать и восставать» (Иер. 1, 9—10). С того времени двадцать три года пророчествовал Иере- мия, обличая иудеев за отступление от Истинного Бога и поклоне- ние идолам, предрекая им бедствия и опустошительную войну. Он останавливался в воротах города, у входа в храм, всюду, где соби- рался народ, и увещевал с угрозами и нередко со слезами. Но люди отвечали ему насмешками, ругательствами и даже покуша- лись его убить.    Изображая предстоящее иудеям рабство царю вавилонскому, Иеремия по повелению Божию надел на свою шею сначала дере- вянное, а потом железное ярмо и так ходил среди народа. Гне- ваясь на грозные предсказания пророка, старейшины иудейские бросили пророка Иеремию в темничный ров, наполненный зловон- ной тиной, где он едва не умер. По предстательству богобоязнен- ного царедворца Авдемелеха, пророк был извлечен изо рва и не переставал пророчествовать, за что был посажен в темницу. При царе иудейском Седекии пророчество его сбылось: пришел Наву- ходоносор, избил народ, остаток увел в плен, а Иерусалим разгра- бил и разрушил. Навуходоносор освободил пророка из темницы и позволил ему жить, где пожелает. Пророк же остался на развали- нах Иерусалима и оплакивал бедствия своего отечества. По пре- данию, пророк Иеремия взял ковчег Завета со скрижалями и скрыл его в одной из пещер горы Наваф, так что иудеи более не могли его найти (2 Мак. 2). Впоследствии был сделан новый Ков- чег Завета, но он уже не имел славы первого.    Среди оставшихся в своем отечестве иудеев вскоре возникли междоусобные столкновения: наместник Навуходоносора Годолия был убит, и иудеи, боясь гнева вавилонского, решили бежать в Египет. Пророк Иеремия отклонял их от этого намерения, пред- сказывая, что кара, которой они боятся, настигнет их и в Египте. Но иудеи не послушались пророка и, взяв его насильно с собой, ушли в Египет и поселились в городе Тафнисе. Там пророк жил четыре года и был почитаем египтянами, так как умертвил своею молитвою крокодилов и прочих гадов, наполнявших те места. Когда же он стал предсказывать, что царь вавилонский опусто- шит землю египетскую и уничтожит поселившихся в ней иудеев, то иудеи убили пророка Иеремию. В том же году предсказание святого исполнилось. Существует предание, что через 250 лет Александр Македонский перенес мощи святого пророка Иеремии в город Александрию.    Пророк Иеремия написал книгу «Пророчеств», книгу «Плач» о разрушении Иерусалима и Послание. О временах, когда он жил и пророчествовал, говорится в 4-й Книге Царств (23, 24, 25), во 2-й Книге Паралипоменон (36, 12) и во 2-й Книге Маккавеев (2).    В Евангелии от Матфея указано, что предательство Иуды пред- сказано пророком Иеремией: «И взяли тридцать сребренников, цену Оцененного, Которого оценили сыны Израиля, и дали их за землю горшечника, как сказал мне Господь» (Мф. 27, 9—10). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
Прⷪро́ка твоегѡ̀ ї҆еремї́и па́мѧть, гдⷭи, пра́зднꙋюще, тѣ́мъ тѧ̀ мо́лимъ, сп҃сѝ дꙋ́шы на́шѧ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Ѡ҆чи́стивъ дх҃омъ, вели́кїй прⷪро́че и҆ мч҃нче, твоѐ свѣтоза́рное се́рдце, сла́вне ї҆еремї́е, прⷪро́чествїѧ да́ръ свы́ше прїѧ́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ возопи́лъ є҆сѝ, велегла́снѡ во страна́хъ: сѐ бг҃ъ на́шъ, и҆ не приложи́тсѧ и҆́нъ къ немꙋ̀, и҆́же вопло́щьсѧ на землѝ ꙗ҆ви́лсѧ є҆́сть. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Holy Prophet Jeremiah"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
The Holy Prophet Jeremiah, one of the four great Old Testament prophets, was son of the priest Helkiah from the city of Anathoth near Jerusalem, and he lived 600 years before the Birth of Christ, under the Israelite king Josiah and four of his successors. He was called to prophetic service in his 15th year of life, when the Lord revealed to him, that even before his birth the Lord had assigned him to be a prophet. Jeremiah refused, pointing to his own youthfulness and lack of skill at speaking, but the Lord promised to be always with him and to watch over him. He touched the mouth of the chosen one and said: &quot;Lo I do put Mine words into thy mouth, I do entrust unto thee from this day the fate of nations and kingdoms. By thine prophetic word wilt they fall and rise up&quot; (Jer. 1: 9-10). And from that time Jeremiah prophesied for twenty-three years, denouncing the Jews for abandoning the True God and worshipping idols, predicting for them woes and devastating wars. He stood by the gates of the city, and at the entrance to the Temple, everywhere where the people gathered, and he exhorted them with imprecations and often with tears. But the people answered him with mockery and abuse, and they even tried to kill him. 	Depicting the slavery to the king of Babylon impending for the Jews, Jeremiah at the command of God put on his own neck at first a wooden, and then an iron yoke, and thus he went about among the people. Enraged at the dire predictions of the prophet, the Jewish elders threw the Prophet Jeremiah into an imprisoning pit, filled with horrid slimy creatures, where he all but died. Through the intercession of the God-fearing royal-official Habdemelek, the prophet was pulled out of the pit but he did not cease with the prophecies, and for this he was carted off to prison. Under the Jewish king Zedekiah his prophesy was fulfilled: Nebuchadnezzar came, made slaughter of the nation, carried off a remnant into captivity, and Jerusalem was pillaged and destroyed. Nebuchadnezzar released the prophet from prison and permitted him to live where he wanted. The prophet remained at the ruins of Jerusalem and bewailed the misfortune of his fatherland. According to tradition, the Prophet Jeremiah took the Ark of the Covenant with the LawTablets and hid it in one of the caves of Mount Nabath (Nebo), such that the Jews were no more able to find it (2 Mac. 2). Afterwards a new Ark of the Covenant was fashioned, but it lacked in the glory of the first. 	Among the Jews remaining in their fatherland there soon arose internecine clashes: the viceroy of Nebuchadnezzar, Hodoliah, was murdered, and the Jews, fearing the wrath of Babylon, decided to flee into Egypt. The Prophet Jeremiah disagreed with their intention, predicting that the punishment which they feared, would befall them in Egypt. But the Jews would not hearken to the prophet, and taking him by force with them, they went into Egypt and settled in the city of Tathnis. And there the prophet lived for four years and was respected by the Egyptians, since with his prayer he killed crocodiles and other nasty creatures infesting these parts. But when he began to prophesy, that the king of Babylon would invade the land of Egypt and annihilate the Jews settled in it, the Jews then murdered the Prophet Jeremiah. In that very same year the prophesy of the saint was fulfilled. There exists a tradition, that 250 years later Alexander the Great of Macedonia transported the relics of the holy Prophet Jeremiah to Alexandria. 	The Prophet Jeremiah wrote his Book of &quot;Prophesies&quot; (&quot;Jeremiah&quot;), and also the Book of &quot;Lamentations&quot;, -- about the Desolation of Jerusalem and the Exile. The times in which he lived and prophesied are spoken of in the 4th (2nd) Book of Kings (Ch. 23-25) and in the 2nd Book of Chronicles (36: 12) and in 2 Maccabbees (Ch. 2).  	In the Gospel of Matthew it points out, that the betrayal of Judas was foretold by the Prophet Jeremiah: &quot;And they took thirty pieces of silver, the price of Him on Whom the sons of Israel had set a price, and they gave them over for the potter&apos;s field, as did say the Lord unto me&quot; (Mt. 27: 9-10).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
Celebrating the memory/ of Thy prophet Jeremiah O Lord,// through him do we entreat Thee, save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Having cleansed thy radiant heart with the Spirit,/ O glorious Jeremiah, great prophet and martyr,/ thou didst receive from on high the gift of prophecy/ and didst cry aloud among the lands: "Behold our God!// There is none other to compare with Him, Who hath appeared, incarnate, on the earth!"
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>