<SAINT>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 3">
<NAME Nominative="Преподобный Иоанн Лествичник"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Протоиерей Сергий Булгаков. Настольная Книга.">
   Преподобный Иоанн Лествичник почитается Святой Церковью как великий подвижник и автор замечательного духовного творе- ния, называемого «Лествицей», поэтому преподобный и получил прозвание Лествичника.    О происхождении преподобного Иоанна почти не сохранилось сведений. Существует предание, что он родился около 570 года и был сыном святых Ксенофонта и Марии, память которых празд- нуется Церковью 26 января. Шестнадцати лет отрок Иоанн при- шел в Синайский монастырь. Наставником и руководителем пре- подобного стал авва Мартирий. После четырех лет пребывания на Синае святой Иоанн Лествичник был пострижен в иночество. Один из присутствовавших при постриге, авва Стратигий, пред- сказал, что он станет великим светильником Церкви Христовой. В течепие 19-ти лет преподобный Иоанн подвизался в послушании своему духовному отцу. После смерти аввы Мартирия преподоб- ный Иоанн избрал отшельническую жизнь, удалившись в пустын- ное место, называемое Фола, где провел 40 лет в подвиге безмол- вия, поста, молитвы и покаянных слезах. Не случайно в «Лестви- Це» преподобный Иоанн так говорит о слезах покаяния: «Как огонь сожигает и уничтожает хворост, так чистая слеза омывает все нечистоты, наружные и внутренние». Сильна и действенна была его святая молитва, об этом свидетельствует пример из жи- тия угодника Божия.    У преподобного Иоанна был ученик, инок Моисей. Однажды наставник приказал своему ученику наносить в сад земли для грядок. Исполняя послушание, инок Моисей из-за сильного лет- него зноя прилег отдохнуть под тенью большого утеса. Преподоб- ный Иоанн Лествичник находился в это время в своей келлии и отдыхал после молитвенного труда. Внезапно ему явился муж почтенного вида и, разбудив святого подвижника, с упреком ска- зал: «Почему ты, Иоанн, спокойно отдыхаешь здесь, а Моисей находится в опасности?» Преподобный Иоанн тотчас пробудился и стал молиться за своего ученика. Когда его ученик возвратился вечером, преподобный спросил, не случилось ли с ним что-либо плохое. Инок ответил: «Нет, но я подвергся большой опасности. Меня едва не раздавил большой обломок камня, оторвавшийся от утеса, под которым я в полдень уснул. К счастью, мне предста- вилось во сне, что ты зовешь меня, я вскочил и бросился бежать, а в это время с шумом упал огромный камень на то самое место, с которого я убежал...»    Об образе жизни преподобного Иоанна известно, что питался он тем, что не запрещалось уставом постнической жизни, но — умеренно. Не проводил ночей без сна, хотя спал не более того, сколько необходимо для поддержания сил, чтобы непрестанным бодрствованием не погубить ума. «Я не постился чрезмерно,— говорит он сам о себе,— и не предавался усиленному ночному бдению, не лежал на земле, но смирялся.., и Господь скоро спас меня». Примечателен следующий пример смирения преподобного Иоанна Лествичника. Одаренный высоким проницательным умом, умудренный глубоким духовным опытом, он с любовью поучал всех приходивших к нему, руководя их к спасению. Но когда яви- лись некоторые, по зависти упрекавшие его в многословии, кото- рое они объясняли тщеславием, то преподобный Иоанн наложил на себя молчание, чтобы не подавать повода к осуждению, и без- молвствовал в течение года. Завистники осознали свое заблужде- ние и сами обратились к подвижнику с просьбой не лишать их духовной пользы собеседования.    Скрывая свои подвиги от людей, преподобный Иоанн иногда уединялся в пещере, но слава о его святости распространилась далеко за пределы места подвигов, и к нему непрестанно прихо- дили посетители всех званий и состояний, жаждавшие услышать слово назидания и спасения. В возрасте 75-ти лет, после сорока- летнего подвижничества в уединении, преподобный был избран игуменом Синайской обители. Около четырех лет управлял пре- подобный Иоанн Лествичник святой обителью Синая. Господь наделил преподобного к концу его жизни благодатными дарами прозорливости и чудотворений.    Во время управления монастырем по просьбе святого Иоанна, игумена Раифского монастыря (память в Сырную субботу), и была написана преподобными знаменитая «Лествица» — руководство для восхождения к духовному совершенству. Зная о мудрости и духов- ных дарованиях преподобного, Раифский игумен от лица всех иноков своей обители просил написать для них «истинное руко- водство для последующих неуклонно, и как бы лествицу утверж- дену, которая желающих возводит до Небесных врат...» Препо- добный Иоанн, отличавшийся скромным о себе мнением, сначала смутился, но затем из послушания приступил к исполнению прось- бы раифских иноков. Свое творение преподобный так и назвал — «Лествица», объясняя название следующим образом: «Соорудил я лествицу восхождения... от земного во святая... во образ трид- цати лет Господня совершеннолетия, знаменательно соорудил лествицу из 30 степеней, по которой, достигнув Господня возраста, окажемся праведными и безопасными от падения». Цель этого тво- рения — научить, что достижение спасения требует от человека нелегкого самоотвержения и усиленных подвигов. «Лествица» пред- полагает, во-первых, очищение греховной нечистоты, искоренение пороков и страстей в ветхом человеке; во-вторых, восстановление в человеке образа Божия. Хотя книга была написана для иноков, любой христианин, живущий в миру, получает в ней надежного путеводителя для восхождения к Богу, и столпы духовной жиз- ни— преподобный Феодор Студит (память 11 ноября и 26 янва- ря), Сергий Радонежский (память 25 сентября и 5 июля), Иосиф Волоколамский (память 9 сентября и 18 октября) и другие — ссылались в своих наставлениях на «Лествицу» как на лучшую книгу для спасительного руководства.    Содержание одной из степеней «Лествицы» (22-я) раскрывает подвиг истребления тщеславия. Преподобный Иоанн пишет: «Тще- славие высказывается при каждой добродетели. Когда, например, храню пост — тщеславлюсь, и когда, скрывая пост от других, раз- решаю на пищу, опять тщеславлюсь — благоразумием. Одевшись в светлую одежду, побеждаюсь любочестием и, переодевшись в худую, тщеславлюсь. Говорить ли стану — попадаю во власть тще- славия. Молчать ли захочу, опять предаюсь ему. Куда ни поверни это терние, оно всё станет спицами кверху. Тщеславный... на взгляд чтит Бога, а на деле более старается угодить людям, чем Богу... Люди высокого духа сносят обиду благодушно и охотно, а слушать похвалы и не ощущать никакой приятности могут толь- ко святые и непорочные... Когда услышишь, что ближний или друг твой в глаза или за глаза злословит тебя, похвали и полюби его... Не тот показывает смирение, кто сам себя бранит: как быть несносным самому себе? Но кто, обесчещенный другим, не умень- шает своей любви к нему... Кто превозносится природными даро- ваниями— счастливым умом, высокой образованностью, чтением, приятным произношением и другими подобными качествами, кото- рые легко приобретаются, тот никогда не приобретает даров сверхъестественных. Ибо кто в малом не верен, тот и во многом будет не верен и тщеславен. Часто случается, что Сам Бог сми- ряет тщеславных, насылая неожиданное бесчестие... Если молитва не истребит тщеславного помысла, приведем на мысль исход души из этой жизни. Если и это не поможет, устрашим его позором Страшного суда. «Возносяйся смирится» даже здесь, прежде буду- щего века. Когда хвалители, или лучше — льстецы, начнут хвалить нас, тотчас приведем себе на память все беззакония свои и най- дем, что вовсе не стоим мы того, что нам приписывают».    Этот и другие примеры, находящиеся в «Лествице», служат образцом той святой ревности о своем спасении, которая необхо- дима каждому человеку, желающему жить благочестиво, а пись- менное изложение его мыслей, составляющих плод многих и утон- ченных наблюдений его над своей душою и глубокого духовного опыта, является руководством и великим пособием на пути к исти- не и добру.    Степени «Лествицы» —• это прехождение из силы в силу па пути стремления человека к совершенству, которое не вдруг, но только постепенно может быть достигаемо, ибо, по слову Спаси- теля, «Царство Небесное силою берется, и употребляющие усилие восхищают его» (Мф. 11, 12). 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
Сле́зъ твои́хъ тече́ньми пꙋсты́ни безпло́дное воздѣ́лалъ є҆сѝ, и҆ и҆̀же и҆з꙽ глꙋбины̀ воздыха́ньми, во сто̀ трꙋдѡ́въ ѹ҆плодоноси́лъ є҆сѝ, и҆ бы́лъ є҆сѝ свѣти́льникъ вселе́ннѣй, сїѧ́ѧ чꙋдесы̀, ї҆ѡа́нне ѻ҆́тче на́шъ, молѝ хрⷭта̀ бг҃а сп҃сти́сѧ дꙋша́мъ на́шымъ. 
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
На высотѣ̀ гдⷭь воздержа́нїѧ, и҆́стинна тѧ̀ положѝ, ꙗ҆́коже ѕвѣздꙋ̀ неле́стнꙋю, свѣтоводѧ́щꙋю концы̀, наста́вниче ї҆ѡа́нне ѻ҆́тче на́шъ. 
</KONTAKION>

</LANGUAGE>
<LANGUAGE Cmd="LS == 0">
<NAME Nominative="Monk John of the Ladder (Lestvichnik; Klimatikos; Climaticus)"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
The Monk John of the Ladder (Lestvichnik; Klimatikos; Climaticus) is honoured by Holy Church as a great ascetic and author of the reknown spiritual work called &quot;The Ladder&quot;, whereby the monk likewise received the title &quot;of-the-Ladder&quot; [Lestvichnik (Slav.); Klimatikos (Grk.); Climaticus (Lat.)]. 	About the origins of the monk John there is almost no account preserved. Tradition suggests, that he was born about the year 570, and was the son of Saints Xenophones and Maria, -- whose is celebrated by the Church on 26 January. The sixteen year old lad John arrived at the Sinai monastery. Abba Martyrios became instructor and guide of the monk. After four years of living on Sinai, Saint John Lestvichnik was vowed into monasticism. One of those present at the taking of vows, -- Abba Stratigios, predicted, that he was set to become a great luminary in the Church of Christ. Over the course of 19 years the monk John pursued asceticism in obedience to his spiritual father. After the death of abba Martyrios the monk John chose an hermit&apos;s life, settling into a wild place called Tholos, where he spent 40 years in deeds of silence, fasting, prayer and tears of penitence. It is not by chance that in &quot;The Ladder&quot; the monk John speaks thus about tears of repentance: &quot;Just as fire burns and destroys firewood, so thus do pure tears wash away all impurity, both outer and inner&quot;. His holy prayer was strong and efficacious, as evidenced from an example from the life of the God-pleasing saint. 	The Monk John had a student, the monk Moses. One time the instructor ordered his student to bring ground to the garden for bedding. Having fulfilled the obedience, the monk Moses lay down to rest under the shade of a large rock, because of the strong heat of summer. The monk John Lestvichnik was at this time in his cell resting after a prayerful labour. Suddenly a man of remarkable appearance appeared to him and, having roused the holy ascetic, said to him in reproach: &quot;Why dost thou, John, rest peacefully here, when Moses is in danger?&quot; The monk John immediately woke up and began to pray for his student. When his disciple returned in the evening, the monk asked, whether some sort of woe had befallen him. The monk answered: &quot;No, but I was exposed to great danger. A large fragment of stone, having broken off from the rock under which I had fallen asleep at mid-day, just barely missed me. By luck, I had a dream that thou wast calling me, and I woke up and started to run off, and at that very moment the huge stone fell with a crash on that very spot, from which I had fled...&quot; 	About the manner of life of the monk John is known, that he nourished himself by such as what is not prohibited a fasting life by the ustav, but -- in moderation. He did not spend the night without sleep, although he slept not much, only as much as was necessary for keeping up his strength, so that by an unceasing vigilance he would not destroy the mind. &quot;I do not fast excessively, -- said he about himself, -- nor do I give myself over to intense all-night vigil, nor lay upon the ground, but restrain myself..., and the Lord soon saved me&quot;. The following example of humility of the monk John Lestvichnik is noteworthy. Gifted with a deeply penetrating mind, and having become wise by profound spiritual experience, he lovingly received all who came to him so as to guide them to salvation. But when there appeared some who through envy reproached him with loquacity, which they explained away as vanity, the monk John then gave himself over to silence so as not to give cause for blame, and he kept silence for the space of a year. The envious realised their error and they themselves returned to the ascetic with the request not to deprive them of the spiritual profit of his conversation. 	Concealing his ascetic deeds from people, the monk John sometimes withdrew into a cave, but accounts of his holiness spread far beyond the locality: incessantly there came to him visitors from every rank and calling, wanting to hear his words of edification and salvation. At age 75, after forty years of ascetic striving in solitude, the monk was chosen as hegumen of the Sinai monastery. For about four years the monk John Lestvichnik governed the holy Sinai monastery. Towards the end of his life, the Lord granted the monk grace-bearing gifts of perspicacity and wonderworking. 	During the time of his governing the monastery, -- at the request of the hegumen of the Raipha monastery Saint John (Comm. on Cheesefare Saturday), there was written for the monks the reknown &quot;Ladder&quot;, -- an instruction for rising to spiritual perfection. Knowing about the wisdom and spiritual gifts of the monk, the Raipha hegumen on behalf of all the monks of his monastery requested him to write down for them &quot;a true instruction for those following after invariably, and as such would be a ladder of affirmation, which would lead those wishing it to the Heavenly gates...&quot; The monk John, noted for his humble opinion about himself, was at first perplexed, but afterwards out of obedience he set about fulfilling the request of the Raipha monks. The monk thus also named his work -- &quot;The Ladder&quot;, and explained the title in the following manner: &quot;I have constructed a ladder of ascent... from the earthly to the holy... in the form of the thirty years of age for the Lord&apos;s maturity, symbolically I have constructed a ladder of 30 steps, by which, having attained the Lord&apos;s age, we find ourselves with the righteous and secure from falling down&quot;. The purpose of this work, is to teach -- that the reaching of salvation requires difficult self-denial and demanding ascetic deeds. &quot;The Ladder&quot; presupposes, first, a cleansing from the impurity of sin, the eradication of vices and passions in the old man; second, the restoration in man of the image of God. Although the book was written for monks, any christian living in the world receives from it the hope of guidance for ascent to God, and a support for spiritual life. The Monks Theodore the Studite (Comm. 11 November and 26 January), Sergei of Radonezh (Comm. 25 September and 5 July), Joseph of Volokolamsk (Comm. 9 September and 18 October), and others -- in their instructions relied on &quot;The Ladder&quot; as an important book for salvific guidance. 	The content of one of the steps of &quot;The Ladder&quot; (the 22nd) discusses the ascetic deed of the destruction of vainglory. The monk John writes: &quot;Vanity springs out in front of each virtue. When, for example, I keep a fast -- I am given over to vanity, and when I in concealing the fasting from others permit myself food, I am again given over to vanity -- by my prudence. Dressing up in bright clothing, I am vanquished by love of honour and, having changed over into drab clothing -- I am overcome by vanity. If I stand up to speak -- I fall under the power of vanity. If I wish to keep silence, I am again given over to it. Wherever this thorn comes up, it everywhere stands with its points upwards. It is vainglorious..., on the surface to honour God, and in deed to strive to please people rather than God... People of lofty spirit bear insult placidly and willingly, but to hear praise and feel nothing of pleasure is possible only for the saints and for the unblameworthy... When thou hearest, that thy neighbour or friend either afront the eyes or behind the eyes slandereth thee, praise and love him... Does this not shew humility, and who can reproach himself, and be intolerant with himself? But who, having been discredited by another, would not diminish in his love for him... Whoever is exalted by natural gifts -- a felicitous mind, a fine education, reading, pleasant elocution and other similar qualities, which are readily enough acquired, that person might yet never obtain to supernatural gifts. Wherefore whoever is not faithful in the small things, that one also is not faithful in the large, and is vainglorous. It often happens, that God Himself humbles the vainglorious, sending a sudden misfortune... If prayer does not destroy a proud thought, we bring to mind the leaving of the soul from this life. And if this does not help, we threaten it with the shame of the Last Judgement. &quot;Rising up to humble oneself&quot; even here, before the future age. When praisers, or better -- flatterers, start to praise us, immediately we betake ourselves to recollection of all our iniquities and we find, that we are not at all worth that which they impute to us&quot;.  	This and other examples, located in &quot;The Ladder&quot;, offer us an image of this saint&apos;s zealousness about his own salvation, which is necessary for each person who wishes to live piously. It is a written account of his thought, the collective fruit of many and also of his refined observation from his own soul and his own profound spiritual experience. It reveals itself as a guide and great help on the way to truth and good. 	The steps of &quot;The Ladder&quot; -- this proceeding from strength to strength on the path of man&apos;s proclivity to perfection, is not something suddenly but rather gradually to be reached, as in the saying of the Saviour: &quot;The Kingdom of Heaven is taken by strength, and those utilising strength shalt delight of it&quot; (Mt 11: 12).
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="8">
With the streams of thy tears thou didst irrigate the barren desert,/ and with sighs from the depths of thy soul thou didst render thy labors fruitful an hundredfold./ Thou wast a beacon for the whole world, radiating miracles.// O our father John, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="4" Podoben="1">
In the firmament of true abstinence hath the Lord set thee/ as a true star guiding the ends of the earth with light,/ / O father John our instructor.
</KONTAKION>
</LANGUAGE>
</SAINT>