<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Apostle Simon Zealotes (1st C)" Short="Apostle Simon"/>
<SERVICE Type="4"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
 The Holy Apostle Simon Zelotes hailed from Cana of Galilee. He was a son of Joseph the Betrothed, and hence a brother of the Lord after the flesh, and he was also one of the 12 Apostles. The first miracle which the Saviour worked, -- the transforming of water into wine, occurred at the house of Simon: at the time of a wedding-feast there was insufficient wine for the guests. Then the Lord, at the prompting of the MostHoly Mother of God, transformed water into wine. Struck by the miracle, Simon with all his heart and soul believed in the Lord Jesus as the Promised Messiah and, having left behind everything, he followed after Him. Simon received the title &quot;Zelotes&quot;, i.e. a zealot, meaning a person who is zealous. On the day of Pentecost he received the gift of the Holy Spirit together with the other Apostles. The holy Apostle Simon preached the teaching of Christ at Judea, Egypt, Libya, Cyrenia and Britain. At Abkhazia he accepted a martyr&apos;s death, and was crucified on a cross. He was buried at the city of Nikopsia around Sukhum. Afterwards (in the XIX Century), at the place where the holy Apostle Simon asceticised near Mount Iveria, there was established the Novoathonite monastery of Simon the Canaanite. To the present day is preserved the cave wherein the holy Apostle Simon asceticised. 
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="3">
 O holy apostle Simon/ entreat the merciful God// that He grant to our souls remission of transgressions.
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="2">
 In laudations let us all bless the divinely eloquent Simon,/ who hath diligently set the doctrines of wisdom in the hearts of the pious;/ for he standeth now before the throne of glory and dwelleth with the incorporeal ones,// praying unceasingly for us all.
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>