<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Venerable Nicetas the Confessor, Bishop of Chalcedon (9&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; C)" Short="Venerable Nicetas"/>
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman’s Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
&lt;p&gt;The Monk Nikita the Confessor, Bishop of Chalcedon, lived during the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; half of the VIII Century. For his God-pleasing life he was elevated to the dignity of bishop of Chalcedon. Saint Nikita distinguished himself by his charity, he always helped the poor, he took in wanderers into his dwelling, he concerned himself about the orphaned and the widowed, and he interceded for the wronged. During the reign of the Iconoclast Leo the Armenian (813-820), Saint Nikita bravely denounced the Iconoclast heresy and urged his flock reverently to venerate the holy icons of Christ, the Mother of God and the holy Saints. Saint Nikita endured much suffering from the impious emperor and his like-minded cohorts; he was subjected to tortures and sent off to exile. The holy Confessor Nikita died at the beginning of the IX Century. From his relics occurred miracles of healing. In the Canon of the service to him, written by the Constantinople presbyter Joseph, it declares as glorified amongst the Saints also the brother of Saint Nikita—Saint Ignatios. &lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE>
<SERVICE Type="1">
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
&lt;p&gt;The truth of things revealed thee to thy flock as a rule of faith, * a model of meekness and a teacher of abstinence * wherefore thou hast attained the heights through humility * and riches through poverty. ** O hierarch Nicetas our father, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.&lt;/p&gt;
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="0">
&lt;p&gt;Thou didst shine forth in the splendor of thy deeds, * and becamest an heir to the throne of the apostles, O venerable Nicetas; * and, wholly filled with divine doctrines, O father, * thou didst shine forth like the sun upon the flock. ** Wherefore, we cry to thee: Rejoice, O adornment of Chalcedon!&lt;/p&gt;
</KONTAKION>
</LITURGY>
</SERVICE>
</SAINT>
