<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Venerable Amphilocius, Macarius, Tarasius and Theodosius of Glushetsk"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Fr. Eugene Tarris">
        The Venerable Amphilocius already a monk came to the Glushetsk
monastery to assist its rector the Venerable Dionysius (June 1). And he became the
most reliable helper for Dionysius during the building of the monastery, strictly
supervising and observing the monastery Typikon (Ustav) for twenty years. His
meekness and humility was immeasurable; he cared only for the soul, which is
why he wore the most modest clothing. After the death of his guide he became the
hegumen of the monastery and died in peace in 1452. His relics are in a hidden
place in the temple named for him. The Venerable Macarius succeeded him. He
was born in Rostov, and spent twelve years in ascetic efforts in the Glushetsk
Monastery and died in 1478. His relics are in a hidden place in the Glushetsk
Monastery. The Venerable Tarasius was the hegumen of one of the monasteries
built by Bishop Stephen (see April 26) and was one of his fervent co-workers in
the propagation and the establishment of the Orthodox faith among the Zirians.
Having entered into voluntary obedience to the Venerable Dionysius, he practiced
asceticism in the Glushetsk Monastery for ten years, leading a most severe and
strict life in fasting and vigils, destroying his body. Tears of affection constantly
moistened his cheeks, testifying to his deep humility and afflicted heart, so that all
marveled at his patience and looked upon him as on one of the ancient great
ascetics. Reaching deep old age, he died in 1440. His relics are in a hidden place in
the Glushetsk St. Dionysius Monastery (see the Vologda Diocese). The Venerable Theodosius was a disciple of the Venerable Dionysius. His relics repose in the
same Glushetsk Monastery, near the relics of the Venerable Tarasius.

</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">

</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="" Translator="Aleksandr Andreev">

</KONTAKION>

</SAINT>