<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Venerable Theodore the Confessor, Abbot of the Studion († 826)" Short="Venerable Theodore"/>
<SERVICE Type="1"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
Born in Constantinople, he received his higher education and, having accepted monasticism, he was tonsured in their Saccudion monastery, committing his life to the high principle of good works. During the reign of the Emperors Constantine Copronymus and Leo the Armenian Saint Theodore suffered much as a venerator of icons and underwent imprisonment. In the reign of Irene he founded the Studite Monastery in Constantinople, for which he wrote the rule and in which he was the rector. The venerable Theodore put in the basis of the monastic organization the general rule of St. Basil the Great, for which he was given special respect and with which he knew to perfection, while yet a monk in the Saccudion monastery. Following these rules in his the personal life, he soon became rector, and tried to apply them to the structure of the whole monastery. Owing to the increase in the number of brothers, the venerable Theodore did not have enough time, nor the strength to enter into it himself and personally to keep the rules, that is why he set up the entire order of positions, to help him with the administration and management of the monastery. For the direction of these persons he wrote a manual in iambic verses, where he set forth the duties beginning with the abbot and ending with the least of the brethren. He died in 826 in the little place of Acritos. The Venerable Theodore left many compositions, letters, canons, and church stikhera. The Typikon is indebted to the Venerable Theodore for his significant additions, concerning the structure and cycle of the church services. For the Great Lenten services the Venerable Theodore structured the Three Ode Canon for Matins, and together with his own brother Joseph of Saloni_a was called the author of the Triodion. 
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="8">
O instructor of Orthodoxy, teacher of piety and purity,/ beacon for the whole world, divinely inspired adornment of monastics./ O most wise Theodore by thy doctrines thou hast illumined all.// O harp of the Spirit, entreat Christ God that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="2">
Thine angelic life of fasting/ thou didst adorn with the struggles of suffering,/ O divinely blessed Theodore,/ and thou hast been shown to abide with the angels.// With them cease thou never to pray to Christ God for us all.
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>