<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Holy Great Martyr Anastasia the Medicine Woman"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
       St. Anastasia was born a Roman and was the spouse of a rich pagan Publius. Instructed in the Christian faith by St. Chrysogonus, she devoted herself to ministering to prisoners and confessors of Christ. Traveling from country to country, she comforted the imprisoned Christians, treated their wounds and with the help from her estate released them from prison. For all this she was called Pharmakolytrias, i.e. Medicine woman. She suffered in Illyria, having been attached to 4 pillars and burned by fire. St. Chrysogonus was for a long time kept in a Roman prison and, finally, was beheaded by the sword in Aquileia. St. Theodota, a rich widow from Nicaea, receiving into her home St. Anastasia, together with her three children, one of whom was Evodias, suffered for Christ in Nicaea (see Jul. 29). After torture they were burned. St. Eutychianus and the rest (120 others), who accepted Christ during the torture of St. Anastasia, were beheaded by the sword. In the church hymns of this day only the Great Martyr Anastasia is glorified, and of the other holy martyrs only Martyr Chrysogonus is mentioned.
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="4">
Thy ewe-lamb Anastasia crieth out to Thee with a loud voice, O Jesus:/ "I love Thee, O my Bridegroom,/ and, seeking Thee, I pass through many struggles:/ I am crucified and buried with Thee in Thy baptism,/ and suffer for Thy sake, that I may reign with Thee;/ I die for Thee that I might live with Thee./ As an unblemished sacrifice accept me,/ who sacrifice myself with love for Thee// By her supplications save Thou our souls, in that Thou art merciful.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="2" Podoben="3">
When they have recourse to thy temple,/ those who find themselves in temptations and sorrows/ receive precious gifts through the divine grace/ which dwelleth within thee, O Anastasia.// For thou ever pourest forth healings upon the world.
</KONTAKION>

</SAINT>