<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Martyrs Eustratios, Auxentios, Eugene, Mardarius and Orestes at Sebaste († c. 284-305)" Short="Martyrs Eustratios"/>
<SERVICE Type="4"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
&lt;p&gt;These holy martyrs suffered deeply for Christ during the reign of theEmperor Diocletian in Sebaste, Armenia. St. Eustratius, “the accuser ofHellenic thinkers of fables and preacher of Christian divine wisdom,” wasthe magistrate of Satalios. For his belief in Christ, being “relentlesslybeaten, and burned in fire, and nailed in his boots with iron, and driven on the way,and enclosed in prison,” he was burned to death after these severe tortures. Auxentius,”who with wise words and patience became a martyr exposing godlessness,” waspresbyter of the Arabian church and, after being “tested by various torments,confessing Christ God,” died, being beheaded by the sword. Eugene, “needed by Godfor good and not needed for torture was saved by his confession,” and Mardarius, “themeek dove,” were voluntarily led into martyrdom for the sake of Christ and died whilebeing tortured. St. Orestes, “a true and wonderful warrior for every Cæsar,” whofound his faith in Christ by the cross on his chest, after being tortured “was burned onan iron griddle,” received “a blessed end to his life and an incorruptible crown.” Therelics of these holy martyrs repose in Rome.&lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
&lt;p&gt;In their sufferings, O Lord, * Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God; * for, possessed of Thy might, * they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons. ** By their supplications save Thou our souls.&lt;/p&gt;
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="2">
&lt;p&gt;Thou hast been shown to be a most splendid luminary, * for those who sit in the darkness of ignorance, O passion-bearer; * for, armed with faith as with a spear, * thou wast undaunted by the arrogance of the enemy, O Eustratius, ** who art far more eloquent than any orator.&lt;/p&gt;
</KONTAKION><KONTAKION Type="2" Tone="3">
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of divine things eloquently before the iniquitous, O all-wondrous one, * thou didst endure beatings with most courageous heart, * didst shine forth with godly signs, * and didst extinguish the towering flame of falsehood. ** Wherefore, we honor thee, O most blessed Eustratius, martyr of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>
