<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Venerable Xenophontes with his wife Maria, and their sons Arkadius and John of Constantinople (5th-6th C)" Short="Venerable Xenophontes"/>
<SERVICE Type="1"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1997 by translator Fr. S. Janos.">
&lt;p&gt;The Monk Xenophontes, his spouse Maria and their sons Arkadios and John, were noted citizens of Constantinople and lived in the V Century. Despite riches and position, they distinguished themselves by their simplicity of soul and goodness of heart. Wishing to give their sons John and Arkadios a more complete education, they sent them off to the Phœnician city of Beirut. Through Divine Providence the ship on which both brothers sailed became ship-wrecked. The brothers were pitched by the waves onto shore at different places. Aggrieved at being separated, the brothers dedicated themselves to God and accepted monasticism. For a long time the parents received no news about their children and presumed them to have perished. Xenophontes, however, now already quite old, maintained firm hope in the Lord and consoled his wife Maria, telling her not to sorrow but to believe that their children were watched over by the Lord. After several years the spouses made pilgrimage to the Holy places and at Jerusalem they met their sons, pursuing asceticsm at different monasteries. The joyful parents gave thanks to the Lord for providently re-uniting the whole family. For the remainder of their lives, the monastics Xenophontes and Maria dedicated themselves to God and accepted monasticism. The Monks Arkadios and John, having taken leave of their parents, went out into the wilderness, where after long ascetic toil they were glorified by gifts of wonderworking and perspicacity. The monastic elders Xenophontes and Maria, having pursued asceticism in silence and strict fasting, also received of God the gift of wonderworking.&lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
&lt;p&gt;O God of our fathers, * deal with us ever according to Thy meekness. * Deprive us not of Thy mercy, * but through their supplications ** direct our life in peace.&lt;/p&gt;
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="4">
&lt;p&gt;Having gladly distributed thy riches to the poor, O blessed one, * with thy spouse and children thou wast vigilant in the commandments of the Lord. ** Wherefore, ye have inherited divine delight.&lt;/p&gt;
</KONTAKION><KONTAKION Type="2" Tone="4">
&lt;p&gt;Having fled the sea of life, * the righteous Xenophon, with his honored spouse and children. ** rejoice together in the heavens, magnifying Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>
