<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Holy Prophet Daniel and the Three Holy Youths: Ananias, Azarias, and Misael"/> 
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
They were children of notable Jews. Taken in captivity by the Babylonian King Nebuchadnezzar, they were brought up at the court of this king, but they were faithful to their God and &quot;were not willing to be defiled by the most unlawful food&quot;. For opening and interpreting the dream which was seen by and bothered Nebuchadnezzar, the prophet Daniel was made the ruler of Babylon. Soon after that Nebuchadnezzar put up a statue on the plain of Dura and commanded all to render it divine honor. Refusing to obey this command Ananias, Azarias and Misael were thrown into the blazing furnace, but the Lord kept them safe in the flame and Nebuchadnezzar glorified the true God. During the reign of Belteshazzar the Holy Prophet Daniel interpreted a mysterious inscription which was shown on the wall during a feast and announcing the downfall of the Babylonian kingdom. During the reign of the Persian King Darius, St. Daniel, on the slander of his enemies, was into a pit with lions, but the Lord shut up the mouth of the lions and the prophet remained unharmed. St. Daniel died in Persia. He wrote a book in which he precisely tells the specified time of the coming of the Messiah. The Holy Empress Helena translated the relics of St. Daniel to Constantinople. The Three Holy Youths, by tradition, were beheaded by the sword during the reign of the Persian King Cambyses. 
</LIFE>
<TROPARION Tone="2">
Great are the accomplishments of faith!/ In the fountain of flame, as in refreshing water, the three holy children rejoiced;/ and the Prophet Daniel/ was shown to be a shepherd of lions, as of sheep.// By their prayers, O Christ God; save Thou our souls.
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Tone="3" Podoben="1">
Enlightened by the Spirit,/ thy pure heart became the receptacle of most splendid prophecy:/ for thou beheldest far-off things as though they were present,/ and, cast into the pit, didst tame the lions.// Wherefore, we honor thee, O blessed and glorious Prophet Daniel.
</KONTAKION>

</SAINT>