<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Martyr Sebastian at Rome with his companions: Martyrs Nicostratus, his wife Zoe, Castorius, Tranquillinus the Presbyter and his sons the Deacons Marcellinus and Mark, Claudius, his son Symphorian and brother Victorinus, Tiburtius and Castulus († c. 287)" Short="Martyr Sebastian"/>
<SERVICE Type="1"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
&lt;p&gt;Holy Martyr Sebastian (defender of the church) and his companions (Nicostratus, master of the rolls, his wife Zoe and his brother Castorius, the Presbyter Tranquillinus and his two sons, Deacons Marcellian and Mark, Claudius the interpreter, his son Symphorian and brothers Victorinus, Tiburtius and Castulus, suffered for Christ in Rome about 287. St. Sebastian was the chief of the court guards. Secretly confessing Christ, he used all means to ease the suffering of persecuted Christians and at the same time convinced them to courageously die for Christ. Accused of this, he was turned over to torture: attached to a tree, he was completely pierced with arrows and then hammered to death with canes. Nicostratus (prison chief), Castorius, Claudius, Victorinus and Symphorian, converted to Christ, were drowned in the sea. Tranquillinus was beaten with stones and thrown into the river. Marcellian and Mark taken first for torture were crucified headlong. Tiburtius was beheaded by the sword. Castulus was buried alive. After being tortured for Christ Zoe, formerly a deaf mute healed by Sebastian, was thrown into the Tiber River. The relics of St. Sebastian repose in Rome. The Church hymns for this day are devoted mainly to glorifying Martyr Sebastian. The other holy martyrs Zoe, Mark, Marcellian and Tiburtius are commemorated in these hymns. &lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
&lt;p&gt;In their sufferings, O Lord, * Thy martyrs received imperishable crowns from Thee our God; * for, possessed of Thy might, * they set at nought the tormentors and crushed the feeble audacity of the demons. ** By their supplications save Thou our souls.&lt;/p&gt;
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="1">
 
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>
