<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Nun-Martyr Eugenia of Rome, and with her the Martyrs Philip, her father, Protus, Hyacinth, Basilla, and Claudia (+c.262)" Short="Nun-Martyr Eugenia"/>
<SERVICE Type="1"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
        The Roman maiden Eugenia was the daughter of the Alexandrian eparch Philip, protector of Christians &quot;completed for the sake of their way of life and a philosophy&quot;. She &quot;was very sharp and diligent in learning, comfortably understanding everything, and whatever she heard or read once, that she remembers well, as if written on copper sheets, having it in her heart&quot;. Possessing beauty, Eugenia at the same time was distinguished &quot;by chaste thoughts and virginal purity&quot;.         One of the most famous and well-born young men strenuously sought her hand, but she answered the proposal of her parents concerning marriage with him: &quot;It is better for a man to be moral than it is for him to be noble, for it is to live with him, but not born of him&quot;. Other &quot;bright young men born in glory and wealth&quot; also sought the hand of Eugenia, but she, &quot;loving chastity, fled from marriage&quot;, refused all, having decided &quot;to remain in chaste virginity&quot; forever. Casually having read through the book of the Epistles of the Holy Apostle Paul once, the wise virgin learned from them the true teaching of Christ.         Later she secretly left with two servants, Protus and Hyacinth, from her parent&apos;s home to one of the monasteries, where she changed into men&apos;s clothing, and asked the former Bishop Helenus of this monastery to enlighten them with Holy Baptism. In a wonderful vision it was revealed to the bishop, that the maiden Eugenia, and he &quot;knowing that she willingly was to prevail in the likeness of a man, inasmuch as none knows this secret&quot;, and baptized all three of them and tonsured them into monasticism.         The parents of Eugenia, not looking with all diligence, could not open the residence of their daughter. They &quot;with inconsolable grief&quot; cried for her day and night, &quot;often calling out her name and powdering their heads with ashes, falling to the ground from exhaustion and sickness of heart&quot;.         Meanwhile St. Eugenia living in a monastery succeeded in her monastic efforts. &quot;For her words were humble, loving, meek and few, full of the awe of God and His advantage&quot;. She arrived in church before everyone and left after everyone else left. Everything she did she did humbly &quot;in building: she comforted the afflicted, rejoiced with the rejoicing, flying into a rage with anger she subdued one with a word, proud of the paradigm of her humble way of life&quot;. For such a holy life the Lord granted her the gift of healing. Sts. Protus and Hyacinth, imitating their former lady, also succeeded in a virtuous life.         After three years passed the abbot of the monastery died. Under the unanimous and persistent request of the brethren and obeying her &quot;commitment to Christ&quot;, St. Eugenia felt compelled to take upon herself the rule over the monastery. She was a high example for the monks, &quot;continually laboring for all the brethren, carrying water, cutting fire wood, cleaning all the cells and serving all with much diligence&quot;, unfailingly attending all church services and herself living in the gatekeeper cell.         Subsequently St. Eugenia, being slandered for an infringement of chastity, resulted her being in court before her father and here she revealed the secret of her flight, after which both her father and her mother Claudia converted to Christ. Later her father became a bishop and died as a martyr.         After the death of her father St. Eugenia together with her mother and servants moved to Rome and here again converted many notable maidens to Christ and convinced them to always remain virgins.       During the persecution of Emperor Gallienus, St. Eugenia together with Protus and Hyacinth were beheaded by the sword for their faith in Christ. St. Claudia and the noble maiden Basilla, who believed in Christ, received the same crown of martyrdom. All their relics repose in Rome. In the church service dedicated to Martyr Eugenia, the Martyr Basilla is also mentioned, but the names of other martyrs are not. 
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="1">
 
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="1">
 
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>