<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="20,000 Martyrs burned at Nicomedia including Glycerios the Presbyter, Zeno, Theophilus the Deacon, Dorotheus, Mardonius, Migdonius the Deacon, Indysos, Gorgonios, Peter, Euthymios, Secundos, Nicostrates, the Women martyrs Agatha, Domna, Theophila, Antonia Antonia and others († 302)" Short="Martyrs"/>
<LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="Bulgakov Handbook. Copyright 1999-2008 Archpriest Eugene D. Tarris.">
&lt;p&gt;    They were burnt and others outside the church suffered there. In 302 the Emperor Maximian Hercules offered solemn sacrifices to the gods in Nicomedia in celebration of his victories. Christians, who casually were in the area, began to leave afraid of being sprinkled with the blood of idol-sacrifice. Angry with them the Emperor ordered to burn the Christians of Nicomedia together with their temple when they gathered for celebrating the Nativity of Christ. According to the Synodal Menologion of 1862, soon after the burning of these holy martyrs the following holy martyrs died from various tortures: Indes, Gorgonius, Peter, Zeno, Dorotheus, Mardonius, Migdonius, Glycerias, Theophilus, Euthymius and the maidens: Domna, Agatha, and Theophila. The following names of martyrs are listed in the service of this day: Theophilus, Dorotheus, Migdonius, Gorgonius, Secondus, Peter, Indes and Anthimus. The names of the holy martyrs Secundus and Anthimus are not mentioned in the Synodal Menaion of 1863 and 1891 (Refer to Sep. 3). &lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE>
<SERVICE Type="1">
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="2">
&lt;p&gt;O athletes of the Lord, * blessed is the ground which drank in your blood, * and holy the habitations which have received your bodies, * for in your contest ye vanquished the enemy and preached Christ with boldness. ** Entreat Him, we pray, in that He is good, that our souls be saved.&lt;/p&gt;
</TROPARION>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="2">
&lt;p&gt;Made steadfast in soul by faith, * the twenty thousand holy athletes accepted suffering by fire, * crying out to Him Who was born of the Virgin: * "O preeternal God, accept us as wholeburnt offerings to Thee, ** as thou didst accept the gold, myrrh and frankincense from the Persian kings!"&lt;/p&gt;
</KONTAKION>
</LITURGY>
</SERVICE>
</SAINT>
