<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Martyr Dometios of Persia and his two Disciples (+ 363)" Short="Martyr Dometios"/>
<SERVICE Type="1"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
 The Monk Dometios lived during the IV Century, and he was by birth a Persian. In his youthful years he was converted to the faith by a Christian named Uaros. Forsaking Persia, he withdrew to the frontier-city of Niziba (in Mesopotamia), where he accepted Baptism in one of the monasteries and was tonsured into monasticism. But then fleeing the ill-will of the monastery inhabitants, the Monk Dometios moved on to the monastery of Saints Sergios and Bacchus in the city of Theodosiopolis. The monastery was under the guidance of an archimandrite named Nurbelos -- a strict ascetic, about whom it was reported, that over the course of 60 years he did not taste of cooked food, nor did he lay down for sleep, but rather took his rest standing up, supporting himself upon his staff. In this monastery the Monk Dometios was ordained to the dignity of deacon, but when the archimandrite decided to have him made a presbyter, the saint in reckoning himself unworthy hid himself away on a desolate mountain in Syria, in the region of Cyr. Reports about him constantly spread about among the surrounding inhabitants. They began to come to him for healing and for help. Many a pagan was brought to the faith in Christ by Dometios. And one time, in the locality where Saint Dometios asceticised with his disciples, the emperor Julian the Apostate (361-363) arrived, journeying along on his campaign against the Persians. By order of the emperor, soldiers searched out Saint Dometios praying with his disciples in a cave, and stoned them to death (+ 363).
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
 Having struggled in fasting upon the mountain,/ thou didst destroy the noetic hordes of the enemy/ with the weaponry of the Cross, O most blessed one./ And thou didst likewise manfully array thyself for battle,/ slaying Copronymus with the sword of faith.// And for both thou hast been crowned by God,// O ever-memorable venerable martyr Dometius.
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="6">
 Having utterly spurned corruptible things and thoughts/ which draw one down to the depths, O venerable martyr Dometius,/ thou didst show thyself to be a great leader of monks,/ turning to fear the wrath of the king who did not wish to worship Christ as the true God./ Wherefore, thou didst repose, chanting the hymn;// God is with me, and no one is against me!
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>