<SAINT>

<NAME Nominative="Hieromartyr Eutychius, disciple of the Apostle John the Theologian (1st C)" Short="Hieromartyr Eutychius,"/>
<SERVICE Type="1"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Copyright="The Clergyman's Handbook. Moscow. 1978. English translation Copyright 1997 Fr. S. Janos.">
 The PriestMartyr Eutykhios, a disciple of the holy Apostles John the Theologian and Paul, lived from the I Century into the beginning II Century, and was from the city of Palestinian Sebasteia. Although Saint Eutykhios is not reckoned among the number of the 70 Disciples, he received the title Disciple for his labours together with the older Apostles, by whom he was made bishop. Having heard the preaching about Christ the Saviour, Saint Eutykhios at first became a student of the Apostle John the Theologian, and then having met the Apostle Paul, he preached together with him on the early journeys. Saint Eutykhios underwent many sufferings: they starved him with hunger, struck at his body with iron, they flung him in the fire and then for devouring by wild beasts. One time there was let loose upon the saint a lion, which brought fright to everyone in that it rendered praise to the Creator -- having been given human voice. The Priestmartyr Eutykhios finished with his works in his native city, where he was beheaded with a sword at the beginning of the II Century.
</LIFE><SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<TROPARION Type="1" Tone="4">
 As thou didst share in the ways of the apostles/ and didst occupy their throne,/ thou didst find thine activity to be a passage to divine vision,/ O divinely inspired one./ Wherefore, ordering the word of truth,/ thou didst suffer for the Faith even to the shedding of thy blood.// O hieromartyr Eutychius, entreat Christ God, that our souls be saved.
</TROPARION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
<SERVICE>
<LITURGY>
<KONTAKION Type="1" Tone="3">
 As one who shared the throne of the apostles and the adornment of holy hierarchs,/ O Eutyches, thou wast glorified in martyrdom,/ didst shine forth like the sun, illumining all,/ and didst dispel the profound night of ungodliness,// Wherefore, we honor thee as a truly divine initiate of the mysteries of Christ.
</KONTAKION></LITURGY></SERVICE>
</SAINT>