<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Repose of Saint Herman, Archbishop of Kazan († 1567)" Short="St. Herman"/>
<SERVICE Type="0"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
St. Herman descended from a family of boyars, Sadirev-Polev (descendants of the princes of Smolensk), was born in the city of Staritsa, Tver province at the beginning of 16th century and in the world bore the name Gregory. From his young years he loved church services and the reading of the divine scriptures, observed much moderation in food and all the time devoted himself to pious exercises. When he was 25 years old, with the blessing of his parents and taking the name of Herman, he entered the Volokolamsk-St. Joseph Monastery. And here he learned the high moral qualities of a monk, was the first in the temple for prayer and the last leaving it, and when he was free from services and monastic obediences he devoted his time to the transcription of church service books. Since 1543 Hegumen Gurius, later the first archbishop of Kazan, revealed Herman as the leader in monastic asceticism. In 1555, when St. Gurius was installed the Archbishop of Kazan, St. Herman already was known for his holy life, and was entrusted to build a monastery in the city of Sviazhsk (see Kazan Diocese), in order that it serve as a garden of the holy faith among the Moslems. The Ven. Herman honorably performed his duties and upon the death of St. Gurius in 1564 was installed as the Archbishop of Kazan. Called in 1566 to Moscow to become Metropolitan, St. Herman, with deep monastic humility, distinguished by sincere love of truth and unshakable firmness, powerfully accused the disordered oprichnina (private court) during the first personal appointment of Ivan the Terrible. For this he was quietly removed as Metropolitan and remained in Moscow under the ban of the Tsar for a year and seven months before his death. However the imperial anger did not frighten the firm spirit of Herman. At the council called in 1568 by Ivan the Terrible for the condemnation of St. Philip, St. Herman was one among all who raised his voice in the defense of the innocent. Soon after that council on November 6, 1568, St. Herman died in Moscow in abject poverty from the plague epidemic and was interred in the Nicholay-Mokrago Church. Within 24 years his relics were transferred to the Dormition Monastery in Sviazhsk (see the Kazan Diocese), during which a wonderful odor permeated not only throughout the temple but also the entire monastery. 
</LIFE>
</SAINT>
