<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Venerable Simon of Yuriev († 1584)" Short="Venerable Simon"/>
<SERVICE Type="0"/><LIFE Id="bulgakov" Translator="Archpriest Eugene Tarris">
&lt;p&gt; The son of a villager, living in the village of Odelev, Nerekhta District, Kostroma Province (not far from the unattached city of Ples), since his early years he distinguished himself with unusual diligence (an artesian well dug by him serves as a memorial of this, and by the way, is found near a chapel by the village of Odelev). Wishing to carry out a virgin life, Simon secretly left the house of his parents and practiced asceticism first near the village of Elnat (Yuriev District), and then in Yurievets Volga region. Here, being homeless, he went to the streets, pretending a deprived mind. His favorite places were church porches, and especially the church porch of the Holy Theophany Monastery where at night he fervently prayed to God. From this severe life and strong winter frosts his body turned black and his skin stuck to his bones. For these God-pleasing efforts he received the gift of insight from God. He died as a martyr, being beaten by the governor who threw him into a cellar in 1584. In 1619 a new church into which his coffin was finally brought inside was built in the Yuriev Theophany Monastery where the Blessed Simon was buried. In 1635 Patriarch Joasaph blessed, “for the sake of the patient the life and miracles of the Blessed Simon, which existed during his lifetime and after his repose,” to write his icon “with light around his head, together with his namesake the Apostle Simon the Zealot and to honor him among the saints.” This local celebration of the Blessed Simon stopped since 1722 and has not been subsequently restored. At the present time an easy approach to the tomb is open. The shrine of the Blessed Simon is remodeled, and in it is placed a cypress icon in a covering, representing the blessed one with the fingers of his hands intertwined. The memory of the Blessed Simon is considered holy in Yuriev and its vicinity. &lt;/p&gt;
</LIFE>
</SAINT>