<SAINT>
<NAME Nominative="Great Friday. Remembrance of the Holy and Salvific Passion of our Lord Jesus Christ" Short="Great Friday. Remembrance of the Holy and Salvific Passion of our Lord Jesus Christ"/>
<SERVICE>
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;<TROPARION Header="Tropar, Tone 1" Tone="1" Type="1">
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you were crucified, O Christ, the tyranny of the enemy was destroyed, his power trampled underfoot; for it was not an Angel, not a human, but you, the Lord himself, who saved us. Glory to you!
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;</TROPARION>
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;<TROPARION Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Tone="6" Type="2">
Lord, the Jews condemned you, the life of all, to death; those who by a staff crossed the Red Sea on foot nailed you to a cross, and those who sucked honey from a rock offered you gall. But you endured willingly, that you might free us from the slavery of the fœ. Christ God, glory to you!
</TROPARION>
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;<TROPARION Header="Tropar, Tone 2" Tone="2" Type="3">
You have worked salvation in the midst of the earth, Christ our God. You stretched out your most pure hands on the Cross, gathering together all the nations, as they cry: Lord, glory to you!
</TROPARION>
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;<TROPARION Header="Tropar, Tone 8" Tone="8" Type="4">
The Thief, seeing the Prince of life hanging on the Cross, said: If he who is crucified with us was not God incarnate, the sun would not have hidden its rays, nor would the shaken earth be quaking. But you who bear all things, remember me, Lord, in your kingdom.
</TROPARION>
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;<KONTAKION Header="Kontak, Tone 1" Tone="1" Type="1">
Come, let us all sing the praise of him who was crucified for us; for Mary looked upon him on the Tree and said: ‘Though you endure the Cross, yet you are my Son and my God’.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;</KONTAKION>
<ROYALHOURS><!-- The verses for the Idiomels are the same in all the hours -->
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;<IDIOMEL Type="11" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8<BR>The Work of Sophronios, the Patriarch of Jerusalem" Author="Sophronios, the Patriarch of Jerusalem">
Today the veil of the Temple is rent, as a reproof against the transgressors; and the sun hides its own rays, as it sees the Master crucified.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;</IDIOMEL><!-- Note the difference in assigned Tones here -->
<VERSE Type="1" >
Why were the nations insolent and why did the peoples meditate vain things?
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="12" Tone="3" Header="Tropar, Tone 3">
You were led like a sheep to the slaughter, Christ King, and as an innocent lamb you were nailed to the Cross by lawless men for our sins, O Lover of mankind.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="2">
The kings of the earth stood up, and the rulers were assembled together against the Lord and against his Christ.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="13" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Allowing the lawless to arrest you, Lord, you cried out, ‘Though you strike the shepherd and scatter the twelve sheep, my disciples, I could call to my side more than twelve legions of Angels; but I forbear, that the hidden and secret things, which I revealed to you through my Prophets, may be fulfilled.’ Lord, glory to you! 
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="1P" Tone="4" Header="Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
He gathered iniquity to himself; he went out and spoke in the same manner.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="1P" >
Blessed is one who considers the poor and needy; the Lord will deliver in an evil day.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="31" Tone="8" Header="Тropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Through fear of the Jews Peter, your friend and neighbour, denied you, Lord; and in bitter grief he cried out: Do not pass by my tears in silence, compassionate Master; for I said I would keep faith, but have not kept it. Accept our repentance too, and have mercy on us. 
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="31">
Give ear to my words, O Lord; understand my cry.
</VERSE>
<!-- On Good Friday, the verses are varied for each idiomel and hour. -->
<IDIOMEL Type="32" Tone="8" Header="Troparion, Tone 8">
Before your precious Cross as the soldiers mocked you, Lord, the spiritual hosts were struck with amazement. For you were wreathed with a crown of outrage, you who painted the earth with flowers; and you wore a cloak of mockery, you who wrap the firmament in clouds; by such a dispensation was your compassion made known, O Christ, and your great mercy. Glory to you!
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="32">
Attend to the voice of my prayer, my King and my God.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="33" Tone="3" Header="Tropar, Tone 3" Author="">
As you were dragged to the Cross, Lord, you cried out thus: For what work do you wish to crucify me, O Jews? Because I braced the paralytic? Because I raised the dead from sleep? I healed the woman with an issue of blood, I took pity on the woman of Canaan. For what work do you wish to slay me, O Jews? But, transgressors, you will see Christ whom now you pierce.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="3P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
For I am ready for scourges; * and my pain is with me continually.
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="3P">
&lt;p&gt;O Lord, do not rebuke me in your anger; nor chasten me in your wrath.&lt;/p&gt;
</VERSE>
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
<IDIOMEL Type="61" Tone="8" Header="Tropar, Tone 8" Author="">
Thus says the Lord to the Jews, ‘My people, what have I done to you? Or in what have I wearied you? I gave light to your blind, I cleansed your lepers, I set upright a man lying on a bed. My people, what have I done to you, and how have you repaid me? Instead of the manna gall; instead of the water vinegar; instead of loving me, you have nailed me to a cross. I can endure no longer; I will call my nations, and they will glorify me, with the Father and the Spirit; and I shall grant them eternal life
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="61">
They gave me gall for food, and for my thirst they gave me vinegar to drink.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="62" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6">
Lawgivers of Israel, Jews and Pharisees, the choir of the Apostles cries out to you, ‘See a Temple, which you have destroyed! See a Lamb, whom you have crucified! You handed him over to a tomb, but by his own authority he has risen. Do not be deceived, O Jews, for it is he who saved you in the sea, and fed you in the desert; he is the life and the light and the peace of the world.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="62">
Save me, O God; for the waters have come in, even as far as my soul.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="63" Tone="5" Header="Tropar, Tone 5" Author="">
Come, Christ-bearing peoples, let us see what Judas the betrayer has plotted with the lawless priests against our Saviour. Today they have found the immortal Word guilty of death, and having betrayed him to Pilate, crucified him on the place of the Skull. And as he suffered all this our Saviour cried out and said, "Forgive them this sin, Father, that the nations may know my Resurrection from the dead."
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="6P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
Lord, our Lord, how wonderful is your name in all the earth!
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="6P" >
For your majesty is raised high above the heavens.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="91" Tone="7" Header="Tropar, Tone 7" Author="">
A strange wonder it was to see the Maker of heaven and earth hanging on a cross; the sun darkened, the day changed again into night and the earth giving back the bodies of the dead from their tombs; with them we worship you. Save us.
</IDIOMEL>
<VERSE Type="91">
They parted my garments among them, and cast lots for my clothing.
</VERSE>
<IDIOMEL Type="92" Tone="2" Header="Tropar, Tone 2">
When the transgressors saw you, the Lord of glory, nailed to the Cross, you cried out to them, "How have I grieved you? In what have I angered you? Before me, who delivered you from affliction? And now how do your repay me? With evils for blessings: instead of a pillar of fire, you have nailed me to a cross; instead of a cloud, you have dug me a tomb; instead of the manna, you have offered me gall; instead of water, you have given me vinegar to drink. From now on I shall call the nations, and they will glorify me with the Father and the holy Spirit."
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.1" Tone="5" Header="Tropar, Tone 5" Author="">
To-day he is hung upon a tree, he who hung the earth upon the waters 
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.2" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
He is arrayed in a crown of thorns, he who is the King of the Angels. He is wrapped in mocking purple, he who wraps the heaven in clouds. He receives a blow on the face, he who freed Adam in Jordan. He is transfixed with nails, the Bridegroom of the Church. He is pierced by a lance, the Son of the Virgin. 
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.3" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
We worship your Sufferings, O Christ
</IDIOMEL>
<IDIOMEL Type="93.4" Tone="6" Header="Tropar, Tone 6" Author="">
Show us also your glorious Resurrection.
</IDIOMEL>
<PROKIMENON Type="9P" Tone="4" Header="The Prokeimenon of the Prophecy, Tone 4">
The fool has said in his heart: "There is no God."
</PROKIMENON>
<VERSE Type="9P">
There is none who does good; no, not one.
</VERSE>
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;</ROYALHOURS>
</SERVICE>
</SAINT>
